<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732905" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Versace family seeks to protect designer's image.</title>
<headline>Versace family seeks to protect designer's image.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The family of slain Italian fashion designer Gianni Versace warned investigators and the news media on Wednesday against disseminating information that might taint his image or that of his fashion firm.</p>
<p>&quot;The Versace family urges the media and information sources to neither express nor distribute unproven theories or conjecture concerning the circles in which the murder of their brother Gianni Versace may have been planned,&quot; the family's lawyers said in a printed statement.</p>
<p>The lawyers said their brief statement was intended to protect Versace's image and that of his firm the Versace Group.</p>
<p>The statement was issued as police and FBI agents scoured south Florida in a huge manhunt for Andrew Cunanan, the alleged serial killer and homosexual prostitute suspected of murdering the designer at his Miami Beach mansion on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Cunanan was wanted in connection with four previous murders, including that of his former male lover, during a two-week, cross-country killing spree that began in Minneapolis in April.</p>
<p>FBI Special Agent in Charge Paul Philip said he did not know if Versace, a 50-year-old homosexual who headed a multimillion-dollar fashion empire, had any relationship with Cunanan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
