<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732960" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italian fashion will miss trail-blazer Versace.</title>
<headline>Italian fashion will miss trail-blazer Versace.</headline>
<byline>Jude Webber</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gianni Versace was one of the brightest stars in the Italian fashion firmament, but his legacy is not just one of cutting edge creativity.</p>
<p>The 50-year-old designer, shot dead on the doorstep of his Miami Beach mansion on Tuesday, also taught an industry how to mix marketing know-how with fashion flair.</p>
<p>He and Giorgio Armani, the king of cool, classic elegance, were the two Italian stylists who really understood the power of marketing and distribution in the label-conscious 1980s.</p>
<p>Although some other big-name Italians, such as Gianfranco Ferre and Missoni, also saw the importance of creating integrated groups, experts said Versace was a guiding light.</p>
<p>&quot;We consider the Versace group an Italian 'top model',&quot; Vittorio Giulini, chairman of Modaindustria, which represents Italian clothing manufacturers, told Reuters on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;Versace was probably the designer in the vanguard of integration between design and business...(He) was an example of how to run a design empire in a more modern way.&quot;</p>
<p>Versace learnt the basics of his trade from his seamstress mother in the poor southern Italian town of Reggio Calabria, and went on to build a multi-million dollar worldwide business and become the designer of choice for royalty and rockstars.</p>
<p>Admired for his curiosity and willingness to innovate, Versace was at first considered a wild child of Italian fashion with designs bordering on the vulgar and brash.</p>
<p>One of few stylists to encourage the new British enfants terribles Alexander McQueen at Givenchy and John Galliano at Dior, whose designs have taken Paris by storm, Versace once admitted: &quot;Poor taste can be terribly trendy.&quot;</p>
<p>That instantly set him apart from Armani, whose name has become a byword for unutterably elegant, fluid, suits.</p>
<p>Versace's empire, built from scratch in 19 years, ranks second only to that of Armani in turnover and Chanel designer Karl Lagerfeld paid tribute to Versace as &quot;one of the flagships of Italian fashion&quot;.</p>
<p>With Versace's death, Armani, Ferre, Prada, Valentino and Dolce &amp; Gabbana seem set to remain the standard-bearers of a 54 trillion lire ($31 billion) integrated fashion industry in which Italians say they are proud to lead the world.</p>
<p>Ferre, a trained architect who has proved himself able to turn out both elaborately-cut confections and elegant evening wear, quit as Dior designer a year ago because the success of his own labels was making it hard for him to juggle two roles.</p>
<p>Miuccia Prada's simple nylon handbag was the chic chick's must-have a few seasons back and she made the retro 1970s look her own before weighing in with a more austere approach at this month's menswear collections in Milan.</p>
<p>One of Italy's best-known stylists abroad, Valentino, is known for elegant femininity and says Rome remains the fount of his inspiration, even though he now only shows in Paris.</p>
<p>Meanwhile design duo Domenico Dolce and Stefano Gabbana are creators of the freshest young styles around, with feminine, sexy clothes for women and most recently the deliberately crumpled suit for men.</p>
<p>&quot;Versace was and remains one of the greatest stars,&quot; said Federico Galdi, vice-chairman of the Ente Moda fashion body.</p>
<p>&quot;Fortunately there are very many stars.&quot;</p>
<p>Industry-watchers said they fully expected Versace's empire to go on without him, as the Moschino label and famous French couture houses had done despite the death of their founders. All eyes are on Versace's influential sister Donatella, they said.</p>
<p>But the fashion editor of one influential U.S. style magazine, who declined to be named, said Versace left a gap.</p>
<p>&quot;His fashion was about sexiness, glitz, colour, fun...he always portrayed a lifestyle,&quot; she said. &quot;He was unique. I don't think there's anyone else who does that quite as well.&quot; ($1=1,748 lire)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
