<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="732957" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Santo and Donatella Versace to carry the standard.</title>
<headline>Santo and Donatella Versace to carry the standard.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Hurst</byline>
<dateline>MILAN 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The murder of king of haute couture Gianni Versace robbed Italy of a creative genius but the fashion world is already looking to his brother Santo and sister Donatella to carry the family standard.</p>
<p>While Versace, killed by a lone gunman outside his Miami home on Tuesday, was clothing international celebrities his brother Santo was the man with a good head for figures running the business behind the catwalks.</p>
<p>&quot;Santo is a very astute manager,&quot; said Paola Berti, an Italian fashion writer. &quot;He handles all the investments and contacts with suppliers.&quot;</p>
<p>The question now is whether Santo and Donatella, who stayed on the sidelines while their celebrated brother Gianni basked in the limelight, can now fill the void.</p>
<p>Italian newspaper commentators said although Gianni was a bottomless fountain of invention, Santo had played a key role in engineering the stunning rise to prominence of the Versace name.</p>
<p>Donatella, a creative force in her own right, was encouraged by Gianni recently to develop her design talents while he was being treated for cancer. She is now responsible for the fashion house's Versus line aimed at younger people.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no doubt that in scaling the peaks of fashion, the presence of brother Santo was, from the start, a fundamental element,&quot; said Turin daily La Stampa. &quot;Santo brought to the building of the empire the capacity of a tough organiser and a wise administrator,&quot; the newspaper added.</p>
<p>The Milan-based Gianni Versace group is a family enterprise in the Italian tradition with key positions firmly in the hands of Gianni, Santo and Donatella.</p>
<p>Gianni owned 45 percent of the company shares, Santo has 35 percent and Donatella 20 percent. Santo is chairman and managing director while Donatella deputises for him. Gianni, a creative powerhouse, had no formal title.</p>
<p>While Gianni's murder leaves a yawning gap in the creative heart of the company, Santo and Donatella are free if they need to buy design talent from outside as other big fashion houses have done.</p>
<p>Italian fashion houses, like their French counterparts such as Givenchy, Chanel and Christian Dior, have survived and even flourished after the death of their founders.</p>
<p>Moschino has continued to prosper since the death of Franco Moschino in 1994 and Enrico Coveri, whose founder of the same name died seven years ago, is still in business.</p>
<p>British designer John Galliano recently triumphed with his creations for France's Christian Dior after its earlier revival under the guidance of Italian fashion guru Gianfranco Ferre.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the strength of the Versace brand may have already outgrown its creator,&quot; said an Italian investment banker. &quot;From now on the challenge for the family business will be to manage the brand.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Given the size and complexity of the Versace group it's now almost harder to manage the business than to handle the design side,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The Versace group's sales totalled 845 billion lire ($485 million), with 80 percent sold abroad, but total turnover from all Versace brands was much higher at 1.705 trillion lire ($1 billion).</p>
<p>The Versace name has been attached to everything from haute couture, jeans, T-shirts, perfumes and even bedclothes.</p>
<p>What has been irretrievably lost is the self-sufficient family team. &quot;They were always very close to each other and there was always a sense of everyone in the family group interacting with and influencing each other,&quot; said Berti.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MILAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
