<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733053" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India says to go ahead with Australian wheat deal.</title>
<headline>India says to go ahead with Australian wheat deal.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>India has decided to go ahead with the purchase of one million tonnes of wheat from Australia, which was stalled due to the presence of weeds in earlier shipments from Australia, a senior official said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;We are getting that one million tonnes,&quot; Food Secretary B.K. Taimini, the most senior civil servant in the Food Ministry, told reporters in New Delhi.  </p>
<p>Taimini said India had decided to take delivery of the wheat from Australia.</p>
<p>&quot;We are trying to ensure that some of the wheat arrives in September and the rest after the (Indian) sowing season in January and February,&quot; Taimini said.</p>
<p>The wheat was earlier due for shipments from August.</p>
<p>India has already bought more than one million tonnes of wheat from Australia.</p>
<p>Indian Agriculture Minister Chaturanan Mishra said in June that weeds were detected in earlier wheat shipments from Australia but it was not harmful and was common in wheat of any origin.</p>
<p>An Indian delegation visited Australia in June to discuss the presence of weeds in its wheat exports to India and new specifications for further exports with the Australian Wheat Board.</p>
<p>Taimini said the government considered various options such as bring the wheat in the form of wheat flour, sell it domestically during the off-season or despatch it to non-wheat growing areas.</p>
<p>The two latter options were accepted, he said.</p>
<p>Taimini said the government had decided to keep on hold the purchase of another one million tonnes of wheat out of two million it was authorised to import during 1997/98 (April-March).</p>
<p>-- New Delhi newsroom +91-11 301 2024</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M141">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
