<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733015" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Thousands of Hindu devotees start annual pilgrimage.</title>
<headline>Thousands of Hindu devotees start annual pilgrimage.</headline>
<byline>Ashok Pahalwan</byline>
<dateline>JAMMU, India 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of Hindu devotees, singing and chanting hymns, began an annual Himalayan pilgrimage through troubled Kashmir on Wednesday under tight security, police said.</p>
<p>They said more than 10,000 army and paramilitary troops stood guard over some 1,600 pilgrims as they began a five-day journey to a sacred cave 330 km (200 miles) northeast of Jammu, the winter capital of the Moslem-majority state of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
<p>Their trail passes through the Kashmir Valley, where dozens of guerrilla groups have been waging a separatist revolt since 1990. Police and hospitals say more than 20,000 people have died in insurgency-related violence.</p>
<p>&quot;The entire route up to the cave has been provided with adequate security,&quot; Ajay Khajuria, an official supervising the pilgrimage, told Reuters.</p>
<p>At least 214 pilgrims died last year after bitter winds and heavy snow lashed the trail to the mountain cave of Amarnath, located 12,500 feet (3,846 metres) above sea level.</p>
<p>In 1995 the pilgrimage was threatened by Moslem separatist guerrillas, who staged two bomb attacks on the heavily-guarded pilgrims, who rely on ponies to climb the upper reaches. A state civil servant was killed in one of the blasts.</p>
<p>The annual pilgrimage, which includes a steep, slippery 48-km (29-mile) trek, leads more than 100,000 devotees through monsoon rain-swollen streams and past a glacier-fed lake to the cave where they worship an ice stalagmite, believed to be a symbol of Lord Shiva, the Hindu god of regeneration.</p>
<p>The 5,000-year-old cave's chief priest, Mahant Giri, said he expected 120,000 pilgrims to visit Amarnath this year. The pilgrimage can be undertaken any time between July 16 and August 18.</p>
<p>&quot;Between 4,000 and 5,000 registration forms have been received by our bureaux at different places in the country so far. The actual number of pilgrims will emerge after two days when the compilation of these figures is over,&quot; Khajuria said.</p>
<p>Legend has it that the cave was discovered by a Moslem shepherd, Adam Malik, four centuries ago. His descendants still receive a share of the cash and other offerings made by devotees to the Hindu god at the cave.</p>
<p>The trek's picturesque base camp, Pahalgam, is in the region where six Western tourists were kidnapped by Moslem separatist rebels two years ago.</p>
<p>One, American John Childs, escaped and another, Norwegian Hans Christian Ostroe, was beheaded. The fate of the others -- Britons Paul Wells and Keith Mangan, American Donald Hutchings and German Dirk Hasert -- is still unkown.</p>
<p>After more than 200 pilgrims died during the trek last year, the government had considered regulating the number of pilgrims, fixing an age limit of 16 to 65 years for devotees and providing advance weather warnings.</p>
<p>&quot;The telecommunications department is setting up scores of public telephones along the pilgrimage route for the first time in the history of the pilgrimage to facilitate the pilgrims' speaking to their families,&quot; chief telecommunications general manager Prakash Narain said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAMMU, India"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
