<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733060" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Gunmen kill Sunni Moslems in Pakistani city.</title>
<headline>Gunmen kill Sunni Moslems in Pakistani city.</headline>
<dateline>LAHORE, Pakistan 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gunmen on a motorcycle shot dead two Sunni Moslems and wounded one in Lahore on Wednesday in what police said appeared to be a sectarian attack.</p>
<p>They said two gunmen fired on Rashid Ahmed, owner of a stationery shop, and his salesman Nizam Din when they were opening the store in the morning. They died at the scene.</p>
<p>A third salesman was critically wounded.</p>
<p>Ahmed was a well-known supporter of the militant Sunni Sipah-i-Sahaba Pakistan (SSP) group, and a month ago his brother was killed in Lahore.</p>
<p>There was no immediate claim of responsibility for the shooting, but it appeared to be the latest in a series of attacks for which rival militant groups of the majority Sunni and the minority Shi'ite sects blame each other.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, gunmen killed Haji Mohammad Yousaf, a SSP activist in Jhang town in the central province of Punjab.</p>
<p>Sectarian violence is rife in Punjab, where Sunni and Shi'ite factions are engaged in a feud that officials say has killed more than 100 people this year, including religious scholars, lawyers and doctors.</p>
<p>Sunni-Shi'ite disputes over Islamic beliefs have often turned violent in Pakistan. Such disputes cost at least 170 lives last year.</p>
<p>Shi'ites form about 15 percent of Pakistan's mainly Sunni population of more than 135 million people but are the majority in nearby Iran.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LAHORE, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
