<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733357" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: House passes $13 billion interior bill.</title>
<headline>House passes $13 billion interior bill.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The House of Representatives on Tuesday passed a $13 billion spending bill that would abolish the National Endowment for the Arts and trim subsidies to timber companies.</p>
<p>The bill for interior programs, ensnarled for several days in a fight over the fate of the arts agency, passed 238-192.</p>
<p>The Clinton administration has threatened to veto the legislation -- which covers a range of fiscal 1998 spending for public lands and parks, energy and Native Americans -- if the final version that emerges from Congress kills the NEA.</p>
<p>Democrats who fought to save the NEA -- which gives grants to community orchestras, theater groups, sculptors and other artists -- said the Senate likely would preserve it.</p>
<p>The House soundly rejected another measure to close the National Endowment for the Humanities which gives grants to universities, libraries, museums and other entities to study and preserve the nation's heritage and culture.</p>
<p>Legislation was introduced in the Senate on Tuesday to fund each of the endowments at $175 million next year, well above House bill levels. The Senate is to start work on its interior spending bill in a few days.</p>
<p>The House bill also would reduce by roughly half subsidies the U.S. Forest Service offers to timber companies for building logging roads in national forests. But lawmakers rejected an effort to kill the program in which loggers get more federal trees in exchange for building roads.</p>
<p>Rural lawmakers said the road program sustained logging jobs and yielded broader benefits by giving access to forests for recreation, fire-fighting and for isolated communities.</p>
<p>But environmentalists and taxpayer advocates said the program was a wasteful subsidy that paid loggers for roads that they would have to build anyway to extract trees from forests.</p>
<p>Roads wash out into streams, cause landslides, and damage ecosystems, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;We have for the first time made a real dent in the timber roads subsidy, and I'm very hopeful that this will lead to some reform in the program,&quot; Illinois Republican John Edward Porter, who sponsored the measure to end the program, said.</p>
<p>The House also refused to use $700 million from a Land and Water Conservation Fund to buy public lands, including $65 million to pay a company not to develop a gold mine on the edge of Yellowstone National Park, and $250 million to save the Headwaters grove in California, the nation's largest remaining uncut old-growth forest.</p>
<p>The White House said the money must be provided in a final bill to meet its balanced budget agreement with Congress. But Republicans said the money should not be used to buy new land when the government has trouble maintaining the land it has, and some balked at being forced to pay for a White House initiative.</p>
<p>In another objectionable move to the White House, the House bill would sell $209 million worth of oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve which the nation keeps as a buffer against supply disruptions.</p>
<p>The House would use the money to cover operating costs of the reserve. But the White House said it had money to run the reserve, and the sale was expected to be dropped from the bill when it was meshed with the Senate version.</p>
<p>The House also narrowly passed a measure to bar federal funds from being used for the U.S. Man and Biosphere program or the World Heritage Program, which are under the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. U.S. agencies contributed a total of $170,000 last year.</p>
<p>The bill also provides $1.2 billion for operating national parks, up $78 million from this year; $637 million for energy conservation programs, up $67 million from this year; $510 million for Native American education programs, up $28 million from this year; and $136 million for restoring the Everglades, up $79 million from this year.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I02000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C17">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
