<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733343" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Maternal infection raises cerebral palsy risk-study.</title>
<headline>Maternal infection raises cerebral palsy risk-study.</headline>
<dateline>CHICAGO 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The risk of developing cerebral palsy rose nine-fold in babies of normal birth weight who were exposed to infection in their mothers' wombs, a study said on Tuesday.</p>
<p>Judith Grether of the California Birth Defects Monitoring Program and Karin Nelson of the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke studied 424 babies born in Northern California from 1983 to 1985, 46 of whom suffered from disabling spastic cerebral palsy.</p>
<p>&quot;Maternal fever exceeding 38 degrees Celsius (100.4 Fahrenheit) in labor was associated with a 9.3-fold increase in the risk of unexplained spastic cerebral palsy, as was a clinical diagnosis of chorioamniotis,&quot; they wrote in the Journal of the American Medical Association.</p>
<p>Chorioamniotis is an infection involving the membrane surrounding the fetus, the amniotic sac and amniotic fluid.</p>
<p>&quot;One or more indicators of maternal infection, placental or other, during the admission for delivery were noted in 22 percent of children with unexplained cerebral palsy,&quot; the researchers wrote.</p>
<p>Previous research had associated maternal or placental infection with an increased risk of cerebral palsy in low birth weight infants, but not among normal birth weight babies who represent about half of all cases.</p>
<p>The current study also found maternal infection was linked to delivery room depression and neonatal seizures, symptoms commonly attributed to birth asphyxia.</p>
<p>Two to six babies per 1,000 born in the United States develop cerebral palsy, which stems from brain damage suffered in the later months of pregnancy, during the birthing process, or early in life, according to the American Medical Association's Encyclopedia of Medicine. Many sufferers are also mentally retarded, although a proportion are of normal or high intelligence.</p>
<p>In an accompanying editorial, David Eschenbach of the University of Washington in Seattle said the new study clarified some issues but raised new questions, including treatment options for pregnant women with evidence of infection and for their newborns.</p>
<p>But he said any progress was welcome for the affliction that incurs annual medical costs of $2.4 billion, &quot;representing one-third of the cost of the 18 most common birth defects.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CHICAGO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
