<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733529" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: NHS hospitals must have equal waiting lists - Dobson.</title>
<headline>NHS hospitals must have equal waiting lists - Dobson.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1996-07-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Patients using the free services of the National Health Service (NHS) will in future have equal access to hospital care irrespective of the fundholding status of their family doctors, Health Secretary Frank Dobson said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>&quot;From next April, hospitals will no longer be able to set different waiting time standards between GP fundholder and Health Authority patients,&quot; Dobson said in a press statement.</p>
<p>Just over half of all general practices in England are fundholding and maintain their own budgets, negotiating contracts for services from one or more hospitals. The balance of practices are non-fund holding and refer patients to hospitals with which their local health authority has a contract.</p>
<p>Patients from non-fundholding practices who are seeking routine elective surgery at a hospital outside their health authority's area can wait more than four months just to learn whether the surgery will be authorised, academic studies have shown.</p>
<p>This had led to accusations that the health service operates a &quot;two-tier system&quot; benefitting patients of wealthier general practices at the expense of the poor.</p>
<p>Commenting on the new policy, Dobson said, &quot;This is good news for patients. It is also good news for doctors and other NHS staff, many of whom have found the unfair two-tier system repugnant to administer.&quot;</p>
<p>He said that from April, 1998 hospitals must maintain a common waiting list for for all urgent admissions irrespective of whether hospital care is being funded by a general practise or a health authority. And health authorities must maintain standards for the maximum length of time a resident in their area waits for hospital admission.</p>
<p>Also from next April, residents seeking non-urgent hospital treatment must be admitted on the basis of clinical need rather than on the basis of who is paying for the procedure, Dobson said.</p>
<p>Finally, hospitals will not be allowed to offer patients of fundholders preferential admission nor will fundholders be allowed to press for quicker treatment &quot;except on clinical or social grounds,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>-Victoria English, London Newsroom 011 44 171 542 6472</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1996-07-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
