<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733531" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Prince Charles holds 50th bash for lover Camilla.</title>
<headline>Prince Charles holds 50th bash for lover Camilla.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>In the most publicly-scrutinised private party of the year, Prince Charles throws a 50th birthday bash on Friday for his mistress Camilla Parker Bowles in a bold declaration of a 25-year love affair that refuses to die.</p>
<p>The party for about 80 guests at Charles's Highgrove country home is something of a gamble for the heir to the throne as he tries to win public acceptance of the much-maligned Parker Bowles as his lover, if not his bride.</p>
<p>Too lavish and open a display of affection for the woman blamed for wrecking the fairytale marriage of Charles and the glamorous Princess Diana could destroy the cautious progress made recently in improving Parker Bowles's image.</p>
<p>No guest list has been published, no details announced for the gathering to fete a woman who has never given an interview, faced a photographer or said a word in public about her relationship with Charles.</p>
<p>But New Zealand soprano Kiri Te Kanawa, who ironically sang at the glittering 1981 royal wedding, is said to have been invited to lead the &quot;Happy Birthday&quot; chorus and representatives of Charles's private office and his Prince's Trust charity are thought to be attending in a show of support.</p>
<p>Some guests, however, have turned down their invitations, apparently anxious that the campaign to influence public opinion towards the woman Diana once dubbed &quot;The Rottweiler&quot; is going too far.</p>
<p>&quot;I know for a fact that there are those among their closest friends who feel they are being used as part of a pro-Camilla propaganda campaign and because of that some of them have turned down invitations to the party,&quot; said Charles Benson, one of the few friends in Parker Bowles's circle to break ranks and speak to the media.</p>
<p>The Highgrove party, estimated by the media to cost 50,000 pounds ($84,000), takes place just 11 months after Charles and Diana's acrimonious divorce, following mutual admissions of adultery.</p>
<p>The media and much of the British public wished Diana well in finding happiness elsewhere but Charles's popularity -- and with it respect for the institution of monarchy -- slumped to an all-time low.</p>
<p>Charles said at the time he had no plans to remarry, probably to quell public anger at the divorce.</p>
<p>But like his great-uncle Edward VIII, who in 1936 renounced the throne to marry American divorcee Wallis Simpson, Charles has made clear he cannot envisage his future without the help and support of the woman he loves.</p>
<p>Portrayed in the British media as frumpish and frowning, Parker Bowles looks unhappy in the role of femme fatale. She met Charles in 1971 but after a brief romance they both married elsewhere. Charles has said they resumed their affair only after his relationship with Diana had irretrievably broken down.</p>
<p>Friday's party puts their affair on a new, more open footing although persistent reports that the two divorcees will soon make a public outing together have yet to materialise.</p>
<p>After her own divorce in 1995, Parker Bowles bought a house just 17 miles from Highgrove. Her horse is stabled at Highgrove and Charles and Camilla hold frequent dinner parties for close and trusted friends.</p>
<p>Penny Junor, former biographer of Prince Charles, says Camilla &quot;is extraordinarily good for him. He lights up when she is around.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;She's real. She says what she thinks, laughs long and loud when something amuses her, has no pretensions, no guile; she is mildly chaotic, refreshingly uncomplicated and totally uninterested in style,&quot; Junor wrote recently.</p>
<p>Unfortunately for Charles, British public opinion has yet to be convinced although an hour-long television documentary about Camilla last week and serious discussions among churchmen about the possibility of a royal re-marriage have been surprisingly sympathetic towards them.</p>
<p>A much-criticised south of France holiday by Diana this week with Mohammed al-Fayed, controversial boss of the London store Harrods, and a bizarre speedboat meeting with the press where she promised a forthcoming surprise revelation have also helped sway public opinion.</p>
<p>The Sunday Telegraph's Robert Hardman compared the plight of Charles and Camilla to that of South African President Nelson Mandela, who took tea with Queen Elizabeth at Buckingham Palace last week hand in hand with his new love Gracha Machel.</p>
<p>&quot;Prince Charles cannot even afford to be seen on the arm of Camilla Parker Bowles in his own home. If they swept into Buckingham Palace together, the media's response would be a noisy 'aagh'.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The fact that Mrs Parker Bowles and Mrs Machel attract such contrasting public reactions is down to the women they have replaced.</p>
<p>&quot;Had the Prince been married to Winnie (Mandela), Camilla would now be held aloft as a national saviour,&quot; Hardman wrote. ($ = 0.596 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
