<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733690" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Versace murder suspect wanted for trail of killings.</title>
<headline>Versace murder suspect wanted for trail of killings.</headline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The San Diego high school year book of Andrew Cunanan, the male prostitute suspected of killing fashion designer Gianni Versace, named him &quot;Most Likely to be Remembered.&quot;</p>
<p>Cunanan, 27, has already earned a place on the FBI's 10 most-wanted list, sought in connection with four previous murders during a two-week, cross-country killing spree that began in Minneapolis in late April.</p>
<p>Miami Beach police named him as the only suspect in the killing of Versace, who was shot twice in the back of the head outside his Miami Beach mansion on Tuesday morning.</p>
<p>There have been numerous unconfirmed sightings of Cunanan from Boston to Oklahoma City. Photographs of him have show a clean-shaven, brown-haired man with wire-rim glasses.</p>
<p>Friends of Cunanan in San Diego said he led a lavish, gregarious lifestyle in the city's gay community, despite not having a job. His mother, who was living in public housing in a small Illinois town, told a Chicago newspaper he was &quot;a high-priced prostitute.&quot;</p>
<p>At a farewell party in San Diego, Cunanan reportedly told friends he was moving to San Francisco but had business to finish in Minneapolis. He bought a one-way plane ticket there, paying with a credit card strained to its debt limit.</p>
<p>Police believe Cunanan met up with a former lover, Minneapolis architect David Madson, 33, and another friend from San Diego, former Navy man Jeffrey Trail, 27.</p>
<p>Trail's body was found rolled up in a rug in Madson's apartment, apparently beaten to death with a hammer. Madson was found shot to death in the weeds of a lake in nearby Chisago County. Cunanan was believed to have stolen Trail's .40-calibre handgun.</p>
<p>Cunanan was believed to have then travelled to Chicago in Madson's Jeep Cherokee, where he may have encountered real estate mogul Lee Miglin, 72, by chance. Miglin's body was found in his garage, slashed to death and possibly run over by his own car.</p>
<p>The suspect apparently ate a sandwich and shaved in Miglin's luxury home before leaving in his Lexus automobile. The Jeep Cherokee stolen from Madson was discovered illegally parked nearby days later.</p>
<p>The Lexus was found near the scene of the shooting death of cemetery caretaker William Reese, 45, in Pennsville, N.J., who was discovered murdered on May 9. Reese's late-model red pickup truck was missing. Miami police are checking if a vehicle found in a parking garage after Versace's murder is the same one.</p>
<p>According to a profile the San Diego Union-Leader ran in May, Cununan graduated in 1987 from the exclusive Bishop's School, a private school in La Jolla, California.</p>
<p>In the yearbook he was named &quot;Most Likely to be Remembered.&quot; He was a member of cross-country team and was named to the San Diego Tribune's All-Academic team in 1986.</p>
<p>The Union-Leader quoted a teammate, Jeffere Ferris as saying of Cunanan: &quot;He certainly loved to shock people. I can believe he would tell people that he killed someone.</p>
<p>&quot;But if he told me that, I'd probably disbelieve him, just like I disbelieved him when he told me what he was doing.&quot;</p>
<p>The Union-Leader also said Cunanan was well-known in Hillcrest, the gay section of San Diego. One unidentified man told the paper &quot;He's quite a social animal.&quot;</p>
<p>The paper said Cunanan was a long-time resident of San Diego.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
