<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733630" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: U.S. ex-hostage gives press award to Turk editor.</title>
<headline>U.S. ex-hostage gives press award to Turk editor.</headline>
<dateline>SARAY, Turkey 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A U.S. journalist formerly held hostage in Lebanon presented a Turkish newspaper editor with a press award on Wednesday in a jail where he is serving a 15-year sentence for his paper's stance on the Kurdish issue.</p>
<p>Terry Anderson, a former Associated Press reporter held for seven years by Lebanon's Islamic Jihad group, praised editor Ocak Isik Yurtcu in a short ceremony at Saray prison in western Turkey.</p>
<p>&quot;We would like to present this award to you for your fight for press freedom in Turkey and to honour you for your courage and integrity,&quot; said Anderson, head of a delegation from the U.S.-based Committee to Protect Journalists (CPJ).</p>
<p>Anderson, CNN television reporter Peter Arnett, Turkish author Yasar Kemal and Yurtcu hugged each other after the presentation of the group's International Press Freedom Award in a sparsely decorated prison waiting room.</p>
<p>Yurtcu was jailed in 1994 for a series of articles about a Kurdish guerrilla campaign in southeast Turkey which appeared in the pro-Kurdish daily Ozgur Gundem.</p>
<p>He was the newspaper's &quot;responsible editor&quot;, which means he managed the reporting staff and was legally responsible for articles appearing in the paper.</p>
<p>Ozgur Gundem often published interviews with leaders of the Kurdistan Workers Party rebel group and drew attention to alleged human rights abuses by Turkish forces. The paper was closed down by a court three years ago for making &quot;separatist propaganda&quot;.</p>
<p>The CPJ says 78 journalists are in jail in Turkey, the highest number of any country in the world.</p>
<p>New Prime Minister Mesut Yilmaz said last weekend he would ask parliament soon to ease Turkey's strict laws on freedom of expression, which are often criticised by Ankara's Western allies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="LEBAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SARAY, Turkey"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
