<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733691" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. unveils new plan to protect Atlantic whales.</title>
<headline>U.S. unveils new plan to protect Atlantic whales.</headline>
<byline>Allan Dowd</byline>
<dateline>PORTLAND, Maine 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Federal regulators, under intense pressure from New England's lobster industry, on Tuesday unveiled a less restrictive proposal to protect endangered Atlantic whales.</p>
<p>The rules are designed to protect whales from entanglement in fishing gear by requiring some equipment modifications and prohibiting lobstering in a few areas when whales are known to be present.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think (the rules) are watered down ... I think they're more workable for both the whales and the fishermen,&quot; said Andrew Rosenberg, the National Marine Fisheries Service's regional administrator.</p>
<p>The new proposal won initial praise from the industry and its political supporters, who had argued a more extensive plan unveiled this year would have cost at least $50 million and forced many lobstermen out of business.</p>
<p>&quot;With this announcement we will be all right,&quot; said Robin Alden, Maine's Commissioner of Marine Resources, who had threatened to sue the federal government over its original proposal.</p>
<p>Alden said the controversy had made lobstermen more aware of the danger some gear poses for whales, in particular the northern right whale, whose population has been reduced to an estimated 300.</p>
<p>&quot;(The whales) now have 7,000 friends looking out for them on the ocean,&quot; Alden said, citing a proposal to train fishermen to assist special rescue crews that will disentangle the whales.</p>
<p>Sen. John Chafee, a Rhode Island Republican who negotiated with Commerce Secretary William Daley to get the rules modified to prevent problems for local fishermen, praised the regulations in a statement late Tuesday.</p>
<p>He called the rules &quot;a reaonable and practical attempt to strike the right balance between preserving a critical community and livelihood on one side, and conserving the right whale species on the other.&quot;</p>
<p>Whales caught in gear can drown or be unable to eat. They can drag a tangle of lines and lobster traps for years. Officials hope to reduce the northern right whale's death rate from entanglement to less than one per year.</p>
<p>The fishing industry had complained they were being singled out for regulation. Rosenberg acknowledged whales also face the danger of being hit by ships, but said his agency cannot regulate the shipping industry.</p>
<p>&quot;This is not just a problem for the fishing industry, it is a problem for people who live on the East Coast and value the (whale) resource,&quot; Rosenberg told reporters.</p>
<p>The rules will also restrict the use of gillnets used off New England and driftnets used off Georgia and Florida. The United States will also work with Canada to coordinate whale protection efforts.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I03000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PORTLAND, Maine"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
