<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733625" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turkey plans secularist education reform this year.</title>
<headline>Turkey plans secularist education reform this year.</headline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's Deputy Prime Minister Bulent Ecevit said on Wednesday the government would this year introduce secularist education reforms at the heart of a row under the former Islamist-led coalition.</p>
<p>&quot;Eight-year uninterrupted education will be put into practice from this year,&quot; Ecevit told his Democratic Left Party deputies at a meeting in parliament.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Mesut Yilmaz's right-left coalition is expected to present a bill to parliament before the assembly's annual holiday, expected to be delayed until August as the new government presses ahead with its programme.</p>
<p>The secularist military ordered former prime minister Necmettin Erbakan in February to introduce state education for children from the age of seven to 15 in a bid to limit the role of religious schools.</p>
<p>Erbakan, the country's first Islamist leader, had stalled on the demand and others designed to curb rising religious activism in public life. He left office in June under intense pressure from the secularist elite.</p>
<p>At the moment, Turkish pupils attend primary school for a minimum of five years after which they can go to religious schools, increasingly popular in recent years.</p>
<p>Ecevit said work on the education bill was underway. He did not name a date for its presentation to parliament.</p>
<p>A government minister told Reuters a multi-party commission had begun work on the eight-year education plan on Tuesday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
