<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733781" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE-Haitian band plays voodoo with Puritan streak.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Haitian band plays voodoo with Puritan streak.</headline>
<byline>Angus MacSwan</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The ancient drum rhythms of African slaves and the beat of modern American pop, infused with the experience of repression and revolution, bubble in the irresistable music of Haitian band RAM.</p>
<p>The stew was cooked up under the roof of a favourite haunt of writer Graham Greene in Port-au-Prince and the group's danceable songs and politically savvy lyrics have made them one of Haiti's most popular bands.</p>
<p>RAM fans include U.S. film-maker Jonathan Demme, who first brought them to international attention when he featured their song &quot;Ibo Lele&quot; (Dreams Come True) on the soundtrack of his movie &quot;Philadelphia,&quot; and singer-songwriter Jimmy Buffet, who has signed them to his Margaritaville record label.</p>
<p>It has just released their new album &quot;Puritan Voudou,&quot; which should help spread the word further. The album's name reflects the mixed heritage of RAM leader Richard Morse, a descendant of Puritan settlers in New England and Haitian slaves. His father was chairman of Latin American studies at Yale and his mother, Emerante de Pradines, a famed Haitian singer and dancer.</p>
<p>Morse, 40, grew up in Connecticut and attended Princeton before moving to Haiti in the mid-1980s to discover his Haitian roots. &quot;I was stuck in both worlds, not quite understanding what my function was. It seems to have come together in my music,&quot; he said at a party for the band at Tap-Tap, a Haitian restaurant in Miami Beach. &quot;I write music and put it to voodoo rhythms. It's danceable pop.&quot;</p>
<p>'VOODOO ROCK' REFLECTS HAITI'S TURMOIL</p>
<p>The style is called &quot;rasin&quot; (roots) or voodoo rock. Other practitioners include Boukman Eksperyans, named after a rebel voodoo priest, who have already tasted international success.</p>
<p>The turmoil of Haiti is reflected in RAM's lyrics, many of which are based on old Haitian folk songs and parables. &quot;People take the songs seriously even though they like to dance and drink. All the parables are being interpreted politically,&quot; Morse said. &quot;People take the songs to make an analysis, so it has a day-to-day impact.&quot;</p>
<p>Morse is also the manager of the legendary Oloffson Hotel in Port-au-Prince, the gingerbread-style mansion that served as the model for the Hotel Trianon in Greene's novel of the Duvalier dictatorship, &quot;The Comedians.&quot; The hotel was once a favourite of celebrities like Richard Burton, Mick Jagger and Truman Capote. Now it is the main watering-hole for diplomats, aid workers, United Nations peacekepers and foreign reporters drawn by Haiti's unending crisis.</p>
<p>Almost every week for years, to a background of coups, dictatorships, revolts and military intervention, RAM has performed to packed crowds at the venerable hotel. The stage is packed, too -- RAM's 15-strong lineup includes three voodoo drummers as well as back-up singers and horn players. Morse plays guitar and sings and his wife Lunise sings and dances.</p>
<p>A GREAT, MYSTICAL PLACE TO MAKE MUSIC</p>
<p>&quot;Historically voodoo and the Oloffson have gone hand-in-hand,&quot; Morse said. &quot;It's a mystical place and a great place to make music. Its inspirational. It's still very Graham Greenish. He could still come to Haiti and write that book.&quot;</p>
<p>Despite an international effort to keep the peace and rehabilitate Haiti, violence often resurfaces and the air of repression has never quite disappeared. Morse says he has had several run-ins with Port-au-Prince Mayor Manno Charlemagne, who is also a popular singer. He accuses Charlemagne of burning RAM's float for this year's Carnival in February, preventing them from playing.</p>
<p>&quot;We left town. We didn't feel safe,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Morse declined to discuss the root of the dispute but rumours in Port-au-Prince say it began with an argument over a large unpaid bill run up by Charlemagne at the Oloffson. The mayor reportedly took offence at lyrics in a RAM song written for Carnival that mentioned &quot;people who sit down and eat with you and then try to poison you.&quot;</p>
<p>Since the incident, RAM have returned to the Oloffson and played a few dates in New Orleans, Miami and elsewhere in the United States. &quot;We're not taking it at jet speed,&quot; Morse said. &quot;People (in the United States) don't know what to make of our music. They're seeing what we do. We put it out and people seem to like it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HAIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
