<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733795" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: EPA says 280 counties will exceed new smog standard.</title>
<headline>EPA says 280 counties will exceed new smog standard.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nationwide, 280 counties will fail to meet the Environmental Protection Agency's strict new limits on smog and 150 counties will not meet its new soot standards, the Environmental Protection Agency said in documents released on Tuesday.</p>
<p>The numbers are lower than were predicted by industry groups battling the EPA's new clean air standards. The groups feared they would have to install expensive new pollution controls to meet the new standards.</p>
<p>In a letter to House Commerce Committee Chairman Thomas Bliley, a Virginia Republican, the EPA said many of the counties in the eastern half of the country would be able to meet the new standards by working with neighboring areas.</p>
<p>&quot;In fact, EPA believes that the vast majority of areas that would not currently meet the updated ozone standards would be able to do so without additional new local measures under a regional plan to address transported air pollution,&quot; EPA acting associate administrator Julie Anderson said.</p>
<p>The regional plan was expected to include trading of emissions credits and new controls on industry in cleaner areas to help protect downwind states from drifting pollution.</p>
<p>Under current standards, 106 counties were out of compliance with smog limits and 41 counties were violating limits on particulate matter or soot.</p>
<p>A statement from the House Commerce Committee said Bliley was &quot;skeptical of EPA's figures as they are not consistent with other lists that illustrate well over 600 counties will violate the new standards.&quot;</p>
<p>House and Senate opponents to the new standards were building support for a bill that would force EPA to delay its new standards and study the health impact of soot over the next five years before enforcing the new rules, which EPA was set to publish this week.</p>
<p>In order to block the new rules, lawmakers would have to secure a two-thirds majority in both chambers to override an expected veto from the White House.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel very comfortable that we can come up with a veto-proof margin in the House,&quot; said Rep. Ron Klink, a Pennsylvania Democrat who co-sponsored the bill to stop the new clean air standards.</p>
<p>He told an industry gathering that the Commerce Committee would likely move the bill in September and then put it to a vote on the House floor soon afterward.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
