<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733784" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: U.S. criticized on California nuclear dump tests.</title>
<headline>U.S. criticized on California nuclear dump tests.</headline>
<byline>Sonali Paul</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-07-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>The U.S. Interior Department does not have the expertise to assess whether a site in the Mojave desert would be safe for a low-level nuclear waste dump, a government watchdog office said Tuesday.</p>
<p>The Interior Department delayed transferring land to the state of California for the dump so it could test whether water could percolate from Ward Valley's trenches and carry radioactivity into groundwater, which could affect drinking water supplies for millions of people.</p>
<p>The Clinton administration sought the new tests after the U.S. Geological Survey found radioactive material in soil near a similar dump in Nevada.</p>
<p>&quot;Interior's underlying reasons for preparing a second supplement were that it should provide a forum for the resolution of the public's concerns about the facility and independently determine if the site is suitable for containing radioactive wastes,&quot; the General Accounting Office said.</p>
<p>&quot;Interior, however, has neither the criteria nor technical expertise in radiological safety matters to independently determine if the site is suitable for a disposal facility,&quot; it said in a report done for Sen. Frank Murkowski, chairman of the Senate Energy Committee.</p>
<p>Murkowski is pushing legislation that would require the Clinton administration to transfer the land to California and make the state conduct tests at the site. He plans to hold a hearing on the GAO report next week.</p>
<p>Ward Valley supporters said the report vindicated their position. &quot;We've complied with the requirements. There's no reason for these continued delays,&quot; said Lisa Kalustian, a spokeswoman for California Gov. Pete Wilson.</p>
<p>Ward Valley opponents complained that the GAO had not been objective and failed to consult them at all. In a July 14 letter to the agency, tribal groups questioned whether &quot;GAO had been directed to reach a preordained conclusion.&quot;</p>
<p>Wilson, a Republican, has pressed the Clinton administration to hand over the land, which state agencies have tested, so California can build a dump for radioactive waste from biotech labs, hospitals and nuclear plants.</p>
<p>State officials have long billed the dump as crucial for helping labs and hospitals get rid of contaminated materials that are piling up at their facilities.</p>
<p>But a separate report by the Congressional Research Service, released Tuesday by opponents of the Ward Valley dump, said 60 percent to 90 percent of the waste that would be going there would be components from nuclear plants, which were more contaminated than hospital gloves, gowns and test tubes.</p>
<p>&quot;This (Congressional Research Service) report demonstrates the need for doing what the Department of Interior is doing -- that is being conservative and cautious and making sure that the safety of the water supply for 12 million Californians is intact,&quot; said David Sandretti, spokesman for California Sen. Barbara Boxer.</p>
<p>Boxer and fellow California Democrat Sen. Diane Feinstein last year effectively killed bipartisan legislation to transfer the Mojave Desert land to the state.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
