<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733769" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Miami police seek serial killer in Versace murder.</title>
<headline>Miami police seek serial killer in Versace murder.</headline>
<byline>Angus MacSwan</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI BEACH 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Police and FBI agents hunted an alleged serial killer and male prostitute they believe murdered fashion king Gianni Versace as royalty, stars, friends and admirers mourned the man who dressed the world's beautiful people.</p>
<p>Versace was shot twice in the head on the steps of his Miami Beach mansion by a lone gunman on Tuesday morning .</p>
<p>Miami Beach Police Chief Richard Barreto said lawmen were searching for Andrew Cunanan, 27, already wanted in connection with four previous murders during a two-week, cross-country killing spree that began in Minneapolis in April.</p>
<p>&quot;We have a number of articles of evidence that tie Mr. Cunanan to that crime,&quot; Barreto said. &quot;He is the only suspect at this time.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Cunanan is known to be a male prostitute who services a broad clientele,&quot; he said, adding he did not know if he had any relationship with Versace, who was homosexual.</p>
<p>As night fell over Miami Beach, usually a pulsating playground for models, fun-seekers and tourists, sombre crowds kept vigil outside the wrought-iron gates of Versace's luxury Mediteranean-style mansion on Ocean Drive.</p>
<p>They built a shrine of flowers and candles on the steps where he had slumped dead, blood pouring from two head wounds, after the killer struck.</p>
<p>Shock and disbelief reverberated from the cafes and model agencies of Miami Beach, an area he had helped revitalise, to the capitals of the fashion world over which he reigned.</p>
<p>&quot;My reaction is one of revolt against such an unnatural and violent death, and one of profound grief,&quot; Giorgio Armani, along with Versace one of Italy's top stylists, said in Rome.</p>
<p>Diana, Princess of Wales, said she was devastated.</p>
<p>Versace, 50, symbolised Italian fashion to the world and dressed the likes of Diana, singers Madonna, Sting and Elton John, and actresses Demi Moore and Liz Hurley. He had built a multi-million-dollar empire after learning the basics of fashion from his mother</p>
<p>He was killed as he walked back home after buying magazines at the News Cafe on Ocean Drive, a beach-front street of renovated art deco hotels and trendy restaurants.</p>
<p>The killer ran away and several hours later police named Cunanan as the sole suspect. Police said he was armed and dangerous and they warned gays and lesbians in particular to be on guard.</p>
<p>&quot;It appears that on occasion he frequents places where gay folks hang out,&quot; FBI special agent Paul Philip said. &quot;Nobody's safe in this. Everybody's at risk. Everybody's got to help us put this guy in jail.&quot;</p>
<p>Law enforcement officers stressed they had no knowledge if Cunanan had a relationship with Versace.</p>
<p>Barreto said a red truck found by police in Miami after Versace's killing belonged to Cunanan's last alleged victim, a New Jersey cemetery caretaker shot dead in May.</p>
<p>Cunanan is on the FBI's list of 10 most wanted criminals. The FBI had distributed about 2,000 wanted posters portraying Cunanan in Florida in recent weeks but had sightings of him from around the country.</p>
<p>Globe-trotting Versace, who dressed some of the world's most beautiful women, was not a permanent resident of Miami Beach but frequently stayed at the white stone mansion, the only private residence on Ocean Drive.</p>
<p>Miami Beach, a finger of land off the Florida mainland, is the centre of Miami's vibrant fashion and music industry.</p>
<p>A senior manager at the News Cafe said Versace was his usual gracious self when he walked to the shop to buy magazines on Tuesday morning. He was a regular customer.</p>
<p>&quot;He would hang out, relax, chill out, watch the parade on Ocean Drive. He didn't come here for business. He was always very gentle, unassuming, gracious, very private,&quot; Ryan Yorke told Reuters.</p>
<p>Other celebrity Miami residents such as singer Gloria Estefan and movie star Sylvester Stallone also lamented the tragedy. &quot;He will never be duplicated,&quot; Stallone said.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no words to describe how I feel right now,&quot; said top designer Gianfrance Ferre. &quot;What happened is absurd, unexplainable, terrible...I feel only infinite pain.&quot;</p>
<p>Princess Diana, a friend and client, said in a statement from the south of France: &quot;I am devastated by the loss of this great and talented man.&quot;</p>
<p>But ordinary people who could probably not afford his lavish designs also mourned.</p>
<p>&quot;It's very sad. Versace was to the fashion world what John Lennon was to music,&quot; said John Winarski, 35, a South Beach resident. &quot;I think Miami Beach will suffer from this.&quot;</p>
<p>Versace's early collections were classic, clean lines but he later began to explore brighter colours and designs inspired by the antiquity of ancient Greece. At last week's &quot;haute couture&quot; shows in Paris, he showed a collection consisting largely of tight black dresses with heavily padded, angular shoulders which he characterised as &quot;a kind of Byzantine minimalism&quot; and &quot;neo-Japanese.&quot;</p>
<p>The grey-haired designer, who often sported stubble on his chin, was born on December 2, 1946. He moved to Milan at the age of 25 and drew his first pret-a-porter collection in 1972.</p>
<p>In 1978 he launched his own Gianni Versace label in a fashion show in Milan.</p>
<p>Versace had been in partnership with his brother Santo and was planning to issue public stock in the company, whose sales rose by 23.5 percent in 1996 to $483 million. But the murder seemed certain to derail any immediate plans to issue shares.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI BEACH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
