<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733783" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: FEATURE-&quot;Old Ironsides&quot; to sail for first time in 116 years.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-&quot;Old Ironsides&quot; to sail for first time in 116 years.</headline>
<byline>Michael Ellis</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>&quot;Huzzah, her sides are made of iron!&quot; a seaman exclaimed as he watched cannon balls from the British warship HMS Guerriere bounce off the thick oak hull of the U.S.S. Constitution during the War of 1812.</p>
<p>So began the nickname and the legend of &quot;Old Ironsides,&quot; the historic U.S. warship that will unfurl its canvas this month and set sail on its own for the first time in 116 years. In celebration of the 200th birthday of the world's oldest commissioned warship, tugboats will tow the refitted frigate from its berth in Boston Harbour into Massachusetts Bay, where it will drop the tow line and set out on a one-hour sail.</p>
<p>The voyage is a far cry from its days of fighting the British off the coast of a young American nation or Barbary pirates off the shores of Tripoli, but it caps a 44-month, $12 million refurbishment and months of training by its crew.</p>
<p>Navy Cmdr. Michael Beck, the current skipper, said his colleagues thought he was crazy when he talked two years ago about one day sailing the national treasure. &quot;I'm not a tall ship sailor by trade, I'm a modern-day sailor,&quot; he said, standing on the deck of the Constitution as his crew practiced setting sails overhead.</p>
<p>But the history of the ship beckoned him to try, he said. The Constitution, one of six frigates whose construction was authorised by President George Washington to beef up the infant U.S. Navy, first floated from its drydock in Boston in October, 1797.</p>
<p>AMERICA'S FIRST CAPTURE OF A BRITISH MAN-OF-WAR</p>
<p>The 44-gun frigate earned its place in history, and the respect of the Royal Navy, with its victory over the Guerriere in the Atlantic Ocean in August, 1812. The capture of the Guerriere was the first time America's tiny navy had taken a British man-of-war. Four months later, the Constitution's defeat of the HMS Java off the coast of Brazil led Britain to order its fleet to confront the American adversaries only when British numbers were superior.</p>
<p>Victorious in all its engagements, the Constitution ended its war service in 1815 but faced another enemy, neglect and deterioration. By 1830, the ship was deemed unseaworthy and condemned to the scrap heap. But a poem entitled &quot;Old Ironsides&quot; by American author Oliver Wendell Holmes aroused national support to pay for its restoration, saving the ship also known as &quot;the Eagle of the Sea&quot; from the scrapheap.</p>
<p>In 1844, the Constitution went on a round-the-world tour and in 1853 it served as the flagship of a squadron searching for American slave traders off the coast of Africa. But &quot;Old Ironsides&quot; was rapidly becoming outdated with the advent of steam-driven ships and the Navy began using it chiefly as a training ship in 1860.</p>
<p>A black-and-white photo taken by a soldier at Fortress Monroe, Virgina, in the summer of 1881 is the only known picture of the Contitution under sail. In October, 1881, the ship sailed for the last time from Newport, Rhode Island, to New London, Connecticut, as part of a training cruise.</p>
<p>On its hundredth anniversary in 1897, the Constitution was docked at the Charlestown Navy Yard in Boston -- within sight of the Bunker Hill Monument commemorating another great battle with the British -- where the ship became a national symbol and a tourist attraction.</p>
<p>HOW DO YOU SAIL AN 18TH CENTURY SHIP?</p>
<p>The most recent restoration, completed last year, strengthened the vessel's hull and made the ship seaworthy again. Then it was up to Beck and his crew to learn how to sail it. &quot;I really didn't know how to do this,&quot; he said. &quot;You could read all the 18th century sailing books until you were blue. The terms are unknown to us.&quot;</p>
<p>Beck's crew learned how to sail an 18th century ship by training on a reproduction of the HMS Bounty and a U.S. Coast Guard ship, the USCG Eagle. But the size of the Constitution, 204 feet (62 metres) long from bow to stern and the tallest of the tall ships with a mainmast 220 feet (67 metres) high, was overwhelming and presented real difficulties, Beck said.</p>
<p>It was unnerving the first time he climbed the rigging up to the yardarms nearly 100 feet (30 metres) above the deck, 23-year-old Petty Officer Louis Padilla said. &quot;The first time I went aloft I was pretty scared. My heart was pumping. But after that I got used to it. It's like riding a bike.&quot;</p>
<p>At first, it took the crew eight hours to trim the sails. Now it takes only minutes and the crew feels ready and excited about their first sail, Beck said.</p>
<p>Provided the seas are calm and winds moderate, tugboats will tow the Constitution into Massachusetts Bay on July 21, when her six sails will be unfurled and she will sail for the first time since 1881. As part of the Navy's active Atlantic fleet again, Constitution and a crew of about 150 will sail in formation with the destroyer USS Ramage and the frigate USS Halyburton. The Blue Angels, the Navy's crack aerial acrobatic team, will perform overhead.</p>
<p>After sailing for about five miles (8 km), its canvas will be furled and tugboats will return the frigate to the Boston Navy Yard. If weather conditions prove unfavourable, the crew will try again on July 22 or 23.</p>
<p>The Navy has not disclosed any further plans after the July sail but the crew is eager to take the ship on tour.</p>
<p>&quot;I hope maybe we can do a mini-cruise, maybe go to New York with the other tall ships. You want to show off the ship,&quot; Petty Officer Padilla said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
