<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733878" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Russian minister criticises Bonn on art booty.</title>
<headline>Russian minister criticises Bonn on art booty.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Russia's Culture Minister Yevgeny Sidorov told a German weekly magazine Moscow would not return war booty seized from Nazi Germany until Bonn did more to compensate Russia for wartime looting and destruction.</p>
<p>&quot;Why should Russia give it back?&quot; Sidorov asked in an interview published in Stern and released ahead of publication on Thursday. &quot;They (the Germans) destroyed wonderful old cities like Smolensk and St Petersberg. Now they keep saying 'Give us back our art treasures'.</p>
<p>&quot;Germans carried off wagon-loads of pictures, frescos, gold and marble. After the war the Americans took much of that,&quot; he said. &quot;Why don't the Germans make a serious attempt to buy back that art and give it back to us?&quot;</p>
<p>Russia's upper and lower houses of parliament have voted in favour of a bill that would prevent Moscow returning &quot;trophy art&quot; seized by the Red Army at the end of World War Two mainly from Germany, but President Boris Yelsin has vetoed the law.</p>
<p>Germany, Russia's biggest trading partner and creditor, wants Moscow to return a vast hoard including a rare Gutenberg bible, gold artefacts supposedly from the site of ancient Troy and paintings by Claude Monet and Henri Matisse.</p>
<p>Sidorov said the issue of returning the treasures could have been resolved a few years ago if Germany had offered gestures of reconciliation, such helping to rebuild a church or museum.</p>
<p>Asked if Bonn had done too little to settle the row, Sidorov replied: &quot;It is not only doing too little, but nothing.&quot;</p>
<p>Many Russians say Moscow should hold on to the seized artwork as compensation for Nazi Germany's destruction of Russian cultural treasures and the suffering of the Soviet Union, which lost 27 million citizens in the war.</p>
<p>But Yeltsin, who values close political and economic ties with Germany and German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, has promise to return the treasure.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="RUSS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
