<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733830" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>SWITZERLAND: Moslems rail as WTO accepts Vatican as observer.</title>
<headline>Moslems rail as WTO accepts Vatican as observer.</headline>
<byline>Robert Evans</byline>
<dateline>GENEVA 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>The World Trade Organisation on Wednesday admitted the Vatican as an observer, sparking demands from Moslem countries that Islamic bodies be granted similar access to its work.</p>
<p>Agreement to grant observer status to the Holy See, which does not claim to be a trading state, came only after India demanded, and received, assurances that the decision would not create a precedent, trade sources said.</p>
<p>The move was welcomed by WTO Director-General Renato Ruggiero, a former Italian trade minister, who said the Holy See had &quot;always played an exceptional role in international relations&quot; by working for peace and development.</p>
<p>Delegates to the ruling General Council of the WTO, which currently has 131 members, approved the decision by consensus and agreed to waive a requirement that observers have to apply for full membership within five years.</p>
<p>But Egypt, backed by Pakistan, Bangladesh and Indonesia, told the Council it should now review requests for observer status from the Organisation of the Islamic Conference, the Islamic Development Bank and the Organisation of African Unity.</p>
<p>All three bodies have asked to be admitted, but major trading powers are known to be opposed to letting in organisations, rather than states, as full observers.</p>
<p>Some global bodies -- like the International Monetary Fund, the World Bank and the United Nations trade and development agency UNCTAD -- are observers in specialised WTO committees.</p>
<p>India initially argued that since the purpose of the WTO was to promote commercial relations between states, it would be wrong to admit an entity which was not engaged in trading.</p>
<p>But after consultations, it accepted assurances from Council chairman Celso Laffer of Brazil that the Vatican was a special case, according to the sources.</p>
<p>In its formal request, the Holy See -- which argues it is a champion of the world's poorer states -- accepted that &quot;the insignificant size of its international trade....does not warrant any special economic or trade policy&quot;.</p>
<p>But it asserted that its presence in international bodies -- it is also an observer in the U.N. -- helped global economic progress, and said it wanted &quot;official and permanent relations&quot; with the WTO to cooperate in its activities.</p>
<p>The 1994 treaty setting up the body &quot;could promote a better international understanding, suitable for the economic progress of all countries, including the least-developed ones&quot;, a statement from the Holy See said.</p>
<p>As an observer, the Vatican will join 30 other countries -- including China and Russia and other smaller developing countries and emerging economies -- whose applications for full membership of the WTO are pending.</p>
<p>Observers are allowed to sit in on most WTO meetings, including the monthly General Council sessions, to attend ministerial conferences -- the WTO's highest forum, held every two years -- and to have access to documents.</p>
<p>Their representatives can speak if there is no objection from full members present, but they cannot block any WTO decisions, all taken by consensus, by witholding approval.</p>
<p>The Vatican is a permanent observer in many bodies of the United Nations system -- to which the WTO does not belong -- and a full member of UNCTAD and the World Intellectual Property Organisation, WIPO.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ISLAM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWITZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="VCAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E512">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GENEVA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SWITZERLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
