<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="733985" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italians mourn Versace -- a son who died far away.</title>
<headline>Italians mourn Versace -- a son who died far away.</headline>
<byline>Philip Pullella</byline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Italians, used to mourning violent death on their own soil, grieved on Wednesday over the murder of fashion king Gianni Versace in a far away city many associate only with television police serials.</p>
<p>But the television tales of cops and criminals turned into grim reality that hit home in a horrific way when Versace was shot twice in the head on the steps of his Miami Beach mansion by a lone gunman.</p>
<p>&quot;This time, the name Miami and all the rest of it evoke in us a real figure, a person whom we knew here in Milan,&quot; said the Corriere Della Sera, the main newspaper in the city where the Versace fashion empire was based.</p>
<p>During decades of Mafia and terrorist violence, Italians had become accustomed to seeing their own sons and daughters killed on the streets of Palermo, Rome or Milan.</p>
<p>This time they watched with horror on television as Miami Beach police draped a plastic sheet over the pool of Versace's blood on the sidewalk.</p>
<p>Pictures of paramedics desperately applying cardiac massage to the fashion king on a cold steel ambulance stretcher were splashed on the front pages of all newspapers.</p>
<p>&quot;Versace: Death in Miami&quot; headlined Rome's La Repubblica newspaper, noting the irony of Versace dying in the city he perhaps loved most.</p>
<p>Even newspaper graphics were reminiscent of the coverage of the big Mafia and terrorism crimes years past.</p>
<p>They showed detailed drawings of Versace walking towards his Mediterranean-style villa with a bundle of newspapers under his arms. A man with a gun appears in the next comic book frame and in the third, Versace languishes on the ground.</p>
<p>Still, despite the area's violent image, friends said Versace loved it because of its rhythm, its Latino influence, its ocean breeze and and even its dangerous side.</p>
<p>&quot;Miami was in his heart,&quot; La Repubblica said. &quot;He would say 'tomorrow I'm flying to Miami' like other people would say 'I'm going to get a coffee.'</p>
<p>&quot;In Miami, Gianni Versace found death, with a pile of newspapers under his arm, outside his front door,&quot; it added.</p>
<p>&quot;He fell on the steps of a villa that should have been a monument to his life and instead will always be the mausoleum of his death,&quot; the newspaper said.</p>
<p>As Miami Beach police searched for Andew Cunanan, a 27-year-old male prostitute suspected in the killing, tributes continued to pour in for the man who dressed the world's beautiful people.</p>
<p>Valentino, one of Italy's best-known stylists, wrote a first-person farewell letter to Versace published in Turin's La Stampa newspaper.</p>
<p>&quot;Dear Gianni, they asked me to remember you. I am doing it, broken down and devasted, only because you are a friend in this world of fashion that is often cruel and without rules,&quot; he wrote.</p>
<p>&quot;You managed to keep up a sense of great human dignity and fair play that is very rare.&quot;</p>
<p>The gala closing of the Rome high fashion shows that was to have been held on Wednesday night on Rome's Spanish Steps was cancelled in a sign of mourning.</p>
<p>On Wednesday morning, tourists visiting the steps found two bunches of roses with notes attached. One was a handwritten poem -- the other simply said: &quot;You are fashion&quot;.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFAS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GOBIT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
