<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="734050" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: FLOOD DAMAGE TO CZECH INDUSTRY SEEN AT CZK 8-10BLN.</title>
<headline>FLOOD DAMAGE TO CZECH INDUSTRY SEEN AT CZK 8-10BLN.</headline>
<byline>Jan Lopatka</byline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Czech industry suffered an estimated loss of up to 10 billion crowns in the massive flooding which hit the eastern part of the country last week, an Industry and Trade Ministry spokesman said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Hundreds of companies have been forced to reduce or shut production in the worst flooding this century, caused by torrential rains last week which killed dozens of people and cut major sections of rail and road connections.</p>
<p>&quot;The ministry estimated the loss in the industrial sector at eight to 10 billon crowns,&quot; ministry spokesman Miroslav Konvalina told Reuters. He said the estimate included direct damage and losses from stoppages of production and sales.</p>
<p>He stressed that the estimate was rough and preliminary.</p>
<p>A total of 43 people have died in the flooding, the Czech CTK news agency reported. Several towns and villages were still battling with high water, but the flooding has receded in most areas.</p>
<p>Gross estimates of the entire damage to the flooded area -- including damage to homes, crops, and businesses -- range from between 50 to 100 billion crowns.</p>
<p>Prague-based investment house WoodCommerz said in a report to investors on Wednesday that the net effect on gross domestic product should be &quot;neutral or slightly negative this year.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;The floods would subtract up to a maximum one percentage point from our earlier 1997 forecast of two percent (GDP growth),&quot; WoodCommerz said in its report.</p>
<p>It said actual losses would depend on how quickly production and transport resumed in the area, but the losses would be tempered, macro-economically at least, by an expected surge in building in the flooded area.</p>
<p>The afflicted companies included:</p>
<p>* The country's three largest steelmills, Nova Hut a.s. , Vitkovice a.s. , Trinecke Zelezarny a.s. , and the largest coal mine OKD a.s. .</p>
<p>The mills have had to cut output as produced steel has piled up in rail cars unable to move, and raw materials have been unable to make it to the plants.</p>
<p>* Regional power distributor Severomoravska Energetika a.s. estimated its loses at around 450 million crowns, mostly from a loss of sales and damage to infrastructure.</p>
<p>* Tyre maker Barum Continental, a unit of Germany's Continental AG , has lost about one billion crowns, the economic daily Hospodarske Noviny said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>* Skoda Automobilova a.s., a unit of Volkswagen AG, halted production of its flagship Felicia car last week due to a lack of supplies, but has since returned to full output. No loss estimates have been made available.</p>
<p>* Fixed-line monopoly SPT Telecom a.s. has said its losses in sales and damaged facilities would be in the &quot;hundreds of millions of crowns&quot;.</p>
<p>Agriculture Minister Josef Lux has said the floods caused roughly 12 billion crown damage to crops, livestock, buildings, landscape and water installations including dykes, dams, cleaning stations and others.</p>
<p>However, Lux said that no shortages were expected, and that no agricultural imports would be organised.</p>
<p>Over 1,000 houses and apartment buildings have been destroyed, thousands of others have been damaged.</p>
<p>The government and the parliament have approved a multi-billion-crown relief package including an issue of up to five billion crown tranche in state bonds, and the release five billion from privatisation proceeds.</p>
<p>-- Prague Newsroom, 420-2-2423-0003</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I11000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I16000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I22100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I48110">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
