<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="734384" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>SINGAPORE: Petron tenders to buy gasoline after two years.</title>
<headline>Petron tenders to buy gasoline after two years.</headline>
<dateline>SINGAPORE 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Philippines oil refiner Petron Corp has issued its first spot tender in about two years to import unleaded gasoline for delivery in August, a company official said on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The tender seeks 70,000 barrels of 95-octane unleaded gasoline for August 11-15 delivery, on a cost-and-freight basis to Bataan.</p>
<p>The tender closes on July 18 and is vaild for the day.</p>
<p>&quot;The last time we issued a tender to buy gasoline was in 1995,&quot; the official said.  </p>
<p>The official said the tender was issued due to increased domestic demand.</p>
<p>But industry sources said the import requirement was also partly due to the unexpected shutdown of a 15,000-barrel-per-day (bpd) thermal cracker on June 20 following an explosion.</p>
<p>The unit, which produces diesel, gasoline and liquefied petroleum gas, is expected to be shut for about one month.</p>
<p>Petron, which is 40-percent owned by Saudi Aramco, operates a 155,000-bpd refinery in Bataan, north of the capital Manila.  </p>
<p>The official said Petron went ahead with the decision to issue the import tender despite the de facto devaluation of the peso last week.</p>
<p>The peso has lost about 11.74 percent of its value after the central bank's announcement last Friday that it would allow the peso to trade in a wider band against the U.S. dollar. The peso was last trading at 28.90/29.00 to the dollar.</p>
<p>&quot;We cannot postpone our purchase. There is a need for the product,&quot; the official said.  </p>
<p>The official said Petron went ahead with the purchase as it was unclear if the substantial weakening of the peso would be temporary or permanent.</p>
<p>But the company is evaluating the need to raise domestic petrol prices following the devaluation, the official said.</p>
<p>Petron, the country's biggest refiner, reduced the price of unleaded premium gasoline by 20 centavos to 9.9365 pesos per litre on July 2 in reaction to lower Singapore posted prices.</p>
<p>-- Raj Rajendran, Singapore Newsroom (+65-870 3093)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SINGP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I14000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M143">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SINGAPORE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
