<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="734341" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: FEATURE - Foreign firms seek success amid Japan reform.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Foreign firms seek success amid Japan reform.</headline>
<byline>Yoko Nishikawa</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign financial institutions are gingerly returning to Japan, hoping for another crack at the Tokyo market as it undergoes wide-ranging reforms as part of Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto's &quot;Big Bang&quot; deregulation plan.</p>
<p>Adept at competing in a deregulated environment and equipped with products that are in hot demand, the firms stand a good chance this time of overwhelming their Japanese rivals.</p>
<p>&quot;Many Japanese financial institutions have not decided how to survive in the coming deregulation by selecting their expertise, but we have,&quot; said Shinji Yamada, managing director of Credit Suisse Financial Products (CSFP) in Tokyo.</p>
<p>&quot;If we can literally take Big Bang's three main pillars of 'free, fair, global' at face value, the reforms should benefit foreign financial institutions,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>In recent years, high costs and complex regulations have been blamed for an exodus of foreign financial institutions. Many have moved their Asian headquarters to more open and less costly financial centres, such as Singapore or Hong Kong.</p>
<p>FOREIGN FIRMS EXPAND TOKYO OPERATIONS</p>
<p>But now, foreign firms, which are keen to take a bigger slice of the Japanese investment pie away from local firms, are expanding their operations in Tokyo.</p>
<p>CSFP, a London-based global derivatives power house specialising in risk management products, chose Tokyo as the place for its first overseas branch in April, eyeing demand for credit derivatives products in Japan under the deregulation.</p>
<p>Some of the top U.S. mutual fund players are also paying close attention to Tokyo.</p>
<p>Fidelity Select Brokerage Services (Japan), a unit of Fidelity Brokerage Services, has recently received a licence allowing it to deal, broker and sell securities in Tokyo.</p>
<p>Merrill Lynch International Capital Management, a Japanese unit of Merrill Lynch Asset Management, intends to enter the investment trust business within this year.</p>
<p>The number of foreign securities houses in Japan has been gradually increasing, Ministry of Finance (MOF) data show. In early July, it rose to 58 firms, compared with 48 in 1993.</p>
<p>SOME EXPERTS COUNSEL CAUTION</p>
<p>But some experts say it will take time and patience for foreign firms to profit in the Tokyo markets as the reforms are not going to happen overnight.</p>
<p>&quot;Big Bang is a handy label, but it is a common misperception that with Big Bang...a whole bunch of things are going to happen. It will be an evolutionary step by step process,&quot; said William Kirk, chairman of the executive committee at the Institute of Foreign Bankers (IFB) in Tokyo.</p>
<p>Hashimoto unveiled plans late last year to liberalise Japan's financial markets by 2001 under the Big Bang reforms in an attempt to catch up with reforms carried out more than a decade ago in Europe and North America.</p>
<p>EXPERIENCE BACK HOME MAKES FOREIGN FIRMS UPBEAT</p>
<p>Investment expertise, global research and management networks and experience having undergone similar reforms around the world have made foreign firms confident in taking the lead in coming changes in Japan's financial sector.</p>
<p>&quot;I think money from 1,200 trillion yen ($10.61 trillion) worth of Japanese individual financial assets will naturally flow into products offered by foreign financial institutions,&quot; said CSFP's Yamada.</p>
<p>Goldman Sachs Investment Trust Management Co Ltd, an affiliate of Goldman Sachs and Group, attracted 420 billion yen ($3.71 billion) in individual investment funds by the end of April, the largest amount out of the 15 foreign investment trust firms operating in Japan. The company launched its first investment fund just a year ago.</p>
<p>But experts note that Japanese financial institutions, especially with large assets and domestic sales channels, will not remain silent in the face of challenges from foreign firms.</p>
<p>&quot;If Japanese financial institutions eagerly reorganise their company structures and accumulate the know-how (of asset management), they will be able catch up with foreign firms in two or three years,&quot; said a foreign brokerage house analyst.</p>
<p>&quot;I never under-estimate the power of Japanese banks,&quot; IFB's Kirk said. &quot;Dominant market shares, presence, nationwide networks for large banks certainly give them a lot of advantage from a customer-marketing standpoint.&quot;</p>
<p>SINK OR SWIM UNDER BIG BANG REFORMS</p>
<p>Foreign financial institutions are well aware of a possible downsizing of the financial sector as competition is expected to intensify.</p>
<p>It is in the investment trust fund arena, where the deregulation is opening the door for a wider variety of products, that foreign firms have taken steps to meet the diverse and more sophisticated demand from Japanese clients.</p>
<p>One way they have done so is by forming alliances with local firms.</p>
<p>The Franklin Templeton Group, which manages funds in excess of $200 billion, recently announced that it had signed an agreement on strategic cooperation with Sumitomo Life Insurance Co regarding equity investment in Asia.</p>
<p>&quot;We specialise in global asset management, while Sumitomo Life has a large client base (in Japan). So both of us will benefit from this tie-up,&quot; said Hiroshi Yoh, president of Templeton Investment Management Co in Tokyo, said. Putnam Investors Fund, the sixth-largest mutual fund manager in the United States with total assets of nearly $180 billion, formed a strategic alliance with top life insurer Nippon Life Insurance Co to manage Japanese pension fund assets in June.</p>
<p>In the wake of the parent company's action, Takehiko Watanabe, managing director of Putnam Advisory Company Inc, the Japanese subsidiary of Putnam Investments told Reuters: &quot;It is possible that we (Tokyo branch) will form an alliance or a joint venture in the future with Japanese trust management firms that are affiliated with banks or life insurers.&quot;</p>
<p>Currently, Japan's investment trust market is worth about 45 trillion yen ($398 billion) against about 200 trillion yen ($1.76 trillion) in the United States.</p>
<p>($1=113 yen)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I81502">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C311">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C34">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E511">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
