<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="734462" id="root" date="1997-07-16" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: FEATURE-Lone Englishwoman battles for China rule in HK. [CORRECTED 02:50 GMT]</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Lone Englishwoman battles for China rule in HK. [CORRECTED 02:50 GMT]</headline>
<byline>Peter Humphrey</byline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-07-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>A grey-haired, elderly Englishwoman seems an odd crusader at first in the heady politics of Hong Kong since its takeover by China.</p>
<p>But the peppery politician Elsie Tu, straight-backed at 84, is no ordinary pensioner. She's witnessed plenty of upheaval and plans to see more change from inside the political arena.</p>
<p>Vilified by colonials for taking China's side, the former Christian missionary from Newcastle-upon-Tyne is a household name in Hong Kong as champion of the underdog, anti-corruption campaigner and veteran legislator.</p>
<p>Age is apparently no obstacle. Elsie Tu is embarking on a second political career among a new elite in the era of Chinese rule.</p>
<p>She is the sole Western expatriate member in the controversial unelected legislature that took over when China resumed sovereignty from Britain on July 1, ending 156 years of humiliating colonial rule.</p>
<p>Her reward for a grassroots left-wing political career and her constant vilification of the colonial authorities, perhaps.</p>
<p>&quot;I can't remember a time in my life when I wasn't geared to doing some kind of service for a community. I would never, never give up on life because once you do that you're just a vegetable waiting to die,&quot; Elsie Tu told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>She sits in a book-lined study in her flat, tucked away on the roof of a 1,500-pupil high school, which she and her husband Andrew Tu have lovingly developed over the past 40 years.</p>
<p>ONE MISSION CAREER CHANGES INTO ANOTHER</p>
<p>&quot;We didn't really want to come to Hong Kong,&quot; she said. The Chinese civil war swept her out of China almost 50 years ago, when the price of rice could double in hours, when she had to barter a Bible for a few eggs, when communists saw missionaries as spies.</p>
<p>She gave up her missionary life in Hong Kong and embarked on a mission of her own, at odds with the colonial establishment.</p>
<p>&quot;The first thing I learned was that everything was corrupt, right to the very top. Things were as bad as, if not worse, than we had seen in China,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>As mainland refugees poured into Hong Kong, Elsie began a reform-crusade when she saw infants forced to work to earn food, officialdom keeping education from the poor and taking bribes.</p>
<p>&quot;We bought an army tent and pitched it and brought in 30 students for very low fees. I had to go and find an additional job to earn money to support the school.&quot;</p>
<p>From this humble start among the have-nots in the squatter areas of Wong Tai Sin grew Elsie's successful Mu Kuang School, its motto &quot;Love, Light and Understanding&quot;, now set in the working class industrial area of Kwun Tong.</p>
<p>From her school headquarters Elsie launched a community service and political career, famed for a &quot;problem clinic&quot; where hundreds, sometimes thousands, of people, many illiterate, lined up to tell her their woes and injustices, and Elsie would dash out letters to authorities in a bid to right wrongs.</p>
<p>CRUSADE BRINGS CLASH WITH CORRUPT POLICE</p>
<p>Her crusade brought conflict. The police, in an era when corruption was legend, accused Elsie Tu of paying hooligans and fomenting riots in 1966 (corrects year from 1996), when thousands of youths ran amok ostensibly over a fare rise on the harbour ferries.</p>
<p>Tu denies she fanned the unrest and blames it on triad gangs linked to corrupt policemen. She also denies a role in Maoist riots here inspired by the China's Cultural Revolution turmoil.</p>
<p>Her efforts to expose corruption helped bring a major crackdown against the police in the 1970s, spurring creation of the powerful Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC).</p>
<p>Since 1963 Elsie has served variously as a local councillor, advisor to the colonial government and legislator, under rules that until five years ago allowed scant democracy.</p>
<p>But she was defeated in 1995 when Hong Kong elected a new Legislative Council with the most democratic electoral system so far, engineered in the twilight of British rule through reforms of Governor Chris Patten.</p>
<p>&quot;They drew the constituency line through my school and I was ousted,&quot; Elsie railed bitterly. She viewed the poll as rigged in favour of Martin Lee's victorious Democrats, the biggest party in the former legislature, which was scrapped at the handover.</p>
<p>Elsie attacks both Patten and Lee, whose party captured her seat, believing neither is truly democratic.</p>
<p>Tu's 59 fellow legislators are drawn from an elite local Chinese pool of pro-Beijing politicians and tycoons. Polls show she is the most popular member of that provisional legislature.</p>
<p>Tu is the only expatriate to receive Hong Kong's new public service award, the Grand Bauhinia, which was instituted after the handover to rival the knighthoods that the colonial power previously conferred on Hong Kong stalwarts.</p>
<p>Unlike her pro-democracy opponents, Tu beams confidence that China will not lay an iron hand on Hong Kong. &quot;I don't think they really want to interfere,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-07-16"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-07-16"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
