<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789584" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Moslem rebels kill 14 civilians in Algeria - papers.</title>
<headline>Moslem rebels kill 14 civilians in Algeria - papers.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Suspected Moslem guerrillas have killed 14 civilians by cutting their throats or heads in four attacks across Algeria this week, Algerian newspapers said on Saturday.</p>
<p>Four girls, one woman and three men were killed, their heads cut off, in a rebel attack on Thursday in Ouled Yahia village in Tiaret province, 240 km (150 miles) southeast of Algiers, El Watan and Liberte newspapers said.</p>
<p>Suspected rebels slashed the throats of two shepherds, aged 17 and 22, in the same day in Bab Taza in the province of Tlemcen, about 440 km (275 miles) west Algiers, they said.</p>
<p>A truck driver and his assistant were killed in the same way near the town of Bou-Saada, some 200 km (125 km) south of Algiers, the newspapers said.</p>
<p>Two other civilians were killed on Wednesday in Oued Djer village in Ain Defla province, some 130 km (80 miles) southwest of Algiers, the newspapers said.</p>
<p>The latest killings brought to more than 1,000 the number of people reported slaughtered in a series of mass killings since June 5, when Algeria held a general election which voters and officials hoped would help usher in peace and stability.</p>
<p>Most of the dead, around 700, were civilians, but Algerian newspapers also said that 300 rebels were killed in a two-week government military offensive in July.</p>
<p>Algeria's President Liamine Zeroual, speaking against a background of years of bloodshed which Algerian officials blame on Moslem fundamentalists, told a police meeting on Thursday that his country had made &quot;heavy sacrifices in its struggle against the forces of evil&quot;.</p>
<p>About 60,000 people have been killed in the North African country since early 1992 when the authorities cancelled a general election in which radical Islamists had taken a huge lead.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
