<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789588" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: SOCCER-SCHALKE ROCK DORTMUND WITH LATE WINNER.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-SCHALKE ROCK DORTMUND WITH LATE WINNER.</headline>
<byline>Erik Kirschbaum</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Substitute Ingo Anderbruegge fired UEFA Cup champions Schalke to a 1-0 victory over European Cup winners Borussia Dortmund with a late goal in the German first division on Saturday.</p>
<p>In the always emotional 108th match between the  Ruhr Valley rivals, midfielder Anderbruegge came off the bench with 12 minutes left to drill home the winner in the 86th minute, watched by a crowd of 68,200.</p>
<p>&quot;It is a great feeling to beat Dortmund,&quot; said Anderbruegge. &quot;This win means so much for our team.&quot;</p>
<p>Schalke, with two wins and one defeat in three matches, climbed to third in the Bundesliga behind Karlsruhe and Kaiserslautern while Borussia Dortmund are fifth behind champions Bayern Munich.</p>
<p>&quot;That we beat the (European) Champions isn't as interesting to me as picking up three points with the win,&quot; said Schalke trainer Huub Stevens, who said sweltering conditions made it difficult for the players.</p>
<p>Dortmund trainer Nevio Scale said: &quot;I am not at all satisfied with my team. They played poorly and Schalke deserved to win. We were unable to play fluidly after the match on Wednesday against Cologne. But we have to accept this defeat without making a drama out of it.&quot;</p>
<p>Dortmund defender Juergen Kohler said Anderbruegge was able to take advantage of his mistake, but warned would-be detractors against rushing to judgment about the team or its new trainer.&quot;</p>
<p>Scala replaced Ottmar Hitzfeld after the European Cup triumph.</p>
<p>&quot;Schalke played well and made it very difficult for us,&quot; Kohler said. &quot;But there is no problem with our system. Rather, we just lack some freshness at the moment.&quot;</p>
<p>Karlsruhe lead the early-season table after a 3-1 win over Arminia Bielefeld, newly promoted Kaiserslautern slipping to second after drawing 0-0 with Cologne, while Bayern Munich notched their first win, 5-2 over Wolfsburg.</p>
<p>For Karlsruhe, German international Thomas Haessler scored from the spot and two late goals by Belgian international Gunther Schepens sealed their second win in three matches.</p>
<p>Karlsruhe played most of the game with 10 men after libero Thomas Hengen was sent off in the 23rd minute for repeated fouls.</p>
<p>Bayern Munich, after just one goal in their first two matches, went on a five-goal spree against newly promoted Wolfsburg.</p>
<p>Striker Giovane Elber and Ruggiero Rizzitelli each scored twice and Thomas Strunz added the fifth.</p>
<p>&quot;I am only partially satisfied,&quot; said Bayern trainer Giovanni Trapattoni. &quot;In the first half we played well and really applied the pressure. But we fell apart in the second half. The win was neverthless deserved.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
