<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789587" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: CRICKET-TAYLOR LEADS AUSTRALIA CLOSER TO THE ASHES.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-TAYLOR LEADS AUSTRALIA CLOSER TO THE ASHES.</headline>
<byline>Steve Tongue</byline>
<dateline>NOTTINGHAM, England 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australian captain Mark Taylor took a blinding catch in the slips and made a polished 45 as his side took a firm grip on the fifth test -- and the Ashes -- against England at Trent Bridge on Saturday.</p>
<p>Taylor put on 51 for the first wicket with Matthew Elliott as Australia began their second innings looking to capitalise on a first innings lead of 114.</p>
<p>Elliott fell to a magnificent diving catch by John Crawley on the square-leg boundary as he tried to hook Andy Caddick.</p>
<p>But Taylor and Greg Blewett ensured that England, who must win the test to have a chance of winning the series, ended the third day thinking more realistically only of survival.</p>
<p>Both were dismissed, along with Mark Waugh, before the close but Australia, who lead the six-test series 2-1, finished on 167 for four, an overall lead of 281.</p>
<p>Taylor, like Elliott, miscued a hook off Ben Hollioake and skied a simple chance to Nasser Hussain at mid-wicket and Mark Waugh was lbw to Dean Headley.</p>
<p>Blewett, ignoring the scoreboard which was posting his name as &quot;Blewitt&quot;, consolidated Australia's dominance, however, with a fine 60.</p>
<p>Unfortunately it ended when he was adjudged to have gloved another attempted pull off Caddick to wicketkeeper Alec Stewart. Replays suggested, however, that he may not have touched the ball.</p>
<p>The day started well for England, who resumed on 188 for four in reply to Australia's first innings of 427.</p>
<p>The Surrey pair of Graham Thorpe, dropped in the slips by Steve Waugh on 31, and Adam Hollioake extended their fifth wicket stand to 102 before both departed in the space of five deliveries.</p>
<p>Adam Hollioake was the first to go for 45 when he edged a delivery from Paul Reiffel and Taylor took a fine catch diving low to his right at first slip.</p>
<p>In the next over, Thorpe, on 53, gave leg-spinner Shane Warne his fourth wicket when Blewett snapped him up at short-leg.</p>
<p>Ben Hollioake, denied the chance of batting with his brother, made an assured 28 but Reiffel and Glenn McGrath worked their way through the lower order to dismiss England for 313. McGrath took four for 71 and Warne four for 86.</p>
<p>McGrath said: &quot;We're in a pretty good position. If we get a lead of 400 tomorrow, that's pretty daunting.</p>
<p>&quot;The wicket will start to turn a bit more, which should help Shane.&quot;</p>
<p>England coach David Lloyd said: &quot;We bowled with great fire, determination, commitment and endeavour.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm pleased with a number of things from the match. Both Hollioakes looked assured, strong and comfortable. But we're firmly second favourites.&quot;</p>
<p>Earlier in the day, Michael Atherton denied a report in a British newspaper that he had offered to resign as England captain on the eve of the match.</p>
<p>Atherton said he intended to continue as captain at least until the end of the series.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NOTTINGHAM, England"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
