<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789591" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: SOCCER-TWO-GOAL ASPRILLA FILLS THE GAP FOR NEWCASTLE.</title>
<headline>SOCCER-TWO-GOAL ASPRILLA FILLS THE GAP FOR NEWCASTLE.</headline>
<byline>Alan Baldwin</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Colombian international Faustino Asprilla scored twice on Saturday to give Newcastle a winning start to the new English season and make up for injured Alan Shearer's absence.</p>
<p>The fiery attacker grabbed the fastest goal of the day as last season's runners-up beat Sheffield Wednesday 2-1 at St James' Park, plundering the first after one minute 48 seconds and the second in the 72nd minute.</p>
<p>The goals calmed anxious Magpies fans and answered one of the big pre-season questions -- namely who would score Newcastle's goals in the absence of Shearer and last season's strike partner Les Ferdinand.</p>
<p>Ferdinand has been sold to Tottenham, who host champions Manchester United on Sunday.</p>
<p>Asprilla also fulfilled another popular prediction -- that a foreigner would score the first goal in a premier league flooded by fresh imports over the summer.</p>
<p>Italian Benito Carbone equalised for Wednesday in the eighth minute but Newcastle, who play Croatia Zagreb in a European Cup qualifier next week, made the running and had three goals disallowed in the first half.</p>
<p>A home-grown player outscored the Colombian, with Coventry's Dion Dublin hitting the first hat-trick of the season in a late 3-2 home win against Chelsea on a day of sweltering heat around the country.</p>
<p>&quot;It's only my second one (hat-trick) in the premier league, it's just a great time to get it,&quot; said Dublin, whose goals came in the 41st, 82nd and 88th minutes. That victory, by perennial relegation-battlers against the F.A. Cup holders, was the surprise of the day and made Coventry league leaders after one match.</p>
<p>Liverpool, with Paul Ince making his debut as captain, also nearly suffered an upset.</p>
<p>The favourites to replace Manchester United as champions made a shaky start at Wimbledon despite strong performances from new signings Ince and German international KarlHeinz Riedle.</p>
<p>Marcus Gayle sent Wimbledon ahead in the 55th minute before Michael Owen equalised from a penalty, awarded after Vinnie Jones felled Riedle.</p>
<p>&quot;It was about 105 degrees and most of the players were dehydrated,&quot; said Wimbledon manager Joe Kinnear. &quot;But both sides deserved to get beat, I thought it was a cracking game considering the conditions.&quot;</p>
<p>Arsenal, another team fancied for the title, drew 1-1 at former manager George Graham's Leeds. Ian Wright put Arsenal ahead in the 35th minute but Dutch signing Jimmy-Floyd Hasselbaink equalised in the 42nd.</p>
<p>Roy Hodgson, Ince's former coach at Internazionale, had a winning premier league start at his new club Blackburn. They beat Derby 1-0 at home. &quot;Had we been able to play in the second half as we did in the first, it might have been a more comfortable ride for me,&quot; said a relieved Hodgson after Derby challenged strongly in the final minutes.</p>
<p>Kevin Gallagher headed the goal in the 20th minute.</p>
<p>Crystal Palace's new Italian signing from Juventus, Attilio Lombardo, scored on his debut, splitting the Everton defence as promoted Palace won 2-1.</p>
<p>Lombardo scored in the 36th minute and also set up the second penalty goal for Bruce Dyer in the 77th.</p>
<p>Newcomers Barnsley, appearing in the top flight for the first time in their 110-year history, made a dream start at home to West Ham when Neil Redfearn scored after nine minutes but faded and lost 2-1.</p>
<p>&quot;It wasn't an ideal first game,&quot; said West Ham manager Harry Redknapp. &quot;Barnsley away was always going to be a big crowd...it was a tough game.</p>
<p>&quot;I said in the dressing room that I felt (Barnsley manager) Danny Wilson would be saying 'get steamed into these southern softies and they might wilt a bit'. But we didn't, it was a good all round performance.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
