<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789583" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: Holbrooke, Milosevic resume Bosnia face-off.</title>
<headline>Holbrooke, Milosevic resume Bosnia face-off.</headline>
<byline>Jovan Kovacic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. envoy Richard Holbrooke renewed his carrot and stick Balkan diplomacy on Saturday, urging Yugoslav President Slobodan Milosevic to live up to his commitments under the 1995 Dayton peace treaty.</p>
<p>Serbian state television showed footage of the start of a second round of talks between the two men with Momcilo Krajisnik, the Serb member of the Bosnian presidency, also in attendance.</p>
<p>Krajisnik is the most powerful man in the Bosnian Serb republic after Radovan Karadzic, the former Bosnian Serb president and indicted war criminal.</p>
<p>His attendance showed that Bosnia and Karadazic figured high on the agenda.</p>
<p>&quot;The discussions (with Milosevic) were intense as always,&quot; Holbrooke told reporters as he entered his hotel after Friday night's first round.</p>
<p>&quot;It would not be fair to disclose anything at this time,&quot; added Holbrooke, architect of the Dayton treaty which ended the wars in Bosnia and Croatia.</p>
<p>Holbrooke and Milosevic, both adroit and ruthless players in peace diplomacy, matched wits for 3-1/2 hours before agreeing to an unscheduled extension of their talks on Saturday morning.</p>
<p>The envoy and his staff had little sleep during the night, a U.S. official said. One diplomat described the meeting as &quot;the first round of a slugging match&quot;.</p>
<p>Belgrade analysts said the fact that the talks were to be continued on Saturday raised expectations of results and showed how high the stakes were, both for the fate of the peace accords and Yugoslavia's future.</p>
<p>But diplomats and Serbian officials familiar with Friday night's parley were cautious about the outcome.</p>
<p>&quot;The price of compliance (with the Dayton accords) is very high,&quot; a senior Yugoslav source warned.</p>
<p>&quot;I did not see anyone coming any closer (to agreement). We were nibbling away but no one ate well,&quot; he said of the talks, which took place over dinner in Milosevic's White Court palace.</p>
<p>Diplomats expected Holbrooke threatened Milosevic with renewed economic sanctions unless he abided by his Dayton commitments, which include handing over his former protege Karadzic and others wanted by a U.N. war crimes tribunal in The Hague.</p>
<p>Under a deal Holbrooke brokered a year ago, Karadzic should have stepped down and left politics.</p>
<p>But he has not, and still rules with an iron fist the Serb-controlled half of Bosnia, persistently circumventing the accords and undermining his successor as Bosnian Serb president, Biljana Plavsic.</p>
<p>Milosevic's choice is stark. Handing over Karadzic, revered by some 600,000 Serb refugees from Bosnia and Croatia, could be politically very damaging to him at home.</p>
<p>But his moribund economy cannot continue without a life-saving infusion of fresh capital for much longer and feed its 11 million people, of whom already one third are poor and another 600,000 starving.</p>
<p>&quot;It pains us to see this happening - we don't want to do it (impose new sanctions),&quot; the current U.S. envoy for former Yugoslavia, Robert Gelbard, said. He stressed the United States had &quot;enormous sympathy&quot; for the people of Yugoslavia.</p>
<p>&quot;Holbrooke is bringing a bagful of carrots and sticks. It's up to Milosevic to choose which he would rather have,&quot; one diplomat said.</p>
<p>Milosevic also faced tough questioning about Serbia's handling of human rights in its mostly-Albanian populated province of Kosovo, freedom of the media in Serbia and the slow pace of democratic and economic reforms.</p>
<p>And Holbrooke is not giving him any maneouvering space. He ruled out a proposal from Karadzic that he be tried within Bosnia under international supervision.</p>
<p>Calling Karadzic's proposal &quot;bizarre and totally unacceptable&quot;, Holbrooke told CNN the former Bosnian Serb leader could expect no special deals.</p>
<p>&quot;That is out of the question. He has got to be brought to justice,&quot; Holbrooke said in an interview from Belgrade.</p>
<p>Holbrooke flew into Belgrade on Friday fresh from having resolved a row between Bosnia's ethnic leaders over diplomatic posts which had triggered a punitive international cut-off of contacts with Bosnian ambassadors.</p>
<p>Under the deal, a Moslem will be the Bosnian ambassador to the United Nations, a Serb will be ambassador to Washington and a Croat will be envoy to Japan, according to Holbrooke.</p>
<p>Holbrooke had come out of self-imposed &quot;retirement&quot; from the diplomatic service for the second time in a year to salvage key aspects of the peace treaty he engineered.</p>
<p>Members of Bosnia's multi-ethnic collective presidency also agreed on the composition of a joint military commission and on a single area code for Bosnia's telephone network to support a reintegration of the country envisaged by the peace pact.</p>
<p>&quot;These agreements are full evidence of Western determination (to enforce the peace agreement),&quot; Holbrooke told reporters after the agreement reached in Sarajevo. &quot;These are steps forward, and pretty solid ones.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
