<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789627" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>HUNGARY: MOTOR RACING-HILL SPRINGS SURPRISE IN BUDAPEST.</title>
<headline>MOTOR RACING-HILL SPRINGS SURPRISE IN BUDAPEST.</headline>
<byline>Timothy Collings</byline>
<dateline>BUDAPEST 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Reigning world champion Damon Hill stunned everyone including himself on Saturday when he claimed third place on the starting grid for Sunday's Hungarian Grand Prix.</p>
<p>Since leaving Williams at the end of last year, the Briton has struggled to impose himself with his new Arrows team, collecting only one championship point this season.</p>
<p>But he turned back the clock to post his best lap in the dying seconds of the session and finished just ahead of Finn Mika Hakkinen in a McLaren.</p>
<p>Championship leader Michael Schumacher secured his 17th pole position, with a best time of one minute 14.672 seconds in his Ferrari and Jacques Villeneuve, in his Williams, was 0.187 of a second slower to claim the other place on the front row.</p>
<p>&quot;I could not believe it myself at first. I saw the readout in my cockpit and did not think it was right. I thought something had gone wrong,&quot; Hill admitted.</p>
<p>&quot;It is absolutely fantastic to be back up here and so competitive.</p>
<p>&quot;I really thought a place in the top 10 would have been brilliant. Now I will go out to really enjoy myself in the race. Can I win? Of course, I can. Anything can happen.&quot;</p>
<p>Hill won his first Formula One victory at the Hungaroring in 1993 and triumphed again in 1995. He finished second last year and there is no doubt that his know-how was an important factor in negotiating a difficult circuit.</p>
<p>His team boss Tom Walkinshaw described Hill's effort as &quot;world class&quot; and it is now possible, according to some sources close to Hill, that he may consider Arrows sufficiently competitive to remain with them in 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;It is too early to talk about that. All I want to do is to concentrate on this race this weekend and make the most of it,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hill, criticised for not doing his best on the eve of the British Grand Prix at Silverstone four weeks ago, received a standing ovation from the team when he returned to the pits.</p>
<p>&quot;I knew it was possible because it is so tight and competitive but I did not expect it to come off quite like this,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Hill now has a chance of being an unexpected player in the championship battle between Schumacher and Villeneuve.</p>
<p>&quot;I know they will have a lot more pressure on them than I will have on me,&quot; said Hill. &quot;I've been there and it is a factor. I can be relaxed and just have some fun.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="HUNG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BUDAPEST"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="HUNGARY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
