<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789605" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: CRICKET-STRANG SPINS KENT TO TOP OF THE TABLE.</title>
<headline>CRICKET-STRANG SPINS KENT TO TOP OF THE TABLE.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Zimbabwe leg-spinner Paul Strang produced a telling spell of four for 36 in 10 overs to bowl Kent to the top of the English county championship on Saturday.</p>
<p>Strang finished with five for 119 from 36 overs as Kent beat Essex by an innings and eight runs on the fourth and last day at Canterbury.</p>
<p>Essex, following on 369 behind, were dismissed for 361, to which their captain Paul Prichard contributed an outstanding 224.</p>
<p>Prichard had made 171 out of the overnight 277 for five, and continued to battle almost single handedly as Strang worked through the lower order.</p>
<p>The Essex opener, batting with a runner because of hamstring problems, was finally prised out by fast bowler Martin McCague, having faced 295 deliveries and hit 35 fours.</p>
<p>Kent's win lifted them from third to first in the championship on 171 points from 12 matches. Second-placed Glamorgan, who were not involved in the current round of fixtures, have 159 points from 11 games.</p>
<p>Gloucestershire, third on 158 points after 12 games, were denied victory by Somerset last pair Graham Rose and Kevin Shine, who survived the final 37 balls to force a draw at Taunton.</p>
<p>Somerset, set 277 to win in a minimum of 45 overs, collapsed to 38 for six before all-rounder Rose put a good batting pitch in perspective with a chanceless 67 not out off 120 balls.</p>
<p>Rose found an effective ally in Pakistan leg spinner Mushtaq Ahmed, the pair adding 65 for the seventh wicket as Somerset edged to safety at 138 for nine.</p>
<p>Another Pakistan test slow bowler, off-spinner Saqlain Mushtaq, captured five for 111 as Surrey beat Durham by nine wickets at The Oval.</p>
<p>Saqlain had match figures for 10 for 128, but his success was tempered for Surrey by the Pakistan Cricket Board's insistence that he return home for a one-day tournament next month.</p>
<p>At Lord's, five wickets from ex-England seamer Angus Fraser, preceded by South African Jacques Kallis's second century of the season, off 148 deliveries, helped Middlesex to a 217-run win over Hampshire.</p>
<p>Kallis (102 not out) and Mike Gatting (69 not out) took Middlesex's second innings to 178 for one declared to leave Hampshire 315 to win.</p>
<p>Fraser (five for 38), aided by fellow pacemen James Hewitt (three for 27) and Richard Johnson (two for 10), routed Hampshire for 97.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
