<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789661" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: ATHLETICS-QUIROT PROVES IMMENSE PHYSICAL AND MENTAL RESILENCE.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-QUIROT PROVES IMMENSE PHYSICAL AND MENTAL RESILENCE.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Warner</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cuban Ana Fidelia Quirot proved her immense physical and mental resilence again on Saturday whe she retained the world women's 800 metres title.</p>
<p>Quirot, who returned to the top of her sport despite  a domestic accident in 1993 during which she suffered severe burns, produced a devastating kick in the final 50 metres to speed away from Mozambique's former world champion Maria Mutola.</p>
<p>The Cuban had come off the final bend level with 1993 champion Mutola and Russian Yelena Afanasyeva but burst away halfway down the home straight to win by three strides in one minute 57.14 seconds.</p>
<p>Afanasyeva just pipped Mutola on the line to take the silver in 1:57.56. Mutola, who failed to make the final of the 1995 championships in Gothenburg after being disqualified in the semifinals because she run out of lane, took third in 1:57.59.</p>
<p>Quirot said she had planned the late kick after a sleepless night on Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I am very happy to have got this gold and beaten Mutola,&quot; Quirot said. &quot;My coach told me not to go at 100 but to wait for 80. There was so much bumping that I couldn't go for the world record.</p>
<p>&quot;I was excited about this race. I didn't get to sleep until three in the morning.&quot;</p>
<p>Mutola, who looked in a perfect position to win the race on the final bend, had no excuses.</p>
<p>&quot;One day you win. One day you lose. Today I lost,&quot; she said. &quot;Fifty-eight seconds was very slow and there was a lot of bumping around 200. At the end I did not see the Russian. I thought I was second. There are no excuses. I lost it and that's all there is to it.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CUBA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MOZAM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
