<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789633" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: RUGBY UNION-ALL BLACKS SINK SPIRITED SPRINGBOKS.</title>
<headline>RUGBY UNION-ALL BLACKS SINK SPIRITED SPRINGBOKS.</headline>
<dateline>AUCKLAND 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>The All Blacks overwhelmed the Springboks 55-35 in a hard-fought test match at Eden Park on Saturday, claiming their win by a record margin with a rollicking display of rugby.</p>
<p>In a fast and action-packed game, New Zealand outscored the South Africans by seven tries to five to tighten their grasp on the Tri-Nations championship.</p>
<p>It was the highest score an All Blacks side has ever posted against South Africa and the largest winning margin.</p>
<p>But it was the underdog Springboks who drew first blood when just two minutes into the game they engineered a powerful rolling maul to send flanker Ruben Kruger in for the first try.</p>
<p>The lead changed hands regularly in the first half as each team vied for dominance in a blistering, often violent encounter. With three tries apiece there was little between the arch rivals at the break, the All Blacks ahead 23-21.</p>
<p>Two penalties early in the second spell widened the home side's lead, but it was a red card offence by South African loose forward Andre Venter which swung the match decisively in New Zealand's favour.</p>
<p>Venter was sent off 10 minutes into the second half for stomping on All Black captain Sean Fitzpatrick's face while he was on the ground in a ruck.</p>
<p>The Springboks were forced to play the remaining 30 minutes with only 14 men, and the All Blacks took full advantage, piercing their weakened opponents' defence to score four more tries.</p>
<p>The Springboks staged a spirited rally as full-time neared, crossing twice, but their fate had already been sealed.</p>
<p>The win puts the All Blacks firmly in control of the Tri-Nations series, and only Australia now have any chance of wresting the championship from them.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="AUCKLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
