<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789635" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: SWIMMING-RETREAT ON DRUGS WRONG, SWIM COACHES SAY.</title>
<headline>SWIMMING-RETREAT ON DRUGS WRONG, SWIM COACHES SAY.</headline>
<byline>Scott McDonald</byline>
<dateline>FUKUOKA, Japan 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>A decision by athletics officials to ease the ban on drug cheats is a step back in the war on doping in sports, swimming coaches say.</p>
<p>&quot;I think it was a strategic error. It disappointed me,&quot; Australian head coach Don Talbot said before the start of an international swim meeting in Fukuoka on Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;If they were serious about wanting to get rid of drugs in sport, they would be gone by now.</p>
<p>&quot;The International Amateur Athletic Federation (IAAF) voted late last month to halve the ban for serious drugs offences from four years to two because of difficulties with domestic courts.</p>
<p>&quot;Civil courts -- that should not be the reason to cease the war on drugs in sport,&quot; Talbot said, while watching his team train for the Pan Pacific Swimming Championships in Fukuoka on the southern Japanese island of Kyushu.</p>
<p>The decision by the athletics federation, at a meeting in Athens before the world athletics championships, was made because civil courts in some countries had regarded the four-year suspension as too harsh under restraint of trade legislation.</p>
<p>&quot;They just encouraged everyone to take drugs,&quot; said John Wright, a coach with the South African team.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think they should have dropped it just like that.&quot;</p>
<p>Swimmers can still be banned for four years, Talbot said, but he added that he did not know how long that would last.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm sure that after these IAAF moves there will be an effort to go to a two-year ban in swimming,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Head U.S. women's coach John Collins said although he wants the tougher penalties to remain, recent court decisions made that difficult.</p>
<p>&quot;We feel very strongly that anyone who gets caught should be penalised for four years,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;But U.S. swimming officials are concerned that if someone is caught, can they make it stick.&quot;</p>
<p>Collins pointed to the Jessica Foschi case, saying: &quot;Everyone is concerned about the repercussions of that precedent&quot;.</p>
<p>In June, the Court for Arbitration for Sport (CAS) in Lausanne, Switzerland, cut Foschi's two-year suspension for steroid use.</p>
<p>The decision ended a roller-coaster saga of bans and appeals that stretched back to August 1995 when the then 15-year-old tested positive at the U.S. national championships.</p>
<p>FINA, international swimming's ruling body, had stepped in on August 3, 1996, and suspended Foschi for two years, after earlier bans in the United States had been reversed.</p>
<p>Foschi has said she is innocent and that the tests were sabotaged.</p>
<p>Other countries have also had problems, including China which had four swimmers banned earlier this year for two years after positive dope tests at the Chinese national championships in January 1996.</p>
<p>The four were banned for only two years because the offences were committed before swimming's four-year ban came into force.</p>
<p>Seven Chinese tested positive for anabolic steroids at the 1994 Asian Games a month after the world championships in Rome.</p>
<p>World champions Yang Aihua and Lu Bin were among those suspended for two years.</p>
<p>The Pan Pacific championships, which have drawn about 300 swimmers from 23 countries and regions, are considered an important meeting prior to next January's world championships.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FUKUOKA, Japan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
