<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789642" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: ATHLETICS-JONES WINS SECOND GOLD MEDAL.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-JONES WINS SECOND GOLD MEDAL.</headline>
<byline>John Mehaffey</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Marion Jones won her second gold medal of the sixth world championships on Saturday as the U.S. women's 4x100 metres relay team set the second fastest time in history.</p>
<p>The American quartet, anchored by Olympic 100 metres champion Gail Devers, clocked 41.47 seconds. East Germany set the world record of 41.37 at the World Cup in Canberra 12 years ago.</p>
<p>Earlier the men's team failed to move past the first round for the second consecutive world championships when Brian Lewis and Tim Montgomery bumped into each other after the first baton exchange.</p>
<p>A similar misfortune ruined the American team's hopes two years ago in Gothenburg.</p>
<p>&quot;We wanted to make sure what happened to the men did not happen to us,&quot; said Jones, who won the 100 title last Sunday.</p>
<p>Jones, who finished 10th in the long jump final, said the relay gold was &quot;icing on the cake&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;I have such high expectations for myself, I was disappointed I didn't have three golds.&quot;</p>
<p>Two other women who had endured serious physical injury triumphed on the penultimate day of the championships.</p>
<p>Russian Lyudmila Galkina, given up for dead by doctors after a serious car accident last October, won the women's long jump title.</p>
<p>&quot;I was just happy to be alive and here,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Ana Fidelia Quirot, badly scarred after a house fire four years ago, retained the women's 800 metres title after timing her final surge to perfection.</p>
<p>The first title of the day went to Japan's Hiromi Suzuki, who translated her track speed to the road to win the women's marathon on the historic route from Marathon to Athens.</p>
<p>Norwegian Trine Hattestad regained the women's javelin title and Romanian Gabriela Szabo won the women's 5,000.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
