<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789643" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: ATHLETICS-AMERICAN RELAY TEAMS EXPERIENCE MIXED FORTUNES.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-AMERICAN RELAY TEAMS EXPERIENCE MIXED FORTUNES.</headline>
<byline>Patrick Vignal</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gail Devers anchored the U.S. women's 4x100 metres relay team to the second fastest time ever on Saturday after the men's team had crashed out of the heats.</p>
<p>World 100 metres champion Marion Jones won her second gold medal as the women's quartet clocked 41.47 seconds. East Germany set the world record of 41.37 at the World Cup in Canberra 12 years ago.</p>
<p>Earlier the men's team failed to move past the first round for the second consecutive world championships when Brian Lewis and Tim Montgomery bumped into each other after the first baton exchange.</p>
<p>A similar misfortune ruined the American team's hopes two years ago in Gothenburg.</p>
<p>&quot;We wanted to make sure what happened to the men did not happen to us,&quot; said Jones.</p>
<p>The win was particularly sweet for Devers, who was given a wild card to compete in Athens as the defending 100 metres hurdles champion and decided to concentrate of the relay.</p>
<p>&quot;I was injured at the national championships and my coach decided to pull me out before the 100 metres final, telling me I was already a world and Olympic champion,&quot; she explained. &quot;I understood that but this gold medal does in a way compensate for missing the 100 metres.&quot;</p>
<p>Inger Miller, who ran the penultimate leg, said she felt sorry for the men.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a tragedy for the guys,&quot; she said. &quot;They had a wonderful relay team.&quot;</p>
<p>Olympic champion Donovan Bailey, who anchored the Canadian team to victory at the 1995 championships and again at the Olympics last year, said he would miss his country's greatest rivals.</p>
<p>&quot;I am a little sorry. It is not quite the same without them in the race,&quot; Bailey said. &quot;Instead of talking about how they are going to beat us, they should learn about the little baton. You have got to pass it to each other.&quot;</p>
<p>Lewis admitted he was in the wrong while Montgomery left the arena without talking to reporters.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a poor mistake and I can't explain it,&quot; Lewis said. &quot;It was simply a misunderstanding of when to call for the stick.&quot;</p>
<p>Devers, who did not see the men's race, said she had expected both U.S. teams to win gold.</p>
<p>&quot;Never mind, &quot; she said. &quot;At least we've got one. And it's nice to see new faces coming up like Marion. That's a great feeling.&quot;</p>
<p>Jones said she had little to do: &quot;My job was easy. Those girls are so talented.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
