<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789620" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CZECH REPUBLIC: GOLF-RYDER CUP BECKONS FRONT RUNNER GARRIDO.</title>
<headline>GOLF-RYDER CUP BECKONS FRONT RUNNER GARRIDO.</headline>
<dateline>PRAGUE 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ryder Cup hopeful Ignacio Garrido battled through another weather-affected day to take a one shot lead over fellow Spaniard Miguel Jimenez after the third round of the Czech Open on Saturday.</p>
<p>The two enjoyed a tremendous tussle but Garrido went ahead with a late eagle as the round ended at dusk.</p>
<p>With fog holding up the completion of the second round for two hours in the morning, the third round only began at the Karlstein course in mid-morning.</p>
<p>Garrido and Jimenez began it one ahead of the field on 11-under-par along with Sweden's Patrik Sjoland.</p>
<p>By the time an electrical storm brought the players in for nearly two hours in late afternoon, Jimenez had nosed in front by the 11th and held his lead until a two-stroke swing came at the long 17th.</p>
<p>While Jimenez could only scramble par, Garrido holed a 20-foot putt for an eagle-two to take himself to the top of the leader board with a six-under 66 for a 16-under 197 total.</p>
<p>Garrido's eagle and four birdies with one dropped stroke put him on the brink of clinching his Ryder Cup place.</p>
<p>He already holds the 10th and final automatic place and will be in the European team for Valderrama comfortably next month if he takes the $211,000 first prize.</p>
<p>It would be his second win of the year following his maiden success seven weeks ago in the German Open.</p>
<p>Jimenez carded 67 for 198, two clear of Australian Stephen Allan and Britain's David Howell.</p>
<p>Sjoland, after challenging for the lead for much of the fragmented day, dropped shots after returning to the course after the storm break and finished a further stroke back.</p>
<p>Bernhard Langeso in the group on 201, seeking his third win of the year with a 64.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CZREP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SPAIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRAGUE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CZECH REPUBLIC"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
