<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789698" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>KENYA: Kenya quiet, opposition slammed after violence.</title>
<headline>Kenya quiet, opposition slammed after violence.</headline>
<byline>Manoah Esipisu</byline>
<dateline>NAIROBI 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Calm returned to the capital Nairobi and other towns on Saturday a day after a strike called by opposition groups to press for reforms turned violent and claimed the lives of three people.</p>
<p>Kenyan newspapers said the alliance of opposition groups -- the National Convention Executive Council (NCEC) -- were main losers in Friday's general strike for promoting violence to demand constitutional reforms.</p>
<p>Police said a total of three people, two of them policemen, were killed in Nairobi and in and near the town of Kiambu, 10 km (six miles) to the north, and one policeman was wounded.</p>
<p>&quot;It is now increasingly clear that the National Convention Executive Council (NCEC) and its supporters are not for peace and dialogue,&quot; the East African Standard newspaper said.</p>
<p>&quot;Events of yesterday's...strike were not only uncalled for but they have also exposed the NCEC as a body opposed to peaceful means towards national reconciliation and dialogue in this time of change,&quot; the newspaper added in an editorial.</p>
<p>Police said life was back to normal in Nairobi and  other provincial towns overnight.</p>
<p>President Daniel arap Moi, 73, on Friday rejected the strike as a move by the opposition-backed alliance to derail political reforms. He singled out for attack palaeontologist and opposition politician Richard Leakey and opposition legislator Paul Muite.</p>
<p>&quot;They asked for reforms. Now we have accepted they still seek other ways to disrupt the country,&quot; Moi told a rally.</p>
<p>The Daily Nation newspaper said the killing of innocent policemen was &quot;as senseless as it was uncalled for&quot;.</p>
<p>It added: &quot;Even worse, a stone was hurled at the president's limousine and it was extremely lucky he had chosen to fly back to Nairobi.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;If he had been in the car, it is anybody's guess how his security would have reacted.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Even if one disagrees with the president's point of view, the civilised way to show this is not to block his entourage or hurl stones and abuse him. It is clear that a lot of work must go into educating people on the civilised way to protest against issues,&quot; the Daily Nation said.</p>
<p>The Kenya Times newspaper, owned by the ruling Kenya African National Union (KANU) party, said the NCEC was working at the behest of Leakey who is intent on unleashing chaos in Kenya.</p>
<p>The Friday toll contrasted with nine dead, none of them policeman, on July 7 when riot police brutally broke up reform rallies in Kenya, bringing international condemnation down and forcing the authorities quietly to rein in their forces.</p>
<p>Opposition and pro-reform alliance leaders who addressed a rally in Nairobi's Uhuru park declared Friday's strike a great success but many shopowners -- especially from the Asian community -- only closed out of fear of violence and looting.</p>
<p>Barely 1,000 activists attended the rally in Uhuru park which began on an ugly note when gangs of youths chased down and beat several suspected police spies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KENYA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NAIROBI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="KENYA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
