<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789603" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: GOLF-ELS TAKES FOUR-SHOT LEAD AT BUICK OPEN.</title>
<headline>GOLF-ELS TAKES FOUR-SHOT LEAD AT BUICK OPEN.</headline>
<dateline>GRAND BLANC, Michigan 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>U.S. Open champion Ernie Els of South Africa fired a blistering nine-under-par 63 Friday to seize a four-stroke lead after the second round of the $1.5 million Buick Open.</p>
<p>Els, who has made a habit of winning Buick-sponsored events in recent years, was one shot off the course record at the Warwick Hills Golf and Country Club.</p>
<p>He began the second round at four under but spectacularly catapulted into the lead at 13-under-par 131 with a laser-like display of short iron play that included chipping in twice.</p>
<p>Els -- who also won the Buick Classic in Westchester for the second straight year in June -- posted seven birdies and an eagle and needed just 24 putts in a bogey-free round to stand four shots ahead of Dan Forsman, who followed his opening-round 68 with a 67.</p>
<p>John Morse, Chris Perry, Brad Fabel, Lanny Wadkins, Hal Sutton and Allen Doyle were all at eight-under 136, five shots back.</p>
<p>Little-known first-round leader Scott Skinner, who tied Jim Furyk's course record on Thursday, carded a 76 and fell to six under.</p>
<p>Els had his lowest-scoring day since carding a nine-under 61 en route to winning the 1995 Byron Nelson Classic in Texas.</p>
<p>&quot;It was a lot of fun out there,&quot; said the 27-year-old two-time U.S. Open champion.</p>
<p>&quot;Yesterday I let a 63 become a 68 but today I let what could have been a 68 become a 63.</p>
<p>&quot;I just felt that I left a lot of good shots out there in my first round and I just tried to make up for that today, though I suppose the golfing gods will probably get me back tomorrow.&quot;</p>
<p>Els birdied four of the first seven holes, including holing a 25-foot pitch shot at the 421-yard, par-four sixth hole.</p>
<p>At the 548-yard, par-five 13th, he was forced to take a compulsory drop when his second shot landed under a grandstand. He then had the crowd erupting with applause when he holed out with his third shot from 40 yards.</p>
<p>&quot;Today was the sort of day when you know things are going your way,&quot; said Els.</p>
<p>&quot;Things were happening for me and I just felt I could throw everything at the flags and that's what I did.&quot;</p>
<p>Despite his solid lead, Els worried that someone could still emerge from the pack over the final two rounds to challenge him.</p>
<p>&quot;Any player within 10 or 11 shots can jump all the way up to 11 or 12 under par and if I make 68 tomorrow, that guy is only going to be four behind me,&quot; said Els.</p>
<p>&quot;But you play this game with the goal to lead a golf tournament. I'm positive as I can be at present and that's the way I'm going to play.&quot;</p>
<p>Skinner, the overnight leader at 10 under, posted a disastrous five-over 76 to fall back into a share of 12th place at four under.</p>
<p>Fiji's Vijay Singh extended his run of making the halfway cut in the PGA Tour event to 41 successive tournaments after rounds of 67 and 73. Singh, the winner of last May's Memorial, has not missed a cut since the 1995 PGA Championship.</p>
<p>The par-72 Warwick Hills Golf and Country Club course measures 7,105 yards. Robert Wrenn established the tournament record with a 26-under 262 in 1987.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="GRAND BLANC, Michigan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
