<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789602" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: TENNIS-SAMPRAS, CHANG ADVANCE, MUSTER RALLIES TO BEAT SIEMERINK.</title>
<headline>TENNIS-SAMPRAS, CHANG ADVANCE, MUSTER RALLIES TO BEAT SIEMERINK.</headline>
<dateline>MASON, Ohio 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Top seed Pete Sampras and second seed Michael Chang expended little energy in winning quarter-final matches Friday but fifth seed Thomas Muster had a long struggle against Jan Siemerink at the ATP Championship Friday.</p>
<p>It took Muster two hours, 43 minutes to grind out a 6-7 (1-7) 7-6 (7-3) 7-6 (7-5) against the 36th-ranked Dutchman.</p>
<p>By contrast, Sampras beat seventh-seeded Yevgeny Kafelnikov of Russia 6-2 6-2 in a brief 53 minutes and Chang scored a 6-1 6-2 victory over 10th-seeded Gustavo Kuerten of Brazil in 57 minutes.</p>
<p>With the win, Chang reached his sixth consecutive ATP Championship semifinal. He won the title here in 1993 and 1994 and reached the final the past two years.</p>
<p>In a match between Spanards, 14th-seeded Albert Costa emerged the victor over sixth-seeded Sergi Bruguera when at 4-6 6-3 5-2 Bruguera retired from the match with cramps that started in his left leg. Earlier in the week, Bruguera was experiencing problems with his neck.</p>
<p>The semifinals pit Sampras against the 17th-ranked Costa and Muster against Chang.</p>
<p>Muster holds a 5-2 edge over Chang. Sampras beat Costa both times they played.</p>
<p>Sampras won here in 1992 but lost in the quarter-finals the past two years at the ATP Championship.</p>
<p>&quot;I played just about as well as I could. I couldn't play any better,&quot; Sampras said. &quot;He, I think, started to press a little bit because he saw me serving very big. I served just about as well as I could serve.&quot;</p>
<p>Chang lost to Kuerten 6-3 6-1 in 57 minutes last week in the semifinals at Montreal.</p>
<p>&quot;Last week was Gustavo's time, this week was my time,&quot; Chang said. &quot;We played the reverse roles. The matches were almost a straight reversal.&quot;</p>
<p>Chang offered Kuerten one chance to break serve in Friday's match when he double faulted at 30-30 in the second game of the second set. He won the next three points to hold serve and led 4-0 before Kuerten held serve to win a game.</p>
<p>Six of the eight players in the quarter-finals were ranked in the top 10 in the world -- number one Sampras, number two Chang, number four Muster, number six Kafelnikov, number eight Bruguera and number 10 Kuerten. Only Costa and Siemerink are not members of this elite group.</p>
<p>Dealing with Siemerink, a fellow left-hander, was a difficult task for Muster as the Dutchman played serve-and-volley the entire match.</p>
<p>Muster's strategy to lob against Siemerink failed miserably except on the final point of the match, when the Austrian finally hit a winning lob which sailed way over Siemerink's head and too far back to run down.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't lob well except that last one, maybe the most important one,&quot; Muster said. &quot;He puts a lot of pressure on you because he gives you one, two metres where you can pass.&quot;</p>
<p>Siemerink kept Muster out of the first-set tiebreaker with his aggressive play, winning the first five points quickly.</p>
<p>In the second set, Muster trailed 4-2 before breaking back to 4-4 and heading to a second set tiebreaker.</p>
<p>Muster fell behind again in the final set, losing his serve in an erratic fourth game. Three crucial double faults in the eight-point seventh game cost Siemerink the service break edge.</p>
<p>Even in the final-set tiebreaker, Muster struggled before reaching his second consecutive semifinal appearance at the ATP Championship. He raced out to a 5-1 lead in the breaker but lost the next four points before winning the last two points.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MASON, Ohio"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
