<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789614" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: BASEBALL-GIANTS' MARK GARDNER TWO-HITS MONTREAL.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-GIANTS' MARK GARDNER TWO-HITS MONTREAL.</headline>
<dateline>MONTREAL 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Former Expo Mark Gardner had a no-hitter for 6 1/3 innings before settling for a two-hitter as the red-hot San Francisco Giants beat Montreal 4-0 Friday.</p>
<p>Gardner (12-5) tossed his second career shutout and second complete game of the season. He walked one and struck out seven -- including all three batters in the ninth -- and faced just one batter over the minimum.</p>
<p>Gardner was cruising with his no-hitter until, with one out in the seventh, rookie Vladimir Guerrero hit a long fly to the top of the wall in left field, just out of the reach of Barry Bonds. It went for a double.</p>
<p>&quot;I was surprised he swung at the pitch,&quot; Gardner said. &quot;It was a 3-1 curveball and he acted like he knew it was coming. He hit it pretty high and I saw Barry trying to time it so I knew it was going to be close.&quot;</p>
<p>Gardner, who also yielded a leadoff single to Darrin Fletcher in the eighth, said he didn't expect a no-hitter.</p>
<p>&quot;I was aware of it, but I don't think you could ever no-hit that team,&quot; Gardner said. &quot;I figured Fletcher would get a hit anyway because he owns me. What makes this special is we are in a pennant race and don't have a whole lot of room for error.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Gardner is a solid pitcher in this league and I think you have to get him early if you are going to get him,&quot; Fletcher said. &quot;We weren't able to and he got stronger.&quot;</p>
<p>The win was the fifth in six games for San Francisco, which remained 1 1/2 games ahead of the Dodgers in the National League West.</p>
<p>J.T. Snow hit his 20th homer of the season, a two-run shot off Expos starter Carlos Perez (11-7) in the sixth. Perez, who went the distance, allowed four runs and nine hits, walking one and striking out six as his three-game win streak ended.</p>
<p>In Atlanta, Charles Johnson homered and drove in three runs and Alex Fernandez went six innings to win his fourth straight start as the surging Florida Marlins held off the Braves 6-4 for their ninth win in 11 games.</p>
<p>The Marlins beat the Braves for the fourth time in five meetings over the last eight days and moved within 4 1/2 games of first-place Atlanta in the N.L. East. They also stayed two games ahead of the Mets in the wild-card race.</p>
<p>Fernandez (14-8) allowed two runs and seven hits for his second win over the Braves in six days. Robb Nen struck out two in a scoreless ninth for his 28th save in 34 chances.</p>
<p>In Chicago, Kevin Orie snapped a tie with an eighth-inning RBI single that lifted the revamped Cubs to a 3-1 victory over the San Diego Padres.</p>
<p>Reliever Marc Pisciotta (2-0), recalled from Class AAA Iowa to fill one of the roster spots vacated when the Cubs dealt outfielder Brian McRae and pitchers Mel Rojas and Turk Wendell to the Mets for outfielder Lance Johnson and a pair of players to be named, allowed one walk and struck out four in two hitless innings.</p>
<p>In New York, Brian Bohanon allowed three hits over 7 2/3 innings and McRae went 3-for-4 with two runs scored in his debut for the Mets, who beat the Houston Astros 6-1.</p>
<p>Bohanon (3-1) allowed a homer to James Mouton in the first and little else. He walked three and struck out six in winning for the second time in four starts since being recalled from the minors July 22.</p>
<p>The Mets, who won their fourth in five games, improved to 36-18 at home, the best home mark in the National League.</p>
<p>In Cincinnati, Eric Karros had a run-scoring double that snapped a tie in a six-run fourth inning, leading the Los Angeles Dodgers to a 10-5 victory over the Reds.</p>
<p>Karros, Raul Mondesi and Todd Zeile each drove in two runs as the Dodgers remained 1 1/2 games behind San Francisco for the lead in the National League West.</p>
<p>Tom Candiotti (8-4) allowed five runs and 10 hits over five innings but got the win. Darren Dreifort allowed one hit, walked one and struck out six in four scoreless innings of relief for his second save.</p>
<p>Joe Oliver and Eduardo Perez homered for the Reds. Mike Morgan (3-10) took the loss.</p>
<p>In St. Louis, Donovan Osborne allowed three hits over seven innings and Mark McGwire homered in his home debut after coming over from Oakland as the Cardinals defeated the Philadelphia Phillies 6-1 to snap a five-game losing streak.</p>
<p>Osborne (2-4), who had lost his last two starts, allowed only an unearned run with no walks and six strikeouts. The Phillies tagged him for eight runs in three innings five days ago. McGwire, who hit 34 homers while with the A's, is hitting .107 (3-for-28) as a Cardinal.</p>
<p>At Colorado, Jamey Wright (6-7) allowed three runs over 6 2/3 innings and Eric Young had three hits and two RBI to lead the Rockies to a 5-3 victory over the Pittsburgh Pirates.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M132">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MONTREAL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
