<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789637" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: BASEBALL-RANDY JOHNSON STRIKES OUT 19 AS MARINERS BLANK CHICAGO.</title>
<headline>BASEBALL-RANDY JOHNSON STRIKES OUT 19 AS MARINERS BLANK CHICAGO.</headline>
<dateline>SEATTLE 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Seattle Mariners ace Randy Johnson became the first pitcher in history to notch two 19-strikeout games in one season as he blanked the Chicago White Sox 5-0 Friday.</p>
<p>Johnson (16-3), allowed just five singles and three walks in his second shutout of the season and 17th of his career.</p>
<p>&quot;He was nearly unhittable,&quot; Seattle manager Lou Piniella said. &quot;His stuff tonight was as good as I've seen from him. His fastball was just alive.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Tonight was a special night,&quot; said Johnson, who threw 149 pitches. &quot;I went out there against Lou, the pitching coach and the trainer's advice in the ninth. I got through the inning with the fewest pitches the whole night because I was focused.&quot;</p>
<p>Johnson, who tied his American League mark for strikeouts by a left-hander, fell one short of Roger Clemens's major-league record of 20. He also got at least 10 strikeouts in a game for the 12th time in 24 starts this season.</p>
<p>Johnson joined Clemens and Minnesota's Brad Radke as the only pitchers in the league with at least 16 wins. Clemens leads the majors with 17 wins.</p>
<p>Johnson rolled through the first four innings, allowing a hit and a walk with eight strikeouts. He fanned Frank Thomas, Albert Belle and Lyle Mouton in the fourth.</p>
<p>Johnson toyed with the second through fifth hitters in the White Sox order as they went 0-for-15 with 14 strikeouts. He fanned Mike Cameron and Mouton four times apiece and he got Thomas and Belle three times. The left-hander also struck out the side in the sixth and ninth innings.</p>
<p>&quot;He was extremly dominating,&quot; Thomas said. &quot;He made us chase pitches when he had to. He was very nasty.&quot;</p>
<p>Edgar Martinez (19) and Ken Griffey Jr (35) homered for Seattle, which moved a half-game ahead of Anaheim for the lead in the A.L. West when the Orioles beat the Angels. Griffey, who leads the league with 104 RBI, is two homers behind New York's Tino Martinez for the league lead.</p>
<p>Chris Clemons (0-2) lost his second major-league start.</p>
<p>In Anaheim, Mike Mussina allowed three hits over 7 1/3 innings and Chris Hoiles drove in a pair of runs as the Baltimore Orioles got their 13th win in 16 games, 6-2 over the Angels.</p>
<p>Mussina (13-4) gave up two runs with three walks and six strikeouts to win his third straight start. He became the third 13-game winner on the Orioles, joining Jimmy Key and Scott Erickson.</p>
<p>In the ninth, Randy Myers got out of a bases-loaded, no-outs jam by getting Luis Alicea to pop out and inducing Gary DiSarcina to hit into a game-ending double play for his 33rd save in 34 opportunities.</p>
<p>The Orioles extended their lead to six games over the second-place Yankees in the A.L. East.</p>
<p>Anaheim lost for the third time in 12 games.</p>
<p>In Cleveland, Jim Leyritz's two-run single highlighted a three-run ninth as the Texas Rangers edged the Indians 6-5 for just their third win in 11 games.</p>
<p>Mike Jackson (2-4), who started the ninth, gave up a single to Juan Gonzalez, a walk to Will Clark and hit Ivan Rodriguez with a pitch to load the bases with no outs before giving way to Albie Lopez.</p>
<p>Gonzalez scored on a passed ball, cutting the deficit to 5-4 before Leyritz singled to right.</p>
<p>Jackson, who blew a save Sunday in Texas and has yielded six earned runs in one inning combined in those two games, fell to 1-6 with an ERA of 4.81 lifetime against the Rangers.</p>
<p>Ex-Indian Scott Bailes (1-0) picked up his first win since June 3, 1992, when he beat Baltimore as a member of the Angels. John Wetteland retired the side in the ninth for his 23rd save in 29 opportunities.</p>
<p>At Minnesota, Greg Myers and Roberto Kelly each drove in a pair of runs in a six-run first inning, Kelly with an inside-the-park homer, as the Twins chased New York Yankees starter Dwight Gooden (5-4) on their way to a 9-1 victory.</p>
<p>Chuck Knoblauch also homered and finished with three hits for the Twins, who snapped a three-game losing streak. Paul Molitor had his sixth three-hit game of the season.</p>
<p>In Toronto, Carlos Delgado homered twice, including a two-run shot that capped a four-run third inning, as the Blue Jays ended Willie Blair's seven-game winning streak with a 6-3 victory over the Detroit Tigers.</p>
<p>Delgado was in a 4-for-59 slump before going 4-for-7 with five RBI and three runs in his last two games.</p>
<p>In Boston, Scott Hatteberg went 4-for-4 and scored three runs and Reggie Jefferson added a three-run homer to lift the Red Sox to their season-high fifth straight victory, 8-2 over the Kansas City Royals.</p>
<p>Jefferson extended his hitting streak to a career-high 22 games, the longest by a Boston player since Wade Boggs's 25 in a row in 1987.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEATTLE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
