<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789671" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: OLYMPICS-BOLDON SAYS STOCKHOLM BOMB HAS UPSET ATHLETES.</title>
<headline>OLYMPICS-BOLDON SAYS STOCKHOLM BOMB HAS UPSET ATHLETES.</headline>
<byline>Adrian Warner</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Trinidad's world 200 metres champion Ato Boldon said on Saturday that the person who blew up Stockholm's historic Olympic stadium had upset some of the world's leading athletes.</p>
<p>&quot;Now they have some real opposition. We don't take kindly to violence,&quot; said Boldon who is backing the Swedish city's bid to stage the 2004 Olympic Games.</p>
<p>&quot;Whoever did it is going to have me up against you and (American 100 metres world champion) Maurice Greene.&quot;</p>
<p>Friday's massive explosion that damaged the stadium which hosted the 1912 Games was the latest in a series of unexplained attacks on sports venues in the city.</p>
<p>The blast ripped a gaping hole in the roof above the main entrance on the east side of the stadium. Arsonists have struck seven sports venues in Stockholm since May and several indoor tennis arenas have been destroyed.</p>
<p>Officials from the Stockholm 2004 committee stressed at a news conference at the world athletics championships that Swedish police had found no connection between the recent attacks and the Olympic bid.</p>
<p>But it is clear that the latest incident has upset the composure of the Stockholm 2004 officials at a crucial stage of the bidding process because the media are connecting the incident with their Olympic campaign.</p>
<p>The International Olympic Committee (IOC) will decide on the venue of the Summer Games on September 5. Athens, Rome, Buenos Aires and Cape Town are also bidding.</p>
<p>At the news conference Stockholm chief official Olof Stenhammar initially made a veiled attack on International Amateur Athletic Federation (IAAF) chief Primo Nebiolo, who is backing rivals Rome, for sending a letter of sympathy to the Swedes.</p>
<p>Stenhammar, a millionaire businessman, said the letter might help the attack to be connected to the bid. But the Swedes later backed down on the criticism, saying Stenhammar had not chosen his words correctly.</p>
<p>&quot;I know Primo well and he is genuinely upset that such an arena has been attacked,&quot; Sweden's IOC member and IAAF chief Arne Ljungqvist said.</p>
<p>Stockholm have brought together an impressive number of sportsmen to support their bid. Former Wimbledon tennis champion Stefan Edberg, one of the leading figures, said he hoped the attack would not damage the campaign.</p>
<p>&quot;You can't do anything about it. Hopefully it will not have too much negative impact on the bid,&quot; Edberg said. &quot;Hopefully there will be no more incidents. Most people are behind the Olympic bid in Sweden.&quot;</p>
<p>With Cape Town and Buenos Aires viewed as outsiders, Rome, Athens and Stockholm are in fierce competition to persuade IOC members to vote for their bid.</p>
<p>The bomb could not have come at a worse time for the Swedes with just weeks to go before the IOC vote in Lausanne.</p>
<p>There was confusion in Athens on Saturday when athletics officials initially said that the Panathinaikon Stadium which hosted the end of the women's marathon had been closed to spectators for security reasons after the Stockholm bomb.</p>
<p>The claim was later denied by Greek Sports under-secretary Andreas Fouras and Athens mayor Dimitris Avramopoulos.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="SWED">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="TRTO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
