<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789674" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GREECE: ATHLETICS-SUZUKI TAKES MARATHON TITLE AND WORLD CUP FOR JAPAN.</title>
<headline>ATHLETICS-SUZUKI TAKES MARATHON TITLE AND WORLD CUP FOR JAPAN.</headline>
<byline>Mike Collett</byline>
<dateline>ATHENS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Japan's Hiromi Suzuki, running alone for much of the second half of the world women's marathon, scored an emphatic victory for herself and her country on Saturday.</p>
<p>The 28-year-old from Chiba, running in only her third marathon, set a course record of two hours 29 minutes 48 seconds to finish almost a minute and half ahead of defending champion Manuel Machada of Portugal (2:31:12) who was celebrating her 34th birthday.</p>
<p>Lidia Simon of Romania, vomited halfay through the 42.195 kms race from Marathon to Athens, but battled back to take the bronze in 2:31.55. She was carried away on a stretcher after finishing.</p>
<p>For the first time the World Marathon Cup, a team event with the top three finishers from each country scoring points, was staged in conjunction with the event.</p>
<p>Suzuki's victory together with the fourth place finish of Takako Tobise and the 10th place of Nobuko Fujimura guaranteed Japan first place.</p>
<p>The race, following the traditional course based on the run of the messenger Phidippides in 490 B.C. began just after eight a.m. from the town of Marathon and ended in the Panathinaikon Stadium, site of the 1896 Olympic Games.</p>
<p>But there was disappointment for thousands of fans who were refused entry into the stadium to watch the finish.</p>
<p>Athens mayor Dimitris Avramopoulos closed the stadium to the public following the bombing at the Stockholm Olympic Stadium on Friday. Both Athens and Stockholm are bidding to host the 2004 Olympics.</p>
<p>The most dramatic moment of Saturday's race came just before the 21 kms mark when Fatuma Roba of Ethiopia, the Olympic champion, suddenly dropped out after looking comfortable at the head of the leading group, and walked by the roadside holding her stomach.</p>
<p>&quot;I didn't notice it happen,&quot; said Suzuki afterwards. &quot;I was just concentrating on running and getting to the finish as soon as I could. I was running smoothly and it was just natural for me to go to the front. I had prayed every day at the Tomb of the Marathon Warriors on the course to help me win.&quot;</p>
<p>Suzuki accelerated away from the field around 26 kms on the hilliest and most gruelling part of the course, and was never in any trouble on the downhill section of the race into the centre of Athens.</p>
<p>&quot;When I made that spurt even running uphill seemed to be quite natural for me,&quot; she said. &quot;It is nice to win one after finishing second in my first two marathons.&quot;</p>
<p>The medals were effectively decided in five dramatic kilometres in the middle of the race.</p>
<p>The first development came when Roba, dropped out. Then a few minutes later Simon, who had also been in the leading group carried on running despite vomiting.</p>
<p>She lost her rhythm and form for a spell and appeared to be out of contention, but despite the heat, the humidity and her own personal discomfort, she rallied over the downhill section to take the bronze.</p>
<p>As early as the first 10 kms a leading group of around 20 had formed including Roba and Machada.</p>
<p>A spurt by Roba at the town of Nea Makri after 38 minutes had a devastating effect on the leading pack, reducing it by more than half in less than a kilometre.</p>
<p>The leading group, now reduced to nine and including Suzuki and Simon, then dug in for the gruelling climb over the hills.</p>
<p>After Roba departed, Machada battled bravely to keep in touch with Suzuki performed superbly to take the silver, just six weeks after being injured in a car crash.</p>
<p>&quot;I had terrible chest pains from the crash and I had to stop training for two weeks. I went through hell today but I had faith. Something inside of me told me to keep going, I couldn't give up.&quot;</p>
<p>She also revealed that she ran with an olive leaf from Portugal tucked inside her vest. &quot;A friend of mine found it and had it blessed in church and gave it to me for luck,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>Suzuki's victory follows that of Junko Asari who won the world title in Stuttgart in 1993 and Hiromi Taniguchi who won the men's title at the 1991 Tokyo championships.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GREECE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PORL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GSPO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ATHENS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GREECE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
