<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789739" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH KOREA: SEOUL STOCKS CLOSE HIGHER ON STRENTHENING YEN.</title>
<headline>SEOUL STOCKS CLOSE HIGHER ON STRENTHENING YEN.</headline>
<dateline>SEOUL 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>The strengthening yen against the dollar fuelled investors' anticipation of an economic turnaround, sending the Seoul stock market to a higher close on Saturday, dealers said.</p>
<p>&quot;Many investors are pinning their hopes on an improving economy as the dollar plunged to 114 yen from a 118 yen previously,&quot; said Cha Hee-gun at Sungkyong Securities.</p>
<p>South Korea is competing with Japan on world markets with similar products.</p>
<p>The composite stock index rose 8.83 points, or 1.17 percent, to close the half-day session at 760.84.  </p>
<p>The market shot up to the day high of 764.81, but immediate profit-taking and selling pressure around the 750 level eclipsed the early rises.</p>
<p>Brokers said strong buying interest was shown among low-priced large-capitalised shares as they would benefit from the yen's strength.</p>
<p>Daewoo Heavy Industry rose 550 won to 8,450 with Saturday's largest trading volume of 1.01 million shares. Samsung Heavy went limit up, gaining 800 won to 11,400 with hefty volume of 825,940.  </p>
<p>Core blue chips also spearheaded the index rise.</p>
<p>Samsung Electronics gained 2,500 won to 72,000 and POSCO added 800 won to 61,400.</p>
<p>Brokers said the market would show gradual rises next week, aided by anticipation of an economic turnaround and falling interest rates.</p>
<p>But a Daishin Securities report recommended a flexible attitude with close monitoring of yen/dollar movements.</p>
<p>-- Yeom Yoon-jeong (822) 727 5647</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M11">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SEOUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH KOREA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
