<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789759" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: UAW, GM reach tentative deal at Cadillac plant.</title>
<headline>UAW, GM reach tentative deal at Cadillac plant.</headline>
<byline>David Lawder</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>General Motors Corp. and the United Auto Workers union reached a tentative contract deal early on Saturday that averted a threatened strike at GM's Cadillac assembly plant in Detroit.</p>
<p>UAW spokesman Frank Joyce said the agreement was scheduled for a ratification vote by the 3,600 members of United Auto Workers Local 22 on Sunday. The deal is expected to keep GM's launch of its 1998 Cadillac Seville on track.</p>
<p>Workers streamed out of the plant in the Hamtramck, Mich. enclave in Detroit after an 11:59 p.m. EDT Friday deadline expired and began picketing, but union officials quickly said talks were continuing and no strike had been declared.</p>
<p>&quot;They put the pen to the paper and signed the agreement at 3:15 a.m.,&quot; said GM spokeswoman Marsha Hall-Jenkins. Both she and UAW officials declined to reveal details of the settlement.</p>
<p>As in six strikes this year and numerous strike threats, the UAW demanded more jobs at the plant to replace retiring workers and ease a growing workload. GM resisted such moves, maintaining that it needed to shrink its workforce to become competitive with Ford Motor Co., Chrysler Corp., and Japanese automakers.</p>
<p>The plant on the Detroit-Hamtramck border is the only assembly site for Cadillacs, producing the Seville, DeVille and Eldorado models.</p>
<p>A prolonged walkout could have disrupted GM's ambitious launch plans for the '98 Seville, which it aims to position as a world class luxury car that can compete head-to-head with Mercedes-Benz, BMW and Lexus. GM will unveil the car next month in the German automakers' backyard, at the international auto show in Frankfurt, Germany.</p>
<p>Cadillac plans to build a right-hand-drive version of the car and hopes to export the Seville all over the world in a bid to shed its stuffy, land-yacht image.</p>
<p>A seven-week strike that started in April at GM's Oklahoma City assembly plant disrupted the launch of GM's mid-size Chevrolet Malibu and Oldsmobile Cutlass sedans, which were viewed as critical to GM's efforts to regain market share.</p>
<p>&quot;The most damaging thing about the strike in Oklahoma City was that it forced the company to relaunch the Malibu,&quot; said Schroder Wertheim &amp; Co. auto analyst John Casesa. &quot;If the strike had not happened, that car would have better awareness and better sales.&quot;</p>
<p>GM sold a respectable 12,996 Malibus in July, but that still fell short of the Corsicas and Berettas it replaced, which had sales of 15,698 units for the month.</p>
<p>Analysts also worry that consumers' attention will be drawn away from the car by Honda's launch of an all-new Accord this autumn.</p>
<p>The strikes have been costly to GM, cutting second-quarter profits by $490 million and reducing its share of the domestic car and light truck market well below GM's 1997 goal of 33 percent.</p>
<p>The automaker also said Friday that a three-month walkout at a Pontiac, Michigan, truck plant and a six-day strike at a Warren, Michigan, transmission plant, forced it to cut its third-quarter production schedule by 20,000 vehicles.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I35101">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
