<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789702" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAJIKISTAN: Fighting rocks part of Tajik capital-witnesses.</title>
<headline>Fighting rocks part of Tajik capital-witnesses.</headline>
<dateline>DUSHANBE 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Clashes broke out between two rival armed groups in a northern district of the Tajik capital Dushanbe on Saturday, witnesses said.</p>
<p>A Reuter correspondent was turned back from the area of fighting by police but said he heard small arms fire and an explosion. Tajikistan, a former Soviet republic, is trying to emerge from a four-year civil war following a peace accord.  </p>
<p>Yakub Salimov, a tax official and a nominally pro-government commander, said by telephone the fighting involved his own armed group and men from an elite unit of Interior Ministry troops led by a commander called Sufrob Kasimov.</p>
<p>&quot;They are shooting here but I have not heard of any casualties so far,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>Tajik military sources said the fighting was linked to a vendetta between local armed groups but there was no official reaction to the fighting.</p>
<p>The Tajik government and armed Islamist guerrillas signed a peace agreement in June to end the civil war but a kaleidescopic array of armed bands threaten stability in the country of 5.7 million people bordering Afghanistan and China.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TADZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUSHANBE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAJIKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
