<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789746" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: REPORT TIPS 20 PCT DROP IN HK PROPERTY PRICES.</title>
<headline>REPORT TIPS 20 PCT DROP IN HK PROPERTY PRICES.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong property prices will slump by 20 percent in the next 15 months, and property stocks could be dragged downwards as a result, a report by investment bank SBC Warburg says.</p>
<p>But the bearish report says three leading property groups -- Cheung Kong (Holdings), New World Development and Amoy Properties -- will be insulated from the decline, having diversified into mainland China infrastructure and cut their reliance on the Hong Kong market.</p>
<p>&quot;The market has over-estimated demand for Hong Kong properties from mainland interests, migrants from China..., returning Hong Kong emigrants and new arrivals of expatriates,&quot; said the report, quoted by the South China Morning Post.</p>
<p>The report struck a contrast with the bullish view of most property forecasts which say the residential and office sectors will be boosted by an inflow of mainland cash.</p>
<p>The report said this factor was not strong enough to move the market. Home prices have jumped by up to 30 percent this year but would drop by 20 percent over the next 15 months due to the discrepancy between actual and perceived demand, it said.</p>
<p>Hong Kong's stock market ralkies this year have been driven in large part by the property sector. The Hang Seng Index powered into record territory last week, hitting an all-time high of 16,820.31 and a record close of 16,673.27 on Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I50100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I85000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
