<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789733" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: Hong Kong ill-prepared for millenium bug - report.</title>
<headline>Hong Kong ill-prepared for millenium bug - report.</headline>
<dateline>HONG KONG 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hong Kong, one of the most computer-literate places in the world, is ill-prepared for the millennium bug that could bring computers crashing down in 2000, and must spend over US$170 million on the problem, a government survey said.</p>
<p>The police, for example, will have to spend more than $4 million by January 1, 2000, to protect their computer systems, according to a survey by the Hong Kong Productivity Council.</p>
<p>The survey, covering 1,000 companies and government departments, was the first major study on the millennium bug in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>It showed that 86 percent relied heavily on computers but nearly 40 percent of Hong Kong businesses were unaware of the problem. Small and medium-sized firms were most ill-prepared.</p>
<p>The so-called millennium bug refers to the inability of older computer programmes to process the last two digits of years correctly after December 31, 1999.</p>
<p>When 2000 arrives, the computers would misinterpret the &quot;00&quot; date as 1900 and crash or lose data, the theory goes.</p>
<p>A recent international study found the global spending on solving the problem would reach US$280 billion between 1997 and 2002, with US$145 billion of this to be spent in North America.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="HKONG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I33020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HONG KONG"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
