<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789771" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Germany restores ties to Bosnian embassy - Kinkel.</title>
<headline>Germany restores ties to Bosnian embassy - Kinkel.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel said Germany had reinstated contacts with the Bosnian embassy in Bonn on Saturday, a day after Bosnia's squabbling leaders settled a dispute on sharing out ambassadorial posts.</p>
<p>The move came less than a week after Germany led several other western European countries and the United States in suspending contacts with Bosnian envoys because Moslem, Croat and Serb political leaders had failed to agree on the allocation of major posts by an August 1 deadline.</p>
<p>&quot;The tough policies are bearing fruit,&quot; Kinkel said in an interview with the Bild am Sonntag weekly, released in advance of its Sunday publication. &quot;We were the first country to suspend ties with the Bosnian embassy and other countries followed us.</p>
<p>&quot;As a result of that, an agreement was reached in Bosnia on Friday (over the ambassadorial posts). I thus reinstated contacts with the Bosnian embassy on Saturday.&quot;</p>
<p>Under the deal reached on Friday, the Bosnian ambassador to the United Nations will be a Moslem, a Serb will be ambassador to Washington and a Croat will be ambassador to Japan, U.S. envoy Richard Holbrooke and other mediators said.</p>
<p>In response, France resumed contacts with the Bosnian embassy in Paris on Friday.</p>
<p>Bosnia's current ambassadors were appointed by the wartime Moslem-led Bosnian government which fought separatist Serbs and, for 10 months, Croat forces, their nominal allies.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BSHZG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
