<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789741" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Cambodia's Khmer Rouge say support ASEAN effort.</title>
<headline>Cambodia's Khmer Rouge say support ASEAN effort.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cambodia's Khmer Rouge guerrillas said on Saturday they supported mediation efforts in Cambodia by the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN) and still regarded ousted Prince Norodom Ranariddh as prime minister.</p>
<p>Strongman Hun Sen, who overthrew Ranariddh after a weekend of bloody fighting on July 6, was creating obstacles for the ASEAN mediation mission, the rebels said in a message addressed to the foreign secretary of the Philippines read out on their clandestine radio.</p>
<p>&quot;The coup created serious insecurity and instability in Cambodia and it is a threat to stability and security in the region,&quot; Khmer Rouge political leader Khieu Samphan said in his message to Domingo Siazon.</p>
<p>Siazon is one of three ASEAN foreign ministers who have been trying to mediate a solution to Cambodia's crisis. It was not clear why the rebels' message was addressed to Siazon alone.</p>
<p>ASEAN postponed Cambodia's scheduled entry to the regional group last month because of the political turmoil.</p>
<p>Khieu Samphan, for long seen as a more acceptable front man for the notorious guerrilla group, said the appointment of Foreign Minister Ung Huot as Ranariddh's replacement was an attempt by Hun Sen to block the ASEAN mission's efforts.</p>
<p>Ung Huot was appointed first prime minister by acting head of state Chea Sim on Thursday after King Norodom Sihanouk, who is required by the constitution to approve a new first prime minister, told Chea Sim he could sign the decree of appointment.</p>
<p>Hun Sen backed Ung Huot's nomination which had originally been opposed by Sihanouk.</p>
<p>&quot;The appointment of Ung Huot as first prime minister in place of Prince Ranariddh is an additional indication that Hun Sen and his bosses have no goodwill to end the political crisis by peaceful means,&quot; Khieu Samphan said in his message.</p>
<p>&quot;The appointment is an obstacle to block ASEAN's efforts.&quot;</p>
<p>The United States says Ung Huot's nomination was undemocratic because of the atmosphere of intimidation in the country.</p>
<p>The Khmer Rouge said that by not signing the decree appointing Ung Huot, the king was showing he did not recognise him as first prime minister.</p>
<p>Sihanouk is currently in the Chinese capital where he is receiving medical treatment.</p>
<p>In recent weeks rebel radio has been directing a stream of criticism at Hun Sen, labelling him a puppet of former occupiers Vietnam and calling for united opposition to his rule.</p>
<p>Hun Sen has warned of military action against the rebels in their Anlong Veng base in the remote north of the country.</p>
<p>The guerrillas, who issued their Saturday message in the name of Khieu Samphan's political organisation, the National Solidarity Party, purged their notorious leader Pol Pot late last month after he tried to block an alliance with Ranariddh.</p>
<p>The rebels boycotted a 1993 election organised by the United Nations and fought a low-intensity guerrilla war against the coalition government that emerged from the poll, an unhappy partnership between Hun Sen and Ranariddh.</p>
<p>More than a million Cambodians died during Pol Pot's 1975-79 &quot;killing fields&quot; reign of power.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ASEAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PHLNS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
