<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789718" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: N. Korean hunger to worsen as drought takes toll.</title>
<headline>N. Korean hunger to worsen as drought takes toll.</headline>
<byline>Scott Hillis</byline>
<dateline>BEIJING 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Searing drought in much of North Korea has wiped out nearly three-fourths of the maize crop and will further plunge the country into hunger and malnutrition, a United Nations aid worker said on Saturday.</p>
<p>An initial survey by international food agencies of crops in North Korea had found stunted plants struggling to survive the blistering summer in the hermit nation, said Hilary Mackenzie, spokeswoman for the World Food Programme in Pyongyang.</p>
<p>&quot;Seventy percent of the maize crop has been lost, which has resulted in a loss of 1.5 million tonnes of cereals,&quot; Mackenzie said in an interview in Beijing after two months based in the North Korean capital.</p>
<p>&quot;The most stark effect that I saw was in the northeast, where the corn was a matter of inches high because of the drought,&quot; Mackenzie said. &quot;It just couldn't grow.&quot;</p>
<p>Pyongyang, armed with its &quot;juche&quot; philosophy of defiant self reliance, had desperately mobilised brigades of people to carry water to the fields in a vain attempt to revive the withered crops, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;The best thing now that they can do with the maize is chop it down and either use it as animal feedstuff with the leaves or plough it back into the land,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The failed crops would only worsen the already severe food shortages in North Korea, which has been hit with its worst heatwave in 61 years after floods ravaged the country in 1995 and 1996, Mackenzie said.</p>
<p>North Korea was already short about one million tonnes of grain for the year, she said.</p>
<p>Pyongyang had pinned hopes of immediate hunger relief on the maize harvest but the drought's impact on that and other crops meant chronic food shortages would last until at least November 1998, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are concerned about the effect on paddy fields, which could be of alarming proportions,&quot; she said. &quot;We'll have to wait and see how it affects the overall food shortfall.&quot;</p>
<p>The food shortage had forced many people to forage for wild grasses, treebark, roots and berries to supplement their meagre daily grain rations of 100 grams (3.5 ounces), she said.</p>
<p>&quot;What you've got at the moment is a deteriorating situation and we know...that there is under-nutrition, malnutrition and severe malnutrition,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>&quot;The food shortage has affected everybody,&quot; she added.</p>
<p>Visits to schools and hospitals throughout North Korea had turned up starving children with skin hanging loosely from their limbs and festering sores on their bodies, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;To go into classrooms, nurseries and kindergartens and see apathetic, lifeless children staring vacantly into space is heartbreaking,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>The proportion of malnourished children appeared to be much higher than the 37 percent claimed by Pyongyang, and the World Food Programme would launch a survey next week to try to gather more accurate data about the extent of the hunger, she said.</p>
<p>&quot;Until we get this objective study looking at the prevalence in a random sample, we just have no firm statistics,&quot; she said.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BEIJING"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
