<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789780" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: PRESS DIGEST - INDIAN NEWSPAPERS - AUGUST 9.</title>
<headline>PRESS DIGEST - INDIAN NEWSPAPERS - AUGUST 9.</headline>
<text>
<p>Following is a summary of major Indian business and political stories in leading newspapers prepared for REUTERS by Business News and Information Services Pvt Ltd, New Delhi Tel:3326806, 3326813, 3326849 Fax:+91-11-3351006 E-mail: biznis@giasdl01.vsnl.net.in</p>
<p>Reuters has not verified these stories and does not vouch for their</p>
<p>accuracy.</p>
<p>		   -------oo0oo-------</p>
<p>			TOP STORIES</p>
<p>The Times Of India</p>
<p>CONGRESS PARTY MEET DILUTES CRITICISM OF RAO ERA</p>
<p>The 80th plenary session of the All India Congress Committee (AICC) opened in Calcutta amid indications of growing polarisation between pro-Rajiv Gandhi leaders and anti-Rajiv Gandhi leaders in the party. A few senior leaders who were close to former prime minister Narasimha Rao are likely to scuttle efforts by Sitaram Kesri and Arjun Singh to take the party closer to the Nehru-Gandhilegacy. Party vice president Jitendra Prasada, Sharad Pawar, Pranab Mukherjee and a few other leaders have joined hands to try drop negative references to the Narasimha Rao period contained in the draft resolution.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Hindustan Times</p>
<p>KHURANA QUITS PARTY POST</p>
<p>Former Delhi chief minister Madan Lal Khurana resigned from the post of Bharatiya Janata Party vice president. Khurana said he would continue to serve the party as an ordinary party worker and was not resigning from the Delhi state assembly. He also relinquished his post as the person in charge of the party affairs of Punjab and Rajasthan states. His resignation came after the party leadership decided to retain the present chief minister of Delhi. While Khurana was talking to media representatives, his supporters who gathered outside his home demanded justice from the party leadership and denounced the decision to retain Sahib Singh Verma as Delhi chief minister.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Economic Times</p>
<p>EXPORT-IMPORT BANK SNIPS RATE TO 12.5 PCT</p>
<p>The Export-Import Bank slashed the interest rate on post-shipment rupee export credit by 200 basis points to 12.5 percent from 14.5 percent. It also introduced a new maturity-linked rate structure for all export loans. The reduced rates will come into force immediately. The Bank's executive director Y.B. Desai said export credit above two years and up to five years would attract an interest of 13.5 percent, while credit above five years would be at 14 percent. He said the minimum rate for post-shipment credit in U.S. dollars for one year was reduced to Libor plus 75 basis points.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>MORGAN STANLEY OFFLOADING ASIAN PAINT SHARES</p>
<p>Morgan Stanley began offloading Asian Paints stock and is believed to have sold a few hundred thousand shares this week. The Asian Paints' share price plummeted Friday to 308.50 rupees from Thursday's 342.5 rupees before recovering to close at 315 rupees. The stock being sold does not form part of the 1.5 million Asian Paints shares Morgan Stanley bought on July 31. On August 7 it sold 40,000 of Asian Paints shares to the Government of Singapore Investment Corporation.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Financial Express</p>
<p>BOURSE INDICATOR FALLS BY 50 POINTS</p>
<p>The last day of settlement on the Bombay bourse saw the sensitive index drop by 49.52 points to close at 4,397.54 points. The bourse recorded net turnover of 10.28 billion rupees with the number of trades touching a new high of 101,560. According to market participants, the last 15 minutes of the trading session on the Bombay bourse experienced a revived bull run with punters entering the market to take fresh positions at counters such as State Bank of India and Reliance.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>ENRON SUBMITS $2 BLN PROJECT PROPOSAL</p>
<p>Enron International has proposed setting up a $2 billion gas pipeline distribution system and liquefied natural gas (LNG) re-gasification terminal in Maharashtra state. The company has applied for the Foreign Investment Promotion Board's permission to set up the projects. The proposal is to set up a new company in which Enron's affiliates will initially bring in $500 million by way of equity. It will develop an integrated re-gas facility for sourcing, importing, handling, storing and re-gasifying LNG plus a pipeline system, the application states. The new company will supply the LNG to private and government companies and to Enron's own 2,184 mw power plant at Dabhol.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Standard</p>
<p>MORGAN BREACHES 20 PCT LIMIT IN SHARE PURCHASE</p>
<p>A broker struck a deal to buy about 200,000 shares of State Bank of India on behalf of Morgan Stanley on the Bombay bourse. The order was placed at a price of 350 rupees, a premium of about 10 percent over the then ruling market price. The broker however made a punching error and the deal was actually struck at 324 rupees for the lot. The broker thus lost 1.6 million rupees. Bombay bourse sources said Morgan Stanley had decided to take delivery and the transaction will go through. But it will have to take special permission from the Reserve Bank of India to buy the stock since foreign institutional investors' investment in the scrip has already reached the 20 percent limit.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>FIAT TO FLOAT NEW VENTURE</p>
<p>Fiat SpA of Italy rejected French giant Peugeot's overtures to join the PAL-Peugeot joint venture in India. It will now link up with Premier Automobiles (PAL) to form a new joint venture which will be named PAL Auto. Fiat will hold a majority stake of 51 percent in the new venture. The remaining 49 percent will be held by PAL. PAL Auto will produce Fiat Uno and PAL's Premier Padmini in India. PAL's Kurla factory will be sold as a running business to the new company at a total value of about 5.01 billion rupees. The new venture will strip PAL of most of its major business and reduce it to marketing the Padmini and making auto components for Fiat.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>The Observer</p>
<p>NON-CONGRESS GOVERNMENTS BLAMED FOR ECONOMIC ILLS</p>
<p>Former finance minister Manmohan Singh blamed all non-Congress party governments at the centre for mismanagement of the economy in his address to the Congress party plenary session in Calcutta. He strongly defended the economic reforms initiated by the P.V. Narasimha Rao government in 1991. Manmohan Singh said those programmes were not anti-poor as alleged by the Bharatiya Janata Party and the leftist parties. It was the only way to remove poverty and build a vibrant economy. He was critical of the measures taken by the present government and said economic progress was in danger again.</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Business Line</p>
<p>FOREIGN INVESTMENT ONLY IN SELECT AREAS</p>
<p>The Congress party said effective policy measures should be adopted to attract overseas investment in select areas so as to add to the pool of national investible resources. The Economic Policy Resolution adopted at the plenary session of the party in Calcutta said such investments should not become a substitute for domestic resource mobilisation. It said foreign investment ought to be directed towards the development of infrastructure and export-oriented activities where there was considerable scope for transfer of technology. The party favoured independent regulatory authorities for the infrastructure sector to lay down rules for entry and tariff fixation.</p>
<p>----</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
