<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789700" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>TAJIKISTAN: Armed clashes rock capital of Tajikistan.</title>
<headline>Armed clashes rock capital of Tajikistan.</headline>
<dateline>DUSHANBE 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fighting erupted between two rival armed bands in a northern district of the Tajik capital Dushanbe on Saturday, witnesses said, threatening a shaky peace in the former Soviet republic.</p>
<p>A Reuter correspondent was turned back from the area of the fighting by police but he said he heard small arms fire and an explosion.</p>
<p>The former Soviet republic is trying to emerge from a four-year civil war following a peace agreement signed in June.</p>
<p>Yakub Salimov, a senior tax official and a nominally pro-government commander, said by telephone the fighting involved his own armed group and men belonging to an elite unit of Interior Ministry troops led by commander Sufrob Kasimov.</p>
<p>&quot;They are shooting here but I have not heard of any  casualties so far,&quot; he told Reuters.</p>
<p>There was no immediate comment from Kasimov.</p>
<p>Tajik military sources said the fighting was linked to a vendetta between local armed groups, but there was no official reaction to the fighting.</p>
<p>A maverick government commander, Colonel Makhmud Khudoyberdyev, stepped up the pressure by saying he wanted Kasimov to leave Dushanbe.</p>
<p>&quot;If Kasimov does not leave Dushanbe by the end of the day, I will move my armour to Fakhrobad (south of Dushanbe),&quot; Khudoyberdyev told Reuters by telephone from his base near Kurgan Tyube in southern Tajikistan.</p>
<p>He said 700 armed &quot;volunteers&quot; had already taken control of a government checkpoint 30 km (19 miles) south of Dushanbe in the Fakhrobad Valley. This could not be independently confirmed.</p>
<p>Khudoyberdyev, who commands an elite armoured brigade, has mutinied twice. His relations with the government are ambivalent.</p>
<p>The Tajik government and the republic's armed Islamic opposition signed a peace agreement in June to end the civil war which killed tens of thousands of people and displaced many more.</p>
<p>But Khudoyberdyev said last week the return of up to 500 armed Islamic opposition guerrillas to Dushanbe, which the accord provides for, would provoke fresh bloodshed.</p>
<p>A ceasefire has largely held since December but a  kaleidoscopic array of armed bands threaten stability in the impoverished republic of 5.7 million which borders Afghanistan and China.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TADZK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DUSHANBE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TAJIKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
