<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789773" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>UNITED NATIONS: UN says 80,000 North Korean children could starve.</title>
<headline>UN says 80,000 North Korean children could starve.</headline>
<byline>Evelyn Leopold</byline>
<dateline>UNITED NATIONS 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Food aid to 800,000 North Korean children suffering from malnutrition should not be held hostage to the politics of the communist state, UNICEF director Carol Bellamy said.</p>
<p>&quot;People are dying and people are going to die,&quot; said Bellamy on Friday, hours after she returned from North Korea. She recently tripled UNICEF aid appeals to $14.3 million.</p>
<p>She said about 800,000 children or 38 percent of those younger than 5 were suffering from malnutrition. Of this group 80,000 chldren were severely malnourished and in danger of dying from starvation and disease.</p>
<p>Her estimates were similar to those of North Korea and those released last month by the aid agency, Caritas.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very important that the immediate significant humanitarian crisis not find itself hostage to what is also a political crisis. Humanitarian needs can't wait,&quot; she told a news conference.</p>
<p>The United States, South Korea and Japan, among others, have at one time or another indirectly linked food aid to North Korea's presence at peace talks. North Korea, in turn, has done the same in exchange for its cooperation.</p>
<p>The country has suffered from drought this year after food stocks were already depleted by two years of floods.</p>
<p>Bellamy said the circle of affected children grew daily. We are already seeing children up to the age of 15 who are severely malnourished and in danger of dying,&quot; she said. &quot;Starvations hits babies first.&quot;</p>
<p>Bellamy, a former New York City Council president and U.S. Peace Corps director, said her U.N. Children's Fund was working closely with the larger World Food Programme operation in North Korea and was concentrating on high-energy milk, medicines and equipment to treat hunger-related diseases.</p>
<p>UNICEF officials said a previous appeal for $3.4 million had been filled with $2.6 million from the European Union and $310,000 from Norway. In addition, Japan's UNICEF committee raised $300,000 while its counterparts in the United States contributed $60,000. The charity group Oxfam has also sent $82,000 worth of supplies.</p>
<p>Bellamy said she was in negotiations with the United States and Japan for funds but was not &quot;as optimistic about Japan as I am with some of the other donors.&quot;</p>
<p>Japan, she said, was decreasing its overall foreign aid and was also pulling back from assistance to North Korea.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NKOREA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E51">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UNITED NATIONS"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
