<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789782" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>PAKISTAN: Sectarian attacks kill 14 in Pakistan.</title>
<headline>Sectarian attacks kill 14 in Pakistan.</headline>
<dateline>MULTAN, Pakistan 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fourteen people, most of them Shi'ite Moslems, were killed in Pakistan on Saturday in two attacks thought to be part of a bloody feud between Sunni and Shi'ite Moslem militants, witnesses and hospital sources said.</p>
<p>The shootings occurred within hours of each other in the populous province of Punjab, scene of most of the sectarian violence that has claimed at least 144 lives this year.</p>
<p>In the first attack, gunmen struck before dawn, killing six Shi'ites while they slept in the village of Mondka, in Khangarh district, 28 miles (45 km) west of the Punjab city of Multan.</p>
<p>The dead included the local head of the Shi'ite Tehrik-i-Jafria Pakistan (TJP) group, identified only as Mushtaq, and several of his relatives, hospital sources said.</p>
<p>One person was critically wounded and taken to hospital in Multan. His son, Sayed Asif Shah, who witnessed the assault but escaped unhurt, told Reuters that four gunmen on motorcycles had selected their victims before shooting them in the head.</p>
<p>A few hours later, motorcyclists fired Kalashnikov assault rifles at a crowded market in the town of Warbartan, some 60 km (37 miles) northwest of the Punjab capital Lahore, killing eight people and wounding 10, most of them Shi'ites, witnesses said.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif told his brother Shahbaz Sharif, chief minister of Punjab province, on Friday to crack down on sectarian groups, newspapers reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>They quoted the prime minister as urging the Punjab provincial government to push ahead with police reforms and speed up the interrogation and prosecution of suspects.</p>
<p>Police in Khanewal, about 50 km (30 miles) east of Multan, said on Thursday they had arrested two Sunni militants, both members of the Lashkar-e-Jhangvi group, who had admitted killing 37 Shi'ites Moslems in various attacks.</p>
<p>They said the two men had planned to assassinate TJP leader Sajid Naqvi and half a dozen Shi'ite notables, including Population Welfare Minister Abida Hussain and her husband Fakhar Imam, a member of the National Assembly (lower house).</p>
<p>Shi'ites form about 15 percent of Pakistan's mainly Sunni population of more than 135 million. Sunni militants accuse Shi'ite-majority Iran of aiding Shi'ite organisations in Pakistan. Shi'ites say Saudi Arabia helps their Sunni rivals.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MULTAN, Pakistan"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="PAKISTAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
