<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789725" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Nagasaki slams U.S. test 52 years after A-bomb.</title>
<headline>Nagasaki slams U.S. test 52 years after A-bomb.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>The mayor of Nagasaki denounced U.S. nuclear tests as thousands gathered in the southern Japanese city on Saturday to mark the 52nd anniversary of the atomic bombing which killed more than 115,000 people.</p>
<p>More than 25,000 people gathered to remember atomic victims at Nagasaki's Peace Park near where a U.S. bomber dropped the &quot;Fat Man&quot; bomb on August 9, 1945.</p>
<p>The nuclear fireball and the lingering effects of radioactivity killed 115,669 people. The bombing came three days after Hiroshima in southern Japan was devastated in the world's first nuclear attack.</p>
<p>Mayor Itcho Ito also strongly criticised a subcritical nuclear test conducted by the U.S. last month.</p>
<p>&quot;We vehemently denounce the test,&quot; he said, adding the test was conducted to safeguard the United States' nuclear deterrence policy. He urged the Japanese government to make a protest.</p>
<p>The United States maintains the July 2 test did not violate the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty (CTBT) adopted by the U.N. General Assembly last September.</p>
<p>Ito also slammed apologists of the nuclear bombing.</p>
<p>&quot;We will continue to appeal about the horror and inhumanity of the atomic bombings... The citizens of Nagasaki cannot tolerate the fact that there is still a body of opinion trying to justify the atomic bombings.&quot;</p>
<p>Ito also noted that Japan must face the fact that it inflicted suffering on the peoples of other countries during World War II.</p>
<p>&quot;We must confront and reflect deeply upon the fact of Japan's history of invasion and aggression in the Asia-Pacific region,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>However, for the first time in seven years, the word &quot;apology&quot; was dropped from the declaration concerning the war Japan launched in Asia.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
