<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789784" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: PARADES, SONGS MARK HISTORIC INDIA ANNIVERSARY.</title>
<headline>PARADES, SONGS MARK HISTORIC INDIA ANNIVERSARY.</headline>
<byline>Clarence Fernandez</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thousands of school children marched through India's commercial capital on Saturday, waving placards and shouting patriotic slogans in simple ceremonies that marked a historic national anniversary.</p>
<p>&quot;Victory to Mother India,&quot; they shouted in the thin early light of dawn. &quot;We are all one.&quot;</p>
<p>One slogan that has not been heard for over 50 years echoed through the narrow bylanes of the congested city of 13.5 million people as the students marched.</p>
<p>&quot;Quit India,&quot; they yelled, breathing new life into a battle cry that has endured only in the history books. &quot;Quit India.&quot;</p>
<p>They were marking the 55th anniversary of the &quot;Quit India&quot; movement, launched from Bombay's August Revolution grounds in 1942 by Mahatma Gandhi and Congress, the political party he led.</p>
<p>An estimated 130,000 school children participated in the dawn marches according to Pramod Navalkar, cultural affairs minister of western Maharashtra state, of which Bombay is the capital.</p>
<p>The &quot;Quit India&quot; protest was the final move in the campaign to force the British to leave India, which ended with the birth of India and Pakistan in 1947. Each year, the anniversary sparks an outpouring of nationalist fervour.</p>
<p>Nearby, a Buddhist priest rhythmically beat a peace drum as he led white-haired socialists, freedom fighters and Gandhi's followers in a silent parade along Bombay's seaface to the August Revolution grounds.</p>
<p>Earlier, they had laid wreaths before statues of Bal Gangadhar Tilak, a firebrand journalist who coined the nationalist rallying cry, &quot;Freedom is my birthright and I shall have it,&quot; and of Vallabhbhai Patel, free India's first home minister.</p>
<p>The marchers were briefly joined by members of a differing political tradition, Maharashtra Chief Minister Manohar Joshi, and his colleague Navalkar, of the ruling rightwing Shiv Sena party.</p>
<p>Dressed in simple white homespun cotton clothes, the participants carried two large pictures of Mahatma Gandhi. A convoy of school children, millworkers and political workers joined up with the procession as it reached the grounds.</p>
<p>The Indian tricolour was unfurled to the strains of India's national anthem, and the gathering launched into a series of patriotic songs.</p>
<p>It was not all sweet memories, however. Some freedom fighters condemned the widespread corruption in Indian political circles.</p>
<p>&quot;The struggle is still going on,&quot; said Capt Lakshmi Sehgal, a member of the Indian National Army, which took up arms against the British in the closing years of the second world war.</p>
<p>&quot;Fifty years ago it was against the British rulers, but now it is against corruption and atrocities on women and others,&quot; she added. &quot;The fight must continue.&quot;</p>
<p>Prime Minister Inder Kumar Gujral will kick off Maharashtra state's official celebrations at the August Revolution grounds later on Saturday, observing two minutes of silent remembrance in honour of all those who died in the freedom struggle.</p>
<p>--Bombay newsroom (91) 22-265-9000</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
