<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789708" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: At least five dead in Miami plane crash.</title>
<headline>At least five dead in Miami plane crash.</headline>
<byline>Patricia Zengerle</byline>
<dateline>MIAMI 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>The death count in the crash of a cargo jet near Miami International Airport rose to at least five on Friday, when investigators combing the charred wreckage found two more bodies.</p>
<p>&quot;The fourth body was recovered this afternoon,&quot; a spokesman for the Metro-Dade county police department said.</p>
<p>Another officer later confirmed that a fifth body was found on Friday, although he could not confirm whether it was that of another victim on the ground or the fourth member of the jet's crew. At least one of the victims was found in a car beneath the remains of the jet.</p>
<p>Police said two people had been reported missing since the 29-year-old Fine Air Services Inc BIGF.O DC-8-61F aircraft slammed through a busy commercial district at lunchtime on Thursday.</p>
<p>All four members of the cargo jet's crew were believed to have perished in the disaster, although investigators said the bodies of only three people had been pulled from the remains of the cockpit at the crash scene.</p>
<p>At least 25 investigators, including 15 from the National Transportation Safety Board, were working on the crash.</p>
<p>NTSB Chairman Jim Hall told a news conference late Friday that early investigation showed the plane, which crashed just after takeoff, had hit the ground tail first with its right wing low.</p>
<p>Most witnesses had reported seeing it roll on takeoff and heard loud engine noises, he said, adding that some also said they saw flames coming from the jet as it crashed.</p>
<p>Hall said early data from the cockpit voice data recorder showed no problems until just after takeoff, moments before the DC-8 hit the ground. But data from the flight recorder was incomplete, a problem he said had been found before in aircraft retrofitted with the complex devices that record data from sensors throughout aircraft.</p>
<p>&quot;Our offices in Washington say that one or more of those sensors ... were not working, so that we will probably not be able to retrieve the full 11 parameters of information the recorder is capable of recording,&quot; Hall said.</p>
<p>He said similar problems had been found in crashes including the ValuJet crash in Miami's Everglades in May 1996, and that the FAA was expected to order tightened regulation of the devices by this fall.</p>
<p>Hall said the NTSB was thoroughly investigating Fine Air, which announced on Friday it was rescinding an initial public stock offering it began Wednesday.</p>
<p>Separately, the Federal Aviation Administration confirmed on Friday it had proposed to suspend for 60 to 90 days the certificates of 29 pilots who fly for Fine Air in an action unrelated to the Miami crash. Fine also has been in a dispute with the government of Peru, which alleged the company had illegally transported arms to Ecuador.</p>
<p>Hall said workers at the NTSB's laboratory in Washington, already stretched from this week's air disaster in Guam, had labored through the night examining data from the jet's cockpit voice recorder and flight data recorder.</p>
<p>The Fine aircraft laden with thousands of pounds of fabric had slammed through a busy commercial district adjacent to the airport seconds after takeoff, smashing cars, sending up columns of black smoke and scattering flaming wreckage.</p>
<p>WSVN, the local Fox television affiliate, reported on Friday that Renato Alvarez, a 34-year-old Miami resident, had been missing since Thursday afternoon, when he telephoned his wife at her office near the Fine Air crash site and told her he would be arriving shortly with lunch for both of them.</p>
<p>&quot;I have a feeling that he is there (in the wreckage). I have just this gut feeling that he is there,&quot; his wife, Maria Alvarez, told the TV station.</p>
<p>As Hall and other officials spoke with reporters, their news conference was interrupted by shouts of &quot;Smoke, smoke,&quot; as a plume of black smoke eerily similar to that from the Fine crash rose about a mile from the crash site.</p>
<p>Police raced to the scene to find a burning, overturned tanker truck. The smoke from the tanker crash forced closure of a runway at Miami International Airport.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I75000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MIAMI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
