<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789705" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>MEXICO: LITTLE JOY SEEN IN CUTTING MEXICO VAT - OFFICIALS.</title>
<headline>LITTLE JOY SEEN IN CUTTING MEXICO VAT - OFFICIALS.</headline>
<dateline>MEXICO CITY 1997-08-08</dateline>
<text>
<p>Mexican finance officials, weighing the possible impact of proposals to reduce Value Added Tax (VAT), said on Friday that cutting it would bring little benefit to those a change was intended to help.</p>
<p>Some 32 state finance secretaries, meeting at the Mexican coastal resort of Cancun on Friday, said cutting VAT to 10 percent from its current 15 percent, in line with opposition proposals, would also have a negative impact on state budgets, a finance ministry statement said.</p>
<p>&quot;This measure,...would not benefit those people of scarce resources whose expenditure is concentrated in products and services that do not carry this tax,&quot; the statement quoted them as saying.</p>
<p>Opposition politicians, flexing their muscles since making unprecedented gains in elections last month, are mustering their forces for an assault on the unpopular tax that was raised at the height of Mexico's 1995 recession.</p>
<p>Opposition parties are keen to make good their election promises to bring the tariff down when the new Congress meets in September.</p>
<p>The Finance Ministry has said cutting it would blow a 25 billion peso hole in the national budget and would erode state and local finances.</p>
<p>But the state finance officials unanimously approved a request that federal deputies carefully study alternatives to modifying the national tax framework, the statement said.</p>
<p>Tomas Ruiz, head of the Finance Ministry's SAT tax department, said Mexico had chosen the best economic path.</p>
<p>&quot;The stabilization of the economy and its growth over the last two years present the clearest evidence that the correct route is being followed,&quot; he said. ((--Caroline Brothers, Mexico City newsroom +525 728 7905))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="MEX">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-08"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEXICO CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="MEXICO"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
