<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789795" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Talks continue at GM plant as strike deadline passes.</title>
<headline>Talks continue at GM plant as strike deadline passes.</headline>
<byline>David Lawder</byline>
<dateline>DETROIT 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>A midnight deadline at General Motors Corp.'s Cadillac assembly plant passed without a strike as bargainers continued talks early on Saturday in an effort to reach a deal for a new local labour contract.</p>
<p>United Auto Workers Local 22 and its 3,600 members were poised to unleash the seventh strike this year against the auto giant, a walkout that could disrupt the launch of GM's important new 1998 Seville flagship sedan.</p>
<p>Workers streamed out of the plant in the Hamtramck, Michigan, enclave in Detroit after the 11:59 p.m. EDT Friday deadline and began picketing, but union officials said talks were continuing and no strike had been declared.</p>
<p>&quot;We have not been notified that there has been an end to these talks,&quot; said Local 22 recording secretary Karl Burnett. &quot;It is believed they're still at it.&quot;</p>
<p>GM spokesman Paul Spadafora said the union had not informed the company of a strike.</p>
<p>The Cadillac plant on the Detroit-Hamtramck border does not normally build cars on Saturday, so any walkout declared over the weekend would not affect production until Monday.</p>
<p>As in six strikes this year and numerous strike threats, the UAW demanded more jobs at the plant to replace retiring workers and ease a growing workload. GM resisted such moves, maintaining that it needs to shrink its workforce to become competitive with Ford Motor Co., Chrysler Corp., and Japanese automakers.</p>
<p>The plant on the Detroit-Hamtramck border is the only assembly site for Cadillac's Seville, DeVille and Eldorado models, but dealers have ample supplies of 1997 models of the cars.</p>
<p>But a prolonged walkout could disrupt GM's ambitious plans to position the '98 Seville as a world-class luxury car that can compete head-to-head with Mercedes-Benz, BMW and Lexus. GM will unveil the car next month in the German automakers' backyard, at the international auto show in Frankfurt, Germany.</p>
<p>Cadillac plans to build a right-hand-drive version of the car and hopes to export the Seville all over the world in a bid to shed its stuffy, land-yacht image.</p>
<p>A seven-week strike that started in April at GM's Oklahoma City assembly plant disrupted the launch of GM's mid-size Chevrolet Malibu and Oldsmobile Cutlass sedans, which were viewed as critical to GM's efforts to regain market share.</p>
<p>&quot;The most damaging thing about the strike in Oklahoma City was that it forced the company to relaunch the Malibu,&quot; said Schroder Wertheim &amp; Co. auto analyst John Casesa. &quot;If the strike had not happened, that car would have better awareness and better sales.&quot;</p>
<p>GM sold a respectable 12,996 Malibus in July, but that still fell short of the Corsicas and Berettas it replaced, which had sales of 15,698 units for the month.</p>
<p>Analysts also worry that consumers' attention will be drawn away from the car by Honda's launch of an all-new Accord this fall.</p>
<p>The strikes have been costly to GM, cutting second-quarter profits by $490 million and reducing its share of the domestic car and light truck market well below GM's 1997 goal of 33 percent.</p>
<p>The automaker also said on Friday that a three-month walkout at a Pontiac, Michigan, truck plant and a six-day strike at a Warren, Michigan, transmission plant, forced it to cut its third-quarter production schedule by 20,000 vehicles.</p>
<p>A walkout at the Cadillac plant walkout would not have a widespread impact on GM's North American production operations since it is a final assembly plant. But it could force layoffs at plants that produce parts and components for it, such as engines and seats.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DETROIT"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
