<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789758" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>IRAN: Iran's Khatami to appoint first woman to cabinet.</title>
<headline>Iran's Khatami to appoint first woman to cabinet.</headline>
<dateline>TEHRAN 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Iran's new President Mohammad Khatami has appointed the first woman to the cabinet since the 1979 Islamic revolution, an Iranian newspaper reported on Saturday.</p>
<p>Masoumeh Ebtekar, a 36-year-old U.S.-educated professor at Tehran university, was appointed vice president and head of the Environmental Protection Organisation, the English-language Iran News quoted an unnamed source as saying.</p>
<p>It said Ebtekar holds a doctorate in immunology, and had served on the editorial board of an Iranian newspaper group.</p>
<p>Khatami was swept to power by a landslide election victory in May after attracting the female, youth and middle-class vote on expectations of social and economic reform.</p>
<p>The appointment of at least one woman to the cabinet was seen by analysts as a recognition by Khatami that a large section of Iranian women are pressing for a stronger voice in political, legal, social and cultural issues.</p>
<p>The 54-year-old Shi'ite Moslem cleric has until August 18 to submit his full cabinet list for approval to the Majlis, or parliament.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="IRAN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TEHRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="IRAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
