<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789732" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>CAMBODIA: Cambodian king says cannot intervene in &quot;comedy&quot;.</title>
<headline>Cambodian king says cannot intervene in &quot;comedy&quot;.</headline>
<dateline>PHNOM PENH 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cambodia's King Norodom Sihanouk said he cannot be a player in his country's current political &quot;comedy&quot; because his views differed radically from those of the people in power.</p>
<p>He said he was powerless to intervene.</p>
<p>The king, in a message to Cambodian opposition leader Sam Rainsy, said he did not want to take any responsibility for political decisions in Cambodia and that was why he had authorised acting head of state Chea Sim to sign all laws and decrees.</p>
<p>&quot;I presently suffer morally a great deal as much as the innocent people of our country,&quot; the king said in his letter to former finance minister Sam Rainsy.</p>
<p>Sam Rainsy, a political ally of the king's son, the ousted Prince Norodom Ranariddh, is in Bangkok where he translated the king's message from the Cambodian language and made a copy of it available to Reuters on Saturday.</p>
<p>&quot;The fate of our nation is terribly sad: as for me I have no ability to do anything,&quot; Sihanouk, a constitutional monarch, said in his letter from Beijing where he is receiving medical treatment.</p>
<p>&quot;The power is totally in their hands,&quot; he said of government leaders in Phnom Penh. &quot;Their views are totally different from mine. I have no possibility to make them follow my way.&quot;</p>
<p>The Cambodian constitution requires that the king approve a new first prime minister but Sihanouk authorised Chea Sim to appoint Foreign Minister Ung Huot first premier in place of Ranariddh on Thursday.</p>
<p>Ranariddh was overthrown on July 6 by his coalition partner, Second Prime Minister Hun Sen.</p>
<p>&quot;If I give (Mr) Chea Sim the authorisation to sign all laws and decrees in my place, it is to make him responsible for the people and before history,&quot; Sihanouk said in the letter, dated Friday.</p>
<p>&quot;I must not share this responsibility with him nor with (Mr) Hun Sen. If I share this responsibility ...it would mean I associate myself with these people in the ongoing new political game.</p>
<p>&quot;I just cannot take part in this new comedy involving the state,&quot; he said. &quot;History will render justice to each one of us.&quot;</p>
<p>Hun Sen, Ung Huot and Chea Sim are due to travel to Beijing on Monday for a meeting with Sihanouk.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="KAMPA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PHNOM PENH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CAMBODIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
