<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="789727" id="root" date="1997-08-09" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesia says executive not dictating to lawmaker.</title>
<headline>Indonesia says executive not dictating to lawmaker.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-08-09</dateline>
<text>
<p>An Indonesian minister said on Saturday a government course for MPs was not an attempt by the executive to dominate the next parliament.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a concern in a small part of our society. They are worried that this course symbolises the force, dictation and harassment by the executive of the legislative,&quot; State Minister for Special Tasks Harmoko said at the opening of the course.</p>
<p>&quot;All of this is certainly based on unfounded suspicions. The government wants to use the course so the tasks and functions of 1997-2002 members of parliament can be improved,&quot; Harmoko said.</p>
<p>&quot;The government has never forced the candidates for the parliament to join the course. The government has only offered the course to those candidates who want to accept.&quot;</p>
<p>Most of the 500 people nominated by the three authorised parties and the armed forces as legislators in the next parliament are expected to attend the course held at the Bogor Palace from August 10 until September 14.</p>
<p>Lectures and discussions on the state ideology Pancasila and the 1945 constitution are expected to be given by government officials as well as a number of academics and senior community figures.</p>
<p>Last May, Indonesia elected 425 members of the 500-member House of Representatives after an election campaign which was regarded as the most violent during the 30 years of President Suharto's rule.</p>
<p>The military, who do not vote, are given 75 seats in the house, many filled by a number of senior generals.</p>
<p>Suharto said Indonesia was entering a new era that would bring big changes.</p>
<p>&quot;One of the purposes of the course is to anticipate the future... We need to prepare ourselves with a broader outlook,&quot; Suharto said in his speech to the opening ceremony.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-09"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-09"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
