<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798399" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: PAKISTAN'S IMRAN KHAN JUDGED TO BE FATHER OF GIRL. [CORRECTED 01:17 GMT 15/8]</title>
<headline>PAKISTAN'S IMRAN KHAN JUDGED TO BE FATHER OF GIRL. [CORRECTED 01:17 GMT 15/8]</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-08-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Pakistani cricket hero and former prime ministerial (corrects from presidential) candidate Imran Khan was ruled by a U.S. judge on Wednesday to be the legal father of a five-year-old girl born out of wedlock to the daughter of a British nobleman.</p>
<p>&quot;Imran Khan is the father of the child,&quot; Los Angeles Superior Court Commissioner (judge) Anthony Jones ruled after hearing evidence from the girl's mother, Sita White, daughter of the late British industrialist Lord Gordon White.</p>
<p>Khan, who was defeated in his bid to become prime minister of Pakistan in February, did not appear in court for Wednesday's hearing. His attorneys were also absent and Jones entered a &quot;default judgement&quot; against him.</p>
<p>Contacted by telephone in New York, Khan's lawyer Bernard Clair said a decision had been made for Khan and his lawyers to be absent to &quot;avoid a media circus.&quot;</p>
<p>The hearing was attended by three British newspaper reporters and a U.S. news agency reporter.</p>
<p>Clair said Khan &quot;categorically denies the paternity and...if necessary he will take additional steps to clarify the existing situation.&quot;</p>
<p>Judge Jones also agreed to retain jurisdiction over any child support claims White might make against Khan.</p>
<p>White testified that she met Khan, then captain of the Pakistan cricket team, in 1988, and conceived a child with him in 1991. The girl, referred to in court only by her first and middle names, Tyrian Jade, was born on June 15, 1992.</p>
<p>White's attorney, Gloria Allred, said later the girl's last name was not being given because of her age. In court, Allred claimed Khan had &quot;never seen or spoken to the girl,&quot; but had admitted to White that he was the father and had even helped her pick out the girl's names.</p>
<p>White, who lives with her daughter in Beverly Hills, was also granted sole custody of the child, but indicated in court that she would be willing to allow Khan to visit with the girl if he chose to.</p>
<p>Khan, who is married with one son, has steadfastly denied being the father of the girl.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
