<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798660" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>SOUTH AFRICA: FEATURE - S.African justice minister's heavy portfolio.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - S.African justice minister's heavy portfolio.</headline>
<byline>Juliette Saunders</byline>
<dateline>PRETORIA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>South African Justice Minister Dullah Omar, working to transform an apartheid court system and helping in the fight against rampant crime, says his responsibilities disturb his sleep.</p>
<p>An innocent seven-year-old girl has brought the trauma and frustration of his job into sharp focus.</p>
<p>Tiny Mamokgethi Malebane accused a 29-year-old neighbour of raping her.</p>
<p>Instead of protection from the courts, she was kidnapped and murdered after he was freed on bail through the bungling of an overworked public prosecutor.</p>
<p>&quot;There's a very big responsibility on our shoulders -- I don't sleep well at night because there is so much work to be done,&quot; Omar, a 63-year-old father of three, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;It can't be done overnight, unfortunately, but we are doing quite a lot.&quot;</p>
<p>Omar has acted swiftly, introducing ground-breaking draft legislation severely restricting access to bail by suspects accused of serious crimes, including rape. He won the backing of the cabinet early in August, and has promised to take it to parliament before the end of this year.</p>
<p>AN INTIMATE KNOWLEDGE OF INJUSTICE</p>
<p>The son of a greengrocer-hawker who was detained without trial and kept in solitary confinement for his opposition to white rule, Omar opposes calls from an increasingly irate public for a state of emergency to be introduced and the death penalty reinstated.</p>
<p>South Africa's murder rate averaged 65 a day for the first three months of this year and, on average, 149 women were raped each day. The horror of the statistics is mirrored in their prevalence in every-day conversation among South Africans.</p>
<p>But Omar defended the courts against frequent criticism that they fail to convict criminals, saying the success rate was much better than perceived.</p>
<p>&quot;The big problem is that many people escape the entire justice system,&quot; he said. &quot;Dockets are not brought to court and (only) three out of 10 people who commit serious crimes are arrested.&quot;</p>
<p>Candidly admitting a myriad of problems in his portfolio, ranging from overworked and underpaid staff to courts operating without toilets or running water, Omar said he was expanding training and wanted to create 1,500-1,600 new posts.</p>
<p>His department currently has 14,000 employees.</p>
<p>PAST REMAINS HURDLE FOR LAW AND ORDER</p>
<p>Omar, who was pivotal in setting up the statutory Truth and Reconciliation Commission, lauded its success in uncovering the truth of past human rights abuses and in entrenching an individual accountability for crimes.</p>
<p>&quot;It's done an outstanding job. It's been laying the basis for a clean nation,&quot; he said. &quot;We have never had accountability in our country and we are busy establishing that now.&quot;</p>
<p>However, he acknowledged the commission's inability so far to draw the opposition Inkatha Freedom Party into its hearings, and said he was willing to consider special measures for Inkatha members to seek amnesty for political crimes, even though the national deadline for applications expired in May.</p>
<p>&quot;In general, amnesty processes must not drag on,&quot; he said. &quot;Amnesty sends out the signal that you can commit a serious crime and you can be forgiven. Our society does not need that kind of signal.</p>
<p>&quot;But peace is very important there and we will do whatever is necessary to facilitate that. If any adjustments are necessary for KwaZulu-Natal (province), I'm sure the cabinet and government will consider it.&quot;</p>
<p>Although President Nelson Mandela's government has largely subdued political violence around the country, his African National Congress and Inkatha are still locked in a turf war in the Zulu heartland, where about 15,000 people were killed in the decade up to 1994.</p>
<p>Torn between crime and the need for reconciliation of the country's political past, Omar shoulders a heavy load on an uncertain path to achieving the respect for law and order he promised to ingrain when he took up the justice mantle.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="SAFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PRETORIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="SOUTH AFRICA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
