<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798702" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>BULGARIA: Bulgaria Moonies seek registration amid public concern.</title>
<headline>Bulgaria Moonies seek registration amid public concern.</headline>
<byline>Galina Sabeva</byline>
<dateline>SOFIA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Bulgarian followers of Korean evangelist Sun Myung Moon on Thursday appealed to the local authorities for registration amid growing concerns about the activity of their sect in this Balkan country.</p>
<p>Tinko Tinev, coordinator of Moon's movement in Bulgaria, said his sect, which has been denied registration in Bulgaria twice -- in 1992 and in 1994 -- would ask the government for registration as it was not doing anything contrary to the law.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see any reasonable grounds for not being registered -- all we want is to improve understanding among people worldwide, to improve family life and impose new family values,&quot; Tinev told a news conference.</p>
<p>He said the Moon's Unification Church, which has formally existed since 1954, had around three million followers across the world.</p>
<p>It has 400 members in Bulgaria, mainly between 20 and 25 years old, but some 10,000 couples in Bulgaria are supporting Moon's principles for restoring family values, Tinev said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile concerns are growing in Bulgaria about the activity of  Moon's church and its non-religious formations, following allegations in local media about links between suicide attempts by youngsters and membership in the sect.</p>
<p>&quot;It is almost impossible to prove that there is a link between suicide attempts by young people and their association with the Moonies as nobody could know what the reason for a suicide was,&quot; an official, who declined to be named, told Reuters.</p>
<p>The official said it was still a fact that members of the sect had attempted suicides and that many youngsters who had joined the Moon's church have abandoned their families, education and friends to devote themselves completely to their religion.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think that Moon's church would be registered as there are some things in its activity which are contrary to the country's constitution and legislative base,&quot; Georgi Krastev of the government's Ecclesiastical Directorate told Reuters.</p>
<p>He said that some parts of Moon's religion were believed by the authorities to be a threat to the rights of Bulgarian citizens.</p>
<p>The 76-year-old South Korean evangelist is believed by his followers to be an incarnation of God fulfilling the mission of Christ. Critics say he brainwashes vulnerable people into joining the church.</p>
<p>Some countries, such as Germany which last year issued a booklet warning against his church, consider him a threat to public order and refuse him an entry visa.</p>
<p>During the 1980s Moon served 11 months in prison in the United States for tax evasion. His church's assets span the world and include the Washington Times newspaper.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BUL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SOFIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BULGARIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
