<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798862" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Fugitive Biggs may escape British justice again.</title>
<headline>Fugitive Biggs may escape British justice again.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's best-known fugitive, Ronnie Biggs, could escape British justice once again because Brazilian law may prevent his extradition, Brazilian justice officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>Britain signed an extradition treaty with Brazil on Wednesday, but the statute of limitations in Brazil for crimes punishable with more than 12 years in jail runs out after 20 years.</p>
<p>Biggs, sentenced to 30 years in jail, has been a fugitive since 1963, when he took part in a legendary heist of 2.6 million pounds -- the equivalent of $50 million today -- from a Glasgow-to-London postal train that became known as the &quot;Great Train Robbery.&quot;</p>
<p>Brazil's highest law official, Justice Celso de Mello, said on Thursday the statute of limitations in Brazil for crimes punishable with more than 12 years in jail ran out after 20 years.</p>
<p>&quot;This is the big question, the main issue in this case,&quot; Mello, president of the Supreme Federal Tribunal, told Reuters in an interview.</p>
<p>Since fleeing to Brazil in 1970 as an escaped convict, Biggs has led the life of a local celebrity, basking in the glow not only of the tropical sun but also of immunity from prosecution because Brasilia and London had no extradition treaty.</p>
<p>The two countries ratified an extradition treaty on Wednesday for the first time, stoking speculation that officers from Scotland Yard could be flying into Rio de Janeiro within weeks to take Biggs back home in chains.</p>
<p>&quot;It's a bit premature to expect that,&quot; Mello said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's likely to be tough to extradite Biggs,&quot; said another Justice official, asking not to be named.</p>
<p>The Supreme Court judge declined for legal reasons to refer specifically to the Biggs case but spoke in &quot;generic&quot; terms.</p>
<p>Before the extradition treaty even comes into force under Brazilian law, Mello said, President Fernando Henrique Cardoso had to sign and publish a decree. After that, the process of applying for extradition was likely to take three or four months.</p>
<p>Once in court, the 11 judges of Brazil's Supreme Federal Tribunal would have to consider whether the time during which the crime could be punished had expired. In Brazil, the maximum period for a crime to come to trial is 20 years.</p>
<p>Contrary to some reports, Brazil could not bar extradition because the punishment in another country exceeds the punishment the same crime would merit under Brazilian law.</p>
<p>Similarly, the fact that a defendant is married to a Brazilian or has a legal dependent would not prevent their extradition. Marriage or dependents only prevent foreigners from being expelled from Brazil, not extradited.</p>
<p>Biggs, who has led a crime-free life in Brazil, has a son, Michael, who will turn 23 next month.</p>
<p>Biggs, now 68, has kept an usually low public profile in recent days and has hired British and Brazilian lawyers to defend him against any extradition attempt.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
