<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798845" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>YUGOSLAVIA: FEATURE - Yugoslavia faces pensions crisis as economy creaks.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Yugoslavia faces pensions crisis as economy creaks.</headline>
<byline>Gordana Kukic</byline>
<dateline>BELGRADE 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Vera Zivkovic eyes the stalls of fresh fruits, vegetables and meat at one of Belgrade's many open air markets but buys nothing.</p>
<p>&quot;I enjoy walking round the market. I love peaches and melons but they are too expensive for me,&quot; smiles the 74-year-old pensioner.</p>
<p>Vera, a retired bank clerk, lives alone in a modestly furnished one-room flat and is a typical Belgrade pensioner struggling each month to make ends meet on a pension of 600 dinars ($98).</p>
<p>&quot;I buy bread and milk every second day. Vegetables are only an occasional treat. Meat and fruit are a luxury for me,&quot; she says.</p>
<p>Economic forecasts suggest her plight will not improve in the foreseeable future and she might have to suffer even greater deprivation.</p>
<p>Yugoslavia's 1.6 million pensioners, who cost the state around 400 million German marks ($216 million) each month, are a heavy burden on a post-sanctions economy working at only 40 percent of capacity.</p>
<p>Taxes cannot meet the cost of the system of social security benefits inherited from the old communist system.</p>
<p>The government has forecast 1997 public spending at 47.5 percent of targeted gross domestic product of 103.28 billion dinars. Analysts estimate that public spending accounts for 50-55 percent of GDP.</p>
<p>PENSIONS SHAKE-UP PRIORITY FOR NEXT GOVERNMENT</p>
<p>A shake-up of the pension scheme must be among the top priorities for the next government after elections in September, economists say.</p>
<p>&quot;This is politically a very sensitive issue for all governments, but the pension system must be reformed since our moribund economy simply cannot sustain it any longer,&quot; said Zoran Popov, an economist at the Belgrade-based Economics Institute.</p>
<p>Pensioners in Yugoslavia receive up to 85 percent of the average monthly salary, which in June stood at 807 dinars.</p>
<p>But the government managed to secure money for just five monthly payouts by the end of July, and the state's outstanding debt to pensioners from previous years stands at some 2.5 billion dinars.</p>
<p>Zivkovic said the government had promised to pay an outstanding second instalment of the May pension shortly.</p>
<p>The ruling Socialists, facing presidential and parliamentary elections on September 21, and pressure from pensioners and state workers including teachers, doctors and nurses, have promised to put $100 million towards paying outstanding wages.</p>
<p>Analysts predicted the government would use cash from the sale to Greek and Italian companies of part of the state telecommunications combine, Telekom Srbija, to defuse growing social tensions.</p>
<p>&quot;The government must realise that a pay-as-you-go system does not work any more. The reduction of pensions to some 65 percent of the average wage is needed. It is a painful but necessary measure if the system is to function properly,&quot; said economist Aleksandra Posarac.</p>
<p>GROWING NUMBER OF ELDERLY A FACTOR</p>
<p>Besides the poor performance of the economy because of  sanctions, hyperinflation and state mismanagement, analysts blame demographic changes and a growing number of elderly for the pension problems.</p>
<p>&quot;In 1980-96 the number of pensioners increased by some 4.5 percent a year but the number of employed stagnated,&quot; said Popov at the Economics Institute.</p>
<p>The number of pensioners is seen growing at the same pace for the next 10-15 years, but it is unlikely that employment will rise at a rate higher than one percent each year.</p>
<p>Analysts see no quick solution to the problem, which will continue to burden the country's public spending, and suggest a step-by-step approach.</p>
<p>&quot;The least painful measures will be to discourage people from retiring, insist on regular collections of pension fund contributions and increase taxes on things like fuel,&quot; Popov said.</p>
<p>Analysts agreed reform of the pension system was difficult for all governments and did not believe any political leadership in Serbia would embark on it voluntarily.</p>
<p>&quot;Once Yugoslavia returns to the International Monetary Fund it will be forced to do it,&quot; said one analyst. &quot;But politicians will then blame the international community for the consequences.&quot; ($ = 6.108 Yugoslav Dinars) ($ = 1.849 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="YUG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GWELF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BELGRADE"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="YUGOSLAVIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
