<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798914" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil fiscal gap threatens stability-central bank.</title>
<headline>Brazil fiscal gap threatens stability-central bank.</headline>
<byline>Michael Christie</byline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's fiscal deficit is still too wide to ensure sustained economic stability, even though progress has been made in narrowing the gap, a central bank director said Thursday.</p>
<p>Monetary Policy Director Francisco Lopes said the government's 1997 goal was to reduce the nominal consolidated public-sector deficit -- also known as the public-sector borrowing requirement (PSBR) -- to an equivalent of 5.0 percent of gross domestic product.  </p>
<p>&quot;This is still a lot. It is still too large to allow stability to be sustained,&quot; Lopes told the Chamber of Deputies Economics, Industry and Commerce Committee. &quot;It's urgent, it's fundamental that we persist with our fiscal efforts.&quot;</p>
<p>As Lopes noted, Brazil managed to reduce its PSBR to 6.0 percent of GDP last year from 7.0 percent the previous year.</p>
<p>In the 12 months to the end of May, Brazil's public-sector PSBR -- which includes the accounts of the federal, state and municipal governments and state-owned companies -- stood at 5.53 percent of GDP versus 5.67 percent of GDP in the year to the end of April.  </p>
<p>Lopes stuck by a government target for this year of generating a 1.5 percent fiscal surplus in the public sector in primary terms, which excludes interest payment on debt.</p>
<p>&quot;That objective is perfectly achievable,&quot; he said, provided Congress passed key reforms in the civil service and pension system.</p>
<p>Both reforms have languished in Congress in part because they would remove public-sector privileges enjoyed by many lawmakers.  </p>
<p>&quot;I'm convinced that with the cooperation of Congress we will arrive at fiscal equilibrium over the next years,&quot; Lopes said. &quot;There can be no permanent stability without fiscal equilibrium.&quot;</p>
<p>Lopes also told the committee he dreamed of a Brazil where &quot;monetary austerity was institutionalized -- a permanent feature.&quot;</p>
<p>He said the central bank was making progress toward that end, with its Monetary Policy Committee (Copom) setting monthly interest rates on a purely technical basis.</p>
<p>In its three years of existence, the economic stabilization plan has slowed hyperinflation to a projected 6.0 percent this year through policies to encourage a strong exchange rate and high interest rates.</p>
<p>((-- Brasilia newsroom 55-61-3141193))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E212">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
