<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="798968" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>BRAZIL: Brazil house approves special FEF budget fund.</title>
<headline>Brazil house approves special FEF budget fund.</headline>
<dateline>BRASILIA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Brazil's Chamber of Deputies approved late Wednesday in a second round vote a 2-1/2 year extension to a special budget fund, the Fiscal Stabilization Fund (FEF), an official said.</p>
<p>The Congress official said 342 deputies voted in favor of renewing the $26 billion fund until the end of 1999, 121 voted against and four deputies abstained.</p>
<p>The FEF extension must now go to the Senate, where, as a constitutional amendment, it has to be approved in two rounds of balloting.  </p>
<p>The FEF allows the government to hold onto about $26 billion in receipts each financial year that would have been earmarked constitutionally for the states and the cities.</p>
<p>Seen as a key fiscal tool to help the government balance its books, the fund is used to cover unexpected shortfalls, with whatever is left over being passed onto local governments.</p>
<p>But its passage through the lower house was fraught with controversy and haggling, as mayors from across Brazil, whose grassroots political power can make or break federal deputies, protested they would lose money.</p>
<p>The government has pledged to compensate states and municipalities.</p>
<p>The FEF ran out at the end of June but the new bill will be retroactive.</p>
<p>((-- Michael Christie, Brasilia newsroom 55-61-3141193))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BRAZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRASILIA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BRAZIL"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
