<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799129" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Producer, arranger Foster signs pact with Warner.</title>
<headline>Producer, arranger Foster signs pact with Warner.</headline>
<dateline>BURBANK, Calif. 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fourteen-time Grammy award-winning producer, arranger and composer David Foster has entered an exclusive multi-year pact with Warner Music Group, the company said Thursday.</p>
<p>Under the agreement, Foster becomes senior vice president of Warner Music, producing records for all of Warner Music Group labels and acting as a consultant for senior management of the company.</p>
<p>Warner Music Group, one of the world's leading music companies, is a division of Time Warner Inc. The Warner Music Group is comprised of recording labels Elektra, Atlantic and Warner Bros. Records.</p>
<p>The agreement also expands a relationship between Atlantic Records and Foster's 143 Records label into a joint venture between the two companies. Launched in 1994, the label is responsible for the international hit album &quot;Forgiven, Not Forgotten&quot; by the Irish rock band The Corrs.</p>
<p>Foster, who has been a vice president of Atlantic Records since 1994, has produced several hit songs, including Celine Dion's Grammy-winning &quot;Falling Into You,&quot; Natalie Cole's &quot;Unforgettable&quot; and Whitney Houston's &quot;The Bodyguard.&quot;</p>
<p>Foster started out in the music business at age 16 was a member of Chuck Berry's band. Relocating from his native Victoria, British Columbia, to Los Angeles, Foster's group Skylark scored a Top 1O hit, &quot;Wildflower,&quot; in 1971.</p>
<p>Working throughout the early 1970s as one of the industry's premier session musicians, Foster performed with such superstars as John Lennon, George Harrison and Barbra Streisand.</p>
<p>Industry sources speculated that Foster's expanded role represents an effort by Warner Music to shore up its market share which has slipped in recent years.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C33">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BURBANK, Calif."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
