<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799296" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thailand confident of IMF approval of bailout plan.</title>
<headline>Thailand confident of IMF approval of bailout plan.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thai Finance Minister Thanong Bidaya said on Thursday he was confident the executive board of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) would approve an international financial bailout plan for Thailand by the middle of next week.</p>
<p>Thanong said Thailand was determined to meet its obligations in adopting tough austerity measures imposed under the package, including broad reforms of its troubled financial sector and a three percentage point hike of its value added tax (VAT).</p>
<p>&quot;I have no doubt that the IMF will approve the package... which, even though it may cause pains for our people, is essential for national survival,&quot; the minister said on a television programme.</p>
<p>The $16 billion IMF-brokered package includes a $4 billion stand-by credit from the agency and an equal amount of loan from Japan. The rest of the money will come from various Asian countries, Australia and multilateral organisations.</p>
<p>Thanong said with the IMF package, he expects Thailand's economic recovery to be spread over one to three years.</p>
<p>Thai central bank governor Chaiyawat Wibulswasdi said in the same televised programme that Thailand will see exceptionally low economic growth this year of about three percent, which should improve slightly to four percent in 1998 and five to six percent a year later.</p>
<p>The governor said both the Thai private and public sectors must tighten spending in the next few years while the country strives to boost its sagging exports.</p>
<p>He said the aid package's austerity measures should enable Thailand to narrow its current account deficit to five percent of gross domestic product this year and to three percent in 1998, down from eight percent in 1996.</p>
<p>Chaiyawat said Thailand has a target to maintain at least $24 billion of foreign reserves which could finance about four months of its imports.</p>
<p>The targetted reserves compared with peak foreign reserves of $39.9 billion in October last year.</p>
<p>The projected three percent GDP growth for Thailand this year would be the slowest expansion for the country's economy since at least the early 1960s.</p>
<p>Thailand announced a de facto devaluation of its baht on July 2 . It decided to accept an IMF bailout programme early this month because of continued turmoil in its cash-strapped finance sector and the collapse of its property sector.</p>
<p>The central bank governor estimated that the international assistance package would reach $17 billion, after an announcement from China on Thursday that it would contribute $1 billion to the rescue effort.</p>
<p>Thanong said the pains that Thai business and people would experience under the austerity programme were unavoidable as the country's earlier attempts to rectify its problems had failed.</p>
<p>The minister said decisions early this month to close down 42 finance companies that faced liquidity problems and to raise VAT to 10 percent from seven -- a highly unpopular move -- were intended as a gesture to show the IMF that Thailand was serious in embarking on its reforms.</p>
<p>Thanong said the VAT hike and financial sector reform were needed to supplement a 50-75 billion baht ($1.6-2.4 billion) cut in the 1997/1998 (October-September) government budget before Thailand could convince the IMF that its reforms would be successful.</p>
<p>&quot;The next one to two years will be a period of adjustment for Thais,&quot; central bank governor Chaiyawat said.</p>
<p>The finance minister said a substantial part of Thailand's $89 billion foreign debt was imported in the past four to five years, much of it for unproductive sectors like property.</p>
<p>He said the problems were compounded by Thailand's earlier practice to tie its baht to a strong U.S. dollar, had since 1996 had gradually made Thai exports overvalued and uncompetitive.</p>
<p>The $24 billion foreign reserve target would help assure foreign commercial creditors that Thailand has few credit risks and that the country can finance its current account deficit, he said.</p>
<p>Part of the foreign reserves were needed to finance commitments made by the central bank when it intervened to defend the baht in May, Chaiyawat added.</p>
<p>He reiterated that loans from the IMF package would not be used for bailing out troubled private finance institutions.</p>
<p>($1 = 31 baht)</p>
<p>-- Bangkok newsroom (662)-6520642</p>
<p>	 email: bangkok.newsroom@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
