<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799320" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDONESIA: Indonesian tribe thinks Dutch still rule country.</title>
<headline>Indonesian tribe thinks Dutch still rule country.</headline>
<dateline>JAKARTA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Nine Indonesian tribesman have come down from a remote mountain in the eastern island of Sulawesi after decades there and said they believed the Dutch still ruled the country, the official Antara news agency reported on Thursday.</p>
<p>Indonesia proclaimed freedom from 350 years of Dutch colonial rule in 1945 and celebrates its 52nd anniversary of independence on Sunday.</p>
<p>Antara said the nine tribesmen, including a man named Halima who was apparently 115 years old, had come down from the Baliohuto mountain to a village in Gorontalo regency on the northern part of Sulawesi island in recent weeks.</p>
<p>&quot;A food shortage due to the prolonged drought could have forced (the) nine people of the Palahi tribe to come down from the mountain,&quot; the agency reported.</p>
<p>It said Halima had fled to the mountains to escape a spreading cholera epidemic. He also said he was trying to evade Dutch colonial rulers because he did not want to cooperate with them.</p>
<p>&quot;Halima said they have lived in the mountains for so long that they thought they Dutch were still governing Indonesia,&quot; Antara said.</p>
<p>Halima said hundreds of isolated tribes continued to live in different areas of the mountains surrounding Gorontalo.</p>
<p>The nine people were the second batch of tribesmen to have come down from the mountain in the past two months, the agency said. The first batch consisted of seven people.</p>
<p>Antara gave no further details.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDON">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="JAKARTA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDONESIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
