<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799482" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Clinton issues federal guidelines on religion.</title>
<headline>Clinton issues federal guidelines on religion.</headline>
<byline>Laurence McQuillan</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Federal workers may keep a Bible or the Koran at their desks and discuss religion during coffee breaks, according to new guidelines on God in the workplace issued on Thursday by President Bill Clinton.</p>
<p>Tackling the sensitive subject of religious expression -- a passionate issue in a nation where about one-third of the population says religion is the most important thing in their lives -- Clinton offered guidelines for federal managers in dealing with their employees' beliefs.</p>
<p>&quot;Religious freedom is at the heart of what it means to be an American,&quot; Clinton said during a ceremony announcing the new guidelines.</p>
<p>He said the rules clarify that federal employees may engage in personal religious expression to the greatest extent possible; that employers may not discriminate in employment on the basis of religion, and employers must reasonably accommodate employees' religious practices.</p>
<p>&quot;These guidelines will ensure that federal employees and employers will respect the rights of those who engage in religious speech as well as those who do not,&quot; said Clinton, a Southern Baptist and regular churchgoer.</p>
<p>One example cited in a section dealing with private work areas noted &quot;an employee may keep a Bible or Koran on her private desak and read it during breaks.&quot; An employee's religious poster would have to be accepted, unless all posters were banned.</p>
<p>The 13 pages of guidelines on legal-sized paper also said that federal workers should be allowed to &quot;engage in private religious expression in personal work areas,&quot; including &quot;during a coffee break.&quot;</p>
<p>White House officials said they have been working for more than a year with a broad cross-section of religious leaders and legal experts to come up with guidelines that deal with religious concerns without violating the U.S. Constitution's provisions on worship.</p>
<p>Oliver Thomas of the National Council of Churches said he believed the guidelines &quot;will help clarify what was a very confused area of the law.&quot;</p>
<p>He noted that the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission tried issuing guidelines on religious harassment &quot;a few years ago, and it was a disaster ... This is a very important breakthrough so that employers, supervisors and employees understand what their rights are.&quot;</p>
<p>Marc Stern of the American Jewish Congress noted that due to the size of the federal government &quot;not every supervisor is as knowledegable or responsible as they should be. We think that these guidelines ... will make it clear to supervivors&quot; how to deal with various situations.</p>
<p>Rabbi David Saperstein called the guidelines helpful and voiced hope &quot;that state governments and the private sector will see them as a very helpful model ... This is partcularly helpful for minority religions.&quot;</p>
<p>During his remarks, Clinton expressed disappointment that the Supreme Court in June struck down provisions in the Religious Freedom Restoration Act. The administration had supported the act, which was designed to protect religious practices from government interference and covered much more than just federal workers.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
