<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799572" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Arkansas meat processor doubles hamburger recall.</title>
<headline>Arkansas meat processor doubles hamburger recall.</headline>
<byline>Leila Corcoran</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Arkansas meat processor Hudson Foods Inc. has doubled the amount of frozen hamburger patties it is recalling for possible E. coli contamination, the U.S. Agriculture Department said Thursday.</p>
<p>Jacque Knight, a spokeswoman for the department's Food Safety and Inspection Service, said federal officials were going over records at the Columbus, Nebraska, plant where the meat was produced and the recall could grow. It now stands at 40,000 pounds -- about 160,000 beef burgers.</p>
<p>&quot;When these recalls start and as records are continually checked, they find and locate more,&quot; she said. &quot;We're continuing to check records so it could be more.&quot;</p>
<p>Tuesday, the department said Hudson Foods of Rogers, Arkansas, was voluntarily recalling about 80,000 frozen hamburger patties after 16 Colorado consumers became sick in July from grilled burgers linked to E. coli contamination.</p>
<p>Five people were hospitalized for treatment, according to Colorado health officials. The strain of E. coli suspected of contaminating the beef can cause bloody diarrhea and dehydration, and in some, life-threatening kidney failure.</p>
<p>Consumers become ill by eating infected meat that has not been fully cooked or by handling raw meat and failing to wash their hands. E. coli contamination occurs when the intestinal tract or feces of slaughtered animals is mixed into the meat.</p>
<p>Knight said about half the suspect frozen hamburger patties went to fast-food chains and half was distributed to retail and wholesale stores.</p>
<p>Earlier, Burger King Corp. issued a statement saying there was no evidence its beef from Hudson Foods contained the bacteria.</p>
<p>The fast food restaurant operator, which is owned by Britain's Grand Metropolitan Plc., said its restaurants and distribution centers would set aside any beef patties from the two production days in question for pick up.</p>
<p>Hudson Foods is recalling three products:</p>
<p>-- 48-ounce packages of &quot;Hudson Beef Burgers, Individually Quick Frozen&quot; with the code &quot;156A7&quot;</p>
<p>-- Three-pound packages of &quot;Hudson 100% Pure Beef Patties, Individually Frozen&quot; with the code &quot;156B7&quot;</p>
<p>-- 15-pound boxes of &quot;Hudson 60 - 1/4 lb. Beef Patties Uncooked, Individually Quick Frozen&quot; with the code &quot;155B7&quot;</p>
<p>The Agriculture Department has set up a hotline at 1-800-535-4555 for consumers to call with questions about the beef recall.</p>
<p>Four years ago, 700 people became ill and four children died in the Pacific Northwest as a result of eating fast-food restaurant hamburgers tainted with the bacteria.</p>
<p>E. coli was also recently found in alfalfa sprouts for the first time when 108 people in Michigan and Virginia became ill this summer after eating alfalfa sprouts contaminated with E. coli bacteria, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention said Thursday.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I61000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C22">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
