<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799524" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Carey, reformer and fighter, in biggest battle yet.</title>
<headline>Carey, reformer and fighter, in biggest battle yet.</headline>
<byline>Peter Szekely</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Teamsters Union President Ron Carey fought great odds to get his job, waged a bitter battle to keep it and has sparred with his current opponent, United Parcel Service, for about 30 years.</p>
<p>But the 11-day-old strike by some 185,000 members of the 1.4 million-member International Brotherhood of Teamsters that has paralyzed package delivery giant UPS is Carey's biggest battle yet.</p>
<p>Carey, 61, who has urged the government not to intervene in the dispute by seeking a temporary back-to-work order, was able to capture the Teamsters' highest office in part because the government paved the way for him.</p>
<p>A long-time dissident and self-styled reformer in a union that for years symbolized labor corruption, Carey won its presidency in a government-supervised three-way race in late 1991 that was required as part of a settlement of a 1989 federal racketeering lawsuit against the union.</p>
<p>It was the first time in the union's 93-year history that a Teamster president was chosen by the rank and file instead of convention delegates and it gave Carey, the long-shot outsider in the race, the opportunity he had long sought.</p>
<p>A former Marine, the 5-foot, 10-inch Carey worked as a driver for UPS for 11 years until he was elected president in 1967 of Teamsters Local 804 in the New York City borough of Queens where he grew up.</p>
<p>There he represented mostly UPS workers who once staged a  wildcat strike, kept his members covered by a contract that was separate from the nationwide agreement that is now in dispute and was always on the outs with the union's top brass in Washington.</p>
<p>A darling of union reformers inside and outside of the Teamsters, Carey used the 1991 three-way race to his advantage as his two &quot;Old Guard&quot; opponents split their vote and left him with a plurality.</p>
<p>Since winning office, Carey has taken a high-profile stand against corrpution -- three of his six predecessors went to prison -- and lavish spending. He sold the union's jet, cut his own salary and has put 72 Teamster locals into trusteeships, mostly after evidence of corruption was uncovered.</p>
<p>But he has made many enemies in the union along the way.</p>
<p>A three-week nationwide truck strike he led in 1994 left the union unable to pay strike benefits, and members rejected his proposed dues hike to fortify the treasury.</p>
<p>Late last year, he narrowly defeated James Hoffa, son and namesake of the notorious Teamsters president who was presumed murdered in 1975, in another government-supervised election.</p>
<p>But the bitterly fought election is now under a cloud. A federal grand jury in New York has been investigating the Carey campaign's fund-raising practices, and two campaign aides have been charged with fraud so far.</p>
<p>As a result, the court-appointed officer overseeing the election has not certified Carey as the winner and Hoffa has demanded a new election.</p>
<p>Carey was also an early supporter of the 1994 insurgent bid of John Sweeney to become president of the AFL-CIO. As president of the largest union in the 78-union federation, Carey's support was crucial for Sweeney's victory.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79010">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C42">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E41">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GJOB">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
