<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799531" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Farm group seeks Clinton meet on vetoed tax break.</title>
<headline>Farm group seeks Clinton meet on vetoed tax break.</headline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Farm cooperative leaders on Thursday asked to meet with President Clinton to discuss how to revive a food processor tax break he vetoed earlier this week.</p>
<p>Clinton used his line-item veto authority for the first time Monday to strike down three provisions of the balanced budget accord he signed last week.</p>
<p>Clinton expressed support for the goal of the food processor tax break, which was intended to make it easier for farm cooperatives to buy processing facilities.</p>
<p>But he said details of the provision--which the administration estimated would cost $98 million over five years--were poorly designed. He promised to work with congressional supporters to recast the measure.</p>
<p>&quot;On behalf of the nearly 4,000 farmer cooperatives across the U.S. and their nearly two million farmer members, we want to express our disappointment,&quot; David Graves, National Council of Farmer's Cooperatives president, said in a letter to Clinton.</p>
<p>&quot;We believe this should be given an immediate high priority within the administration,&quot; Graves said.</p>
<p>The vetoed provision would have allowed food processors to defer capital gains taxes on the sale of assets to qualified farm cooperatives.</p>
<p>A similiar tax break exists under current law for employee stock ownership plans and worker cooperatives, the farm co-op council said.</p>
<p>((Washington commodities desk 202 898 8341))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I41000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I42000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
