<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799508" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: San Jose says not in talks on moving Oakland A's.</title>
<headline>San Jose says not in talks on moving Oakland A's.</headline>
<dateline>SAN FRANCISCO 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>The city of San Jose is not involved in talks with the Oakland Athletics about moving the baseball team to San Jose, a spokesman for Mayor Susan Hammer said Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;It's premature as far as Mayor Hammer is concerned,&quot; spokesman Kevin Pursglove said.</p>
<p>The San Francisco Chronicle reported Thursday that the San Jose Sports Authority had approached the Oakland A's about the possibility of building a new stadium for the baseball team in the San Jose area.</p>
<p>The Sports Authority, a marketing body that works to bring sporting events to San Jose, was created by the city 10 years ago and has its own board of directors.</p>
<p>&quot;There are no talks going on between the city of San Jose and the Oakland A's about them moving the team here,&quot; Pursglove said.</p>
<p>While he did not speak for the Sports Authority, he said: &quot;I don't think the Sports Authority would be out there on their own.&quot;</p>
<p>The Oakland Athletics had no immediate comment and no one was available to comment at the San Jose Sports Authority.</p>
<p>The Chronicle said that the success of the San Jose Sharks hockey team has whetted the appetite of civic leaders in the area for more sports teams.</p>
<p>Oakland A's owners Steve Schott and Ken Hofmann have a lease with the Oakland Coliseum that gives them the option of leaving after next season. Both have hinted that they are prepared to move the team elsewhere in the San Francisco Bay area if a new stadium were available, the report said.</p>
<p>But it said any effort to build the Athletics a state-of-the-art ballpark in the San Jose area would face numerous obstacles.</p>
<p>Suitable land is scarce in San Jose. Any facility would need to be funded at least in part by public money and area voters defeated ballpark initiatives in 1990 and 1992, it said.</p>
<p>The report said Major League Baseball had an agreement with the San Francisco Giants that Santa Clara County, which comprises San Jose, was Giants' territory. The Chronicle quoted several sources as saying baseball could be expected to block any attempt by the A's to move to San Jose.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I97911">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C24">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SAN FRANCISCO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
