<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799608" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NY precious metals end lower as financials steady.</title>
<headline>NY precious metals end lower as financials steady.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>COMEX and NYMEX precious metals futures ended sharply lower Thursday, on good volume, after the U.S. dollar firmed, along with U.S. stocks and bonds, following more benign U.S. economic data.</p>
<p>The U.S. July CPI rose just 0.2 percent as expected, in the wake of the seventh monthly fall in the PPI reported Wednesday.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, with the S&amp;P500 stock index down 4.9 pct from its peak on August 7, precious metals had received some support from investors worried about the potential for a significant stockmarket correction.  </p>
<p>&quot;Gold closed badly, after looking toppy again, and it feels like there's some more central bank activity going on,&quot; Credit Lyonnais Rouse New York chief bullion dealer Scott Mehlman said.</p>
<p>COMEX December gold ended down $2.70 at $328.00 an ounce, after resistance at the top of the month $320-335 month-old range held once more. Estimated total COMEX gold volume was 45,000 lots.</p>
<p>COMEX gold open interest jumped 4,509 lots Wednesday to 201,194 contracts in data released Thursday, with traders noting one European-based bullion bank was a heavy seller of several thousand lots Wednesday.</p>
<p>In the bullion market, spot gold ended quoted $324.20/70 an ounce, compared to the London Thursday afternoon fix at $326.15 and the New York close Wednesday around $326.90/40.</p>
<p>Implied gold lease rates rose sharply in the past two days, but were off their late Wednesday peaks on Thursday, after the highest yields since January attracted extra central bank lending, traders said.</p>
<p>Comparing Thursday morning rates with Wednesday morning rates though, one month implied lease rates were around 2.68 pct, against 2.29 pct Wednesday, and one year rates were around 2.37 pct, compared to 2.26 pct.</p>
<p>The move suggested funds and producers may be borrowing again to fund short positions and hedges, though rumors of bullion banks borrowing to sell on behalf of central banks also worried traders.</p>
<p>But one analyst said the tightness in lease rates reflected the activity of a Dubai-based refiner who had been buying up non-allocated gold in London to ship to a Mideast refinery for conversion into ten tola bars for Indian consumption.</p>
<p>Demand was also lengthening delivery times at the two main U.S. and Canadian gold refineries also, one bullion banker said.</p>
<p>In industry news, operations at the Omai Gold Mines in Guyana could be affected by a strike by 200 workers, a spokeswoman for the mines owners, Cambior Inc of Montreal said. The Omai mine produced 255,000 ounces in 1996.</p>
<p>Earlier this week Cambior joined the list of miners postponing gold mining developments or closing mines due to the current low level of gold prices, when it said it had deferred a decision on the construction of the Metates project in Mexico's Durango state.</p>
<p>COMEX September silver ended down 10.2 cents at $4.405 cents an ounce, giving back all of Wednesday's 8.2 cent gain which had taken the contract to a six week high. Estimated COMEX silver volume was 32,000 lots.</p>
<p>COMEX silver open interest fell 2,092 lots to 90,136 contract Wednesday, on more shortcovering on what appeared to have been a breakout of the $4.20-4.50 range of the past month.</p>
<p>NYMEX October platinum ended down $3.30 at $427.80, but ended well off the session lows at $421.50, while NYMEX September palladium ended down $6.00 an ounce at $209.85</p>
<p>But one month platinum lease rates were unchanged around 20 pct, as were one month palladium lease rates which were indicated around 80 pct.</p>
<p>&quot;The Russians may be exporting a little again, but inventories are not rebuilding, as the metal is either delivered against a TOCOM short position or consumed by manufactures or possible even hoarded,&quot; one U.S. refining source said.</p>
<p>email: clive.mckeef @ reuters.com</p>
<p>((Clive McKeef, New York Commodities Desk, 212-859-1641))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
