<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799635" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Texas tax relief may hurt school districts-experts.</title>
<headline>Texas tax relief may hurt school districts-experts.</headline>
<byline>Harihar Krishnan</byline>
<dateline>DALLAS 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>A constitutional amendment raising the homestead exemption from school property taxes in Texas helps homeowners but could affect the ability of school districts to issue debt in the future, analysts said.</p>
<p>The amendment approved by voters last Saturday increases the exemption to $15,000 from the current $5,000, giving a tax saving of $140 a year on a $100,000 home.</p>
<p>The tax cut will cost the school districts $1 billion over the next two years but will be made up by the state from its budgetary surplus, estimated at about $1.7 billion.</p>
<p>But market experts said problems could emerge beyond 1999 if the Texas economy soured and the state were not able to make up the school districts' financing gap left by the property tax cut.</p>
<p>&quot;We will continue to monitor each district and see how their funds come in. At this time, we don't see any negative impact from the amendment but if it becomes necessary later on, we will certainly take ratings action,&quot; said Dennis Porcaro, vice president and senior analyst in the Dallas office of Moody's Investors Service.</p>
<p>George Williford, managing director of First Southwest Co, cautioned that many school districts already face rising budgetary pressures, especially those growing rapidly in areas dominated by residential developments rather than businesses.</p>
<p>He said those districts might not be able to make up their losses in the future without raising local taxes, effectively nullifying or cutting the new tax relief for homeowners.</p>
<p>&quot;These districts will have to raise their taxes and that will reduce the benefits,&quot; Williford said. &quot;We are not seeing any immediate impact on the bond markets and I don't see an economic slowdown any time soon. But if it happens, the picture will change.&quot;</p>
<p>Williford also noted that the amendment mandates a five percent salary raise to about 25 percent of the state's 240,000 teachers who earn the state's minimum salary. The larger school districts, who are already paying more than the state's minimum, would be under pressure to match that.</p>
<p>But Vincent A. Matrone, senior vice president at Rauscher Pierce Refsnes Inc, sees the amendement as an economic plus for Texas. &quot;It is economically driven, and any tax decrease is a positive.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;We are in the fourth year of economic growth and the school districts are enjoying growing property values. I think this trend will continue for a while and the ratings should not be affected,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Most Texas school districts' debt issues are guaranteed by the Permanent School Fund (PSF), which automatically gives them high ratings. But with rising costs and higher taxes the school districts may be forced to impose, their ratings could be hurt because institutional investors and mutual funds increasingly are demanding that debt issues have their own underlying credit quality.</p>
<p>Gov. George W. Bush, who staked his political future on getting the amendment passed, insists that school districts not use the property tax cut as an excuse to raise taxes.</p>
<p>Ken Fero, a spokesman for the State Comptroller's office, admits &quot;there are no guarantees (of continued state help) after two years&quot; but said the Texas economy will continue to show solid growth well into the next century.</p>
<p>&quot;Right now, we expect Texas to continue to outpace the national job growth by one percentage point,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The state's limit on school tax is $1.50 per $100 of property valuation. The current statewide average is $1.40, leaving little room for any further hike.</p>
<p>Moody's Porcaro says the concern is that the current ceiling could become the floor as more districts approached the limit.</p>
<p>Additionally, the higher homestead exemption is available only to those who own homes. Businesses and those who rent homes do not get the benefit but would be forced to bear the burden of higher school taxes.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="DALLAS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
