<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799663" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: COMEX copper ends at 4-week low on chart selling.</title>
<headline>COMEX copper ends at 4-week low on chart selling.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>COMEX copper ended at its lowest level in four weeks on trade selling, but respected the down trendline dating back to July 30.</p>
<p>Sell stops are believed to be built up below Thursday's intraday lows.</p>
<p>The December contract ended at 102.60 cents a lb, down 0.50 cents. September ended at 103.80 cents a lb, down 1.35 cents. The spot month ended at 103.60 cents a lb, down 1.40 cents.</p>
<p>The fundamentals are a mixed bag, however, according to Frederick Demler, minerals economist with ED&amp;F Man. &quot;On one hand, the market is being pressured by the rising LME stocks,&quot; he said. &quot;On the other hand, the consumption numbers have been phenomenal.&quot;</p>
<p>The London Metal Exchange warehouse stocks increased another 1,950 tonnes to 256,300 tonnes, the highest level since September 26, 1996. Stocks have been steadily increasing since June 19, when stocks were 121,550 tonnes.</p>
<p>Some traders will be watching Friday's commitment of traders report from the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, for clues as to the funds position.</p>
<p>&quot;It's probably a mixed bag,&quot; Demler said. &quot;I don't think they're on one side or the other.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I think you'd be hard pressed to find a fund who'd be interested in trading in this market,&quot; said one trader with a Japanese trading firm. &quot;Funds tend to like trending markets and this is a market that's been trading sideways for some time.&quot;</p>
<p>Others believe the funds are short and looking for an opportunity to roll their shorts into December.</p>
<p>But the September-December spread has narrowed to a 1.20 banckwardation from a 2.05-cent back Wednesday, the narrowest level this year, which traders said implied long switches and liquidation.</p>
<p>In London, the cash-to-three-month back narrowed to $7/$11, the lowest since October 14.</p>
<p>((--Derek J. Caney, New York Commodity Desk, 212-859-1646))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
