<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799848" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French budget cuts force defence programme delays.</title>
<headline>French budget cuts force defence programme delays.</headline>
<byline>Jean-Michel Belot</byline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Cuts in the French 1998 defence budget, as part of the government's deficit reduction drive, will likely mean spreading out a number of procurement programmes, a source close to the government said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The budget cuts and resulting programme delays, which are expected to hit Dassault Aviation's Rafale combat plane, will also jeopardise the 1997-2002 defence budget law adopted last year by the previous conservative administration.</p>
<p>Even in its first year, the defence spending law has been seriously undermined. Procurement funds for 1997 currently stand at 84.9 billion francs, down from a planned 88.7 billion, after the previous government froze 1.8 billion francs and the new Socialist administration lopped off a further two billion in its search for savings.</p>
<p>&quot;Problems of programming are raised for the future,&quot; a source close to the parliamentary defence committee said.</p>
<p>Confronted with its budgetary problems, the government has decided to drop the idea of a multi-year order for the Rafale multi-role jet.</p>
<p>A multi-year order, instead of the present annual vote for funds in the National Assembly, would have been a breakthrough for the defence industry which has long lobbied for such a change in procurement, arguing that it provides secure funding and economies of scale, rather than a piecemeal approach.</p>
<p>The previous government had agreed in principle to order 48 Rafales, worth 15 billion francs, in the seven years covered by the budget law, in exchange for a 10 percent price reduction.</p>
<p>The defence ministry said that as things stand, the decision to drop the multi-year funding does not endanger the actual order, which consists of 15 Rafales for the navy and 33 for the air force.</p>
<p>&quot;To get multi-year orders, you have to have healthy and and rigorous management under the budget law, which is not the case,&quot; a military budget specialist said.</p>
<p>The outgoing conservative government confirmed an order for 13 Rafales in between the two rounds of voting in the parliamentary elections in late May.</p>
<p>A government source earlier this week said that the second year of the defence budget would also see spending cuts. The defence ministry declined to comment on the size of reductions being negotiated with the finance ministry but French newspapers have reported 1998 procurement will get 80 billion francs instead of the 90 billion envisaged in the budget law.</p>
<p>Defence Mnister Alain Richard has had to choose between simply cancelling entire programmes or spreading out the more costly projects such as the Rafale.</p>
<p>&quot;Programmes will be spread out,&quot; a source close to the government said, adding that that would mean projects would be extended rather than simply dropped.</p>
<p>Cancellations would lead to huge job losses, a prospect that the Socialist government of Prime Minister Lionel Jospin can hardly afford while the unemployment rate in France stands at a record 12.6 percent.</p>
<p>A report by the national audit office published in June pointed out that repeated delays in defence programmes led in the end to significantly higher costs.</p>
<p>During the previous government's tenure, Assembly member Jacques Baumel of the centrist RPR party attacked the French navy's nuclear submarine building programme in a report on the 1997 defence budget.</p>
<p>The cost of building six new-generation boats was initially estimated at 88.3 billion francs, but that had since escalated to 88.4 billion for four vessels, Baumel wrote in his report.</p>
<p>The French government is under pressure to shrink public deficits next year to three percent of gross domestic product in order to meet strict targets for launching a single European currency by 1999.</p>
<p>But faced with sluggish growth and weak revenues, defence spending is seen as an obvious target, as France spends relatively more than its European partners on the military.</p>
<p>A recent defence review by the new Labour government in Britain left untouched its nuclear submarine fleet and the Eurofighter, a multinational combat plane being built with Germany, Italy and Spain. But the government wants big savings on the procurement side.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDEF">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
