<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799840" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: Algeria's parliament ends debate on minibudget.</title>
<headline>Algeria's parliament ends debate on minibudget.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Algeria's National Assembly (lower house) parliament will vote on the 1997 government minibudget on Sunday after it ended public debate on Thursday, the Algerian APS news agency said.</p>
<p>&quot;The National Assembly ended on Thursday its debate on the 1997 complementary budget. The government programme and draft law will be submitted to the Assembly's vote on Sunday,&quot; said APS in a brief statemnt quoting the Assembly President Abdelkader Bensalah.</p>
<p>The government said total revenue would increase to 881.5 billion dinars ($15.74 billion) against 946.22 billion dinars ($16.89 billion) expenditure.</p>
<p>The government figures, reported earlier by APS, showed initial forecasts had put revenue and expenditure respectively at 829.4 billion dinars ($14.8 billion) and 914.1 billion dinars ($16.32 billion).</p>
<p>&quot;This readjustment of the budget is due to a change of the economic and financial parameters, namely those with significant weight,&quot; APS said.</p>
<p>Helped by soaring crude oil prices and a buoyant dollar, Algerian authorities forecast a pruned budget deficit of 64.72 billion dinars ($1.15 billion) in 1997 from an original 84.70 billion dinars ($1.51 billion).</p>
<p>Official data showed that the volume and value of the country's oil and gas exports increased respectively by 7.9 percent and 13.1 percent in the first five months of 1997 compared to the same period in 1996.</p>
<p>($1= 56 dinars)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
