<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799828" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>FRANCE: French minister wants eco-tax to fight pollution.</title>
<headline>French minister wants eco-tax to fight pollution.</headline>
<dateline>PARIS 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>French Environment Minister Dominique Voynet, the first Green to hold the post, said in an interview on Thursday she wanted to introduce an &quot;eco-tax&quot; on energy to fight against worsening air quality.</p>
<p>Voynet told the daily Le Figaro that pollution alerts this week in Paris and other large cities were only &quot;the tip of the iceberg&quot; and that France had to take longer-term measures against rising pollution levels.</p>
<p>Pollution alerts were in force for the third straight day in the French cities of Paris, Lyon, Lille and Strasbourg on Thursday due to a mix of persistent high temperatures, sunlight, car exhaust fumes and a lack of wind, the Environment Ministry announced in mid-afternoon.</p>
<p>The ministry renewed a warning to the elderly, small children and people with respiratory problems to limit their physical activity, and an &quot;invitation&quot; to drivers to leave their cars at home.</p>
<p>But pollution was not severe enough to trigger mandatory curbs on cars and free public transport, it said.</p>
<p>Voynet, in the interview, said the French tax system did not differentiate between cleaner energy sources such as liquefied petroleum gas and more polluting ones such as diesel fuel.</p>
<p>&quot;I would like France to adopt an eco-tax on energy and carbon emissions to promote behaviour that respects health and the environment more,&quot; she told Figaro.</p>
<p>&quot;It would not be an extra tax, but a tax that could gradually replace part of the tax system,&quot; she said. &quot;The prime minister has set up a working group on this issue.&quot;</p>
<p>Voynet, who did not give more details of her tax ideas, said the main cause of pollution was the priority that urban planning gave to automobiles over public transport.</p>
<p>She said all cities with more than 100,000 inhabitants would have to draw up a plan by late 1998 to shift the emphasis towards public transport and non-polluting alternatives such as bicycles or walking.</p>
<p>Voynet said she also favoured stricter automobile emission norms and supported efforts within the European Union to introduce them community-wide by the year 2000.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="PARIS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FRANCE"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
