<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799835" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>ITALY: Italy gives state railway year's tax grace.</title>
<headline>Italy gives state railway year's tax grace.</headline>
<dateline>ROME 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Italian Treasury said on Thursday it was giving the state railway a year's grace to repay 3.0 trillion lire in taxes dating from 1992-95.</p>
<p>It said in a statement it had taken the decision at the request of the railway, which had argued the measure was needed to safeguard jobs and guarantee essential public services.</p>
<p>The Treasury, the only shareholder in the state railway, said the levy would be payed back gradually and would have a neutral impact on Italy's public sector borrowing requirement.</p>
<p>It said the decision was perfectly in line with practices approved by Eurostat, the group of European Union Statiticians.</p>
<p>In February this year, Eurostat approved the Italian government's public deficit accounting practices.</p>
<p>The Italian government has been under pressure to upgrade the country's archaic rail network, which was hit by a series of accidents earlier this month. In the space of four days, a train jumped the tracks in Rome, a crane working to remove it collapsed onto tracks and another train ploughed into a car on a level-crossing, killing three people.</p>
<p>The accidents prompted calls for the resignation of Transport Minister Claudio Burlando, who responded by appealing to his government for more funds.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ITALY">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I71000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ROME"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="ITALY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
