<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799951" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indian businessmen offer 50 pct freedom discounts.</title>
<headline>Indian businessmen offer 50 pct freedom discounts.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Indian businessmen are doing what they can do best. They are offering 50 percent discounts to customers to mark the 50th anniversary of independence from Britain.</p>
<p>&quot;Be a part of celebrations at Hotel Siddarth, New Delhi,&quot; an advertisement by Jaypee Hotels said in the Times of India newspaper on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;A fabulous 50 percent discount awaits you on rooms, food and beverage from the stroke of Midnight, 14 August 1997 to 17th August, 97,&quot; it said.</p>
<p>India won independence on August 15, 1947.</p>
<p>Mobile phone firm Escotel announced a 50 percent cut in tariffs in Harayana state. Retailer Inter Craft Ltd offered 50 percent cuts at its Inter Shoppe outlets. Banaras House said it will sell silk sarees at half the usual price.</p>
<p>Some companies, however, are playing on the number five instead of offering 50 percent cuts.</p>
<p>Computer-maker HCL offered a five-year warranty on computers bought before August 25. Computer education firm Aptech Ltd invited students to save 5,100 rupees ($143) in course fees.</p>
<p>The Indian affiliate of Britain's Cadbury Schweppes has planned to release 50,000 special bottles of its soft drink, Canada Dry, disguised like champagne bottles packed in golden wrappers.</p>
<p>But angry members of parliament frothed and fizzed on Wednesday after hearing unconfirmed reports that entertainer Lata Mangeshkar, who is scheduled to sing a national song in parliament at a special midnight session, would uncork a bottle on the occasion.</p>
<p>An opposition deputy said the Indian way to mark such an occasion would be the breaking of a coconut, not the popping of a bottle of some Western drink.</p>
<p>Cadbury Schweppes India said in a statement on Thursday that Mangeshkar had autographed the bottles, but the endorsement did not mean that the singer would uncork the special bottle.</p>
<p>&quot;There was never any intent or mention in any...publicity material of uncorking of Canada Dry Freedom Salvo in parliament by Lata Mangeshkar or any other person at any stage during the independence day celebrations,&quot; it said. ($1 = 35.7 rupees)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I64000">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
