<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799927" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Indians struggle to be happy for freedom milestone.</title>
<headline>Indians struggle to be happy for freedom milestone.</headline>
<byline>Sunil Kataria</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Citizens of India's capital were quietly celebratory on Thursday ahead of the nation's 50th anniversary of independence but the euphoria was tinged with sadness over political instability and corruption.</p>
<p>&quot;I feel very proud of my country,&quot; said Ashim Sagar, 25, owner of a bookshop in New Delhi's central Connaught Place market. &quot;On such a historic occasion there is joy but so much of corruption makes me feel a little sad.&quot;</p>
<p>Major landmarks in the city were festooned with India's saffron, white and green tricolour. Patriotic songs blared from loudspeakers at intersections. Banners and posters with portraits of famous freedom fighters were plastered on walls and strung over traffic-clogged streets.</p>
<p>India won independence at the stroke of midnight on August 14-15, 1947, after decades of struggle against British colonial rule.</p>
<p>Laser shows and fireworks are planned to mark the celebration. Citizens have been urged to fly kites, hoist flags and hold marches at the crack of dawn on Friday to celebrate.</p>
<p>Rajdev Yadav, a pavement vendor who sells betel leaf, favoured by Indians who chew it with areca-nuts or tobacco, had things other than patriotism on his mind.</p>
<p>Yadav's office-worker customers will disappear during the three-day weekend but he said he would not mind the loss.</p>
<p>&quot;I have my fixed customers and on holidays like these the business suffers but on such a big occasion who cares for business,&quot; said Yadav, who said he did not know when India won freedom or who ruled the country before 1947.</p>
<p>Banwarilal Nagpal, a dried-fruit seller who settled in New Delhi after his family came to India from Gujranwala in Pakistan during the partition in 1947 said what saddened him was the lack of integrity among the country's current leaders.</p>
<p>&quot;The problem is with the leaders, the only concern of today's leaders is to make money.&quot;</p>
<p>Neera Chhabra, an executive with a multinational, said: &quot;It feels great to be an Indian on the eve of the golden jubilee of our independence and more than anything else we are proud of our people, our leaders, we are proud of Mahatma Gandhi who showed the way to win battles without bullets.&quot;</p>
<p>Gandhi led the nation to independence through his unique methods of non-violence and non-cooperation.</p>
<p>&quot;The leaders and the organisers pocket all the money in the name of all these functions, ultimately it is the poor man who has to pay the price for celebrations,&quot; said Ram Avtar, who dispenses chilled water from an aluminium pushcart.</p>
<p>Prashant Kapoor, who decorated his antique shop with marigold flowers for the occasion, said: &quot;The very fact that we are celebrating 50 years of self-rule is a joy in itself.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I am proud that in spite of the leaders we have, there has been progress in many areas,&quot; Kapoor said. &quot;We are proud of our achievements in science and technology and industry, while Pakistan has only weapons and an army.&quot;</p>
<p>Schoolgirl Shikha Sehgal disagreed.</p>
<p>&quot;India is free just for name's sake, there are still so many restrictions on women, girls can't go out, there is not enough security.&quot; Sehgal said. &quot;Frankly speaking I do not think there is much to celebrate.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;I think India would have been a far better place had the British stayed on,&quot; Sehgal said. &quot;We would have had better roads, no electricity breakdowns, less corruption and better law and order.&quot;</p>
<p>Sofia Mojiv, a university student said: &quot;Women still feel a little insecure, we could give a little thought to improving their lot on this historic occasion.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
