<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="799956" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: Gandhi celebrated by fasting, spinning, praying.</title>
<headline>Gandhi celebrated by fasting, spinning, praying.</headline>
<byline>Dev Varam</byline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Fifty years ago on August 15 the frail man who led India to freedom spent his day fasting, spinning and praying for peace.</p>
<p>Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi, called &quot;Mahatma&quot; or &quot;great soul&quot; by millions of followers, was in Calcutta trying to calm frenzied Moslems and Hindus who were slaughtering one another.</p>
<p>Gandhi had arrived in the eastern city six days ahead of India's &quot;tryst with destiny&quot;, its independence after nearly 200 years of British rule.</p>
<p>In New Delhi, a subcontinent away from Calcutta, stands a palatial mansion in whose grounds Gandhi was killed by a Hindu gunman five months after independence. It stands as quiet today as it was on that far-away day.</p>
<p>Birla House, now a memorial to Gandhi, is set in a sprawling garden, shaded with shrubs and massive trees.</p>
<p>On Thursdsay, a group of freedom fighters, who arrived in the Indian capital to take part in the 50th anniversary of the country's independence, broke down in tears as they moved around the memorial.</p>
<p>M. Venkataramani, 77, supporting himself with a walking stick, wiped his cheeks as he stood at the spot where Gandhi fell to Nathuram Vinayak Godse's bullets on January 30, 1948.</p>
<p>&quot;I still feel agony at the thought that he was shot,&quot; said Venkataramani, who spent more than six years in jail for defying British rule as a freedom fighter.</p>
<p>&quot;We are proud to be here, proud for what we have achieved,&quot; he said. &quot;Now we are shedding tears of blood for this country, for the way it is saddled with poverty, corruption, casteism and terrorism.&quot;</p>
<p>R. Sundaram, 76, who joined the Indian National Army of charismatic leader Subhas Chandra Bose, said he was happy to be alive to see the independence anniversary.</p>
<p>&quot;But I still feel India is not fully independent,&quot; the sprightly former soldier said.</p>
<p>Pratibha Nigam, who works at the memorial's bookstall, said sales at this time were better than in the past.</p>
<p>&quot;Gandhi's sayings, thoughts and his autobiography are the most sought after,&quot; she said.</p>
<p>For Gandhi, the house built by industrialist Ghanshyam Das Birla became the equivalent to an &quot;ashram&quot; or spiritual abode where he led daily prayer meetings and created homespun cotton on a &quot;charkha&quot; or spinning wheel.</p>
<p>Gandhi, who himself wore a piece of coarse cloth spun by his own hands, also spent August 15, 1947, at the spinning wheel as he described in a letter to Agatha Harrison, a friend in Calcutta.</p>
<p>&quot;This letter I am dictating while I am spinning. You know my way of celebrating great events such as today's is to thank God for it and therefore to pray,&quot; Gandhi said in his letter.</p>
<p>&quot;This prayer must be accompanied by a fast if the taking of fruit juices may be so described. And then as a mark of identification with the poor and dedicated, there must be spinning.</p>
<p>&quot;Hence I must not be satisfied with the spinning I do everyday, but I must do as much as is possible in consistence with my other appointments....&quot; Gandhi said.</p>
<p>&quot;I rarely get a moment to read newspapers. Some portions are either read to me or I glance during odd moments. What does it matter, who talks in my favour or against me if I myself am sound at bottom? After all you and I have to do our duty in the best manner we know and keep on smiling...I am about to finish my spinning. Therefore I must think of other things....&quot;</p>
<p>The letter was signed &quot;Bapu&quot;, a term of endearment meaning &quot;father&quot; that Indians still use to refer to Gandhi.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
