<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800018" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: FEATURE-Empire builders banished to Bombay zoo.</title>
<headline>FEATURE-Empire builders banished to Bombay zoo.</headline>
<byline>Sifra Samuel Lentin</byline>
<dateline>BOMBAY 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Hidden in Bombay's zoo a headless brother of the Duke of Wellington gathers dust with eight other stony relics of the British Raj in India.</p>
<p>The statue of Lord Wellesley, who conquered large tracts of India with his illustrious younger brother, is not the only former governor general of India without a head.</p>
<p>Lord Cornwallis was also beheaded during a night attack on statues of Britain's Empire builders in August 1965.</p>
<p>Fearing more trouble, civic authorities gave the statues refuge in a gloomy backyard of the Bhau Daji Lad Museum (formerly the Victoria &amp; Albert Museum), located in the zoo's grounds.</p>
<p>&quot;The statues were shifted here in 1965 as a result of a movement in the city for the removal of all public colonial statues,&quot; Suman Tate, research assistant at the museum, told Reuters.</p>
<p>&quot;Just horrible things were done to these valuable statues,&quot; Foy Nissen, a local Bombay historian said.</p>
<p>VICTORIA BEHEADED</p>
<p>Queen Victoria, the Empress of India, escaped the Indian nationalists' attack with a battered crown, but suffered the ignominy of losing her head in transit during the rescue operation and had to have it stuck back on later.</p>
<p>Her son the future Edward VII fared better.</p>
<p>The statue of Albert Edward, the then Prince of Wales, astride a black horse, greets visitors at the gates of the zoo.</p>
<p>But most of these symbols of Bombay's colonial past remain skeletons in the cupboard, while the city prepares to celebrate 50 years of Indian independence.</p>
<p>The statues became the focus of nationalist fervour some 18 years after the last British troops filed through the Gateway of India, a triumphal arch on Bombay's waterfront, to sail home as the sun began to set on the empire.</p>
<p>George Fernandes, a current member of parliament, led the move to rid the streets of these reminders of British power.</p>
<p>&quot;I thought someone just had to take the initiative for their removal,&quot; Fernandes, leader of the Samata party, allied to the Hindu nationalist Bharatiya Janata Party, said.</p>
<p>CONTRAST WITH POMP AND PAGEANTRY</p>
<p>A reawakening of nationalist spirit followed the death of Jawaharlal Nehru, India's first prime minister in 1964, he said.</p>
<p>The statues were removed by authorities following a threat by Fernandes that the valuable bronze equestrian statue of the Prince of Wales, by world-renowned sculptor Boehm, would be dislodged by activists on Independence Day, August 15.</p>
<p>&quot;This really was a contrast to the pomp and pageantry that attended the public unveiling of this statue on June 26th, 1879,&quot; said Nissen.</p>
<p>The Kala Ghoda (black horse), as the statue came to be known locally, was a gift to the city of Bombay by Sir Albert Sassoon, son of the Bombay Jewish merchant, David Sassoon.</p>
<p>The Kala Ghoda commemorated the visit of the Prince of Wales to Bombay in 1875-76, and cost 12,500 sterling.</p>
<p>So famous a landmark was this statue that the area in which it once stood continues to be referred to as Kala Ghoda.</p>
<p>&quot;These statues all represent a certain social ethos characteristic of the last century,&quot; explains Nissen.</p>
<p>&quot;It was fashionable for prominent merchants or groups of people to make such a gift to the city. They earned a lot of kudos for it.&quot;</p>
<p>OPIUM AND COTTON FUND STATUARY</p>
<p>The nineteenth century was a prosperous period for Bombay. Huge family fortunes were made, at first in the opium and cotton trade, and later in the cotton mill industry.</p>
<p>Merchants turned philanthropists to give back a little to the city that gave them so much.</p>
<p>&quot;Besides, statues in Bombay were erected to commemorate specific historic events and honour personalities who contributed to the city,&quot; comments social historian Sharada Dwivedi.</p>
<p>The statue of Sir Patrick Kelly, Bombay police commissioner from 1922 to 1933, was erected by popular public subscription.</p>
<p>This statue, now another sad inmate of the museum's hidden statuary, originally stood in front of the Bombay Police Headquarters.</p>
<p>&quot;The statues were part of the urban landscape. They were beautiful and valuable pieces of public sculpture,&quot; Nissen said.</p>
<p>Now the places where they once stood tall either lie vacant or have been built over. Or they have been co-opted to give expression to Indian nationalist aspirations.</p>
<p>&quot;A case in point is the lion and lioness from the statue of Lord Hardinge of Penhurst, viceroy and governor-general of India from 1910 to 1916,&quot; says Nissen.</p>
<p>&quot;They adorn the pedestal of radical Indian nationalist leader Lokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak on Chowpatty beach.&quot;</p>
<p>By a twist of fate, Tilak's statue was the starting point of the city's Freedom March on August 9, the first of numerous programmes planned to mark 50 years of Indian Independence.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOMBAY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
