<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800165" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NY precious metals called to open lower.</title>
<headline>NY precious metals called to open lower.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>COMEX and NYMEX precious metals futures were seen opening lower on Thursday, following range-bound trading in London, but eyeing upcoming economic date early in Thursday's New York session.</p>
<p>COMEX December gold was seen opening unchanged to down 50 cents an ounce from its previous close at $330.10, and traded in a range of $330.00 to $331.40 an ounce in overnight ACCESS trading.</p>
<p>In the bullion market, spot gold was quoted $326.00/9.50 early, compared to the London Tuesday morning fix at $327.30 an ounce.  </p>
<p>COMEX warehouse gold stocks fell 1,626 ounces to 946,079 ounces in Wednesday's data, while COMEX silver stocks fell 1,275,315 ounces to 165,395,967 ounces.</p>
<p>The consumer price index was projected to be up 0.2 percent over the previous report. The report is due 0830 EDT/1230 GMT. Industrial production is projected up 0.2 percent from the previous report, and capacity utilization is unchanged at 83.5 percent.</p>
<p>COMEX September silver was seen opening down 2.00-2.50 cents from Wednesday's close of $4.507 an ounce.</p>
<p>NYMEX October platinum was expected to open $1.00-$2.00 lower from Wednesday's close at $431.10 an ounce, while NYMEX September palladium was seen opening up $5.00-$6.00 an ounce from the previous close at $215.85 an ounce.</p>
<p>The platinum group metals showed particular weakess, as a result of Russian selling in the Zurich spot market, which led to weaker prices on TOCOM, dealers said. But strong fundamentals in platinum and palladium should provide support in the market.</p>
<p>((--New York Commodities Desk, 212-859-1640))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
