<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800288" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: William: princely hope for British royals?.</title>
<headline>William: princely hope for British royals?.</headline>
<byline>Lyndsay Griffiths</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>At 15, he has inherited much of his mother's charm -- part naive, part practised -- and the best of his father's classical features.</p>
<p>Those who know &quot;Wills&quot; say he is a true prince: kind, charming, with film star looks and British manners.</p>
<p>Prince William is duly emerging as the last hope for the hapless House of Windsor as it faces record low ratings in the polls and rising support for a republic.</p>
<p>&quot;We all thought we were looking at the burial of the the royal family. But this young man is a winner,&quot; said a U.S. producer at a rare photo-call with Wills this week.</p>
<p>The future William V, second in line to the throne after his father Prince Charles, had to grow up fast.</p>
<p>Already a confidant to his highly-strung mother, Princess Diana, he must also protect his younger brother Harry from the harsh realities of modern royal life.</p>
<p>Like many children, William comes from a broken home and had to tackle adolescence as family life collapsed.</p>
<p>Unlike many children, he watched the breakup play out in the national press and saw the remains being picked over in catty talk shows and moralising opinion polls.</p>
<p>Both his parents admitted to adultery on national television.</p>
<p>A palace insider said William was a &quot;fantastic&quot; performer given the stresses of his life.</p>
<p>&quot;Any 15-year-old at the centre of a divorce has a balancing act to perform between his mother and father. He has the added responsibility of doing it in the glare of the world's press,&quot; the insider told the Daily Express.</p>
<p>Just this week, William saw pictures on every news-stand of his elegant, about-town mother aboard a luxury yacht embracing a playboy millionaire -- Dodi Al Fayed, the 41-year-old son of Egyptian tycoon Mohamed Al Fayed, who owns the luxury Harrods department store.</p>
<p>William is now in Scotland with his kilt-wearing father, pursuing more traditional royal pastimes.</p>
<p>Yet while Charles is an old-fashioned prince, he plays by modern rules and wants to win public acceptance for his long-time lover -- the woman blamed for turning his &quot;fairy-tale&quot; marriage into a ghastly menage a trois.</p>
<p>William, as ever, is caught in between.</p>
<p>&quot;He seems to have withstood the stresses of his parents' stormy and public parting with remarkable strength. Only time will tell how the experience may have affected him,&quot; said royal biographer Sarah Bradford.</p>
<p>Bradford said &quot;the burden of the monarchy is still a long way from falling on his shoulders&quot;, despite calls in some quarters for the crown to skip a generation.</p>
<p>Few could envision Charles relinquishing the throne for which he has waited so long, and it is far from clear that fun-loving William is ready for the top job.</p>
<p>Yet something must be done to salvage the monarchy, with a poll out this week showing its popularity had dropped below 50 percent for the first time.</p>
<p>Just three years ago, the royals' approval rating stood at 70 percent and it now falls on William to offer the public some lost cachet and the sort of decency that used to keep the monarchy in business.</p>
<p>&quot;Is brave William the last hope for royals?&quot; asked the Express, saying he &quot;showed the qualities which single him out as the royal family's potential saviour&quot;.</p>
<p>Observers at this week's photo-call said blond, blue-eyed Wills joked easily with his standoffish father even as he mimicked his mother's &quot;accidentally-on-purpose caught on camera pose&quot; to great success.</p>
<p>Such success that the best-selling Sun speculated about an alternative future for the prince who was nominated &quot;most fanciable male&quot; in Smash Hits magazine.</p>
<p>&quot;Could Wills be king of the catwalk?&quot; the paper asked. &quot;Okay, so his career may already have been mapped out for him, but if the heir to the throne ever fancied a sideline in modelling...the sky's the limit.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
