<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800280" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Tightness boosts LME aluminium as shorts scramble.</title>
<headline>Tightness boosts LME aluminium as shorts scramble.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Aluminium tightness came to the fore in Thursday morning LME ring trading as players jostled ahead of the August delivery date next week.</p>
<p>Spreads flared as shorts scrambled to borrow the August dates ahead of Monday, the key trading day ahead of expiration of the August contract.</p>
<p>The benchmark cash/threes spread ballooned to a $20/25 backwardation from about $4 on Wednesday evening, while August/one-day traded at a $11 backwardation.</p>
<p>The tightness is due to a technical squeeze, with metal in generally good supply, but with one or two big players cornering the key August dates, traders and analysts said.</p>
<p>Spread activity was hectic during the rings and at the end of the official ring, cash was bid up as merchants joined the scrum to cover short positions.</p>
<p>The three months market was relegated to the background for most of the morning, but during the kerb the price stormed back above the $1,700 per tonne mark, pulled up by cash buying. It ended the morning kerb $22 firmer at $1,718.</p>
<p>A stocks rise of 1,725 tonnes, the third successive increase in as many days, dented sentiment briefly on the pre-market. But any fears that a trend is emerging after weeks of falling LME inventories were forgotten as the spreads buoyed the market.</p>
<p>Zinc saw reasonable turnover, with the September dates still keenly sought, traders said.</p>
<p>The September/October spread was steady at a $50 backwardation with cash/threes slightly wider at a $120 backwardation.</p>
<p>A 2,400-tonne fall in stocks on Thursday bolstered the market, especially after talk earlier this week of 20,000 tonnes heading to Singapore. Instead, stocks are so far dribbling into Singapore, with a net rise of only 1,525 tonnes on Thursday.</p>
<p>Three months ended the morning at its high of $1,520, a $35 gain.</p>
<p>Copper was hit by widespread lending of the cash/threes spread, with little physical interest to underpin prices as stocks keep rising. Inventories rose by 1,950 tonnes on Thursday to 256,300 tonnes.</p>
<p>The cash/threes shrunk to a $12 backwardation in the second ring from $17 in the first ring and about $19 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>With the last remnants of last month's tightness coming out of the market and more big shipments of metal thought to be heading to LME warehouses, many players are expecting pressure to emerge and tests of support at $2,250/60.</p>
<p>&quot;Every time it gets up toward $2,300 it looks tired,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>Last morning business was little changed at $2,289, down $1.</p>
<p>Nickel saw a short-covering rally, climbing to $6,720, after crumbling by about $700 or 10 percent over the previous four days to a low of $6,520 on Wednesday.</p>
<p>But as covering dried up, prices came off the highs, ending the morning kerb $160 firmer at $6,670.</p>
<p>Tin was quiet, taking a breather after several days of losses. It ended the kerb $30 stronger at $5,440.</p>
<p>Lead hovered above $600, but traders expected more probes of the downside since the efforts to bounce have not been convincing. The last kerb trade for the morning was at $610, up $3.</p>
<p>Alloy closed the morning steady at $1,505/15.</p>
<p>--London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
