<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800244" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Physical aluminium activity seen picking up soon.</title>
<headline>Physical aluminium activity seen picking up soon.</headline>
<byline>Eric Onstad</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>European physical business in aluminium is sluggish but activity should pick up shortly when consumers return from summer holidays and the futures market moves past the tight August dates.</p>
<p>Traders are divided, however, on the extent of any uptick in business.</p>
<p>&quot;There is virtually no activity. There's the backwardation, the high market, high premiums and the strong dollar is the cherry on the cake,&quot; a trader in Europe said.</p>
<p>&quot;But I think it is changing already...I am quite bullish for the next several weeks in terms of business,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>The backwardation, which flared on Thursday to $20 basis the cash/threes spread, has put a crimp in physical business and hit premiums. Tightness is centred in the August contract, which expires next week.</p>
<p>&quot;The physical market depends on what happens to the spreads. It's a technical squeeze and once that's out of the way, the market will be able to make much more of an informed opinion as to where it goes,&quot; another trader said.</p>
<p>Nearby physical premiums are very soft due to the August backwardation, but rates for forward delivery have held up fairly well, traders said.</p>
<p>Russian A7E metal in Rotterdam was quoted at $25/$30 over LME cash, about $5/$10 softer a month ago. Unpaid Western material in Rotterdam was weaker by a similar amount at a $40/$45 premium.</p>
<p>Premiums should hold until November when another lump of tightness is showing up in the spreads, traders said. &quot;November could get quite nasty,&quot; one added.</p>
<p>There is little consensus on how much buying will be seen as the summer winds down, with bulls expecting pent-up demand from consumers who have been living hand-to-mouth and waiting for a major correction.</p>
<p>&quot;There are still quite some shorts in physical all over Europe. Now people have to cover,&quot; one said.</p>
<p>But others said supply is ample.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't see where all this buying is coming from. But even if they come I don't think they'll have a problem in finding metal,&quot; another physical trader said.</p>
<p>Some analysts say strong levels of stock building seen in the first half of 1997 are unlikely to be repeated and the market may move into surplus during the second half.</p>
<p>The physical market will eye upcoming LME stock movements after three successive stock rises this week followed weeks of relentless declines.</p>
<p>By Monday, LME inventories had fallen by about 33 percent during 1997 to 620,4975 tonnes but after Thursday's 1,725-tonne rise, stocks had edged up to 627,025 tonnes.</p>
<p>--London Newsroom +44 171 542-8065</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
