<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800243" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Aluminium tightness flares ahead of August date.</title>
<headline>Aluminium tightness flares ahead of August date.</headline>
<byline>Martin Hayes</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Backwardations for upcoming August delivery dates for aluminium flared up on Thursday on the London Metal Exchange (LME), as speculative and trade shorts scrambled for cover.</p>
<p>Technical tightness has been building up for some time now on the the LME, but Thursday saw a rush of covering - both by borrowing metal and by buying cash outright - with the crunch &quot;third Wednesday&quot; date trading next Monday.</p>
<p>&quot;Clearly, people have been covering ahead of next week. They tend to do that nowadays, rather than leave it to the last moment,&quot; analyst Robin Bhar of LME trader Brandeis said.</p>
<p>In lively ring sessions the premium to borrow August aluminium for one day was at $11, against a backwardation of $17 in place for the whole week. This led to the cash/threes spread moving out to near $20 backwardation, having been level earlier this week.</p>
<p>Next Monday, the cash that is traded will be for the &quot;third Wednesday&quot; of August. This prompt is where volatility is nearly always focussed, as open interest gravitates to this date when it is traded as a forward position beyond three months.</p>
<p>Also, options that are declared on the first Wednesday of the month are for settlement on this day as well.</p>
<p>Floor traders said the tightness has been well-signposted, with bank interests said to be long, while speculative funds and natural trade hedge shorts are on the other side of the market.</p>
<p>Because of this backwardation, spare metal is now being attracted to the market. Consequently, LME stocks are starting to rise, with increases totalling 6,550 tonnes over the last three days.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't think this is a trend yet...I think a bit of metal has been warranted to take advantage of August,&quot; a trader said.</p>
<p>On Thursday, there was the unusual occurrence of 3,075 tonnes delivered into LME Japanese warehouses. Since the LME recognised Japan as a delivery point, aluminium has rarely been stored in these warehouses.</p>
<p>The bulk of Thursday's increase was metal warranted in Yokohama, which is the port where the high tonnages of off-warrant aluminium are held in Japan.</p>
<p>As well as grabbing the backwardation, stocks may be filtering on to the LME as long-term consignment deals come to an end and because the contango has disappeared financing has become unprofitable, Bhar said.</p>
<p>Next Monday's cash trading is not expected to signal an end to the high premiums, as the whole of the month is starting to show signs of tightness with August/September at $30 backwardation.</p>
<p>Also, some positions may have simply been rolled forward three months from August, putting the heat on the November dates.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, traders do not expect the LME authorities to take any immediate action, following the Board's recent reminder to members of its rules regarding market conditions and abuse.</p>
<p>Some noted that cash/one day at $11 is well below a  thereoritical $17 one percent daily limit. In copper, the LME has imposed this limit - based on one precent of the previous day cash price for the daily premium.</p>
<p>But no such limit exists in aluminium, and any action would have to be authorised by the LME Board, others noted.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a lesson here that applies in copper and zinc as well - don't sell what doesn't below to you,' one senior floor trader said.</p>
<p>--London newsroom 44 171 542 8080</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
