<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800329" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Ldn gold lodged in range, watching other markets.</title>
<headline>Ldn gold lodged in range, watching other markets.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Gold meandered around the top end of its recent price range on Thursday and dealers said the market was waiting for more volatility on Wall Street to help prices break above a key resistance level.</p>
<p>Bullion fixed at $327.30 an ounce, compared to $326.20 on Wednesday afternoon and a London clos of $327.60/$328.10.</p>
<p>Gyrations on U.S. stock and bond markets last week elicited a strong rally in gold, and more volatility on Wednesday had lifted prices to just under $330.00, an important resistance level. But that latest surge faltered and gold slid back.</p>
<p>&quot;The funds are the shorts in this market and as we're at the top end of the range they're eyeing financials nervously,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;If there's another shake-up on Wall Street we'll see a short-covering move to the upside. Chances are we'll see gold higher.&quot;</p>
<p>But failure to breach resistance means prices would continue bumping up against that ceiling and eventually fall back to $322-$323 support, dealers said.</p>
<p>Silver was steady after moving up alongside with gold on Wednesday and holding onto some of its gains. had rallied up to a high bid of $4.56 at one point on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Dealers said the market wanted to fill a gap on the September Comex chart which translated to $5.56-$5.60 in the spot market.</p>
<p>&quot;Until it fills that gap, we're not going to see silver too much weaker,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>But another dealer noted that the market needed to establish a base above $4.50 or risk sliding back towards $4.40.</p>
<p>Spot silver was last indicated at $4.48/$4.50, down two cents from Wednesday's London close.</p>
<p>The platinum group metals by contrast were easier and dealers said they expected prices to continue drifting as Russian exports trickled onto the market.</p>
<p>&quot;They'll continue consolidating and edging lower but the market is still very tight and there's no way I'd be short in these markets,&quot; a dealer said.</p>
<p>Platinum was last at $428.00/$431.00, down $4.00 from Wednesday's close, while palladium was off $7.00 at $217.00/$220.00.</p>
<p>--Lida Poletz, London newsroom +44 171 542 2936</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
