<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800349" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Islam is victim of Algeria bloodshed - FIS leader.</title>
<headline>Islam is victim of Algeria bloodshed - FIS leader.</headline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>The leader of the banned Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) Abassi Madani said in remarks published on Thursday that Islam was a victim and not a perpetrator of the bloodshed in Algeria.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not possible that Islam be accused of what is happening,&quot; Madani said in remarks published in the London-based Al-Hayat newspaper.</p>
<p>&quot;If I say Islam is innocent, then this means that Islam was accused. Islam itself is what is being slaughtered...</p>
<p>&quot;How can the victim be the criminal? I can't say the lamb devours the wolf. It's the wolf who devours the lamb. What concerns us is adhering to our behaviour under Islamic law.&quot;</p>
<p>Hundreds of civilians, including babies and pregnant women, have been killed in Algeria this year in massacres blamed by the authorities on Moslem rebels.</p>
<p>About 60,000 people have been killed in the conflict between the government and the Islamists since 1992 when the authorities cancelled a general election in which FIS had taken a commanding lead.</p>
<p>Madani was arrested in 1991 and sentenced in 1992 by a military court to 12 years in jail for threatening Algeria's security. He was set free on parole in July halfway through the sentence and told to refrain from political activity.</p>
<p>Madani said after his release that he and his supporters would do all they could to end the violence.</p>
<p>Al-Hayat quoted Madani as saying that what is happening in Algeria &quot;is a repeat of what took place in Bosnia. Moslems are the victims&quot;.</p>
<p>He denied that he was seeking to take refuge in Morocco.</p>
<p>&quot;I have neither the intention nor the ability, because I am concerned with the issue of the suffering of our people. There is no sleep when I hear what is happening.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="ALG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GVIO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
