<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800370" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: Turk secularists, Islamists battle over education.</title>
<headline>Turk secularists, Islamists battle over education.</headline>
<byline>Daren Butler</byline>
<dateline>ANKARA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's secularist establishment and the former ruling Islamists fought the latest round of a bitter dispute on Thursday in a parliamentary debate on key education reforms.</p>
<p>Deputies crowded into a special session to hear impassioned speeches on a bill touted by government deputies as a reaffirmation of Turkey's secularist credentials set out by the republic's founder, Mustafa Kemal Ataturk.</p>
<p>&quot;The eight-year, uninterrupted education law will be a victory for Ataturk 59 years after his death,&quot; government deputy Metin Sahin told a packed meeting of the 550-seat assembly.</p>
<p>His words drew an angry response from Islamist Welfare Party MPs, who say the bill endangers the future of religious 'Imam Hatip' schools. Secularists, rallied behind the military, see the schools as a breeding ground for radical Moslem activists.</p>
<p>&quot;If you see Imam Hatips as a source of fundamentalism you are a murderer of this country's peace, brotherhood and tolerance,&quot; Welfare's Omer Vehbi Hatipoglu said in a speech on behalf of the party.</p>
<p>Under the bill, compulsory state schooling would be extended to eight years from five, effectively bringing an end to the primary section of Imam Hatip schools.</p>
<p>The draft law was approved by the planning and budget commission on Tuesday after nine days of negotiations which repeatedly broke down in heated exchanges between Welfare and government deputies.</p>
<p>The education plan was the cornerstone of military demands in February aimed at curbing an alleged rise in religious activism under the Islamist-led government of former prime minister and Welfare leader Necmettin Erbakan.</p>
<p>The secularist pressure helped edge Erbakan out of office in June and led to the appointment of a right-left government under Prime Minister Mesut Yilmaz.</p>
<p>Erbakan's coalition ally, the True Path Party, has backed his efforts to block the schooling reforms and attacked the role of the powerful military in bringing the reforms onto the agenda.</p>
<p>&quot;No democratic country in the world binds education problems to the decisions of generals,&quot; True Path's Ayvaz Gokdemir told parliament, calling the bill the &quot;Imam Hatip destruction law&quot;.</p>
<p>Large numbers of Islamists have denounced the bill, taking to the streets to protest at what they see as a direct threat to religious education.</p>
<p>Police have refused permission for further protests which they see as a security threat ahead of Friday's 13th anniversary of the start of an armed Kurdish insurgency in the southeast of the country.</p>
<p>The education plans were supported by just over half those questioned in a recent survey by the Elips Research Company, the state-run Anatolian news agency said.</p>
<p>The survey, based on face-to-face interviews with more than 4,000 people across 14 provinces, showed 25 percent favoured a formula allowing pupils to spend the last three of the eight years in religious or other specialist schools.</p>
<p>Another 17.8 percent favoured keeping the education system as it is.</p>
<p>The parliament session, expected to be addressed by over 100 MPs, was set to continue until midnight (2100 GMT) and resume on Friday if necessary before going to a vote. The summer recess, already delayed to deal with the bill, was to begin after the process was completed.</p>
<p>The commission has approved plans for consumers to contribute to the school reforms, forecast to cost 1,000 trillion lira ($613 million) over the next three years.</p>
<p>($1 = 163,500 Turkish lira)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GREL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ANKARA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
