<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800574" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: NY precious metals mostly lower after U.S. CPI.</title>
<headline>NY precious metals mostly lower after U.S. CPI.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>COMEX and NYMEX precious metals futures slipped lower early Thursday, with the U.S. dollar and stocks and bonds slightly firmer after the U.S. July CPI rose 0.2 pct, exactly as expected.</p>
<p>&quot;The market's reaction was a bit disappointing,&quot; one COMEX dealer said.</p>
<p>&quot;The inflation data was pretty good but pretty much as expected to stocks and bonds did little as did gold, and there's not much paper in the ring,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>But traders remain wary of a further correction of the stock market which may result in December gold testing the top of its $320-335 range of the past month.</p>
<p>So far the S&amp;P500 index has declined 4.4 pct by Wednesday's close from the all time high on August 7.</p>
<p>Ironically, August 14 marks the 60th anniversary of the 1937 high in the stock market which was followed, not by a crash like 1929 or 1937, but by a steady 42 pct decline in a little over two months, analysts noted.</p>
<p>COMEX December gold was down 30 cents at $330.40 an ounce after the first half hour of trade, after dipping to an early session low at $329.50. Minor support is still seen around $328.00, with major resistance around $335.00.</p>
<p>In the bullion market, spot gold was quoted $326.20/70 an ounce early, compared to the London Thursday morning fix at $327.30 and the New York close Wednesday around $326.90/40.</p>
<p>On a bearish note, implied gold lease rates rose sharply again Thursday, to 2.68 pct for one month from 2.29 pct Wednesday, and to 2.37 percent for one year from 2.26 pct.</p>
<p>The move suggested funds and producers may be borrowing again to fund short positions and hedges, as spot gold is back near the top of its range of the past month around $330.00.</p>
<p>COMEX September silver was off 0.2 cent at $4.50 an ounce, after a 8.2 cent gain Wednesday to test the high of the past month around $4.540.</p>
<p>But NYMEX October platinum was down $6.10 at $425.00, while NYMEX September palladium was off $6.00 an ounce at $209.85</p>
<p>Earlier TOCOM platinum and palladium prices slipped overnight on reports of Russian sales of platinum group metals in the spot market in Europe.</p>
<p>But one month platinum lease rates were unchanged around 20 pct, as were one month palladium lease rates which were indicated around 80 pct.</p>
<p>&quot;The Russian may be exporting a little again, but inventories are not rebuilding, as the metal is either delivered against a TOCOM short position or consumed by manufactures or possible even hoarded,&quot; one U.S. refining source said.</p>
<p>email: clive.mckeef @ reuters.com</p>
<p>((Clive McKeef, New York Commodities Desk, 212-859-1641))</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
