<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800636" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Bonn tax-talk debate simmers as revenues fall.</title>
<headline>Bonn tax-talk debate simmers as revenues fall.</headline>
<byline>Terence Gallagher</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>German coalition and opposition leaders haggled over a return to talks on tax reform on Thursday amid warnings that tax revenues would fall further from earlier estimates.</p>
<p>The economy badly needs the shot in the arm promised by the tax reform, which includes 30 billion marks ($16.4 billion) in stimulative tax cuts, but the process has been stalled by the failure of the two sides to reach agreement in parliamentary mediation.</p>
<p>Tax-revenue shortfalls are threatening to keep Germany from meeting the deficit target for EU economic and monetary union (EMU), set by the Maastricht Treaty at three percent of gross domestic product.</p>
<p>Wolfgang Schaeuble, parliamentary faction leader for Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian Democrats, said he would drop everything for another chance to discuss tax reform with opposition Social Democrats (SPD) outside the parliamentary mediation committee, in a round similar to those held at the start of the year.</p>
<p>&quot;I would end my summer holiday on Sylt and fly to Bonn right away for that,&quot; Schaeuble told the Sueddeutsche Zeitung.</p>
<p>But Schaeuble said the SPD must be prepared for &quot;real negotiations&quot; on hard issues, and not just mouth populist slogans.</p>
<p>Germany's high income taxes and corporate taxes are a major obstacle to economic growth, and reform must go beyond the planned cuts in the solidarity tax, he said.</p>
<p>SPD leader Oskar Lafontaine, in a radio interview, said he was sceptical of Schaeuble's offer, and said before such talks could take place the government must set out a plan that would not wreak havoc with public finances.</p>
<p>Hamburg Mayor Henning Voscherau, another SPD budget expert, said Bonn's tax reform plan lacked solid financing and would leave government coffers 45 billion marks short.</p>
<p>Amid the fiscal-policy tension, Finance Minister Theo Waigel shrugged off a rebuff by Kohl and repeated his call for a cabinet reshuffle soon.</p>
<p>Waigel told Bild newspaper a shake-up would help tighten up Kohl's 17-member cabinet and make it more effective in the run-up to the September 1998 general election.</p>
<p>While the tactical debate over tax reform raged, other influential voices warned that Germany's real economic straits were increasingly dire. Bundesbank board member Klaus-Dieter Kuehbacher said that this year's tax revenues could be about 10 billion marks lower than the already lowered expectations the government published in May.</p>
<p>Kuehbacher said in a television interview that the central bank reviews the government's tax revenues monthly. &quot;And unfortunately we have to tell them, 'Your expectations will not be fulfilled.'&quot; The next public tax estimate will be in November.</p>
<p>Rolf Peffekoven, a member of the government's council of economic advisers, said further spending cuts would be needed in subsidies and social outlays if tax revenues fell further short of target.</p>
<p>The only alternative would be a higher deficit, but that would push Germany irrevocably above the EMU target, Peffekoven told the Cologne newspaper Express.</p>
<p>Peffekoven also said the government must persevere in its tax reform efforts, and deliver the promised 30 billion mark tax cuts aimed at stimulating the economy and creating jobs.</p>
<p>The Finance Ministry said on Wednesday it still sees no need to correct its May tax estimate, which showed 1997 tax revenues 18 billion marks lower than the estimate made in November 1996.</p>
<p>-- Bonn newsroom, 49-228-26097150 ($ = 1.831 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
