<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800668" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>FINLAND: Niinisto says 1998 budget deficit may beat target.</title>
<headline>Niinisto says 1998 budget deficit may beat target.</headline>
<dateline>HELSINKI 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Finnish Finance Minister Sauli Niinisto said on Thursday that next year's budget deficit might be even lower than the targeted 17 billion markka.</p>
<p>Asked at a news conference whether the 17 billion markka deficit target was still within reach, Niinisto said: &quot;It looks like that, maybe even lower.&quot;</p>
<p>On the first day of three-day budget negotiations on Wednesday, the five-party coalition agreed that the budget deficit should be no more than 17-18 billion markka compared to some 25 billion this year.  </p>
<p>The talks were on track to be completed on schedule on Friday, Niinisto said.</p>
<p>The government agreed on Thursday to introduce a plan to reduce cash funds at various ministries by a total of about one billion markka, he said.</p>
<p>This would reduce the need to find spending cuts required to push total 1998 budget spending to the 188 billion markka target agreed on Wednesday, Niinisto said. In 1997, budget spending is projected at around 192 billion markka.</p>
<p>The government's budget proposal will be given to parliament on September 2.</p>
<p>--Helsinki newsroom +358-9-680 50 245, news@reuters.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="FIN">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="HELSINKI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="FINLAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
