<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800617" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Kevorkian admits role in death of N.Y. woman.</title>
<headline>Kevorkian admits role in death of N.Y. woman.</headline>
<dateline>FARMINGTON HILLS, Mich. 1997-08-13</dateline>
<text>
<p>Dr. Jack Kevorkian acknowledged on Wednesday that he helped a New York woman die, the first time in nearly a year he has directly admitted his role in an assisted suicide.</p>
<p>Kevorkian and long-time ally Janet Good were present at the suicide of Karen Shoffstall in a local motel, according to Kevorkian's attorney, Geoffrey Fieger. Shoffstall, 34, of Long Beach, New York, suffered from multiple sclerosis, he said.</p>
<p>&quot;Dr. Kevorkian helped her end her suffering,&quot; Fieger told reporters on Wednesday.</p>
<p>Police in Farmington Hills, a suburb west of Detroit, found Shoffstall's body in the motel after the manager discovered her with a note saying Kevorkian had helped her die.</p>
<p>Kevorkian has publicly admitted helping 46 people die since 1990 in his crusade to legalize assisted suicide. It was the first time since October 1996 that Kevorkian has accepted direct responsibility for an assisted suicide.</p>
<p>Since February, 10 bodies have turned up in the Detroit area. Eight of those had notes referring police to Fieger as their attorney. Fieger has hinted that Kevorkian was involved in the two others.</p>
<p>Last month, the prosecutor in Ionia County, Michigan, said he would not re-try Kevorkian on charges of assisted suicide and practicing medicine without a license following a mistrial that was declared in June.</p>
<p>Kevorkian has been acquitted of assisted suicide charges at three trials involving five deaths. Although the Michigan State Supreme Court has ruled that assisted suicide violates the state's unwritten &quot;common law,&quot; prosecutors in the Detroit area have said they will not charge the country's best known assisted suicide advocate.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-13"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="FARMINGTON HILLS, Mich."/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
