<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800791" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: EU may reimpose ban on British bull semen exports.</title>
<headline>EU may reimpose ban on British bull semen exports.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>The European Union may reimpose a ban on British exports of bull semen as a precautionary measure to protect the public from any possible risk of mad cow disease, European Commission officials said on Thursday.</p>
<p>They said that a German report, requested several months ago, is due to be examined by the EU's multidisciplinary committee of independent scientists on September 8.</p>
<p>Semen is the only product exempted from a worldwide ban on British beef exports imposed 17-months ago after London said that it was possible the fatal cattle brain disease, known scientifically as Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy (BSE), could be passed to humans eating infected beef.</p>
<p>&quot;Even if there is no proof that BSE is transmissible through semen, there's not enough scientific research to be 100 percent sure. Therefore to be safe, semen exports may be banned,&quot; a Commission official said.</p>
<p>If the scientists recommended a ban, the Commission would send a proposal to the EU's Standing Veterinary Committee of chief veterinary officers for their opinion before taking a final decision.</p>
<p>Although few countries currently import British bull semen, reimposition of the ban would be a blow to British efforts to gradually ease the crippling curbs on beef exports.</p>
<p>Semen, along with gelatine and tallow, was exempted from the EU ban. But earlier this year curbs on gelatine and tallow were reinstated due to concern that production methods did not fully eradicate the infectious BSE agent.</p>
<p>A ban on British cattle embryos also remained in a place after a report showed a small risk that the deadly disease could be passed from cows to calves.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I01001">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I0100105">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C13">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="C312">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G153">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
