<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800783" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: FEATURE - French-speaking Quebec celebrates Irish heritage.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - French-speaking Quebec celebrates Irish heritage.</headline>
<byline>Patrick White</byline>
<dateline>QUEBEC CITY 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>The capital of the French-speaking province of Quebec is celebrating a people who are an integral part of its history -- the Irish.</p>
<p>One hundred and fifty years after 100,000 Irish immigrants fleeing the Great Famine landed at Quebec City, the &quot;Summer of Sorrows&quot; is being remembered here in song and dance and with bittersweet commemorations that include participants from Canada, the United States and Ireland.</p>
<p>Events are centered on Grosse-Ile, an island in the St. Lawrence River east of Quebec City where Irish immigrants were quarantined before being granted access to the mainland. More than 5,000 died there from hunger and typhoid fever in the summer of 1847.</p>
<p>&quot;Irish immigrants had come to Canada before 1847 and Grosse-Ile wasn't the only place where they arrived,&quot; city historian Mariana O'Gallagher said. &quot;But this is where the story is most touching. Entire families died there. You can see that in the Anglican register.&quot;</p>
<p>Last year, responding to demands to protect Grosse Ile's legacy, the Canadian government certified the island as a memorial to the Irish.</p>
<p>FESTIVAL ON PLAINS OF ABRAHAM</p>
<p>Immigrants' descendants from North America and Ireland will board boats in Quebec City's old port on Aug. 16 and 17 for the last leg of their pilgrimage to Grosse Ile. A street procession, Catholic Mass and reception will follow in Quebec City. Celebrations this summer also include an outdoor festival on Quebec City's Plains of Abraham, a park overlooking the St. Lawrence River where English troops defeated the French to conquer Canada in 1759.</p>
<p>James Gallagher from Connecticut is organizing the Quebec events for the Ancient Order of Hibernians, an Irish-American organization. Action Grosse Ile, a Toronto-based association of Irish Canadians, is co-organizer.</p>
<p>&quot;What we are doing is bringing together the Irish diaspora in North America and thanking the French-Canadians, who adopted all the Irish orphans and allowed them to keep their names and surnames,&quot; Gallagher said.</p>
<p>With the Irish influx in 1847, Quebec City's population of 40,000, already one-quarter Irish, swelled by more than 100,000. The French Catholic population quickly sprang forward to help the new arrivals, adopting thousands of orphans.</p>
<p>Many of the newcomers went on to the United States. Others ventured to other parts of Canada.</p>
<p>IRISH DESCENDANTS ASSIMILATED</p>
<p>Today, this 389-year-old city of 700,000 people is 97 percent French-speaking and most descendants of the original Irish settlers have been assimilated into French-speaking society. Distinctly Irish names such as O'Brien and Ryan are now pronounced with French intonation.</p>
<p>&quot;There are few Irish left. They married French-Canadian women and access to English-language schools has become difficult,&quot; said Laurette Talbot, who married Irish-Quebecker Leslie White in the 1940s.</p>
<p>Although all of her nine children speak English, only one of her 14 grandchildren does. But signs of Quebec's Irish heritage remain. A weekly newspaper, &quot;The Quebec Chronicle Telegraph,&quot; and Irish names on schools, streets, churches, other buildings and cemeteries are reminders of a once-flourishing Irish community.</p>
<p>Petrina Lynch came at the invitation of the Quebec City organization &quot;Irish Summer&quot; to teach Gaelic to English-speaking Quebecers. &quot;They are really into it. They want to go back to their roots even if they just learn a few words,&quot; Lynch said.</p>
<p>More information on Quebec City's Irish celebrations can be found at two Internet addresses: http://www.quebec-region.cuq.qc.ca and http://www.aoh.com.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="FRA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="IRE">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="QUEBEC CITY"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
