<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800805" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>BELGIUM: FUN IN BRUSSELS - NOI, A THAI RESTAURANT IN LINKEBEEK.</title>
<headline>FUN IN BRUSSELS - NOI, A THAI RESTAURANT IN LINKEBEEK.</headline>
<dateline>BRUSSELS 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>As Belgium swelters under a long-awaited heat wave, what better than to add to the atmosphere with a Thai meal -- and, moreover, one that will not stretch your wallet too far.</p>
<p>Noi restaurant in Linkebeek fits the bill perfectly. The food is excellent, the prices are reasonable, the atmosphere relaxed and informal and the service friendly and -- equally important -- informative.</p>
<p>Although the restaurant is open throughout the year (except Sundays) for lunch and dinner, it blossoms during good weather when the garden is opened and diners can sit at clean teak tables surrounded by exotic plants while the unique scent of Thai cooking wafts around them.</p>
<p>The basic fixed menu is augmented by a regularly-changing selection written on a blackboard and which the staff are only too happy to explain in vivid detail -- including appropriate warnings about pepper strength.</p>
<p>First courses, which range in price from 280 to 410 francs, cover all the usual suspects. Leompia (spring rolls), Canomchip (Thai raviolli), Kai Sate (chicken brochettes) jostle for recognition alongside dishes such as Som Tam (green papaya salad) and Khung che nam pla (raw prawns).</p>
<p>Main dishes, which range in price between 420 and 560 francs, include Panang kai (chicken with coconut in red curry sauce), Keng kiowan neua (beef with coconut in green curry sauce), Moo kathiam (pork with garlic and pepper, Plamuk kathiam (prawns and squid with garlic) and Tom yam khung (classic prawn casserole).</p>
<p>On the liquid refreshment side Noi offers a limited but carefully chosen and mid-priced wine list, soft drinks and beers -- including Singha imported from Thailand.</p>
<p>Linkebeek may not be on the beaten track for dwellers in central Brussels and points north, east and west. But Noi is worth the adventure south.</p>
<p>Noi restaurant, Place Communale 6, 1630 Linkebeek.</p>
<p>Telephone: 02/380 6860.</p>
<p>Open: Tuesday to Friday 1200 to 1400. Monday to Saturday 1900 to 2200.</p>
<p>-- Jeremy Lovell, Brussels Newsroom +32 2 287 6810, Fax +32 2 230 7710</p>
<p>FUN IN BRUSSELS is a series in which Reuters reporters offer some brief recommendations on places to go and upcoming events in Europe's capital.</p>
<p>Feedback and suggestions are always welcome. Please phone Reuters Editorial (Brussels) on Tel: 02/287.68.13.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="BELG">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BRUSSELS"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="BELGIUM"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
