<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800893" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Poet ruffles feathers in Scotland with record deal.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Poet ruffles feathers in Scotland with record deal.</headline>
<byline>Jill Serjeant</byline>
<dateline>EDINBURGH 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>With his long dark curly hair and frock coats, he looks like Britain's 19th century romantic poet Lord Byron.</p>
<p>But that's about as far as the comparison goes for 28-year-old Murray Lachlan Young, a previously unpublished bard whose snappy verses about sex, drugs, and rock and roll are set to make him a millionaire.</p>
<p>Young, an American-born Scot with a flair for the melodramatic, has taken the elitist world of poetry by storm by winning a one million pound ($1.6 million) deal with one of Britain's biggest record companies and a 250,000 pound contract with global pop music television station MTV.</p>
<p>The deal is unheard of in the world of British literature, where poets are still thought of as living in garrets, scraping a living from a lonely trade conjuring up pictures in the mind.</p>
<p>Young, however, is one of the new breed of &quot;performance poets&quot;, who declaims his contemporary verse to the sounds of a solo cello, seaside music or rock groups.</p>
<p>The EMI record company says it has never signed up a poet before but is hoping for sales of Young's album &quot;Vice and Verse&quot; of about one million copies.</p>
<p>&quot;Taking on a new young artist is always a risk but we think he is a brilliant poet, a brilliant performer and very, very funny,&quot; said Tony Harlow, EMI marketing director.</p>
<p>&quot;He's three-dimensional. We could have sold him as a performer, as a stand-up comic or as a poet,&quot; Harlow said.</p>
<p>Young's subject matter is perfectly attuned to the 1990s. One verse is about the Rolling Stones, another titled &quot;Casual Sex&quot;, and in &quot;Simply Everyone's Taking Cocaine&quot; he satirises high society drugs culture.</p>
<p>&quot;Well I saw Aunt Milly in last season's clothes,</p>
<p>She said car, house and yacht had gone straight up her nose.....</p>
<p>Simply everyone's taking cocaine.&quot;</p>
<p>He anounces his &quot;MTV collection&quot; of short verses aimed at the youth market as &quot;no longer than 30 seconds, with no big words.&quot;</p>
<p>APPEARANCE AT EDINBURGH FRINGE</p>
<p>Staged to dramatic lighting and sound effects from a cello, Young is going down well with audiences at the Edinburgh Festival Fringe before he embarks on a series of &quot;performance tours&quot; in Britain and the United States.</p>
<p>Fellow poets and some critics have not been so kind.</p>
<p>The Financial Times called his work &quot;puerile&quot;. Guardian newspaper critic Dan Glaister said his poetry failed to challenge the mind.</p>
<p>&quot;It is comforting, reaffirming stuff but there are no broader truths lurking beneath the whimsy,&quot; wrote Glaister.</p>
<p>Established poets are sceptical, if not jealous, of the hype that has seen Young propelled from near obscurity to the front pages of newspapers and magazines.</p>
<p>&quot;For a new poet to land deals like this is unheard of. Much of it may be to do with marketing and hype and my instinct is to disapprove of the whole thing,&quot; said Peter Thorpe editor of the Poetry Review.</p>
<p>Young, in performance as passionate and brooding as any self-respecting romantic poet should be, rejects the notion that he is all hype.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm trying to get an audience for poetry,&quot; he said. &quot;Too often people who write poetry seem like they are divulging some terrible secret or slipping you something when you are depressed.</p>
<p>&quot;If you can show people interesting poems performed in a dynamic way then they might move on to Blake,&quot; Young said.</p>
<p>But he is keenly aware of the pitfalls ahead of him. In a satirical poem written a year ago about another of Britain's much talked about artists -- Damien Hirst of dead sheep in glass boxes fame -- Young may unwittingly have written his own epitaph.</p>
<p>&quot;Whatever you do, whatever you are,</p>
<p>Make sure that you never, never, never believe in your own PR.&quot;</p>
<p>($ = 0.633 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34520">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="EDINBURGH"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
