<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800894" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: Princess Diana seeks to quash marriage speculation.</title>
<headline>Princess Diana seeks to quash marriage speculation.</headline>
<byline>Paul Majendie</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Britain's Princess Diana has sought to quash fevered press speculation that her romance with film producer Dodi Al Fayed is to be accompanied by the sound of wedding bells.</p>
<p>&quot;I haven't taken such a long time to get out of a bad marriage to get into another one,&quot; she was quoted as saying by The Daily Mail as Thursday's tabloids once more gave the romance front-page billing.</p>
<p>Diana and the son of Harrods store magnate Mohamed Al Fayed have been on two Mediterranean holidays together in the past month and blurred paparazzi photos of them embracing have sent interest in her love life soaring.</p>
<p>But The Daily Mail said any talk of marriage was premature. It quoted one of Diana's friends as saying: &quot;She has enjoyed the summer but anyone who thinks there is marriage on the cards is mistaken.&quot;</p>
<p>Another friend said: &quot;She has discovered life in the fast lane and is enjoying it. All the Fayed toys, the plane, the yachts, the house are hers and she loves it. But it doesn't mean she is about to marry Dodi.&quot;</p>
<p>Opinion polls show the popularity of Britain's monarchy has plummeted with the bitter divorce between Diana and heir-to-the-throne Prince Charles and the breakup between Prince Andrew and the Duchess of York.</p>
<p>But this has not halted the insatiable appetite of tabloid readers for every twist and turn in what has been billed as the House of Windsor soap opera.</p>
<p>After reports that Diana had consulted a psychic over the new man in her life, tabloids promptly hired their own clairvoyants to forecast the future. The omens were not good.</p>
<p>Israeli psychic Uri Geller told The Mirror: &quot;I think their friendship will last a long time but I'm not sure if their love relationship will last.&quot;</p>
<p>Daphne, billed as America's top celebrity psychic and seer, said: &quot;They will go down a long road together but I don't feel that a marriage will be forthcoming.&quot;</p>
<p>Psychics consulted by The Sun were equally gloomy about Diana and Dodi's marriage prospects -- in sharp contrast to fashion consultants who said Diana's 15-year-old son, Prince William, had a future on the catwalk.</p>
<p>Shots of the handsome young teenager holidaying with his father in Scotland were given full marks for photogenic poise.</p>
<p>Foercasting that William could earn up to 10,000 pounds ($15,800) fronting an advertising campaign, Kate Hill of the Nevs model agency said: &quot;William has been lucky to inherit his mother's classic looks and posture.&quot;</p>
<p>Fiona McIntosh of Company magazine agreed: &quot;He must have got that accidentally-on-purpose caught on camera pose from Di. He certainly has her looks.&quot;</p>
<p>($ = 0.630 British Pounds)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
