<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800933" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: CALLS FOR NZ'S PETERS TO RESIGN IN WAKE OF REPORT.</title>
<headline>CALLS FOR NZ'S PETERS TO RESIGN IN WAKE OF REPORT.</headline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>New Zealand opposition parties on Thursday called on Treasurer Winston Peters to resign after the release of a tax commission report.</p>
<p>The inquiry, known as the &quot;winebox&quot; commission, found accusations by Peters against the heads of the Serious Fraud Office (SFO) and the Inland Revenue (IRD) to be unfounded.</p>
<p>&quot;The inquiry itself concludes that the consequences are that the allegations made against the corporates and individuals claiming they were guilty of conspiring to commit such frauds were false and completely unjustified,&quot; Labour's finance spokesman Michael Cullen said in a speech applauded by several backbenchers of the ruling National Party.</p>
<p>&quot;This report goes to the very heart of the credibility of (the Treasurer),&quot; Cullen said.</p>
<p>&quot;We are now into banana republic territory in this regard. We have a head of (our) economy and finances that a judge has concluded is false and completely without justification in terms of the accusations that he makes,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Cullen said Peters should resign, apologise to the former heads of the SFO (Charles Sturt), and the IRD (David Henry), and seek compensation for them for being driven from office by his accusations, made in parliament under privilege rules.  </p>
<p>&quot;The Treasurer has three very simple things to do this afternoon. The first is to resign.</p>
<p>&quot;He cannot demand of colleagues that they go, and then not go himself when he is found guilty of much more serious offences. Leadership starts at the top not at the bottom and he must go, he must resign.</p>
<p>&quot;Secondly he must offer an utter and complete and unqualified apology particularly to David Henry and Charles Sturt,&quot; Cullen said.  </p>
<p>&quot;Finally...he must ask for compensation for those two people in particular because they are owed compensation because if he had said outside this house a fraction of what he said inside it, even with some evidence, he would be paying a lot of compensation now.&quot;</p>
<p>The bulk of Peters' allegations, made in the context of the tax deals put under the microscope in Sir Ronald Davison's study, related to the way the government enforcement agencies tackled corporate tax reduction tactics used in the mid to late 1980s.  </p>
<p>Laws have since been tightened significantly, and the publicity generated by the long-running winebox issue is seen by economic observers as one of the main drivers behind a change in attitudes among many corporations to tax matters.</p>
<p>--Wellington newsroom (64 4) 473 4746; Fax (64 4) 473 6212</p>
<p>e-mail wellington.newsroom@reuters.com</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
