<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800947" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>AUSTRALIA: Australia's Howard takes historic gamble.</title>
<headline>Australia's Howard takes historic gamble.</headline>
<byline>Terry Friel</byline>
<dateline>CANBERRA 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Australia's conservative government, confronting falling popularity and mounting criticism over lack of leadership, is taking an historic political gamble with a campaign for sweeping tax reform.</p>
<p>Despite -- or perhaps because of -- their high tax rates, Australians are traditionally deeply suspicious of any moves to change taxes.</p>
<p>The last time Prime Minister John Howard's Liberal-National coalition campaigned on tax reform -- under another leader -- it was heavily punished by frightened voters and lost what was considered an unloseable election in 1993.</p>
<p>But Howard, who on Wednesday announced tax reforms would be drafted before the next election due by mid-1999, believes the public mood has changed.</p>
<p>Business and community groups have increasingly urged an overhaul for what is widely regarded as an outdated, complex and unfair system and polls show growing public support for change.</p>
<p>It also helps that Howard is promising a cut in personal income tax -- currently with a maximum rate near 50 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;There has been a change in mood,&quot; Howard said on Thursday.</p>
<p>&quot;I think the Australian public will vote for something that's better and fairer and which he or she believes will give Australia and particularly their children a better and more prosperous 21st century,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Howard said he is noncommittal on just what shape the reforms should take, beyond insisting on a new broad-based indirect tax.</p>
<p>It is widely believed that means a goods and services tax (GST) of about 15 percent on the purchase of almost all goods and services, replacing a raft of taxes of up to 100 percent levied haphazardly on a range of goods.</p>
<p>The tax push has been portrayed as a brave move by Howard, especially after the battering of 1993.</p>
<p>But commentators believe Howard, a traditionally cautious man, was forced by the government's and his own flagging performance into what may yet be the biggest gamble of his 23-year political career.</p>
<p>The past eight months has seen the government's poll lead over the Labor opposition plunge to less than six points from 12. At the same time Howard's own rating and public assessments of his leadership and performance have fallen to new lows.</p>
<p>Unemployment has remained stubbornly stuck at about 8.5 percent, undermining consumer confidence and restraining spending.</p>
<p>Business and industry, suffering in a sluggish economy with annual growth currently at just 2.4 percent, have been pressing Canberra for help.</p>
<p>Finally, the High Court threw the existing tax system into turmoil by outlawing a series of state and territory taxes that then had to be replaced by levies by the national government.</p>
<p>Political analysts felt Howard had to be seen doing something positive and constructive.</p>
<p>&quot;To those in the inner sanctum of Howard's office and to the most important ministers, the logical conclusion was that there was a bigger risk for Howard if he allowed the opportunity to pass,&quot; said Michael Gordon, political editor at the national daily, The Australian.</p>
<p>But Howard must now do more than convince voters on his vision for a better tax system into the next century.</p>
<p>The government does not have a majority in parliament's upper house, the Senate, and will need the support of minor parties, independents or Labor to pass its measures.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="AUSTR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="CANBERRA"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="AUSTRALIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
