<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800913" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>NEW ZEALAND: Marathon NZ fraud study ends, backfires on Peters.</title>
<headline>Marathon NZ fraud study ends, backfires on Peters.</headline>
<byline>Andrew Huddart</byline>
<dateline>WELLINGTON 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>A marathon inquiry into the handling of suspect corporate tax deals in New Zealand ended on Thursday by clearing most of the parties under scrutiny.</p>
<p>But the 1,000-page report of the so-called &quot;Winebox&quot; inquiry backfired on its flamboyant instigator, Deputy Prime Minister Winston Peters, who championed the fraud-busting cause.</p>
<p>In an angry parliamentary session, opposition leaders called for his resignation and for a formal apology to those officials Peters had accused of mishandling tax enforcement.</p>
<p>Prime Minister Jim Bolger stepped in to offer his apologies, but held back from supporting Peters' position.</p>
<p>As an MP, Peters propelled himself to national fame in the early 1990s by driving to the top of the political agenda the issue of corporate tax avoidance via the Cook Islands.</p>
<p>He tabled what had started as a wine box, or carton, full of documents before parliament in 1994. That initiated the inquiry, and he built on its success as he spearheaded a campaign for his nationalist New Zealand First party in last year's election.</p>
<p>On Thursday, after nearly three years of work, commissioner Sir Ron Davison said his investigations into Peters' allegations of conspiracy and fraud by two government agencies charged with stopping tax dodgers had drawn a blank.</p>
<p>&quot;There is simply no evidence at all of the existence of such a fraud as he alleged in any of the winebox transactions,&quot; Davison said, calling the task &quot;most frustrating&quot;.</p>
<p>Peters looked isolated when he defended his initiative in parliament after the report's release. Prime Minister Jim Bolger moved to a seat further away from his deputy during the speech, and some coalition backbenchers openly applauded opposition attacks on Peters.</p>
<p>Bolger told reporters later: &quot;We disagreed on this matter in the past, and it looks like we might have different views in the future&quot;.</p>
<p>But he insisted the coalition that links NZ First and his conservative National Party would not suffer, saying: &quot;I don't see this as going to damage the unity of the coalition.&quot;</p>
<p>Peters faced down calls for his resignation and for him to apologise to the two men whom he had repeatedly berated, under parliamentary privilege, for not doing their jobs properly.</p>
<p>The pair, former Serious Fraud Office director Charles Sturt and former commissioner of the Inland Revenue David Henry, have both left government service during the inquiry.</p>
<p>Speaking from the United States, Henry told TV One news: &quot;If Peters is a man of integrity he will now apologise to those people and to their families for the harm he has done them&quot;.</p>
<p>However, Peters said he had no intention to do so and would fight on to change the basic legal approach to tax-related transactions which he continued to believe was flawed.</p>
<p>Davison said that the transactions detailed in the winebox were only a few of the many tax reduction moves undertaken by banks, financial institutions and corporations throughout New Zealand during the latter part of the 1980s.</p>
<p>&quot;One might question the ethics of seeking to escape the impact of heavy taxation, but the realities were that tax was regarded as a cost of doing business and something to be minimised to the extent possible within the letter of the law.&quot;</p>
<p>But he said, in making his allegations of fraud, Peters had &quot;grossly overplayed his hand&quot;. Peters' supporters say that without his crusade the substantial tightening of tax laws seen in recent years would not have happened.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="NZ">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WELLINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="NEW ZEALAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
