<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="800984" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: Japan may soon relax tight spending stance-traders.</title>
<headline>Japan may soon relax tight spending stance-traders.</headline>
<byline>Risa Maeda</byline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>The sluggishness of the recovery of Japan's economy has raised expectations that the government will soon give it a fiscal shot in the arm, senior bond traders and analysts said on Thursday.</p>
<p>The possibility of a change in the current ultra-tight fiscal stance as early as next month has been a key factor keeping long-term yen bond yields from falling from their current low levels of just above two percent, they said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is a chance Japan will take fiscal measures in the near future because months have passed without any significant economic progress,&quot; said Kazuto Uchida, chief strategist at Tokyo-Mitsubishi Securities.</p>
<p>The current policy mix of a decrease in fiscal spending and a loose grip in monetary policy was approaching a dead end, Uchida said.</p>
<p>If this went on, shrinking domestic demand would result in Japan relying more on exports for economic growth, causing a continued rise in its current account surplus and accompanying trade friction, particularly with the United States.</p>
<p>Japan may be pressed again to ensure its recovery is led by domestic demand when finance ministers and central bankers of the Group of Seven (G7) nations meet in late September and this could prompt the government into making a fiscal injection, he said.</p>
<p>Traders said that weakness in Japanese financial markets since August showed the government needs to ease constraints on fiscal policy that have been in place since April.</p>
<p>On Monday, the Nikkei stock index fell to 18,824.18, its lowest level since April 28.</p>
<p>The key 182nd 10-year Japanese government bond (JGB) yield stood at 2.075 percent by Thursday's close, just above the all-time low of 2.070 percent hit on August 4.</p>
<p>A rise in the national sales tax on April 1 and a decline in public-sector investment since then has hurt Japan's economic recovery more seriously than many expected. The failures of four major listed firms so far this year have also increased uncertainty over economic prospects, traders said.</p>
<p>Another burden on consumers will be added when a medical reform bill takes effect in September, they said. This will increase the share of costs borne by salaried people for treatment to 20 percent from 10 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;Japan should increase fiscal spending and shift the current low interest rate policy to a neutral one if it wants a recovery led by domestic demand,&quot; Uchida said.</p>
<p>The Bank of Japan (BOJ) has guided the key short-term market interest rate below its record-low 0.5 percent discount rate for almost two years in an effort prop up the economy by lightening financial institutions' fund-raising costs.</p>
<p>Hidetaka Kawakita, general manager of the Treasury and Capital Markets Department at Nippon Life Insurance Co, said Japan would have to prevent further falls in long-term bond yields to avoid more trade friction.</p>
<p>&quot;Further falls in long-term interest rates would accelerate a flow of funds abroad and the yen's fall against the dollar. I think Japan would rather take fiscal measures to prevent this than have to deal with trade friction,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>Other factors keeping long-term interest rates from falling include lack of investor enthusiasm for low-coupon Japanese government bonds (JGBs) and the possibility Japan's recovery will become more solid towards the year-end, traders said.</p>
<p>But they said a rebound in JGB yields was unlikely because the BOJ was unlikely to raise the discount rate soon.</p>
<p>Nippon Life's Kawakita said he does not expect a discount rate rise before next March. Even so, he added, holding say 2.4 percent 10-year JGBs until maturity was still unattractive as nobody could guarantee zero inflation in the next 10 years.</p>
<p>&quot;The current long-term interest rates are justified by the low profit margins of only a limited number of companies -- i.e. small-sized companies and non-manufacturers,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>&quot;A rise to three percent from the current two would result in the failure of more debt-ridden firms. But I don't think it's right for Japan to continue its system of promoting all industries at once as that hinders ongoing restructuring efforts.&quot;</p>
<p>Traders said it was possible the benchmark 10-year JGB yield would rise as high as 2.5 percent by September despite gloomy economic indicators so far this quarter.</p>
<p>&quot;An unexpected factor like an increase in government fiscal spending, or strong results in September's tankan could boost the key 182nd JGB yield as high as 2.5 percent,&quot; Kawakita said.</p>
<p>The BOJ is expected to release its next &quot;tankan&quot; survey of corporate sentiment in late September.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
