<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="801033" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>CHINA: SHANGHAI COPPER ENDS MOSTLY UP IN SLOW TRADING.</title>
<headline>SHANGHAI COPPER ENDS MOSTLY UP IN SLOW TRADING.</headline>
<dateline>SHANGHAI 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Shanghai copper futures ended mostly higher in slow trade on Thursday on speculative buying by retail investors.</p>
<p>But many institutions were sidelined as copper on the London Metal Exchange (LME) hovered between $2,250 and $2,300, traders said.</p>
<p>The LME copper hovered between just under $2,300 and just above $2,260, remaining well within its well-worn range on Wednesday. Business in the last three months was at $2,290 a tonne, up $12 from Tuesday.  </p>
<p>In Shanghai, the most actively traded December 1997 contract ended at 21,250 yuan ($2,563) per tonne, rising 40 yuan. It opened at 21,250 yuan, hitting an intraday high of 21,300 and a low of 21,230.</p>
<p>August rose 40 yuan to 20,790, September 10 to 20,900, October 30 to 21,180, November 20 to 21,250 and the January 1997 contract was unchanged at 21,250.</p>
<p>Combined volume fell to 12,090 tonnes from 25,870.</p>
<p>Copper opened slightly higher and moved in a very narrow range for most of the session.  </p>
<p>Traders said many investors remained on the sidelines due to a lack of market-moving news.</p>
<p>&quot;Speculative buying from retail investors was responsible for today's gains but the short-term market trend is still unclear,&quot; one trader said.</p>
<p>&quot;Volume is thin, indicating most investors are waiting for clearer direction from the LME,&quot; he added.</p>
<p>In Shanghai, physical copper prices are around the 20,800 yuan level, little changed from Wednesday's close due to sluggishness on the futures market.  </p>
<p>Traders said copper was likely to continue moving in a narrow range in the short term if there was no market-moving news.</p>
<p>Aluminium ended mixed. August rose 80 to 14,600 yuan per tonne, September was unchanged at 14,750, October put on 180 to 15,000, November was unchanged at 14,980 and December was flat at 15,050.</p>
<p>Combined volume rose to 3,090 tonnes from 2,810.</p>
<p>($1.0 = 8.2893 yuan)</p>
<p>-- Shanghai Newsroom (86) 21-6279 7004; Fax 21-6279-7174</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CHINA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="SHANGHAI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CHINA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
