<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="801055" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>JAPAN: TOCOM PRECIOUS METALS, EXCEPT SILVER, END LOWER.</title>
<headline>TOCOM PRECIOUS METALS, EXCEPT SILVER, END LOWER.</headline>
<dateline>TOKYO 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Yen-based Tokyo precious metals futures except silver ended lower on Thursday, pressured by a firming of the yen against the dollar earlier in the day and lower spot prices after lacklustre trade due to Japan's Obon holidays, traders said.</p>
<p>Traders said Russia was selling some palladium in the spot market, contributing to a fall in platinum group metals (PGMs).</p>
<p>Palladium futures ranged from 15 yen to 39 yen per gram lower, with benchmark June ending down 20 at 678 yen.</p>
<p>Platinum prices ranged from 20 yen to 36 yen per gram lower. Benchmark June platinum was off 24 yen at 1,488 yen.  </p>
<p>&quot;I heard that Russia was offering relatively large amounts of palladium to sell in the spot Zurich market, which dented spot palladium prices,&quot; a trader at a trading house said.</p>
<p>In PGM futures, trade-house selling pushed down prices although early losses were curbed by late short-covering.</p>
<p>The traders said platinum group metals (PGMs) have been in a phase of a correction but added that they expect further price falls to be limited.</p>
<p>Good palladium demand and steady platinum demand in Japan mean the current tightness in the physical market is unlikely to ease in the near-term, they said.  </p>
<p>In gold futures, activity was mainly dominated by inter-month trade by trade houses with trade moving in line with the currency market, the traders said.</p>
<p>Gold futures ranged from seven yen to 10 yen per gram lower, with most-active benchmark June ending up 10 yen at 1,205 yen.</p>
<p>Spot gold was quoted at $327.00/50 per ounce at 0805 GMT, against $326.90/327.40 in New York on Wednesday. In the local bullion market, spot gold premiums remained low at around 30 U.S. cents per ounce over the world benchmark amid lacklustre gold demand in Japan.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="JAP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TOKYO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="JAPAN"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
