<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="801289" id="root" date="1997-08-14" xml:lang="en">
<title>TURKEY: FEATURE - Refined future for Turkey's gold bazaar.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Refined future for Turkey's gold bazaar.</headline>
<byline>Jon Hemming</byline>
<dateline>ISTANBUL 1997-08-14</dateline>
<text>
<p>Turkey's two-year-old gold exchange has wrought a total transformation of a trade once dominated by the Ottoman merchants of Istanbul's Grand Bazaar.</p>
<p>Success in liberalising gold imports has led to a futures market which opens on Friday and a refinery aimed at reworking gold stocks hoarded 'under mattresses' across the country.</p>
<p>The projects are considered vital to sustaining a sector given new life by the fledgling Istanbul Gold Exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;When the exchange started people talked a lot about mobilising gold kept under mattresses, but it didn't happen,&quot; said trader Murat Ali Oral of Sahin Doviz.</p>
<p>&quot;The main reason is the lack of a refinery. Without a refinery it's impossible to utilise this gold in the economy.&quot;</p>
<p>Turks are estimated to own some 6,000 tonnes of gold -- worth some $70 billion -- in the form of jewellery and coins.</p>
<p>The prospect of introducing some of this into the economy has whet the appetite of the exchange, which was initially intended to ease imports and so eliminate smuggling.</p>
<p>Turkey is said to have the world's third largest gold trading volume after Italy and India. It runs to an annual 250 tonnes, including scrap gold.</p>
<p>There is an estimated 750 tonnes of gold in Turkish shop windows alone and the acknowledged centre of the retail trade is the labyrinthine Grand Bazaar, a focus of trading since the 15th century.</p>
<p>REFUGE FROM CHRONIC INFLATION</p>
<p>Tourists who visit Turkey each summer add to the demand for gold, but this is usually driven by Turks buying gifts. Many hard-pressed citizens also use it as a safe haven from inflation, currently running at an annual rate of around 80 percent.</p>
<p>&quot;We sell to tourists. People are given gold when they get married, when they have a baby, but also they buy gold for saving and it goes under the mattress,&quot; said one merchant in the bazaar.</p>
<p>Before the liberalisation of gold imports, much demand was met by smuggling -- for years the main source of supply for merchants.</p>
<p>An attempt by the government in 1979 to force jewellers to keep a simple accounting system resulted in their closing up shop for 45 days in protest.</p>
<p>Central bank control of gold imports in the 1980s and the early 1990s did little to solve the problem, and no one really knows how much gold flowed into Turkey.</p>
<p>&quot;Before 1990 the amount of gold imported was simply 'X&quot; -- we don't know,&quot; said Kaan Aytogu, general secretary of the gold exchange.</p>
<p>Regulations controlling foreign trade in unprocessed gold were relaxed in March 1993 and at the same time, price setting was liberalised, allowing the price to be set by the market rather than the central bank. These changes cleared the way for the establishment of the exchange.</p>
<p>&quot;With the successful gold liberalisation policy started with the gold exchange, illegal gold importation is now economically unfeasible,&quot; Aytogu said.</p>
<p>Gold currently sells for just around 88 cents more per ounce in Turkey than the prevailing price on the world market.</p>
<p>REFINERY AND TRADING PLANS</p>
<p>The gold trade is also due to be given a boost by the gold refinery, currently under construction, which is expected to handle 400 tonnes of the metal each year, Aytogu said. The operation should begin operations by the end of 1998 if all goes according to plan and the impact should be felt after that.</p>
<p>More immediately, the futures market being launched on Friday should revitalise trading.</p>
<p>&quot;The big help of the Istanbul Gold Exchange has been the deregulation of the physical market for gold. For it to move on now, we must look to new projects, namely the futures market,&quot; said Mert Yazicioglu of Koc Bank.</p>
<p>The gold exchange hopes the futures market will pave the way for the use of the metal as an investment tool -- a hedge against inflation and lira depreciation -- as well as increased volume in the domestic gold market.</p>
<p>Industry analysts agree the futures market is a logical step which will have long-term benefits for Turkish gold trading. But they warn domestic investors unfamiliar with futures to be wary of the pitfalls.</p>
<p>&quot;I think within six months the futures volume will be higher than on the physical market, if there are no huge losses for investors,&quot; Yazicioglu said.</p>
<p>&quot;(But) they might enter the futures market for speculation, not for hedging. This mentality may cause huge losses.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="TURK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="M14">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="M142">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
  <code code="MCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-14"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-14"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ISTANBUL"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="TURKEY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
