<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804446" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>UK: FEATURE - Brain vs. brawn in first Mind Olympics.</title>
<headline>FEATURE - Brain vs. brawn in first Mind Olympics.</headline>
<byline>Scott McCormack</byline>
<dateline>LONDON 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The world of competitive sport faces a new breed of athlete, the mental gymnast, vying for gold at the first Mind Sports Olympiad, a week of brain games that opens in London on Monday.</p>
<p>Instead of slugging it out in the boxing ring or tumbling across padded floormats, competitors perform intellectual acrobatics in events ranging from speed reading to computer programming and crossword puzzles to the more traditional chess and draughts (checkers).</p>
<p>More than 1,500 people have signed up to take part in the Olympiad, which is open to anyone wanting to test his or her cranial capacity -- and spend a week playing games.</p>
<p>&quot;All these people are suddenly coming out and saying 'Yes, we love Scrabble, we think it helps the mind,'&quot; said organiser Tony Buzan without a hint of irony. &quot;People who do crosswords or jigsaws have somehow been made to think they were wasting their time. But this is really important stuff.&quot;</p>
<p>Although the organisers hope to promote the brain over the body, couch potatoes with nothing better to do than spend the day solving crosswords and watching television quiz shows will be unlikely to earn any Olympic laurels.</p>
<p>&quot;The top mental athletes are also extremely physically fit,&quot; Buzan said. &quot;There is a strong connection between the two.&quot;</p>
<p>The event was the brainchild of two chess grandmasters and Buzan, a British memory-guru and motivational speaker who has published 19 books on the power of the mind.</p>
<p>&quot;For thousands of years there have been physical championships...it seemed odd that the world had focused for so long on the body and not on the brain,&quot; said Buzan.</p>
<p>The Olympiad also pits men against women, billing itself as &quot;the first global intellectual battlefield&quot;.</p>
<p>FROM PHONE BOOKS TO FOOTBALL CARDS</p>
<p>Competitors in the events at London's Royal Festival Hall include the likes of Creighton Carvallo, a man who once memorised the infinite mathematical number pi -- the ratio of the circumference of a circle to its diameter -- to 20,013 decimal places.</p>
<p>Just getting that many digits out of his mouth in 1980 took the former psychiatric nurse nine hours and 10 minutes. The 52-year-old retired recently and now travels around the world practising his skills and showing off his cerebral prowess on television programmes.</p>
<p>Asked why he devoted so much time to committing digits to memory, Carvallo explained that he simply liked figures. &quot;I started memorising things when I was seven, at first football cards from bubble gum packets, and just keep getting better and better at it.&quot;</p>
<p>Aside from cramming his head full of sporting statistics and endless streams of decimals, Carvallo can recite by heart 5,000 telephone numbers from his home town Middlesbrough in northeast England, including all those beginning with the letter A and all the Smiths, perhaps the most common surname in Britain.</p>
<p>He is competing in the memory category, a two-day event that includes memorising 2,000 random digits in one hour, reciting poetry, matching names with faces, and learning binary computer code, a string of 1s and 0s.</p>
<p>But Carvallo remains undeterred by the prospect of stiff competition. &quot;I'm not nervous. I just love it,&quot; he said, adding that he won a world record last week when he memorised 12 random digits in 2 seconds.</p>
<p>BUT WHERE'S MY CAR PARKED?</p>
<p>Aside from the memory event, other categories include competitions for mental calculation, creative thinking, and IQ tests.</p>
<p>There are also things for diehard gameplayers, such as jigsaw puzzles, rummikub, mastermind, and stratego plus gin rummy, Chinese chess and more exotic, lesser-known games like Zatre and Dama.</p>
<p>Glory for the victors will not just be wearing a gold metal, but actually growing smarter while they probe the powers of the human mind.</p>
<p>&quot;The brain works as a muscle -- the harder you use it, the more it grows,&quot; proclaims a brochure for the competition, predicting that brain games would be the great growth area of the next millennium.</p>
<p>Buzan, a trained psychologist who advises the British Olympic rowing team, explained that taking part in thought-provoking pursuits actually increases brain capacity.</p>
<p>&quot;With hard mental training we can actually rewire our brains. It gets more sophisticated and the cells become more complex. It's pretty revolutionary,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>For the average person who occasionally forgets where he or she parked the car or put the keys, Buzan -- who says his IQ ranges from 150 to 200 depending on the day -- offered hope.</p>
<p>He said the first step to intellectual improvement was to turn the brain into a hobby. Asked what that meant, he replied: &quot;Anyone who doesn't understand the brain asks that question. It means opening your mind like a child or an artist, improving your ability to imagine and sense things.&quot;</p>
<p>Referring to the car dilemma, Buzan asked: &quot;How could you possibly lose a three tonne object? Because you didn't imagine it, associate it with the environment. You have to find connections, learn to link things together.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="UK">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LONDON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="UK"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
