<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804469" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>CANADA: Dodi's double serving time in Toronto jail.</title>
<headline>Dodi's double serving time in Toronto jail.</headline>
<dateline>TORONTO 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A con artist known for posing as Dodi Al Fayed, the movie producer rumored to be romantically linked to Princess Diana, is locked up in a Canadian jail, a Canadian penitentiary spokesman said on Sunday.</p>
<p>Mohamed Yehia Saed, born in 1949, was sentenced to two years in prison on June 17 for impersonating fellow Egyptian Al Fayed, the Toronto Sun newspaper reported at the time.</p>
<p>Al Fayed has been romantically linked -- through blurry photographs -- with Prince Diana, who was last year divorced from the heir to the British throne, Prince Charles.</p>
<p>Al Fayed is the son of tycoon Mohamed Al Fayed who owns the famous Harrods department store in London. The younger Al Fayed has produced several films, including &quot;Chariots of Fire,&quot; &quot;F/X&quot; and &quot;Hook.&quot;</p>
<p>Saed, a former merchant sailor, wooed lovely women, borrowed thousands of dollars and impressed the Egyptian community in Toronto and other Canadian cities with his lavish lifestyle and claims of contacts with Hollywood stars, the Toronto Sun said.</p>
<p>By the time he was caught in Montreal in November 1996, Saed had already been arrested in Orlando, Florida, in 1990, the Toronto Sun said. There he served about two years of a three-year sentence for fraudulently racking up tens of thousands of dollars in bills while impersonating the senior Al Fayed.</p>
<p>Saed began posing as the senior Al Fayed sometime in 1988, running up hotel, restaurant and car rental bills in the United States, the Toronto Sun said.</p>
<p>While in Canada he posed as the younger Al Fayed and wined and dined many people, including the Egyptian ambassador to Canada and the brother of former Egyptian Prime Minister Gamal Abdel Nasser. He also gained Canadian citizenship, the Toronto Sun said.</p>
<p>The well-dressed Saed paid for expensive dinners, always had an entourage including a bodyguard, and persuaded his girlfriends and others to loan him money and pay some of his condo and limousine bills, the Toronto Sun said.</p>
<p>He received royal treatment from Toronto's Pantages Theater which showcases the musical The Phantom of the Opera, and befriended some of the show's stars.</p>
<p>Late last year one of Saed's business contacts became suspicious after Saed asked for a loan, and called Harrods. The younger Al Fayed himself traveled to Toronto in March to testify against the con artist, the Toronto Sun said.</p>
<p>At that time, Al Fayed told the Toronto Sun, &quot;This has been horrible for my family... Great damage has been done to our name and reputation and also to others. We are trying to repair that damage.&quot;</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CANA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCRIM">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="TORONTO"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CANADA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
