<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804503" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>CROATIA: Ivana Trump to invest in Croatian tourism.</title>
<headline>Ivana Trump to invest in Croatian tourism.</headline>
<dateline>ZAGREB 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Ivana Trump, Czech-born former wife of American billionaire property tycoon Donald Trump, plans to pour money into the Croatian tourism industry, she said on a weekend visit to the Adriatic coast.</p>
<p>&quot;Croatia has a vast tourist potential,&quot; Trump was quoted in Sunday's Vjesnik newspaper as telling local leaders and tourist board representatives in the ancient walled city of Dubrovnik.</p>
<p>&quot;The motive for my visit to Dubrovnik is strictly business. I am interested in investing in hotels, casinos, restaurants or night clubs,&quot; said Trump.</p>
<p>Croatia boasts a long, scenic coastline scattered with wooded islands but infrastructure is run-down. Tourism slumped in 1991 when war broke out in former Yugoslavia and many hotels on the coast were used to house refugees.</p>
<p>Trump planned to visit the island of Rab on Sunday and said the trip would be &quot;strictly business&quot;.</p>
<p>The 48-year-old former fashion model and Olympic skier received more than $50 million in a bitter divorce settlement from Donald Trump in 1990 after his highly publicised affair with former beauty contestant Marla Maples.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="CRTIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GTOUR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="ZAGREB"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="CROATIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
