<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804591" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>THAILAND: Thai shoppers sampling IMF economic medicine.</title>
<headline>Thai shoppers sampling IMF economic medicine.</headline>
<dateline>BANGKOK 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Thais were waking up to a sense of new economic reality as the first austerity measure under a new International Monetary Fund-sposored plan saw prices jump due to a value added tax increase over the weekend.</p>
<p>VAT rose to 10 percent from seven percent, sending prices of most goods, other than exempted fresh foods, higher from Saturday.</p>
<p>The increase had sparked a surge in consumer spending last week with some shops reporting 20 percent rise in sales over the week before as shoppers stocked up ahead of the tax increase.</p>
<p>Business in malls and shops had returned to normal over the weekend, managers and shop workers said.</p>
<p>&quot;It's not busy now. I think a lot of people are staying at home more because the economy is not good,&quot; said an assistant at an empty clothing outlet in an upmarket mall in Bangkok.</p>
<p>After years of heady growth and conspicious consumption by many affluent Thais, local media have begun listing money saving ideas as household budgets tighten to meet the new reality.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't normally come to this mall but the prices are a bit cheaper here and I think people are looking more for that now,&quot; said one young woman.</p>
<p>The increased VAT levy should bring an additional 66 billon baht into government coffers, and along with a 57 billion baht ($1.8 billion) budget cut, is among the first of austerity measures expected to be adopted to secure about $16 billion in IMF organised funding to help prop up the creaking economy.</p>
<p>Thailand is facing its severest economic crisis for decades.</p>
<p>Slowing economic growth last year, a slump in exports, investment in unproductive sectors and recent currency instability have eroded investor confidence in an economy which had become heavily reliant of foreign investment.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="THAIL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E12">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BANGKOK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="THAILAND"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
