<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804689" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Sprint to sponsor Rolling Stones tour says source.</title>
<headline>Sprint to sponsor Rolling Stones tour says source.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK</dateline>
<text>
<p>Sprint Corp. will announce Monday that it is the sole sponsor of an upcoming concert tour by the Rolling Stones, according to a source close to the deal.</p>
<p>Details of the sponsorship were not immediately available, but Sprint Chairman William Esrey was scheduled to appear with the legendary rockers for a splashy event at a stage set up under the Brooklyn Bridge.</p>
<p>Speculation of a Rolling Stones world tour has been rife although no cities or dates have been announced. Published reports have said the tour would include 30 to 40 cities and begin Sept. 23 in Chicago.</p>
<p>Sprint and the Rolling Stones were reported in June to be in the final stages of negotiations on a $5 million to $6 million sponsorship deal.</p>
<p>According to the trade publication Brandweek, the plan under discussion at that time would give Sprint tie-in rights to the Stones' new album, and use of the band's name and likenesses, footage, tickets, hospitality, off-stage venue signage and merchandise.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I79020">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
