<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804691" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Stallone's &quot;Cop Land&quot; opens at top of U.S. box office.</title>
<headline>Stallone's &quot;Cop Land&quot; opens at top of U.S. box office.</headline>
<byline>Dean Goodman</byline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>The Sylvester Stallone police drama &quot;Cop Land&quot; captured the top spot at the weekend box office, while &quot;Air Force One&quot; and &quot;Conspiracy Theory&quot; were in hot pursuit, according to studio estimates released Sunday.</p>
<p>&quot;Cop Land&quot; earned about $13.0 million for the Friday-to-Sunday period, while &quot;Air Force One&quot; held steady in second with $12.6 million and last week's box office champ &quot;Conspiracy Theory&quot; slipped to third with $12.3 million.</p>
<p>Rounding out the top five were &quot;Event Horizon,&quot; a new science fiction horror release starring Laurence Fishburne and Sam Neill. It earned $9.5 million. &quot;Spawn&quot; and &quot;George of the Jungle&quot; each claimed fifth spot, reporting $5.1 million and $5.0 million, respectively. Final data will be released Monday.</p>
<p>Stallone, best known for playing gruff action heroes in big-budget films, turned down his regular $20 million pay check to star in &quot;Cop Land,&quot; a relatively inexpensive movie about police corruption in a small town.</p>
<p>In the film, he plays a slow-witted sheriff opposite Robert De Niro, Harvey Keitel and Ray Liotta. The movie was released by Miramax Films, a unit of Walt Disney Co..</p>
<p>The movie sets a new Miramax record for an opening weekend. The previous record was held by &quot;Pulp Fiction,&quot; which opened to a reported $9.3 million in October 1994.</p>
<p>&quot;This is fantasy time come true,&quot; said Mark Gill, Miramax's president of marketing. &quot;It's very, very nice.&quot;</p>
<p>He said in an interview the film attracted a &quot;bizarre combination&quot; of young action fans as well as discerning moviegoers looking for a &quot;smart, intelligent Miramax film.&quot;</p>
<p>&quot;Cop Land&quot; averaged $5,822 from 2,233 screens, the highest average in the top 10. Still, the average paled against those for recent previous number ones such as &quot;Conspiracy Theory,&quot; &quot;Air Force One&quot; and &quot;Men in Black.&quot;</p>
<p>Critics were generally favorable towards the movie, which represents the second feature for writer/director James Mangold. According to a Variety poll of reviewers in New York, Los Angeles, Chicago and Washington DC, 20 critics liked it, 10 did not and 15 were mixed.</p>
<p>In its fourth weekend, Harrison Ford's &quot;Air Force One&quot; exhibited strong staying power as its gross slipped just 29 percent from last weekend. The 24-day total stands at $130.6 million. The film is released by Columbia Pictures, a unit of Sony Corp..</p>
<p>&quot;Conspiracy Theory&quot; fell 36 percent in its second weekend, as its 10-day total rose to $47 million. The Mel Gibson/Julia Roberts thriller is released by Warner Bros., a unit of Time Warner Inc..</p>
<p>&quot;Event Horizon&quot; averaged a modest $4,111 per screen from its first three days. According to Wayne Lewellen, president of distribution at Paramount Pictures, which released the film, the $9.5 million gross was above expectations. He said it was difficult to make the film stand out above pictures such as &quot;Men in Black,&quot; &quot;Spawn&quot; and the upcoming &quot;Mimic,&quot; all of which are targeted at the young male action crowd. Paramount is a unit of Viacom Inc..</p>
<p>According to Variety, just two critics liked &quot;Event Horizon,&quot; while 10 did not and 11 were mixed.</p>
<p>New Line Cinema and Disney each claimed fifth spot for their respective films &quot;Spawn&quot; and &quot;George of the Jungle,&quot; although New Line's figure was higher. New Line is a unit of Time Warner.</p>
<p>The one other major wide release was Warner Bros.' Shaquille O'Neal action film &quot;Steel,&quot; which opened well out of the top 10 with a paltry $900,000, or $714 average. It's the second consecutive flop for the basketball player, after last year's &quot;Kazaam,&quot; in which he played a genie.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:industries:1.0">
  <code code="I34540">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I83960">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97100">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="I97400">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="C31">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="CCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
