<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804721" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Fans end Elvis Presley fete with concert.</title>
<headline>Fans end Elvis Presley fete with concert.</headline>
<dateline>MEMPHIS, Tenn 1997-08-16</dateline>
<text>
<p>Elvis Presley fans from around the world ended a week-long observance of his death on Saturday with a pounding high-tech concert that did everything but bring the singer back to life.</p>
<p>For many of the several thousand who paid up to $80 a seat at the nearly sold-out event in the Mid-South Coliseum, it may have seemed that Presley was back, 20 years to the day after he died in Memphis. The crowd cheered, wept and rocked in their seats.</p>
<p>The show featured tapes of Presley in concerts, television shows and movies. Elvis's old TCB band with James Burton, Glen Hardin, Jerry Scheff and Ronnie Tutt, the entire Memphis Symphony, Scotty Moore, the Jordanaires, the Imperials and other musicians and vocalists backed up the singer live on stage as his image -- and sometimes their own at a younger age -- cavorted on a towering screen above them.</p>
<p>Elvis even &quot;entered&quot; the hall to a sweeping spotlight, smoke, swirlng lights and the music of &quot;Also Spracht Zarathustra,&quot; the theme from &quot;2001: A Space Odyssey&quot; that traditionally signaled his arrival at concert venues. Many in the audience stood looking for him.</p>
<p>The crowd seemed not to notice, or maybe care, that through the course of more than two dozen songs his costume changed several times, not to mention his haircut and girth. Organizers said it was the largest reunion ever of musicians and vocalists who had performed with Presley during his lifetime.</p>
<p>When the Jordanaires and the Imperials alternated verses with Presley on &quot;How Great Thou Art,&quot; the hall became a southern church meeting. Presley even &quot;introduced&quot; J.D. Sumner and The Stamps to sing a spritual, &quot;Sweet, Sweet Spirit.&quot;</p>
<p>Outside the hall the public address system made a string of announcements in French, German and other languages to guide the heavily international contingent of fans to the proper doorways. Inside, flash bulbs popped incessantly during the show. In the lobby some fans even rented binoculars.</p>
<p>Organizers said matching the live music and vocals to the taped Elvis was not that difficult given that many on the stage had performed with him before his death of a drug-related heart attack at age 42.</p>
<p>Master of ceremonies Wink Martindale said the show captured Presley at his happiest -- on stage and peforming. His fans, many of whom had taken part in an all-night vigil at his grave the evening before, appeared equally happy.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-16"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="MEMPHIS, Tenn"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
