<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804720" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Soros gives $1 million for needles for U.S. addicts.</title>
<headline>Soros gives $1 million for needles for U.S. addicts.</headline>
<dateline>NEW YORK 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A New York philanthropist plans to spend $1 million on sterile syringes to be given to drug addicts at risk of contracting AIDS and other diseases, a newspaper reported on Sunday.</p>
<p>Financier George Soros told the New York Times in an interview published on Sunday that he believes his contribution will &quot;save the most lives&quot; of all his philanthropic donations.</p>
<p>&quot;Probably of all the money that we spend on various projects, this is the one that is actually going to save the most lives,&quot; said the Hungarian-born Soros who immigrated to the United States over 40 years ago.</p>
<p>The article said Soros has spent close to $20 million in an attempt to change how Americans look at illegal drugs.</p>
<p>In 1996 Soros contributed $1 million in California and Arizona to finance voter approval of marijuana for medicinal use, the Times said.</p>
<p>The newspaper said Soros does not support making drugs legal but believes banning their use is impossible. Soros said it is more realistic to reduce the harm that drug users cause themselves.</p>
<p>Soros also told the Times he has experimented with marijuana and has misgivings about making it legal because marijuana impairs motivation and performance of children in school.</p>
<p>&quot;I don't have an answer to the drug problem. I think we need to explore different ways of dealing with it, and I think that which we are doing now is doing more harm than good,&quot; Soros said.</p>
<p>The $1 million needle exchange gift is being made through the Tides Foundation in San Francisco, the paper said. The Foundation matches philanthropic donors with requests for financial support in the field of social change.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GHEA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPRO">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW YORK"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
