<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804716" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Climate change deal may rise from political muck.</title>
<headline>Climate change deal may rise from political muck.</headline>
<byline>Vicki Allen</byline>
<dateline>WASHINGTON 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>A deal to fight global warming could emerge from the mire of international squabbling and finger-pointing by the time talks aimed at reducing heat-trapping pollution end in December, experts say.</p>
<p>But they say the United States is escalating risks of failure by not putting its key negotiating demands on the table until shortly before the talks are to end.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we've slowed down the whole process and we have a very difficult political decision to be made within the government,&quot; Christopher Flavin, of the Worldwatch Institute, said. &quot;I believe the Clinton administration has been a bit derelict in being so late.&quot;</p>
<p>A lack of tangible progress at recent negotiations in Bonn and the United States' tardiness in setting its goals for cutting fuel emissions have some industry groups hoping the talks' final session in December in Kyoto, Japan, will produce little more than an agreement for countries to keep talking.</p>
<p>&quot;I suspect they're going to announce a deal, but I think it will be a deal to meet again,&quot; Harvey Alter, manager of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce's Resources Policy Department, said.</p>
<p>Energy-dependent industries such as automobiles, metals, and oil and coal companies contend that forcing sharp cuts in fuel emissions would derail the economy, push industries and jobs to developing countries without stiff pollution limits, and change the car-dependent American lifestyle.</p>
<p>But most environmentalists contend that pollution can be cut without dire consequences. And they say world leaders, including President Bill Clinton, have put enough political prestige at stake to almost guarantee some kind of deal.</p>
<p>&quot;I would think there is enough political pressure on countries to have some kind of positive outcome in Kyoto. Japan, as the host country would want to save face and do its part to see that Kyoto doesn't just turn into a mandate&quot; to keep negotiating, Benjamin DeAngelo, a research fellow with the Natural Resources Defense Council, said.</p>
<p>Clinton, who took a bruising from European leaders in June at summits on the economy and on the environment, has pledged to muster support for fighting climate change.</p>
<p>At those summits, European leaders blamed Clinton for not agreeing to the their ambitious goal for cutting pollution. But administration officials have said the European goal was unrealistic and largely in Europe's own interest.</p>
<p>Clinton will hold a conference on global warming in early October to try to build public interest on the issue, and then will announce the targets and timeframe for emissions cuts the United States will seek, White House officials have said.</p>
<p>&quot;It is up to Bill Clinton to decide whether we curb global warming to protect our children's future or whether he is the president who looks global warming in the eye and blinks,&quot; Dan Becker, of the Sierra Club, said. &quot;The United States is going to determine what this thing is.&quot;</p>
<p>Becker and others said that whatever plan the United States puts forward will dictate the parameters of any eventual international accord.</p>
<p>But producing this plan so late in the talks may not leave enough time for countries to work out differences and get a firm deal in December, some said.</p>
<p>In addition to disputes over specific targets for cutting pollution are potentially wider gulfs over how much responsiblity developing countries should have to curb emissions, and how to implement and enforce a pact.</p>
<p>&quot;Because of the new 'structure first, targets last' dynamic established by the United States, the Kyoto Protocal is seriously in jeopardy. It has become abundantly clear that it will be logistically impossible to sort out the structural details that the U.S. insists must be in the text of the Protocal in four months,&quot; Kelly Sims, of Ozone Action, said in a report after the recent Bonn session.</p>
<p>&quot;A likely scenario will be that countries agree in principle to some of the structural elements and promise to sort out the details over the next few years,&quot; Sims, of the environmental group, said.</p>
<p>&quot;There will be a deal. The deal will have vague, amorphous, hard to characterize requirements,&quot; Fred Smith, president of the pro-business Competitive Enterprise Institute, said.</p>
<p>Smith, who disputes whether damaging man-made climate changes will occur, said industries appear to have blown their chance to stave off a global warming agreement.</p>
<p>By backing a Senate resolution that acknowledged that pollution is changing the world's climate with potentially harmful results, he said industries &quot;have given up the moral high ground and the scientific high ground.&quot;</p>
<p>But Alter, from the Chamber of Commerce, said the  resolution was important because it showed that the Senate only would approve a treaty that also forced developing countries to limit pollution, which he said should help protect the United States from job losses.</p>
<p>The non-binding resolution last month passed 95-0 in the Senate, the body which will decide whether to ratify a global warming treaty that the administration brings home.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="WASHINGTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
