<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804705" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Containment begins of wildfire near Los Angeles.</title>
<headline>Containment begins of wildfire near Los Angeles.</headline>
<dateline>LOS ANGELES 1997-08-15</dateline>
<text>
<p>Firefighters gained the upper hand Sunday over a wildfire that consumed more than 10,000 acres of forest and threatened the small town of Wrightwood, about 60 miles east of Los Angeles.</p>
<p>The fire was 51 percent contained, a spokesman for the U.S. Forest Service said.</p>
<p>&quot;There is no estimate yet on full containment,&quot; said Jack Horner, chief information officer at the fire.</p>
<p>He said a sprinker system had been installed and was working well. Helicopters and air tankers continue to drop water on the fire in rugged, mountainous terrain, he said.</p>
<p>The fire was started by a camper burning toilet paper, and about 2,000 firefighters battled the blaze as it came within two miles of Wrightwood. But no houses were burned in the town, and the threat has diminished, Horner said.</p>
<p>Only five minor injuries, including heat exhaustion, smoke inhalation and a sprained ankle, have been reported, he said.</p>
<p>The Forest Service estimates the total cost of fighting the fire will be $18 million when it is finally extinguished.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GDIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENV">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-15"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="LOS ANGELES"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
