<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804704" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>USA: Wisconsin controller sees no budget until late Oct.</title>
<headline>Wisconsin controller sees no budget until late Oct.</headline>
<byline>Joan Gralla</byline>
<dateline>BOSTON 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Wisconsin controller Bill Raftery said Sunday he did not expect approval of the state's new two-year budget, which has been caught up in an internal squabble in the Senate, until late October.</p>
<p>&quot;My bet is Halloween,&quot; said Raftery in an interview with Reuters in Boston, where he was attending the National Association of State Auditors, Comptrollers and Treasurers conference.</p>
<p>Raftery expected little progress on the budget until after the Labor Day holiday, when officials return from summer vacations.</p>
<p>The Senate Democrats, who only have a one-vote majority, must then resolve a two-month dispute with Senator Gary George, a Milwaukee Democrat, who has raised questions about due process on budget and committee assignments.</p>
<p>The Senate leaders have the 16 other votes they need, but the house cannot approve a budget without George's 17th yes vote, Raftery said.</p>
<p>Then the budget bill has to go back to the Republican-led Assembly, and given the differences yet to be thrashed out, Raftery said he expected Gov Tommy Thompson to get a final budget around the end of September. The controller said it likely will take the Republican governor, who has a line-item veto, about a month to review the document.</p>
<p>Rating agencies have said delaying the new budget until September, when Thompson had hoped to start putting in place new policies to save money on welfare, might jeopardize that effort.</p>
<p>&quot;I think we can work it out. It will pose difficulties, obviously,&quot;said Raftery, explaining that filling positions for the new welfare programs might have to be postponed.</p>
<p>On other issues, Raftery said he could not predict whether Wisconsin would exceed its revenue targets in fiscal 1998, which began July 1, as it appears to have tidily done in fiscal 1997.</p>
<p>The books have not yet closed on fiscal 1997, but Moody's Investors Services said in a June report that Wisconsin got almost $240 million more in tax revenues than it predicted and spent $320 million less.</p>
<p>&quot;There's no reason to believe that our (fiscal 1998) forecasts aren't good forecasts because we are conservative ...,&quot; said Raftery. &quot;What the actual will be above forecasts, we just can't tell.&quot;</p>
<p>Rating agencies typically applaud conservative forecasting and have been fairly upbeat about Wisconsin's economy. Standard and Poor's Corp, for example, in early June said the state leads the Midwest in jobs and income trends, adding that its strong economic performance should continue even though jobs growth was seen slipping to 1.4 percent through 1999.</p>
<p>Gov Thompson, who built up the undesignated surplus since he was elected in 1986, sharply reduced this sum from around $566 million in fiscal 1996 to about $139 million in fiscal 1997, according to Moody's. The undesignated surplus would slip a bit more in the new pact, hitting $129 million in 1998 and $98 million in 1999.</p>
<p>Asked whether this strategy posed risks, Raftery, who also served as Missouri's controller and was a partner in accounting firm KPMG Peat Marwick LLP, replied, &quot;The important thing is what our cash flows are going to be. Ours are predictable.&quot; He added that this was a fairly common way for states to use their undesignated surpluses.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="USA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BOSTON"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="USA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
