<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804735" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: German SPD welcomes coalition mini-tax reform idea.</title>
<headline>German SPD welcomes coalition mini-tax reform idea.</headline>
<byline>Douglas Busvine</byline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Germany's government floated new scaled-down tax reform proposals this weekend, drawing a guarded welcome from the opposition Social Democrats (SPD).</p>
<p>Leaders of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's coalition pulled back from Finance Minister Theo Waigel's original plan to slash 30 billion marks ($16.5 billion) in income and corporate taxes which was blocked by the SPD in parliament.</p>
<p>The news weekly Der Spiegel said Waigel was now working on a revenue-neutral measure, with a modest cut in the top rate of income tax to 48 or 49 percent from 53 percent now. Waigel had originally planned to slash the top tax bracket to 39 percent.</p>
<p>The entry rate of income tax would fall to 22 or 23 percent from 25.9 percent, compared to the 15 percent earlier foreseen.</p>
<p>Corporation tax would fall to 40 percent, up from earlier plans for a 35 percent rate, Spiegel, which hits news stands on Monday, quoted Finance Ministry officials as saying.</p>
<p>SPD leader Oskar Lafontaine gave a guarded welcome to the new coalition tax plans, but set conditions for fresh talks to break a deadlock stretching back to last winter.</p>
<p>&quot;It is good that the coalition is pulling its previous tax plans out of circulation. These plans were socially unjust and were not a sound basis for negotiations,&quot; Lafontaine told the daily Bild in an interview to be published on Monday.</p>
<p>Lafontaine said the tax reforms must make an average family 2,500 marks a year better off from 1998, and the government must agree a fully financed proposal for talks to make sense.</p>
<p>&quot;The coalition must now put a proposal on the table which has been agreed by the coalition parties and adds up,&quot; he said.</p>
<p>The shift in the government's position follows urging by the Bundesbank to get on with tax reforms to lead Germany out of its unemployment crisis and shore up falling tax revenues.</p>
<p>Waigel has pledged to meet the Maastricht treaty budget deficit goal of three percent of GDP this year, but Bundesbank council member Klaus-Dieter Kuehbacher has warned that revenues could fall 10 billion marks short of target this year.</p>
<p>Kohl also wants to get at least some tax cuts into law before a general election in September 1998. The SPD blocked the previous government tax plan in parliament's upper house.</p>
<p>&quot;Let's at least do part of the job,&quot; Kohl told ZDF TV in an interview to be aired later on Sunday.</p>
<p>The coalition's position on modified reforms has not yet been finalised, however, and a powerful Kohl aide was reported to have drafted a position paper with key differences to Waigel's new reform proposals.</p>
<p>Saturday's Berliner Zeitung said Wolfgang Schaeuble, parliamentary leader of Kohl's Christian Democrats (CDU), had proposed a new top-rate of income tax of 45 percent and an entry rate of 19 percent. Unlike Waigel's revenue-neutral plan, the Schaeuble draft foresees net tax cuts of 15 billion marks.</p>
<p>Still open is the question of raising Germany's 15 percent rate of value-added tax to help offset some of the cuts in direct taxation. A further one-point hike is already planned to pay for pensions reforms next year.</p>
<p>Hermann Otto Solms, tax negotiator for junior coalition partners the Free Democrats (FDP), said his party would go along with a VAT hike only if it financed the pensions reform.</p>
<p>Solms, speaking to the Bild am Sonntag newspaper, also said the FDP would not back down on its demand to cut the 7.5 percent solidarity income tax surcharge by two points in 1998.</p>
<p>&quot;Not just the FDP, but also the finance minister and chancellor support that,&quot; he said. ($ = 1.818 German Marks)</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
