<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804790" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>INDIA: India joins Pakistan in mourning singer's death.</title>
<headline>India joins Pakistan in mourning singer's death.</headline>
<dateline>NEW DELHI 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>India's media and performing artists on Sunday mourned the death of a Pakistani singer who symbolised close cultural relations between two nations usually in the news for diplomatic rows and the wars they have fought.</p>
<p>All leading newspapers carried front-page stories on the death on Saturday of Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan, who fused western rhythms into a mystic, classical style of chorus singing in the subcontinent, called &quot;qawwali&quot;.</p>
<p>&quot;It is very unfortunate that I could not sing for such a great music wizard,&quot; the Press Trust of India quoted the nation's best known playback singer, Lata Mangeshkar, as saying.</p>
<p>&quot;He not only composed tunes which were like a new breeze to Hindi film music but was a great singer himself,&quot; said Mangeskhar.</p>
<p>Khan, died at 49 of a heart attack arising from kidney problems in London one day after the 50th anniversary of secular but largely Hindu India's independence from British rule, which accompanied bloody inter-religious riots in 1947.</p>
<p>Islamic Pakistan, which has fought three wars with India, two of them over disputed Kashmir, marked its 50th anniversary on Thursday.</p>
<p>Khan often spoke of close cultural relations between the two nations, and his Sufi tradition of mystical music that preaches amity between religions.</p>
<p>&quot;He strove to unite the musical legacies of the two countries in the past many years,&quot; said an obituary in Indian Express, which carried Khan's death as its lead story.</p>
<p>&quot;It is not just Pakistan's loss, it is the subcontinent's loss, music's loss,&quot; Indian lyricist Javed Akhtar was quoted by Pioneer newspaper on Sunday as saying.</p>
<p>He dismissed unconfirmed media statements that Khan had made remarks critical of India. &quot;I don't believe a word of that,&quot; said Akhtar, who has worked with Khan.</p>
<p>India saw on its Independence Day the release of a movie, &quot;Aur Pyar Ho Gaya&quot; (And then there was love), for which Khan scored the music. Khan's music and the movie, starring former Miss World Aishwarya Rai, received rave reviews on Sunday.</p>
<p>Khan had also scored a highly successful score for another Indian movie, &quot;Bandit Queen,&quot; a biographical work about former woman bandit Phoolan Devi, who surrendered to police in 1983. Devi is now an Indian lawmaker for a low-caste party.</p>
<p>Khan, whose family had migrated to Pakistan from the town of Jullundur in India's Punjab state at Partition in 1947, also composed music for several foreign films including Hollywood's &quot;Last Temptation of Christ&quot;.</p>
<p>The portly singer, whose quivering, metallic voice enthralled millions, had also announced plans to record an experimental music album with opera singer Luciano Pavarotti, but health problems hit his plans.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="INDIA">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="PAKIS">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GDIP">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GENT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="NEW DELHI"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="INDIA"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
