<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804741" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: N. Europe's first camel races draw huge crowd.</title>
<headline>N. Europe's first camel races draw huge crowd.</headline>
<byline>Erik Kirschbaum</byline>
<dateline>BERLIN 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>More than 30,000 curious spectators turned out at a Berlin horse track on Sunday to watch 25 unpredictable camels take part in what the organisers said were the first camel races ever held in northern Europe.</p>
<p>Horse races they were not. Two camels sat down on the track in the middle of a warm-up lap and it took 15 minutes to get them moving again, while another stopped two metres from the finish and had to be prodded over the line by its jockey to win its race.</p>
<p>Nor could the crowd place bets. &quot;It's a shame we can't place any bets,&quot; said Werner Kiesling, a 63-year-old retired teacher. &quot;The camels would be ideal for bets because you never know what they are going to do in the middle of the race.&quot;</p>
<p>But, under a blue sky and in temperatures above 30 degrees centigrade (90F) that the camels probably enjoyed more than the spectators, the 400 kg (900 lb) animals delighted the crowd.</p>
<p>Trotting at between 25 and 50 km (15 to 30 mph) around the 2.4 km (1.5-mile) grass track, the camels ran in eight races carrying young German women as jockeys.</p>
<p>The camels live on Europe's only camel farm in the southern German town of Rotfelden.</p>
<p>&quot;They are such beautiful animals,&quot; said Monika Reineck, a 40-year-old office worker. &quot;This is a spectacle I just couldn't miss. They are so unpredictable. You never know what might happen. You have to have a good sense of humour to enjoy this.&quot;</p>
<p>The lead would change hands repeatedly during the one-lap races as camels would bolt forward with bursts of supercharged energy for short distances and then slow dramatically.</p>
<p>&quot;It was an incredibly fantastic feeling to ride in front of such a huge crowd,&quot; said Fritzi Pappel, who won one race, the German-Arabian Friendship Cup race.</p>
<p>Sponsored by the Berlin government to boost ties between Germany and the United Arab Emirates and run under the patronage of United Arab Emirates President Zayed bin Sultan al Nahayan, the races attracted three times the crowd that usually attend horse racing at the site.</p>
<p>German animal-lovers had called for a boycott of the races, arguing that camels are not suited to northern European terrain or climate.</p>
<p>Marion Stueve, a 52-year-old architect, and three friends bet among themselves, picking their camels after studying pictures of the animals printed in the programme.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GODD">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BERLIN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
