<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<newsitem itemid="804743" id="root" date="1997-08-17" xml:lang="en">
<title>GERMANY: Kohl wants cut in German payments to EU coffers.</title>
<headline>Kohl wants cut in German payments to EU coffers.</headline>
<dateline>BONN 1997-08-17</dateline>
<text>
<p>Chancellor Helmut Kohl said in an interview released on Sunday that Germany's payments to the European Union were too high and should be reduced.</p>
<p>&quot;The current payment level from Germany is too high, that's undisputed. And we must work to bring down this sum,&quot; Kohl said, according to a transcript of the interview with ZDF television recorded at his Austrian holiday home.</p>
<p>Asked if he would be able to push through a reduction in payments with Germany's EU partners, Kohl said: &quot;We must try, I'm not alone. But I've been able to push through many things. I hope very much that we move in this direction.&quot;</p>
<p>The size of Germany's contributons to the EU has leapt to the top of the political agenda over the past few months, with senior figures in all major parties complaining Bonn can not afford to pay the lion's share of the EU budget.</p>
<p>Finance Minister Theo Waigel said earlier this month that Germany, following unfication with its former communist east, was no longer wealthy enough to go on paying so much.</p>
<p>Kohl said Brussels must recognise the efforts of all EU states to make savings in their own budget and also appeared to hint it was time to cut down on money spent on EU bureaucracy.</p>
<p>&quot;I'm also not of the opinion that the Brussels apparatus can stay as it is now, in its dimensions,&quot; he told ZDF. &quot;That's nothing new. My colleagues know my opinion.&quot;</p>
<p>Germany, by far the largest contributor to EU coffers, will pay around 82 billion European currency units (around $88 billion) this year.</p>
<p>The issue of EU financing is next due to be discussed in 1999, when the bloc will have to work out a new formula to take account of planned enlargement to include new members.</p>
</text>
<copyright>(c) Reuters Limited 1997</copyright>
<metadata>
<codes class="bip:countries:1.0">
  <code code="EEC">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GFR">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<codes class="bip:topics:1.0">
  <code code="E21">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="E211">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="ECAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G15">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="G154">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GCAT">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
  <code code="GPOL">
    <editdetail attribution="Reuters BIP Coding Group" action="confirmed" date="1997-08-17"/>
  </code>
</codes>
<dc element="dc.date.created" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.publisher" value="Reuters Holdings Plc"/>
<dc element="dc.date.published" value="1997-08-17"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location" value="BONN"/>
<dc element="dc.creator.location.country.name" value="GERMANY"/>
<dc element="dc.source" value="Reuters"/>
</metadata>
</newsitem>
