<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Creüsa, Queen of Athens: A tragedy. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Drury-Lane by His Majesty's servants. Written by Mr. William Whitehead.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, William, 1715-1785.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K020910.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3310244664</idno>
            <idno type="ecll">0152601100</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Creüsa, Queen of Athens: A tragedy. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Drury-Lane by His Majesty's servants. Written by Mr. William Whitehead.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, William, 1715-1785.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8],77,[3]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for R. and J. Dodsley; and sold by M. Cooper,</publisher>
                  <date>1754.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K020910.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3310244664</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll">0152601100</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue of the 1754 edition with the titlepage corrected.</note>
                  <note>Based on Euripides' 'Ion'.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf of epilogue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT1555.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>CREÜSA, Queen of ATHENS.</p>
            <p>A TRAGEDY.</p>
            <p>As it is Acted at the Theatre Royal in <hi>Drury-lane</hi> By His MAJESTY's Servants.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN BY Mr. WILLIAM WHITEHEAD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for R. and J. DODSLEY in <hi>Pall-mall;</hi> and Sold by M. COOPER in <hi>Peter-noster-Row.</hi> 1754.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <sp>
               <stage>Spoken by Mr. ROSS.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>PROLOGUES of old, the Learn'd in Language say,</l>
                  <l>Were merely Introductions to the Play,</l>
                  <l>Spoken by Gods, or Ghosts, or Men who knew</l>
                  <l>Whate'er was previous to the Scenes in view;</l>
                  <l>And complaisantly came to lay before ye</l>
                  <l>The several Heads, and Windings of the Story.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But modern Times and <hi>British</hi> Rules are such,</l>
                  <l>Our Bards beforehand must not tell too much;</l>
                  <l>Nor dare we, like the neighb'ring <hi>French,</hi> admit</l>
                  <l>Ev'n Confidantes, who might instruct the Pit,</l>
                  <l>By asking Questions of the leading Few,</l>
                  <l>And hearing Secrets, which before they knew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet what we can to help this antique Piece</l>
                  <l>We will attempt.—Our Scene to-night is <hi>Greece.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, by the Magic of the Poet's Rod,</l>
                  <l>This Stage the Temple of the <hi>Delphic</hi> God!</l>
                  <l>Where Kings, and Chiefs, and Sages came of old,</l>
                  <l>Like modern Fools, to have their Fortunes told;</l>
                  <l>And Monarchs were enthron'd, or Nations freed,</l>
                  <l>As an old Priest, or wither'd Maid decreed.</l>
                  <l>Yet think not all were equally deceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Some knew, more doubted, many more believ'd.</l>
                  <l>In short, these Oracles, and witching Rhimes</l>
                  <l>Were but the pious Frauds of ancient Times;</l>
                  <l>Wisely contriv'd to keep Mankind in awe,</l>
                  <l>When Faith was Wonder, and Religion Law!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus much premis'd, to every feeling Breast</l>
                  <l>We leave the Scenes themselves to tell the rest.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>—Yet something sure was to the Critics said,</l>
                  <l>Which I forget,—some Invocation made!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ye Critic Bands, like jealous Guardians, plac'd</l>
                  <l>To watch th' Encroachments on the Realms of Taste,</l>
                  <l>From you our Author would two Boons obtain,</l>
                  <l>Not wholly diffident, nor wholly vain:</l>
                  <l>Two things he asks; 'tis modest sure, from you</l>
                  <l>Who can do all things, to request but two:</l>
                  <l>First to his Scenes a kind Attention pay,</l>
                  <l>Then judge!—with Candor judge—and we obey.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatispersonae">
            <pb facs="3"/>
            <head>Persons Represented.</head>
            <list>
               <item>XUTHUS, King of <hi>Athens,</hi> Mr. BERRY.</item>
               <item>ILYSSUS, an unknown Youth, At<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tendant on the Temple at <hi>Delphi,</hi> Miss MACKLIN.</item>
               <item>ALETES, a <hi>Grecian</hi> Sage, Mr. GARRICK.</item>
               <item>PHORBAS, an old <hi>Athenian,</hi> Mr. MOSSOP.</item>
               <item>Priests of <hi>Apollo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Citizens of <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CRĖU̇SA, Queen of <hi>Athens,</hi> Mrs. PRITCHARD.</item>
               <item>PYTHIA, Priestess of <hi>Apollo,</hi> Miss HAUGHTON.</item>
               <item>LYCEA, and other Women at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tending on the Queen, Mrs. COWPER, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Virgins belonging to the Temple.</item>
               <item>Guards, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Scene, the Vestibule of the Temple of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Del<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phi,</hi> and the Laurel Grove adjoining.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="4"/>
            <p>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE <hi>GEORGE BUSSY,</hi> Lord Visc. VILLIERS, The following TRAGEDY is inscribed by His Lordship's Most obliged and most affectionate humble Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. WHITEHEAD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>THE Subject of the following Scenes is so ancient, so slight<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly mentioned by Historians, and so fabulously treated by <hi>Euripides</hi> in his Tragedy of <hi>Ion,</hi> that the Author thought himself at liberty to make the Story his own. Some glaring Circumstances he was obliged to ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>here to, which he has endeavoured to render probable.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <head>CRĖU̇SA, Queen of ATHENS. A TRAGEDY.</head>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <head>ACT I. <hi>The Vestibule of the Temple.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>ILYSSUS <hi>and Virgins.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>HASTE, haste, ye Virgins; round the Columns twine</l>
               <l>Your flowery Chaplets; and with Streams fresh-drawn</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Castaly,</hi> bedew the sacred Porch</l>
               <l>Of the great God of Day. Already see</l>
               <l>His orient Beam has reach'd the double Top</l>
               <l>Of high <hi>Parnassus,</hi> and begins to shed</l>
               <l>A gleamy Lustre o'er the Laurel Grove!</l>
               <l>Haste, haste, ye Virgins. From the Vale beneath</l>
               <l>I hear the Noise of Chariots, and of Steeds</l>
               <l>Which hither bend their Course, for every Sound</l>
               <l>Seems nearer than the former.—And behold</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="7"/>A reverend Stranger, who perhaps proclaims</l>
               <l>Th' Approach of some great Monarch, to consult</l>
               <l>All-seeing <hi>Phoebus,</hi> or implore his Aid.</l>
               <l>Haste, haste, ye Virgins!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> PHORBAS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Tell me, gentle Maids,</l>
               <l>And thou, fair Youth, who seem'st to lead the Train,</l>
               <l>Is this the Temple of the <hi>Delphic</hi> God?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>It is; and on the middle Point of Earth</l>
               <l>Its firm Foundations by immortal Hands</l>
               <l>Stand fix'd:—but break we off; the folded Gates</l>
               <l>Unbar, and lo! the Priestess' self appears!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>The</hi> Pythia <hi>speaks as she descends from the Temple</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Hence, ye profane! nor with unhallow'd Step</l>
               <l>Pollute the Threshold of the <hi>Delian</hi> King</l>
               <l>Who slew the <hi>Python!</hi>—Say, from whence thou art,</l>
               <l>And what thy Business, Stranger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Sacred Maid!</l>
               <l>From <hi>Athens</hi> am I come, the Harbinger</l>
               <l>Of great <hi>Creusa,</hi> mine and <hi>Athens'</hi> Queen</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Comes she on pious Purpose, to adore</l>
               <l>The mystic Shrine oracular?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>She does;</l>
               <l>And with her comes the Partner of her Bed,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeolian Xuthus:</hi> he whose powerful Arm</l>
               <l>Sav'd <hi>Athens</hi> from her Fate, and in return</l>
               <l>From good <hi>Erectheus'</hi> bounteous Hand receiv'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="8"/>His Daughter and his Crown.—
<note place="bottom" n="†">
                     <hi>Half aside.</hi>
                  </note> Would he had found</l>
               <l>Some other Recompence!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <stage>Overhearing him.</stage>
               <l>Would he had found?</l>
               <l>Old Age is talkative, and I may learn</l>
               <l>Somewhat of moment from him.—Wherefore come they?</l>
               <l>Does Famine threaten, or wide-wasting Plague</l>
               <l>Infest the Land?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Thank Heaven, our crouded Streets</l>
               <l>Have felt no dire Disease; and Plenty still</l>
               <l>Laughs in our blooming Fields. Alas! I fear</l>
               <l>The childless Goddess who presides o'er <hi>Athens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has found a surer Method to declare</l>
               <l>How ill she brooks that any Stranger Hand</l>
               <l>Should wield th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Scepter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Does from her</l>
               <l>The Vengeance come?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS</speaker>
               <l>I know not whence it comes,</l>
               <l>But this I know, full fifteen Years have roll'd</l>
               <l>Since first their Hands were join'd, and roll'd in vain;</l>
               <l>For still the Royal Pair in Silence mourn,</l>
               <l>Curs'd with a barren Bed. For this they come,</l>
               <l>T'explore the latent Cause, and beg of Heav'n</l>
               <l>To grant an Heir, or teach them where to fix,</l>
               <l>On what selected Head, th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Crown.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>And Heaven, no doubt, will hear and grant their Prayer.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilssus,</hi> haste, and bid the Priests prepare</l>
               <l>For Sacrifice. You, <hi>Nysa,</hi> and your Sisters,</l>
               <l>Amid the Laurel Grove with Speed perform</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="9"/>The Morning's due Lustration.</l>
               <l>Then hither all return.—Myself mean while
<stage>Aside.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Will tempt the Vice of Age, and try to draw
<stage>Aside.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Some useful Secrets from him.
<stage>Aside.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>The good King</l>
               <l>Of whom you spake, <hi>Erectheus,</hi> did his People</l>
               <l>Esteem and love him as they ought? for Fame</l>
               <l>Talk'd largely of his Worth. He was a King—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>He was my good old Master, such a King</l>
               <l>As Heaven but rarely sends. Did we esteem</l>
               <l>And love him, dost thou ask? O, we ador'd him,</l>
               <l>He was our Father, not our King.—These Tears</l>
               <l>At least may speak <hi>my</hi> Heart.—We must not hope</l>
               <l>In these degenerate Times to see him equall'd.</l>
               <l>He never did an unkind Act, but once,</l>
               <l>And then he thought the public Good requir'd it;</l>
               <l>Tho' much I fear the Evils we lament</l>
               <l>From thence derive their Origin.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>What Act?</l>
               <l>What unkind Act?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>O Maid, 'twere long to tell</l>
               <l>The whole unhappy Story, yet in part</l>
               <l>Hear what to me appears too closely join'd</l>
               <l>With these our present Ills. There was a Youth</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Athenian</hi> born, but not of Royal Blood,</l>
               <l>His Name <hi>Nicander;</hi> him unlucky Fate</l>
               <l>Had made the Lover of our present Queen</l>
               <l>While yet a Maid. What will not Love attempt</l>
               <l>In young ambitious Minds? he told his Pain,</l>
               <l>And won the Fair in secret to admit,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="10"/>And to return his Passion. The good King</l>
               <l>Was for a Time deceiv'd, but found at last</l>
               <l>Th' audacious Fraud, and drove the guilty Youth</l>
               <l>To Banishment perpetual. Some say</l>
               <l>'Twas by his Means he fell, tho' that my Heart</l>
               <l>Consents not to believe. Thus much is sure,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi> wander'd forth a wretched Exile,</l>
               <l>And ere few Days had past, upon the Road</l>
               <l>Were found his well-known Garments stain'd with Blood.</l>
               <l>Sure Sign of Murder, and as sure a Sign</l>
               <l>No needy Robber was the Instrument.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>How bore <hi>Creusa</hi> this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>At first her Sorrows</l>
               <l>Were loud and frantic. Time at length subdued</l>
               <l>Her Rage to silent Grief. The good old King,</l>
               <l>To sooth her Woes, consented she should raise</l>
               <l>A Tomb to her <hi>Nicander;</hi> and perform</l>
               <l>A Kind of annual Rites to parted Love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>But that not long continued, for we find</l>
               <l>She married <hi>Xuthus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas a Match of State,</l>
               <l>He sav'd her Country, and she gave her Hand</l>
               <l>Because that Country ask'd it. But her Heart</l>
               <l>Is buried with <hi>Nicander.</hi> Still to him,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Xuthus'</hi> self permits it, she performs</l>
               <l>Her yearly Oft'rings, and adorns with Flowers</l>
               <l>An empty Tomb.—Would he had liv'd, and reign'd</l>
               <l>Her wedded Lord! we had not wanted then</l>
               <l>Th' Assistance of a Stranger Arm to guard</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="11"/>Th' <hi>Athenian</hi> State, nor had we then been driven</l>
               <l>To search for Heirs at <hi>Delphi.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Stop thy Tongue,</l>
               <l>Or speak with Rev'rence of the sacred Shrine.</l>
               <l>—Thy Words were hasty, but thy Silence now</l>
               <l>Makes just Atonement for them.—Then perhaps</l>
               <l>Thou think'st this want of Heirs a Curse entail'd</l>
               <l>By Heaven on <hi>Athens</hi> for <hi>Nicander</hi>'s Death</l>
               <l>And <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Reign?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>I am <hi>Athenian</hi> born,</l>
               <l>Nor love <hi>Aeolian</hi> Kings, however great</l>
               <l>And good they may be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>The Imperial <hi>Xuthus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is much renown'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Is virtuous, brave, and pious;</l>
               <l>Perhaps too pious.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>How!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Forgive me, Maid,</l>
               <l>I speak my Thoughts with Freedom.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>What thou speak'st</l>
               <l>To me, is sacred. Then perchance thou rank'st</l>
               <l>His Journey hither to address the God</l>
               <l>Among those Acts which thou would'st call too pious?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>For me the Gods of <hi>Athens</hi> would suffice.—</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="12"/>Yet do I pay just Rev'rence, holy Maid,</l>
               <l>To thee, and to thy Shrine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Thy Zeal for <hi>Athens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is too intemperate.—But the Train returns</l>
               <l>And interrupts our Converse. Say, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are they prepar'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> ILYSSUS <hi>and Virgins.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>They are, and only wait</l>
               <l>Th' approaching Victims.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>By you Train, the Queen</l>
               <l>Is now on her Arrival. Thou, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Receive her here; while I, as Custom wills,</l>
               <l>Deep in the Temple's inmost Gloom retire</l>
               <l>And wait th' inspiring God.—<hi>Ilyssus,</hi> hear;</l>
               <l>When thou hast paid due Honours to the Queen,</l>
               <l>Haste to <hi>Aletes,</hi> in the Laurel Grove</l>
               <l>Impatient I expect him; tell him, Youth,</l>
               <l>Things of uncommon Import do demand</l>
               <l>His instant Presence.—But the Croud approaches.</l>
               <l>Stranger, farewel.—I feel, I feel within</l>
               <l>An Heav'n-born Impulse, and the Seeds of Truth</l>
               <l>Are lab'ring in my Breast.—Stranger, farewel.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>The</hi> Pythia <hi>returns to the Temple, and the Gates shut.</hi>
            </stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> CREUSA <hi>and Attendants.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>No farther need we Conduct. Bid the Guards</l>
               <l>Return, and wait the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Does ought of Moment</l>
               <l>Detain him on the Road?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="13"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>He stops a while</l>
               <l>
                  <gap resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word" rend="content:〈◊〉">
                     <desc>illegible</desc>
                  </gap> great <hi>Trophonius'</hi> Cave, that he may leave</l>
               <l>
                  <gap resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word" rend="content:〈◊〉">
                     <desc>illegible</desc>
                  </gap> Duty unperform'd. Heaven grant his Zeal</l>
               <l>May meet with just Success!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Please you, great Queen,</l>
               <l>In yon Pavilion to repose, and taste</l>
               <l>Some light Refection.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Ha!—<hi>Lycea,</hi>—<hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What Youth is this? There's something in his Eyes,</l>
               <l>His Shape, his Voice.—What may we call thee, Youth?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>The Servant of the God, who guards this Fane.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Bear'st thou no Name?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus,</hi> gracious Queen,</l>
               <l>The Priests and Virgins call me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! <hi>Ilyssus!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That Name's <hi>Athenian.</hi> Tell me, gentle Youth,</l>
               <l>Art thou of <hi>Athens</hi> then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>I have no Country,</l>
               <l>Nor know I whence I am.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Who where thy Parents?</l>
               <l>Thy Father, Mother?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Ever honor'd Queen,</l>
               <l>I never knew a Mother's tender Cares▪</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="14"/>Nor heard th' Instructions of a Father's Tongue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>How cam'st thou hither?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Eighteen Years are past</l>
               <l>Since in the Temple's Portal I was found</l>
               <l>A sleeping Infant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Eighteen Years! good Heaven!</l>
               <l>That fatal Time recalls a Scene of Woe—</l>
               <l>Let me not think.—Were there no Marks to shew</l>
               <l>From whom or whence thou wert?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>I have been told</l>
               <l>An Osier Basket such as Shepherds weave,</l>
               <l>And a few scatter'd Leaves were all the Bed</l>
               <l>And Cradle I could boast.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Unhappy Child!</l>
               <l>But more, O ten times more unhappy they</l>
               <l>Who lost perhaps in thee their only Offspring!</l>
               <l>What Pangs, what Anguish must the Mother feel,</l>
               <l>Compell'd, no doubt, by some disastrous Fate—</l>
               <l>—But this is all Conjecture.—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>O great Queen,</l>
               <l>Had those from whom I sprung been form'd like thee;</l>
               <l>Had they e'er felt the secret Pangs of Nature,</l>
               <l>They had not left me to the desart World</l>
               <l>So totally expos'd. I rather fear</l>
               <l>I am the Child of Lowliness and Vice,</l>
               <l>And happy only in my Ignorance.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="15"/>—Why should she weep? O if her Tears can fall</l>
               <l>For even a Stranger's but suspected Woes,</l>
               <l>How is that People blest where she presides</l>
               <l>As Mother, and as Queen!—Please you, retire?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>No, stay. Thy Sentiments at least bespeak</l>
               <l>A gen'rous Education. Tell me, Youth,</l>
               <l>How has thy Mind been form'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>In that, great Queen,</l>
               <l>I never wanted Parents. The good Priests</l>
               <l>And pious Priestess, who with Care sustain'd</l>
               <l>My helpless Infancy, left not my Youth</l>
               <l>Without Instruction. But O, more than all,</l>
               <l>The kindest, best good Man, a neighb'ring Sage</l>
               <l>Who has known better Days, tho' now retir'd</l>
               <l>To a small Cottage on the Mountain's Brow,</l>
               <l>He deals his Blessings to the simple Swains</l>
               <l>In Balms and powerful Herbs. He taught me Things</l>
               <l>Which my Soul treasures as its dearest Wealth,</l>
               <l>And will remember ever. The good Priests,</l>
               <l>'Tis true, had taught the same, but not with half</l>
               <l>That Force and Energy; Conviction's self</l>
               <l>Dwelt on <hi>Aletes'</hi> Tongue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aletes,</hi> said'st thou?</l>
               <l>Was that the good Man's Name?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>It is, great Queen,</l>
               <l>For yet he lives, and guides me by his Counsels.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What did he teach thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="16"/>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>To adore high Heaven,</l>
               <l>And venerate on Earth Heaven's Image, Truth!</l>
               <l>To feel for others Woes, and bear my own</l>
               <l>With manly Resignation. — Yet I own</l>
               <l>Some things he taught me which but ill agree</l>
               <l>With my Condition here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What things were those?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>They were for Exercise, and to confirm</l>
               <l>My growing Strength. And yet I often told him</l>
               <l>The Exercise he taught resembled much</l>
               <l>What I had heard of War. He was himself</l>
               <l>A Warrior once.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>And did those Sports delight thee!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Great Queen, I do confess my Soul mix'd with them.</l>
               <l>Whene'er I grasp'd the Osier-platted Shield,</l>
               <l>Or sent the mimic Javelin to its Mark,</l>
               <l>I felt I know not what of Manhood in me.</l>
               <l>But then I knew my Duty, and repress'd</l>
               <l>The swelling Ardor. 'Tis to Shades, I cried,</l>
               <l>The Servant of the Temple must confine</l>
               <l>His less ambitious, not less virtuous Cares.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Did the good Man observe, and blame thy Ardor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>He only smil'd at my too forward Zeal;</l>
               <l>Nay seem'd to think such Sports were necessary</l>
               <l>To soften what he call'd more rig'rous Studies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="17"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA,</speaker>
               <l>—Why should she weep? O if her Tears can fall</l>
               <l>For even a Stranger's but suspected Woes,</l>
               <l>How is that People blest where she presides</l>
               <l>As Mother, and as Queen!—Please you, retire?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>No, stay. Thy Sentiments at least bespeak</l>
               <l>A gen'rous Education. Tell me, Youth,</l>
               <l>How has thy Mind been form'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>In that, great Queen,</l>
               <l>I never wanted Parents. The good Priests</l>
               <l>And pious Priestess, who with Care sustain'd</l>
               <l>My helpless Infancy, left not my Youth</l>
               <l>Without Instruction. But O, more than all,</l>
               <l>The kindest, best good Man, a neighb'ring Sage</l>
               <l>Who has known better Days, tho' now retir'd</l>
               <l>To a small Cottage on the Mountain's Brow,</l>
               <l>He deals his Blessings to the simple Swains</l>
               <l>In Balms and powerful Herbs. He taught me Things</l>
               <l>Which my Soul treasures as its dearest Wealth,</l>
               <l>And will remember ever. The good Priests,</l>
               <l>'Tis true, had taught the same, but not with half</l>
               <l>That Force and Energy; Conviction's self</l>
               <l>Dwelt on <hi>Aletes'</hi> Tongue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aletes,</hi> said'st thou?</l>
               <l>Was that the good Man's Name?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>It is, great Queen,</l>
               <l>For yet he lives, and guides me by his Counsels.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What did he teach thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="18"/>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>To adore high Heaven,</l>
               <l>And venerate on Earth Heaven's Image, Truth!</l>
               <l>To feel for others Woes, and bear my own</l>
               <l>With manly Resignation. — Yet I own</l>
               <l>Some things he taught me which but ill agree</l>
               <l>With my Condition here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What things were those?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>They were for Exercise, and to confirm</l>
               <l>My growing Strength. And yet I often told him</l>
               <l>The Exercise he taught resembled much</l>
               <l>What I had heard of War. He was himself</l>
               <l>A Warrior once.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>And did those Sports delight thee!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Great Queen, I do confess my Soul mix'd with them.</l>
               <l>Whene'er I grasp'd the Osier-platted Shield,</l>
               <l>Or sent the mimic Javelin to its Mark,</l>
               <l>I felt I know not what of Manhood in me.</l>
               <l>But then I knew my Duty, and repress'd</l>
               <l>The swelling Ardor. 'Tis to Shades, I cried,</l>
               <l>The Servant of the Temple must confine</l>
               <l>His less ambitious, not less virtuous Cares.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Did the good Man observe, and blame thy Ardor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>He only smil'd at my too forward Zeal;</l>
               <l>Nay seem'd to think such Sports were necessary</l>
               <l>To soften what he call'd more rig'rous Studies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="19"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>—Suppose when I return to <hi>Athens,</hi> Youth,</l>
               <l>Thou should'st attend me thither! would'st thou trust</l>
               <l>To me thy future Fortunes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>O most gladly!</l>
               <l>—But then to leave these Shades where I was nurs'd</l>
               <l>The Servant of the God, how might that seem?</l>
               <l>And good <hi>Aletes</hi> too, the kind old Man</l>
               <l>Of whom I spake? — But wherefore talk I thus,</l>
               <l>You only throw these tempting Lures to try</l>
               <l>Th' Ambition of my Youth. — Please you, retire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus,</hi> we will find a time to speak</l>
               <l>More largely on this Subject, for the present</l>
               <l>Let all withdraw and leave us. Youth, farewel,</l>
               <l>I see the Place, and will retire at leisure.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycea, Phorbas,</hi> stay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <stage>Aside.</stage>
               <l>How my Heart beats!</l>
               <l>She must mean something sure. Tho' good <hi>Aletes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has told me polished Courts abound in Falshood.</l>
               <l>But I will bear the Priestess' Message to him,</l>
               <l>And open all my Doubts.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Great Queen, why stand'st thou silent? something seems</l>
               <l>To labour in thy Breast.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Alas! good <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Didst thou observe that Youth? When first my Eye</l>
               <l>Glanc'd on his beauteous Form, methought I saw</l>
               <l>The Person of <hi>Nicander.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="20"/>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Queen,</l>
               <l>Your Heart misleads your Eyes. The Image there</l>
               <l>Too deeply six'd makes every pleasing Object</l>
               <l>Bear some Resemblance to itself.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yet, tho' thou wast there I well believe</l>
               <l>Thy Youth can scarce remember how he look'd,</l>
               <l>When from the Fight triumphant he return'd</l>
               <l>Grac'd with the victor Laurel; such a Wreath</l>
               <l>As now <hi>Ilyssus</hi> wears. Indeed, <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy Mother, had she liv'd, had thought as I do.</l>
               <l>Nay when he spake the Voice too was <hi>Nicander</hi>'s.</l>
               <l>I know not what to think, perhaps 'twas Fancy,</l>
               <l>Perhaps 'twas something more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Illustrious Queen,</l>
               <l>You do abuse your noble Mind, and lend</l>
               <l>To mere illusions of the Brain, the Force</l>
               <l>And Power to make you wretched. Grant there were</l>
               <l>Some slight Resemblance of <hi>Nicander</hi>'s Form</l>
               <l>In young <hi>Ilyssus,</hi> tho' my Eyes perceive not</l>
               <l>Even the most distant Likeness, grant there were,</l>
               <l>Yet wherefore should the Sight so nearly touch thee,</l>
               <l>Casual Similitude, we know too well</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi> left no Heir.</l>
               <stage>She seems disturbed.</stage>
               <l>I say not this,</l>
               <l>Great Queen, to heighten but relieve your Sorrows,</l>
               <l>And banish from your Breast each vain Surmise</l>
               <l>Which Fancy might suggest.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="21"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Too well indeed,</l>
               <l>O <hi>Phorbas,</hi> much too well indeed we know</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi> left no Heir to his Perfections,</l>
               <l>No Image of himself.—And yet, good <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Blame not my Folly, nor demand a Reason</l>
               <l>If I intreat thee to examine strictly</l>
               <l>The Fortunes of this young Unknown. The Priests</l>
               <l>Or Priestess may know more than they entrust</l>
               <l>To his unwary Youth. The Sage he spake of,</l>
               <l>Could'st thou not search him out; 'tis somewhere near</l>
               <l>He dwells, I think, upon the Mountain's Brow.</l>
               <l>Thou wonder'st at me, call it if thou please</l>
               <l>A Woman's Weakness; but obey me, <hi>Phorbas.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>You say I wonder, 'tis indeed to see</l>
               <l>My honor'd Queen employ her Thoughts thus idly</l>
               <l>On Griefs long past; when things of dear Concern</l>
               <l>To her and <hi>Athens</hi> should alarm her nearly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What things of near Concern?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>See'st thou not, Queen,</l>
               <l>Thy Crown, <hi>Erectheus'</hi> Crown, the Crown of <hi>Athens,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wav'ring in Fortune's Power?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>The Gods will fix it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>The Gods? Ah, great <hi>Creusa,</hi> may my Fears</l>
               <l>Be vain and groundless; but I fear the Gods</l>
               <l>Have left us to ourselves. When we resign'd</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Scepter to a Stranger Hand</l>
               <l>We did reject their Guidance. Wherefore come we</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="22"/>To <hi>Delphi</hi> now, but that th' offended Gods</l>
               <l>Have turn'd too long an inattentive Ear</l>
               <l>To our ill-judg'd Petitions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Why ill-judg'd?</l>
               <l>We ask'd for Heirs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>We did; for <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Heirs,</l>
               <l>The Race of <hi>Aeolus.</hi>—I know, great Queen,</l>
               <l>They were to spring from thee; but Heaven permits not</l>
               <l>The native Pureness of th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Soil</l>
               <l>Should mix with foreign Clay. I wish we find not</l>
               <l>More alien Kings at <hi>Delphi.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Think'st thou <hi>Xuthus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deceives us then? His Worth, his Piety,</l>
               <l>Forbid the Thought. Besides, the sacred Place</l>
               <l>Admits not of Deceit.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Credulity</l>
               <l>Is not the Vice of Age. Forgive me, Queen,</l>
               <l>If I suspect that Piety which brings us</l>
               <l>To search for Kings at <hi>Delphi.</hi> Might not <hi>Athens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have chosen her own Monarch? Her brave Youth,</l>
               <l>Her bearded Sages, are they not the Flower</l>
               <l>And Pride of <hi>Greece?</hi> Nay, might'st not thou, <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With liberal Hand bestow th' Imperial Wreath?</l>
               <l>And who has better Right?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>The Gods, who gave it</l>
               <l>To me, and my great Ancestors.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="23"/>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Whate'er</l>
               <l>The Gods bestow can never be resum'd</l>
               <l>Tho' we repent. The pious Populace</l>
               <l>Will rev'rence Kings from Heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>And wherefore not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>O Queen, perhaps my Fears are too officious,</l>
               <l>But let thy Servant beg—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I know thy Zeal</l>
               <l>For me, and for thy Country. Rest assur'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creusa</hi> never will consent to ought</l>
               <l>Which can endanger <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>My Heart thanks thee!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Mean while the Youth <hi>Ilyssus</hi>—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Should the King</l>
               <l>Confirm'd by Oracles presume to fix</l>
               <l>A Stranger on the Throne.—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>He will not do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>I hope he will not, yet—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>The Youth I spake of,</l>
               <l>Wilt thou enquire?—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="24"/>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Should <hi>Xuthus</hi> lay aside</l>
               <l>His usual Mildness, and assume at once</l>
               <l>The Monarch and the Husband, could'st thou then —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>In <hi>Athens'</hi> Cause I could resist them all.</l>
               <l>But cease these vain Suspicions. A few Hours</l>
               <l>Will prove thy Fears were groundless. Meanwhile, <hi>Phorbas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou wilt find Methods to inform thyself</l>
               <l>Touching this unknown Youth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>By yonder Guards</l>
               <l>The King should be at hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I will retire</l>
               <l>To the Pavilion, and expect him there.</l>
               <l>Yet hear me, <hi>Phorbas;</hi> let not <hi>Xuthus</hi> know</l>
               <l>Why thou enquir'st.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xuthus</hi> has other Cares.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>The Priestess too, I would confer with her.</l>
               <l>Tho' that <hi>Lycea</hi> may perform. Farewel,</l>
               <l>And prosper in thy Task. — Alas, <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Phorbas.</stage>
               <l>There is a Secret labours in my Breast,</l>
               <l>But Fate forbids that I should give it Utterance.</l>
               <l>This boding Heart was early taught to feel</l>
               <l>Too sensibly; each distant Doubt alarms it;</l>
               <l>It starts at Shadows.—But retire we, Maid,</l>
               <l>Grief is th' unhappy Charter of our Sex;</l>
               <l>The Gods who gave us readier Tears to shed</l>
               <l>Gave us more Cause to shed them.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <trailer>The End of the First ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <pb n="18" facs="25"/>
            <head>ACT II. <hi>The Laurel Grove.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>ALETES <hi>and</hi> ILYSSUS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>SEEM'D she disturb'd when she beheld thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Much;</l>
               <l>And when I gave her the slight Hints I knew</l>
               <l>Relating to my Fortunes, she dissolv'd</l>
               <l>In silent Tears: such soft Humanity</l>
               <l>Sure never dwelt in any Breast but hers.</l>
               <l>Nor did I think till now that I had Cause</l>
               <l>Of Discontent; but since she wept my Fate,</l>
               <l>I seem to find a Reason in her Grief,</l>
               <l>And feel myself unhappy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Why unhappy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>I know not why; and yet to be confin'd</l>
               <l>Thus to a single Spot; to draw in Air,</l>
               <l>To take in Nourishment, to live, to die,</l>
               <l>For this was Man design'd? Ah, good <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sure thou hast taught me, Godlike Man was made</l>
               <l>For nobler Purposes of general Good;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="26"/>For Action, not for Rest.—The Queen propos'd</l>
               <l>I should attend her to th' <hi>Athenian</hi> State;</l>
               <l>Would'st thou advise it? Do'st thou think, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She meant I should attend her?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Doubtless, Youth,</l>
               <l>If she propos'd, she meant it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>And would'st thou</l>
               <l>Advise I should attend her?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Wherefore not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>May I desert these Shades? or can I leave</l>
               <l>Thee, thee, my good <hi>Aletes?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>O <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strive not to hide thy Heart; from me thou can'st not;</l>
               <l>I form'd it, and I know it. <hi>Delphi</hi>'s Shades</l>
               <l>Have now no Peace for thee, thy Bosom feels</l>
               <l>Ambition's active, unrelenting Fires.</l>
               <l>Thou wishest, and thou hop'st, thou know'st not what.</l>
               <l>'Tis Glory thou would'st have: Go then, brave Youth,</l>
               <l>Where Virtue calls thee: be the Means but noble</l>
               <l>Thou can'st not soar too high.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>My more than Father!</l>
               <l>Thy Words inspire me, and I feel a Warmth</l>
               <l>Unknown before.—But then, my Birth—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Thy Birth?</l>
               <l>Did I not early teach thee to despise</l>
               <l>A casual Good? Thou art thyself, <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Inform me, Youth, would'st thou be what thou art,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="27"/>Thus fair, thus brave, thus sensibly alive</l>
               <l>To Glory's finest Feel; or give up all,</l>
               <l>To be descended from a Line of Kings,</l>
               <l>The tenth perhaps from <hi>Jove?</hi>—I see thy Cheek</l>
               <l>Glows a repentant Blush.—Our greatest Heroes,</l>
               <l>Those Gods on Earth, those Friends of Human kind,</l>
               <l>Whose great Examples I would set before thee,</l>
               <l>Were once unknown like thee. And yet, if Birth</l>
               <l>Concern thee, know, prophetic is my Speech,</l>
               <l>Thy Fate is now at work, and a few Hours</l>
               <l>May show thee what thou art.—My Words alarm thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>They do indeed. O tell me—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis in vain</l>
               <l>Thou would'st enquire from me, what Heaven conceals</l>
               <l>Till its fit Time. Didst thou not say, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Pythia</hi> would be here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>She comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Retire</l>
               <l>And leave us to ourselves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>I will.—And yet</l>
               <l>Might I not know—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>From me thou can'st know nothing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>A few Hours, said you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Hence, and beg of Heaven</l>
               <l>To prosper the Event. Retire and leave us.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Ilyssus.</stage>
            <stage>
               <pb n="21" facs="28"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> PYTHIA.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Now good <hi>Aletes,</hi> if thy pregnant Mind,</l>
               <l>Deep judging of Events, has ever fram'd</l>
               <l>Such artful Truths as won believing Man</l>
               <l>To think them born of Heaven, and made my Name</l>
               <l>Renown'd in <hi>Greece,</hi> O now exert thy Power.</l>
               <l>No common Cause demands it. Kings and States</l>
               <l>Are our Solicitors, and <hi>Athens'</hi> Fate</l>
               <l>Hangs on my Lips.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>I know it well. And now</l>
               <l>If, as thou say'st, my secret kind Advice,</l>
               <l>And worn Experience in the Ways of Men,</l>
               <l>Have gain'd thy Altars Credit, and with Gifts</l>
               <l>Loaded thy Shrines, now, by one grateful Act</l>
               <l>Thou may'st repay me all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>What Act? O speak,</l>
               <l>And gladly I obey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>An Act, my PYTHIA,</l>
               <l>Which tho' at first it may seem bold and dangerous,</l>
               <l>Shall in the End add Lustre to thy Shades,</l>
               <l>And make ev'n Kings Protectors of thy Fane.</l>
               <l>—O <hi>Pythia,</hi> 'twas the Hand of Heaven itself</l>
               <l>Which brought these Royal Suppliants to thy Shrine.</l>
               <l>I could unfold a Tale.—But let it rest.</l>
               <l>Thou shalt ere Night know all, and bless with me</l>
               <l>Th' indulgent Powers above. Only in this</l>
               <l>Obey me blindly, <hi>Pythia.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Say in what.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="22" facs="29"/>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Declare <hi>Ilyssus</hi> Heir to <hi>Athens'</hi> Crown.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus</hi> Heir? what mean'st thou? 'tis a Fraud</l>
               <l>Too palpable.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>I knew 'twould startle thee.</l>
               <l>But 'tis because thou know'st the Fraud, my <hi>Pythia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That it alarms thee. Didst thou really think</l>
               <l>This Youth were Heir to the <hi>Athenian</hi> Crown,</l>
               <l>Would'st thou not seize the happy Gift of Chance</l>
               <l>And to the World proclaim it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>True, I should;</l>
               <l>And bless my Fate that in these sacred Shades</l>
               <l>I had nurs'd up unknowingly a King</l>
               <l>For my Protector. But what then might seem</l>
               <l>The Consequence, now seems the Cause, <hi>Aletes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will they not say I made the King, to gain</l>
               <l>The kind Protector?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>So to thee it seems;</l>
               <l>But who will say it? the believing many</l>
               <l>Will bow with Rev'rence and implicit Faith</l>
               <l>To what thy Shrine ordains; and for the few</l>
               <l>Who may suspect the Cheat, true Policy</l>
               <l>Will keep them silent: should they dare detect</l>
               <l>A Fraud like this, and spurn at Right divine,</l>
               <l>Where were their Power? The many-headed Beast</l>
               <l>Would feel the slacken'd Rein, and from his Back</l>
               <l>Shake off the lordly Rider. Nay should <hi>Athens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be blind to her own Good, the States of <hi>Greece,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou know'st it well, would arm in thy Defence,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="30"/>And force her to receive the King thou gav'st her.</l>
               <l>His Form, his unknown Birth, his winning Softness,</l>
               <l>His Education here in Heaven's own Eye,</l>
               <l>All plead in his behalf. And, as he tells me,</l>
               <l>The Queen already with unusual Marks</l>
               <l>Of Favour has beheld him. For the King,</l>
               <l>A pious Awe and Rev'rence for the Gods</l>
               <l>Is his distinguish'd Attribute. Thou seem'st</l>
               <l>To weigh my Words. To clear thy Doubts at once,</l>
               <l>Know many Days have past since first I knew</l>
               <l>Of their Approach. Thou think'st I should have told thee,</l>
               <l>It needed not. I have myself prepar'd</l>
               <l>Each previous Circumstance, and found due means</l>
               <l>To forward the Event. Thy Part is easy;</l>
               <l>Behold the Oracle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA <hi>reads.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>"A banish'd Youth is <hi>Athens'</hi> Cause of Woe."</l>
               <l>How know'st thou that?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Looking earnestly at him.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Demand not, but read on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA <hi>reads.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>"For that Youth banish'd, <hi>Athens</hi> must receive</l>
               <l>"Another Youth; and on the young Unknown</l>
               <l>"Who 'tends my Shrine, and whom I call my Son,</l>
               <l>"Bestow th' Imperial Wreath." The God declare<gap resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter" rend="content:•">
                     <desc>illegible</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>"No more."</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Thou seem'st amaz'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>I am indeed,</l>
               <l>To find thee thus instructed on a Theme</l>
               <l>I came prepar'd to mention. The Queen's Passion,</l>
               <l>Her Lover banish'd—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="24" facs="31"/>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>What thou seest I know</l>
               <l>May tell thee I know more But say, from whence</l>
               <l>Thou gained'st thy Intelligence?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>From one</l>
               <l>Whose Zeal may thwart thy Schemes: a warm old Man,</l>
               <l>And firm in <hi>Athens'</hi> Cause, who came to-day</l>
               <l>Before the rest, and led by my Enquiries</l>
               <l>Gave me those Hints on which I thought to build</l>
               <l>Prophetic, doubtful Answers. But I find</l>
               <l>My best Instructor here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Perhaps thou do'st.</l>
               <l>Of this rest well assur'd, I ne'er had ask'd</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pythia</hi> ought but what I knew with Safety</l>
               <l>She might comply with.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Tell me what thou know'st.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Not yet; 'tis better thou remain in Ignorance</l>
               <l>Till all be finish'd. But pronounce the Oracle,</l>
               <l>And leave the rest to me. Do'st thou distrust me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>I do not.—Yet if on slight Hints alone</l>
               <l>Thou form'st this weighty Fraud, consider well</l>
               <l>What may or may not follow.—By thy Looks</l>
               <l>There should be something hid.—Thy coming hither</l>
               <l>Was much upon the Time we found this Child.</l>
               <l>And since, with what almost paternal Care</l>
               <l>Thou hast instructed him. Tho' that indeed</l>
               <l>Might spring from thy Benevolence of Heart,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="32"/>Which I have known is boundless. Say, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What should I think? Thou smil'st.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Wilt thou obey me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>I must; and yet if 'tis a Fraud, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The warm old Man of whom I spake detests</l>
               <l>A Stranger King. Ev'n <hi>Xuthus'</hi> self, whose Worth</l>
               <l>He doth acknowledge great, he views with Pain</l>
               <l>Upon th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Throne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>I know him well;</l>
               <l>'Tis <hi>Phorbas.</hi> Do not wonder at my Words,</l>
               <l>But find a Means that I may see the Queen</l>
               <l>In secret, unobserv'd by prying Eyes,</l>
               <l>And all that old Man's Fears, and Rage shall vanish.</l>
               <l>He shall with Joy receive a Stranger King.</l>
               <l>Wilt thou devise the Means?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>I now begin</l>
               <l>To hope indeed. There is some Secret hid</l>
               <l>Of most important Weight. But does the Queen—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>I will not answer thee; my Time's too precious.</l>
               <l>Only devise some Means that I may see her</l>
               <l>Quite unobserv'd by all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>You cannot see her</l>
               <l>Till all be past. Will that suffice?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>It will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Here in the Laurel Grove.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="33"/>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>No Place more fit.</l>
               <l>But O be careful, <hi>Pythia,</hi> that the King</l>
               <l>Observe us not; for 'tis of mighty Moment</l>
               <l>He should believe this substituted Youth</l>
               <l>Of Race <hi>Aeolian.</hi> To which End, my <hi>Pythia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I have among the Priests these few Days past,</l>
               <l>When they suspected not th' Approach of <hi>Xuthus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dropp'd doubtful Hints as if I had discover'd</l>
               <l>Some antique Marks amid the Osier Twigs</l>
               <l>Which form'd <hi>Ilyssus'</hi> Cradle, that denote</l>
               <l>He sprang from <hi>Aeolus:</hi> And at the Cave</l>
               <l>Of great <hi>Trophonius</hi> have I ta'en due Care</l>
               <l>Such Answers should be given as would induce</l>
               <l>One of less Faith than <hi>Xuthus</hi> to expect</l>
               <l>An Heir of his own Family.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>The Boy,</l>
               <l>Knows he of thy Intentions?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>No, nor must</l>
               <l>Till ripening Time permit. His Fate depends</l>
               <l>Upon his Ignorance.—Soft, who comes here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>It is the warm old Man, and, as I think,</l>
               <l>Some fair Attendant of the Queen. Retire.</l>
               <l>I would know more, but—Wherefore do'st thou gaze</l>
               <l>So ardently upon them?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Hence, away,</l>
               <l>We must not now be seen.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exeunt</hi> Pythia <hi>and</hi> Aletes.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> LYCEA <hi>and</hi> PHORBAS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>This Place seems quite retir'd. Here if thou wait</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="34"/>I will inform the Queen, and her Impatience</l>
               <l>Will bring her on the Instant. Surely, <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Something mysterious lurks beneath her Tears;</l>
               <l>Her strange Anxieties. Since thou wer't absent</l>
               <l>This unknown Youth alone has fill'd her Thoughts,</l>
               <l>Of him alone she talks, recounts his Words,</l>
               <l>Describes his Looks, his Gestures; loves to dwell</l>
               <l>On each Particular. Ere thou wer't gone</l>
               <l>She wish'd and even expected thy Return;</l>
               <l>Dispatch'd me often, tho' she knew 'twas vain,</l>
               <l>To watch for thy Arrival. When the King</l>
               <l>Approach'd, she smooth'd her Brow, as if to hide</l>
               <l>The Strugglings of her Mind; nay seem'd afraid</l>
               <l>He should suspect her Sorrows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Then to him</l>
               <l>She mention'd not this Youth?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Her Conduct there</l>
               <l>Was most mysterious. With a Voice of Fear,</l>
               <l>She slightly dropp'd that she had seen a Youth</l>
               <l>Whom she could wish to bear with her to <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The King consented, and with Smiles propos'd</l>
               <l>They should adopt him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! adopt him, said'st thou?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>In Sport he spake, but at his Words a Glow</l>
               <l>Of sudden Joy spread o'er her Face, her Tongue</l>
               <l>Forgot Restraint, and in his Praise grew lavish:</l>
               <l>Then stopp'd again, and hesitating strove</l>
               <l>To check its Zeal, as fearful to betray</l>
               <l>Some hidden Transport.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="28" facs="35"/>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Whatsoe'er it be,</l>
               <l>I soon shall damp her Joy. This Youth, <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Must not to <hi>Athens.</hi>—But behold, the Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>O how impatient! ere I could return</l>
               <l>To tell her thou wer't here, she comes herself,</l>
               <l>Eager to learn thy Tidings.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> CREUSA.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Now, my <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Say what thou know'st at once. The King already</l>
               <l>Consents he should attend us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Never, never</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>Athens</hi> see that Youth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA:</speaker>
               <l>What mean'st thou, <hi>Phorbas?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Too much already of <hi>Aeolian</hi> Blood</l>
               <l>Has hapless <hi>Athens</hi> known.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeolian</hi> Blood!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>The King consents! I doubt not his Consent.</l>
               <l>—Yes, 'twas my Word, great Queen, <hi>Aeolian</hi> Blood;</l>
               <l>This Youth descends from <hi>Aeolus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Be dumb,</l>
               <l>Or bring me better Tidings.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS,</speaker>
               <l>Worse I cannot,</l>
               <l>But what I speak is Truth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="36"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Peace, Monster, Peace!</l>
               <l>Thou know'st not Truth. 'Tis thy affected Zeal</l>
               <l>For <hi>Athens,</hi> for thy Country, that suggests</l>
               <l>This horrid Falshood; 'tis thy Hate of <hi>Xuthus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>What means my Queen? or how have I deserv'd</l>
               <l>Such harsh Expressions? Does my honest Love</l>
               <l>For <hi>Athens,</hi> and <hi>Creusa,</hi> subject me</l>
               <l>To such unkind Suspicions?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Gods!</l>
               <l>It cannot be.—Alas, forgive me, <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I know not what I say, thy Words strike thro' me,</l>
               <l>They pierce my very Soul. O I had hop'd—</l>
               <l>But tell me all, tho' I believe thee honest,</l>
               <l>Thy Zeal for <hi>Athens,</hi> and for me, may make thee</l>
               <l>Too hasty of Belief. Why art thou silent?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Amazement stops my Tongue, these Starts of Passion,</l>
               <l>This Violence of Grief, must have a Cause.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Perhaps they have, perhaps to thee, good <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This bursting Heart may open all its Sorrows.</l>
               <l>But tell me first, what are thy Proofs? from whence</l>
               <l>Gain'dst thou this curs'd Intelligence?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>O Queen,</l>
               <l>Thy Looks, thy Words—I know not how to answer.</l>
               <l>Yet if there be Offence in what I speak,</l>
               <l>My Ignorance offends, not I offend.</l>
               <l>Know then, <hi>Creusa,</hi> from the Priests who 'tend</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="37"/>This <hi>Delphic</hi> Shrine, by your Command I learnt</l>
               <l>My first Intelligence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>And did they say</l>
               <l>This Youth was of <hi>Aeolian</hi> Race?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>They did.</l>
               <l>At least their Words imported little less.</l>
               <l>They judg'd me <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Friend, not Enemy,</l>
               <l>As would thy Rage suggest, and as a Friend</l>
               <l>Dropp'd Hints they thought would please me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Then, perhaps,</l>
               <l>It was not Truth they spake, they but deceiv'd</l>
               <l>Thy Ear with well-judg'd Flattery.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>What follow'd</l>
               <l>Confirm'd it Truth. Has the King mention'd to thee</l>
               <l>What Promises were given him at the Shrine</l>
               <l>Of sage <hi>Trophonius?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>General Promises</l>
               <l>Of sure Success, no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Know then, great Queen,</l>
               <l>As I return'd from Converse with the Priests,</l>
               <l>I met his Friend and Bosom Fav'rite <hi>Lycon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Joy sparkled in his Eyes, and his vain Tongue</l>
               <l>O'erflow'd with Transport. I observ'd it well,</l>
               <l>And gave the Torrent Passage, nay with Art</l>
               <l>Ev'n led it blindly forward. Till at length</l>
               <l>He open'd his whole Soul, and under Seal</l>
               <l>Of firmest Secrecy told me the King</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="38"/>Would find an Heir at <hi>Delphi,</hi> such an Heir</l>
               <l>As would rejoice the unapparent Shades</l>
               <l>Of his great Ancestors. At that I started.</l>
               <l>He found his Error then, and told me, glozing,</l>
               <l>That great <hi>Trophonius</hi> had <hi>almost</hi> proclaim'd,</l>
               <l>Tho' not expressly, <hi>Xuthus</hi> here should find</l>
               <l>An Heir of his own Race.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Of his own Race?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>So said he; whether great <hi>Trophonius</hi> spake</l>
               <l>This Oracle, I know not; but I know</l>
               <l>Too well whose Oracle to me declar'd it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Think'st thou this Youth—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Grant it were only done</l>
               <l>To try my Zeal, why should they try it now,</l>
               <l>Unless some close Design requir'd that Trial?</l>
               <l>Yes, mighty Queen, I do believe this Youth</l>
               <l>Is our intended King. But, by yon Heaven,</l>
               <l>If it be he, or any other He</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Race, he shall not reign in <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Poinard first shall drink his Blood.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Forbear!</l>
               <l>That Thought distracts me.—Tho' perhaps 'tis just.</l>
               <l>—O <hi>Phorbas,</hi> 'twas my Hope, my Wish, my Prayer</l>
               <l>That Youth might reign in <hi>Athens.</hi> But thy Words</l>
               <l>Strike deadly Damps like baleful Aconite,</l>
               <l>And poison all within.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>What means my Queen?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="39"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>O <hi>Phorbas,</hi> O <hi>Lycea</hi>—but first swear</l>
               <l>By <hi>Nemesis</hi> and the tremendous Powers</l>
               <l>Who punish broken Faith, no Word, no Hint</l>
               <l>Shall'scape your Lips of all your Queen declares.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BOTH.</speaker>
               <l>We swear!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Know then, O Pain to Memory!</l>
               <l>I had a Son.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>A Son!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Good Heaven!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>A Son!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>O my full Heart! Thy Mother, my <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Knew all the fatal Process of my Woes,</l>
               <l>And was their only Solace. <hi>Phorbas,</hi> yes,</l>
               <l>I had a Son, but witness every God</l>
               <l>Whose genial Power presides o'er nuptial Leagues,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi> was my wedded Lord. That Night,</l>
               <l>That fatal Night which drove him forth from <hi>Athens,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Forc'd from my swelling Womb, ere yet mature,</l>
               <l>Its precious Burthen. To thy Mother's Cares</l>
               <l>I ow'd my Life. In secret she assuag'd</l>
               <l>My piercing Pangs, and to <hi>Nicander</hi>'s Arms</l>
               <l>In secret she convey'd the wretched Infant.</l>
               <l>What follow'd well thou know'st. <hi>Nicander</hi> fell,</l>
               <l>And with him doubtless fell the dear, dear Charge,</l>
               <l>Consign'd to his Protection. Yet, good <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When I beheld this Youth, his Looks, his Voice,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="40"/>His Age, his unknown Birth, all, all conspir'd</l>
               <l>To cheat me into Hopes. Alas, how fallen!</l>
               <l>How blasted all!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Great Queen, my Tears confess,</l>
               <l>An old Man's Tears, which rarely fall, confess</l>
               <l>How much I share your Anguish. Had I known</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi> was your Lord, by Earth and Heaven,</l>
               <l>I would have rais'd all <hi>Athens</hi> in his Cause,;</l>
               <l>Nay, been a Rebel to the best of Masters,</l>
               <l>Ere the dear Pledge of your unspotted Loves</l>
               <l>Should thus have fallen untimely. Now, alas,</l>
               <l>I have not ev'n one flattering Hope to give thee.</l>
               <l>Till now I oft have wonder'd why so far</l>
               <l>Their Rage pursued <hi>Nicander.</hi> 'Tis too plain,</l>
               <l>They knew the precious Burthen which he bore,</l>
               <l>And for the hapless Child the Father died.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>O God! I feel the Truth of what thou utter'st,</l>
               <l>And my Heart dies within me. O <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who, who would be a Mother!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Be a Queen,</l>
               <l>And turn thy Grief to Rage. Shall Aliens sport</l>
               <l>With thy Misfortunes? Shall insulting Spoilers</l>
               <l>Smile o'er the Ruins of thy hapless State,</l>
               <l>While all the golden Harvest is their own?</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>Xuthus</hi> triumph? shall his Race succeed?</l>
               <l>While thine, I mean not to provoke thy Tears,</l>
               <l>Thy tender Blossoms are torn rudely off</l>
               <l>Almost or ere they bloom.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="41"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>It shall not be,</l>
               <l>No, ye immortal Powers!— Yet let us wait</l>
               <l>Till the dire Truth glare on us. One short Hour</l>
               <l>And Doubt shall be no more. Then, <hi>Phorbas,</hi> then</l>
               <l>Should he presume to place on <hi>Athens'</hi> Throne</l>
               <l>His alien Race, nay tho' this beauteous Youth,</l>
               <l>This dear Resemblance of my murder'd Lord,</l>
               <l>Should be the fatal Choice, by that dear Shade,</l>
               <l>Which perish'd as it reach'd the Gates of Life,</l>
               <l>I will, I think I will, assist thy Vengeance.</l>
               <l>—Soft, who comes here? 'Tis he! how innocent!</l>
               <l>How winning soft he looks! Whate'er it be,</l>
               <l>He knows not the Deceit. Look on him, <hi>Phorbas;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay, thou shalt question him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Not I. Great Queen,</l>
               <l>Resume yourself, nor let this fond Persuasion</l>
               <l>Betray you to a Weakness you should blush at.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>If possible I will.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> ILYSSUS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Illustrious Queen,</l>
               <l>The Altar stands prepar'd, and all Things wait</l>
               <l>Your Royal Presence: From the King I come,</l>
               <l>His Messenger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>We will attend his Pleasure.</l>
               <l>Be near me, <hi>Phorbas;</hi> I may want thy Counsel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>She looks not on me sure as she was wont.</l>
               <l>I'll speak to her. Permit me, gracious Queen,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="42"/>To pay my humblest Thanks, for by your means</l>
               <l>The King is kind as you are.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Rise, <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Perhaps you needed there no Advocate.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phorbas,</hi> lead on. My Resolution melts,</l>
               <l>And all my Sex returns. One Look from him</l>
               <l>Outweighs a thousand Proofs. <hi>Phorbas,</hi> lead on,</l>
               <l>Or I am lost in Weakness.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exeunt</hi> Creusa <hi>and</hi> Phorbas.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS,</speaker>
               <stage>
                  <hi>stopping</hi> Lycea.</stage>
               <l>Gentle Maid,</l>
               <l>Stay yet a Moment. Wherefore does the Queen</l>
               <l>Look coldly on me? Know'st thou if in ought</l>
               <l>I have offended?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Things of mightiest Import</l>
               <l>At present fill her Mind, nor leave they room</l>
               <l>For less Affairs. My Duty calls me hence.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>I hope it is no more; yet each Appearance</l>
               <l>Alarms me now. <hi>Aletes,</hi> thou hast rais'd</l>
               <l>Such Conflicts here, such Hopes, such Fears, such Doubts,</l>
               <l>That Apprehension sinks beneath their Weight.</l>
               <l>Well might'st thou say these solitary Shades</l>
               <l>Have now no Peace for me. Yet once thou taught'st me,</l>
               <l>That the pure Mind was its own Source of Peace.</l>
               <l>But that Philosophy I find belongs</l>
               <l>To private Life, for where Ambition enters</l>
               <l>I feel it is not true.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <trailer>The End of the Second ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <pb n="36" facs="43"/>
            <head>ACT III. <hi>The Vestibule of the Temple.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES <hi>alone.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>WHY should I doubt? it will, it must succeed.</l>
               <l>Yet I could wish that I had seen <hi>Creusa</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before 'twas undertaken, for perhaps—</l>
               <l>'Tis better as it is. Her Part had then</l>
               <l>Been difficult to act; now what she does,</l>
               <l>Assisting or opposing the Design,</l>
               <l>Will all seem natural.—The <hi>Pythia</hi> sure</l>
               <l>Will act as I directed.—Hark, the Rites</l>
               <l>Should be ere this perform'd; why stay they then?</l>
               <l>—That Noise proclaims them finish'd, and the Croud</l>
               <l>Will soon be here.—They come, I must not yet</l>
               <l>Be seen; the <hi>Pythia</hi> in the Laurel Grove</l>
               <l>May tell me what has pass'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>CREUSA <hi>descends hastily from the Temple in great Disorder,</hi> LYCEA <hi>following.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, mighty Queen,</l>
               <l>You know not what you do; your Rage transports you;</l>
               <l>You leave the Rites unfinish'd, and the Croud</l>
               <l>In wild Amazement gaze on your Departure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I will not stay, nor will I tamely bear</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="44"/>My disappointed Hopes. O honest <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O good old Man, thy penetrating Mind</l>
               <l>Saw early their Designs. 'Tis to supply</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi>'s Loss (O ne'er to be supply'd!)</l>
               <l>That we must call in Strangers to the Throne,</l>
               <l>And yield our Scepters to <hi>Aeolian</hi> Hands.</l>
               <l>—Yes, ye great Shades of my Progenitors,</l>
               <l>I hear ye call, ye shall, ye shall have Vengeance!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Whatever you design, conceal at least</l>
               <l>This Transport of your Rage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Why loiters <hi>Phorbas?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He saw my Anguish, wherefore comes he not</l>
               <l>To its Relief? They fool me past Endurance.</l>
               <l>Rely they on the Weakness of my Sex?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycea,</hi> they shall find this feeble Arm</l>
               <l>In such a Cause can lay the Distaff by,</l>
               <l>And grasp th' unerring Thunderbolt of <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O <hi>Phorbas,</hi> art thou come?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> PHORBAS <hi>from the Temple.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Now, mighty Queen,</l>
               <l>Are my Suspicions just? is <hi>Phorbas</hi> honest?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>As Light, as Truth itself. My Counsellor,</l>
               <l>My Bosom Friend!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Now shall a casual Likeness,</l>
               <l>If such there be, a semblant Cast of Features,</l>
               <l>The Sport of Nature in a human Form,</l>
               <l>Shall Trisles light as these weigh down Conviction?</l>
               <l>O Queen, from first to last th' apparent Scheme</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="45"/>Glares on us now. Why were we brought to <hi>Delphi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But that this Youth has long been nurtur'd here</l>
               <l>In secret from the World; perhaps the Son</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Xuthus'</hi> self, plac'd here at first to hide</l>
               <l>The Guilt and Shame of some dishonest Mother,</l>
               <l>Tho' now applied to more pernicious Ends.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>It may be so.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>And why, say why, to-day,</l>
               <l>While <hi>Xuthus</hi> stays behind for Oracles</l>
               <l>He wanted not, is young <hi>Ilyssus</hi> bid</l>
               <l>To meet your Eyes, and win with artful Tales</l>
               <l>Your easy Heart?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Bid! was he bid to do it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>I saw the Priestess whisper something to him,</l>
               <l>Then loud she bade him wait for thy Approach.</l>
               <l>She must, forsooth, retire to sacred Glooms,</l>
               <l>And wait for Inspiration. <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Gold</l>
               <l>Was what inspir'd the Traitress. Yet, good Heaven,</l>
               <l>When from the Shrine she gave the fraudful Words,</l>
               <l>With what strange Art the holy Hypocrite</l>
               <l>In mimic Trances died!—"A banish'd Youth</l>
               <l>"Is <hi>Athens'</hi> Cause of Woe." Too truly said,</l>
               <l>Tho' for a wicked Purpose, to allure</l>
               <l>Thy easy Faith, and lead thee to admit</l>
               <l>The Fraud which follow'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Never, never, <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will I that Fraud admit. How readily</l>
               <l>Did <hi>Xuthus,</hi> when my foolish Fondness ask'd it,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="46"/>Consent to my Request!<note n="*" place="marg">
                     <hi>To</hi> Lycoa.</note> Thou heard'st him say</l>
               <l>We should adopt this Youth; in seeming Sport</l>
               <l>He spake it, but ev'n then th' insulting Tyrant</l>
               <l>Couch'd fatal Truths beneath th' ambiguous Phrase.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Why should a Youth design'd for Solitude</l>
               <l>Be taught the Arts of War? He saw himself</l>
               <l>The Impropriety. Who is this Sage</l>
               <l>That has instructed him? And why should <hi>Lycon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O'erflow with sudden Joy, but that he found,</l>
               <l>From thy apparent Fondness for the Boy,</l>
               <l>Their Schemes grew practicable. Nay, to-day,</l>
               <l>When to the Priestess' self my honest Love</l>
               <l>For <hi>Athens,</hi> and Dislike of Stranger Kings,</l>
               <l>Burst freely forth, she chid my hasty Zeal,</l>
               <l>Commended <hi>Xuthus,</hi> talk'd of Piety</l>
               <l>And Rev'rence to the Gods: 'Twas to their Priests</l>
               <l>She meant, their meddling Priests, who dare presume</l>
               <l>To sport with Thrones, to sell their Gods for Gold,</l>
               <l>And stamp rank Falshoods with the Seal of Heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Forbear, you are too loud so near the Temple;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xuthus</hi> himself will hear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>We would be heard.</l>
               <l>Instruct me, <hi>Phorbas,</hi> by what means to crush</l>
               <l>This impious Combination.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Athens</hi> yet</l>
               <l>Has honest Hearts. Yes, <hi>Phorbas</hi> yet has Friends</l>
               <l>Who dare be Patriots, and prefer their Country</l>
               <l>To <hi>Xuthus'</hi> kindest Smile. Some such are here</l>
               <l>Ev'n now at <hi>Delphi.</hi> But, illustrious Queen,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="47"/>We must with Caution act. The Name of Heaven,</l>
               <l>Howe'er usurp'd, adds Vigour to their Cause,</l>
               <l>And weakens ours. We might in secret find</l>
               <l>A sure Revenge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Of <hi>Xuthus?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>His</l>
               <l>Might follow, but the more immediate Cause</l>
               <l>Should earliest be remov'd, the Boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>The Boy!</l>
               <l>Why should he die? Believe me, honest <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He knows not of the Fraud. His every Look</l>
               <l>Proclaims his Innocence. If impious Men</l>
               <l>Make him their Instrument of evil Deeds,</l>
               <l>Can he be blam'd? Bred up in Shades, poor Youth,</l>
               <l>He never knew the Arts of base Mankind,</l>
               <l>Nor should he share their Punishment.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>O Queen,</l>
               <l>They have too well succeeded. This fond Passion,</l>
               <l>Which their insidious Cunning first inspir'd,</l>
               <l>Clings close about your Heart, and may at last</l>
               <l>Undo us all.—But hark, that Noise declares</l>
               <l>The finish'd Rites. Retire we to the Grove,</l>
               <l>And there will I enforce—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>No, let us stay.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="48"/>I will confront this artful Politician,</l>
               <l>And shew him I am yet a Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Perhaps</l>
               <l>'Twere better to retire till our full Scheme</l>
               <l>Were ripe for Vengeance.—
<stage>* <hi>Aside.</hi>
                  </stage> Yet if we remain,</l>
               <l>High Words must rise, which will alarm her Pride</l>
               <l>And fit her for my Purpose.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> XUTHUS, ILYSSUS, <hi>Priests, Virgins, Guards,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>from the Temple.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <stage>XUTHUS, (<hi>coming up to</hi> Creusa)</stage>
               <l>Thy Looks, <hi>Creusa,</hi> thy abrupt Departure</l>
               <l>Affronting to the God himself, and these</l>
               <l>His sacred Ministers, too plainly shew</l>
               <l>Irreverent Rage, resisting Heaven's high Will.</l>
               <l>Nor do'st thou want I see, unthinking Woman,</l>
               <l>Inflamers of thy Folly.—But of this</l>
               <l>Enough; behold the Youth whom Heaven designs</l>
               <l>Thy Heir, and mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>My Heir!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Thy Heir, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What means that haughty Look? Why with Contempt</l>
               <l>Do'st thou behold him? Is he chang'd, <hi>Creusa?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have a few Hours so totally transform'd him?</l>
               <l>Is all that winning Grace of which thou spak'st</l>
               <l>Almost with Rapture, is that native Charm</l>
               <l>Of Innocence all vanish'd? Hear him speak,</l>
               <l>Hear if he talks less sensibly than when</l>
               <l>Thy pleas'd Attention hung upon his Words,</l>
               <l>And lent each Syllable an added Grace.</l>
               <l>What hast thou found, or thy grave Monitor</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="49"/>What has he found, which can so suddenly</l>
               <l>Have wrought this wond'rous Change? Is it because</l>
               <l>The Gods have thought with thee that he deserves</l>
               <l>A Crown? or is it that my Will consents?</l>
               <l>And therefore thine, proud Queen, perversely strives</l>
               <l>To combat thy Affections?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>We methinks</l>
               <l>Have chang'd Affections. The calm, steady <hi>Xuthus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose equal Mind ne'er knew the stormy Gusts</l>
               <l>Of discomposing Passion, now can feel</l>
               <l>Indecent Warmth when touch'd by pious Zeal.</l>
               <l>Nay he, to whom the tend'rer Sentiments</l>
               <l>Seem'd but the Weakness of the human Frame,</l>
               <l>Now wakes inspir'd with some unusual Softness.</l>
               <l>Have Oracles the Power to raise at once</l>
               <l>The kind Affections? or did he conceal</l>
               <l>The smother'd Flame, 'till authoris'd by Heaven</l>
               <l>It might burst out unquestion'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Haughty Queen,</l>
               <l>I understand thee well; thou think'st this Youth</l>
               <l>A Substitute of mine, and dar'st affront</l>
               <l>Yon awful Shrine, the Fountain of pure Truth.</l>
               <l>But by that God who bears the vengeful Bow,</l>
               <l>And whose large Eye—Yet wherefore should I strive</l>
               <l>By Oaths to undeceive thee; Breasts like mine</l>
               <l>Can scorn th' imputed Falshood they detest.</l>
               <l>Nor am I now to learn from what vile Source</l>
               <l>Thy vain Suspicions rise. But know, proud Queen,</l>
               <l>This Youth shall reign in <hi>Athens;</hi> and yet more</l>
               <l>To punish thy vain Pride, since thou provok'st it,</l>
               <l>I do believe him of <hi>Aeolian</hi> Race.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="43" facs="50"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Thou do'st?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>I do. A Race as glorious, Queen,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Cecrops'</hi> boasted lineage. For the Youth,</l>
               <l>Were I to beg the choicest Boon of Heaven</l>
               <l>From my own Loins to rise, I could not hope</l>
               <l>A nobler Offspring.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Aside to</hi> Creusa.</stage>
               <l>Hear'st thou that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I do,</l>
               <l>And will revenge the Insult.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <stage>Kneeling.</stage>
               <l>Gracious Queen!</l>
               <l>What have I done which should estrange thee to me?</l>
               <l>Am I the unhappy Cause of these Dissentions?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Kneel not to me, <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Kneel not to her;</l>
               <l>'Tis I am thy Protector, and thy Friend,</l>
               <l>Nay now thy Father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Yet, O mighty King,</l>
               <l>Permit me at her Royal Feet to pay</l>
               <l>My humblest Duty. If I call thee Father,</l>
               <l>She sure must be a Mother.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>She turns away disorder'd.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Rise, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou seest she stands unmov'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="51"/>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>No, now she softens,</l>
               <l>I see it in her Eyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I will, I will</l>
               <l>Be Mistress of my Soul.—Why kneel'st thou, Youth,</l>
               <l>I blame not thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Men then thou blam'st, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I am the Object of thy Rage. 'Tis <hi>Xuthus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou think'st unworthy of th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Throne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Athens</hi> might well have spar'd a foreign Lustre,</l>
               <l>Secure of Fame, had <hi>Xuthus</hi> ne'er been born.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Ungrateful Queen, had <hi>Xuthus</hi> ne'er been born</l>
               <l>What now had <hi>Athens</hi> been?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Perhaps in Ruins,</l>
               <l>And better so than to become the Prey</l>
               <l>Of needy wand'ring Strangers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Earth, and Heaven!</l>
               <l>This the Return?—I knew thou never loved'st me,</l>
               <l>Yet, witness Heav'n, I ravish'd not thy Hand,</l>
               <l>Thou gav'dst it sullenly, but yet thou gav'dst it;</l>
               <l>And I well hop'd thy Female Sense of Honour,</l>
               <l>Of Duty to thy Lord, might have secur'd</l>
               <l>At least my future Peace. Thy tend'rer Thoughts,</l>
               <l>The Wife's best Ornament, I knew were buried</l>
               <l>In a Plebeian Grave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Plebeian Grave?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Fool that I was, I flatter'd thy vain Sorrows,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="52"/>Indulg'd their weak Excess, and rais'd, I find,</l>
               <l>Imaginary Rivals in the Tomb.</l>
               <l>But never more, <hi>Creusa,</hi> never more</l>
               <l>Shalt thou affront my ill-requited Fondness.</l>
               <l>I will destroy that Pageant of thy Passion,</l>
               <l>Tear from that Idol Shrine th'insulting Wreaths,</l>
               <l>And cancel thy mock Worship.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Queen,</l>
               <l>Retire a while.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Be gone.—Insulting Tyrant,</l>
               <l>Touch but a Wreath that's sacred to <hi>Nicander,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And by pale <hi>Hecate</hi>'s awful Rites I swear</l>
               <l>Thy Life shall pay the Forfeit; nay the Lives</l>
               <l>Of thy whole dastard Race.—Plebeian Grave!</l>
               <l>Had that Plebeian liv'd, Imperial <hi>Xuthus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had crouch'd beneath his Feet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>O would to Heaven</l>
               <l>This scepter'd Arm could raise him from the Earth,</l>
               <l>That thou might'st see how infamous a Slave</l>
               <l>Thou dar'st prefer to <hi>Xuthus.</hi>—Come, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We leave her to her Follies. Look not on her,</l>
               <l>She merits not thy Tenderness. Away.</l>
               <l>If Reason should again resume its Seat</l>
               <l>We may expect her at the Banquet. Come,</l>
               <l>All here must be our Guests.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exeunt</hi> Xuthus, Ilyssus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </stage>
            <stage>Creusa, Phorbas, <hi>and</hi> Lycea <hi>stay.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Curb not thy Passion, give it Vent, great Queen,</l>
               <l>And let it burst in Thunder on thy Foes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="46" facs="53"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>It shall, by Heaven it shall.—I thought till now</l>
               <l>My Griefs were sacred, but this Monster dares</l>
               <l>Insult even Misery itself.—O <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Forgive me if my Tears will force a Passage.—</l>
               <l>Now, they are gone, and I will weep no more.</l>
               <l>Come, faithful Counsellor of Vengeance, come,</l>
               <l>Instruct me how to act, steel all my Soul;</l>
               <l>Let not Remorse or Pity's Coward Voice,</l>
               <l>The Bane of noble Deeds, intrude to cross us.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander</hi>'s injur'd Ghost shall aid our Counsels.</l>
               <l>Say, shall he die?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Not yet, first be his Schemes</l>
               <l>Abortive all, his politic Designs,</l>
               <l>Then let him die despis'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Agreed; but how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Now at the Banquet may we crush at once</l>
               <l>His full blown hopes. The fatal Cause remov'd,</l>
               <l>Th' Effect of course must cease.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>What Cause?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>The Boy.</l>
               <l>I see thou shudder'st at it: but, great Queen,</l>
               <l>Hear but the cogent Reasons I shall offer</l>
               <l>And thou wilt think as I do. For the Boy</l>
               <l>Heav'n knows I wish to spare him, but no Means</l>
               <l>No earthly Means but this can curse compleatly</l>
               <l>This politic Designer. Doubtless long</l>
               <l>This fav'rite Scheme to place on <hi>Athens'</hi> Throne</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="54"/>His hated Race, has labour'd in his Breast,</l>
               <l>And all his Hours employ'd. On this alone</l>
               <l>He builds the firm Foundation of his Peace,</l>
               <l>His Happiness to come. His Death were nothing,</l>
               <l>He knows his Friends, the Minions of his Fortune,</l>
               <l>He knows all <hi>Greece,</hi> such is their Dread and Awe</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Delphi</hi>'s Shrine, will join in the Support</l>
               <l>Of this deceitful Claim; and that firm Hope</l>
               <l>Will make him triumph ev'n in Death, and laugh</l>
               <l>At our too shallow Vengeance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Laugh he shall not.</l>
               <l>No, I will punish home.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>You cannot punish</l>
               <l>By any Means but this. And know, great Queen,</l>
               <l>I have a Poison of such subtile Force,</l>
               <l>(Why do'st thou start?) of such amazing Strength,</l>
               <l>Yet so peculiar in its Operation,</l>
               <l>That it shall seem the Surfeit of the Feast,</l>
               <l>Not we have done the Deed. At least shall seem so</l>
               <l>To all but <hi>Xuthus'</hi> self; for he methinks</l>
               <l>Should know the Truth, at least suspect it strongly,</l>
               <l>And yet not dare Revenge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I cannot bear it;</l>
               <l>Howe'er we fail in our Revenge; my <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Boy must live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Good Heav'n! is this <hi>Creusa?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is this the vengeful Queen who would not hear</l>
               <l>Remorse or Pity's Voice?—Farewel then <hi>Athens;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yes, my poor Country, thou must sink enslav'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="55"/>To foreign Tyrants. She who should defend</l>
               <l>Thy Rights, thy Liberties, stands tamely by</l>
               <l>And sees the Yoke impos'd, nay smiles to see it:</l>
               <l>Thy Queen, the last of her illustrious Line,</l>
               <l>Consents to thy Destruction.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Never, <hi>Phorbas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do what thou wilt. With this last parting Pang</l>
               <l>I give him to thy Rage.—Yet oh, beware</l>
               <l>I see him not again. One Look from him</l>
               <l>Would baffle all thy Schemes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Now at the Banquet</l>
               <l>Will we infuse the Draught, ev'n in the Cup</l>
               <l>Which the King's self presents to his young Heir</l>
               <l>In Token of Election.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, good <hi>Phorbas.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Already have I for the just Design</l>
               <l>Suborn'd a faithful Slave. Nay, should it fail,</l>
               <l>I have a trusty Band, a chosen few,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Athenian</hi> Souls who scorn to bow the Knee</l>
               <l>To any foreign Lord; these will I place</l>
               <l>At the Pavilion Doors, if need require,</l>
               <l>To second our Attempt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Yet stay, good <hi>Pherbas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How kindly did he seem to sympathize</l>
               <l>With my Distress! nay almost chid the King,</l>
               <l>When his loud Rage—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>He had been taught his Lesson.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="56"/>'Twas all Design, all Artifice to work</l>
               <l>Upon a Woman's Weakness.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Think'st thou so?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>I do. But, O my Queen, be more than Woman,</l>
               <l>Conquer this Foible of thy Sex.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Heav'n knows</l>
               <l>How much it costs to do it.—Go then, <hi>Phorbas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I cannot bid thee prosper.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Phorbas.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Thou know'st not what I feel.—Haste, call him back.—</l>
               <l>No, stay—I think the Bitterness is past,</l>
               <l>And I can bear it now. Lend me thy Arm,</l>
               <l>I would retire, <hi>Lycea.</hi>—Yet from what</l>
               <l>Should I retire? I cannot from myself!—</l>
               <l>O Boy, thou art reveng'd; whate'er thou suffer'st</l>
               <l>Is light, to what thy Murd'ress feels!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <trailer>The End of the Third ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <pb n="50" facs="57"/>
            <head>ACT IV. <hi>The Laurel Grove.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>PHORBAS <hi>and Athenians.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>THIS Way, my Friends; at the Pavilion Doors</l>
               <l>Stand ready arm'd, that if we need your Aid</l>
               <l>You may observe the Sign, and crush at once</l>
               <l>These vile Usurpers on the Rights of <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I hope we want ye not.—I must be hid</l>
               <l>A while, lest <hi>Xuthus</hi> should suspect my Presence.</l>
               <l>The Queen too may repent, I'll therefore shun her <hi>Aside.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till the Deed's done, irrevocably done. <hi>Aside.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—But stir not till I come.—What Noise is that?</l>
               <l>Retire, my Friends, the Temple's Postern Door</l>
               <l>Grates on its Hinge.—Be secret, and we prosper.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt severally.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> ALETES <hi>and</hi> PYTHIA.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>This Quarrel was unlucky. A slight Breach</l>
               <l>Had lent my Purpose Strength; but wrought thus high</l>
               <l>It may defeat our Hopes. She cannot now</l>
               <l>With Ease recede from her too rash Resolves,</l>
               <l>At least not unsuspected. Did she, say'st thou,</l>
               <l>Reject thy Message?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="51" facs="58"/>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Scarcely did she pay</l>
               <l>The decent Dues my sacred Office claims.</l>
               <l>And when I prest her more, with sullen Pride</l>
               <l>She silently withdrew.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>See her I must.</l>
               <l>Where went she?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>To the Shades which over-hang</l>
               <l>Th' Aonian Fount.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>I will pursue her thither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>It may not be, for now I know thy Secret</l>
               <l>'Tis my turn to be prudent, Know'st thou not</l>
               <l>Thou should'st be cautious, nor expose thyself</l>
               <l>To prying Eyes? I heard her, as she pass'd,</l>
               <l>In broken Whispers bid <hi>Lycea</hi> haste</l>
               <l>To <hi>Phorbas,</hi> and inform that trusty Friend</l>
               <l>That she would wait him in the Laurel Grove.</l>
               <l>Here then thou may'st surprise them both, and crown</l>
               <l>At once thy whole Design.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Thou counsell'st well,</l>
               <l>And I will guide me by thy kind Advice.</l>
               <l>O <hi>Pythia,</hi> how did every thing conspire</l>
               <l>To give me hopes that I should place the Boy</l>
               <l>Secure on <hi>Athens'</hi> Throne, unknown to all</l>
               <l>But those whom Fate had made his firmest Friends.</l>
               <l>The very Means I us'd to make it sure</l>
               <l>Have been most adverse to the Cause I labour'd.</l>
               <l>Had I relied on <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Piety,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="59"/>Nor mention'd <hi>Aeolus,</hi> Success were mine.</l>
               <l>And let me hope it still. What most I fear</l>
               <l>Is the Queen's Warmth of Passion. To which end</l>
               <l>I must proceed with Tenderness, and hide</l>
               <l>For some short time <hi>Ilyssus</hi> from her Knowledge.</l>
               <l>I have unnumber'd Cautions to premise</l>
               <l>Which her o'erflowing Joy may haply ruin.</l>
               <l>The Banquet, is it ready?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>It has long</l>
               <l>In vain expected its illustrious Guests.</l>
               <l>The King already has forgot his Rage,</l>
               <l>And hopes returning Thought may move the Queen</l>
               <l>To equal Amity: He therefore finds</l>
               <l>Continual Causes to delay the Feast.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Retire. Perhaps 'tis she; I hear the Steps</l>
               <l>Of some who move this way.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Pythia.</stage>
               <l>What means he here?</l>
               <l>Why art thou absent from the Banquet, Youth?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> ILYSSUS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>It has no Joys for me. I fear, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou and the <hi>Pythia</hi> have most foully play'd</l>
               <l>For my Advancement.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Ha!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Where are the Parents</l>
               <l>Whom thou didst promise to my Hopes? Alas</l>
               <l>I find no Parents here, no kind Regards,</l>
               <l>No inexpressive Fondness. Stern Debate,</l>
               <l>And foul Dissention kindle here their Torch</l>
               <l>To usher in my Greatness. Ev'n <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="60"/>Whose Tenderness I know not how alarm'd</l>
               <l>My throbbing Heart with Hopes, and Doubts, and Fears,</l>
               <l>Unfelt before, ev'n she has taught her Eyes</l>
               <l>To look with Strangeness on me. The good King,</l>
               <l>Who yet withdraws not his Protection from me,</l>
               <l>Seems lost in anxious Thought.—Unkind <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Art thou the Cause of this? Say, am I sprung</l>
               <l>Of Race <hi>Aeolian?</hi> For by Heaven I swear,</l>
               <l>By that pure Fountain of immortal Truth;</l>
               <l>I will not brook Deceit. I will again,</l>
               <l>Howe'er the glitt'ring Mischief tempt my Youth,</l>
               <l>Become that humble unknown Thing I was,</l>
               <l>Rather than wear a Crown by Falshood gain'd.</l>
               <l>Speak then, and give me Ease.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>My dearest Boy—</l>
               <l>His Virtue charms me, tho' it may prevent <hi>Aside.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His own Success. O happy, happy <hi>Athens, Aside.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To gain a King like him, whose honest Soul <hi>Aside.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Starts at imagin'd Fraud! <hi>Aside.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Speak on, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And do not by that Look of Tenderness,</l>
               <l>And murm'ring to thyself, alarm me more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>What should I speak? This very Morn, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This very Morn I told thee a few Hours</l>
               <l>Would shew thee what thou wert; but thy Impatience</l>
               <l>Brooks not that short Delay. It seems <hi>Aletes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has lost his usual Credit with <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n with the Youth his anxious Care has form'd.</l>
               <l>Think'st thou the Man who taught thy feeling Heart</l>
               <l>To start at Falshood, would himself commit</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="61"/>The Fraud thou shudder'st at? What have I done,</l>
               <l>Which should induce thee to a Thought so base?</l>
               <l>Did e'er my Precepts contradict my Heart?</l>
               <l>Did I e'er teach a Virtue I not practis'd?</l>
               <l>—I see thou art confounded. Know then, Youth,</l>
               <l>I blame not thy Impatience, nay I praise</l>
               <l>That Modesty which can so soon resume</l>
               <l>Its Seat, when all things round are big with Wonder.</l>
               <l>Ere Night thou shalt know all; till then, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Behave as <hi>Athens'</hi> King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>O good <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Forgive my Rashness. Yes, I know thee honest</l>
               <l>As Truth itself, and know the wond'rous Debt</l>
               <l>I owe thy Goodness. Yet, if thou confess</l>
               <l>That I have Reason for these anxious Cares,</l>
               <l>Thou wilt permit me still to question thee.</l>
               <l>Nay look upon me whilst I speak to thee.</l>
               <l>Perhaps thou hast some secret Cause, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For all that kind Attention thou hast shewn me,</l>
               <l>From Infancy till now? Why do'st thou turn</l>
               <l>Thy Eyes to Earth? 'Tis plain thou hast a Cause:</l>
               <l>Thou know'st from whom I spring; how can'st thou else</l>
               <l>With Confidence assert, that yet ere Night</l>
               <l>I shall know all?—Say this at least, <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall the Queen's Anger cease?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>It shall, <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n now I wait her here; on what Design</l>
               <l>I must not yet inform thee. The next Time</l>
               <l>Thou shalt behold her thou wilt find a Change</l>
               <l>Incredible indeed, from Rage to Fondness,</l>
               <l>From cold Reserve to Tears of bursting Joy.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ilyssus <hi>is going to speak eagerly.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <pb n="55" facs="62"/>
               <l>—Ask me no more.—Yet something didst thou say</l>
               <l>Relating to the Cause which fix'd me here</l>
               <l>Thy Guardian, thy Instructor, and—the Time</l>
               <l>Will come, when thou shalt know it all, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And bless my Memory.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Thou weep'st, <hi>Aletes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Tears will mingle too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Forbear, and leave me.</l>
               <l>Yet stay a while, for now perhaps we part</l>
               <l>To meet no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>No more! Thou wilt not leave me</l>
               <l>When most I want thy Care! 'Twas my first Thought,</l>
               <l>'Twas the first Boon I ask'd of the good King,</l>
               <l>That thou might'st be my kind Instructor still.</l>
               <l>He prais'd my Gratitude, and I had promis'd</l>
               <l>To bring him to thy Cottage. He himself</l>
               <l>Shall be a Suitor to thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Thou hast ask'd</l>
               <l>Thou know'st not what: It cannot be, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Xuthus</hi> and <hi>Aletes</hi> e'er should meet</l>
               <l>On terms of Amity. The Smiles of Greatness</l>
               <l>To me have lost their Value. For thy Love</l>
               <l>I could do much, and to be sever'd from thee</l>
               <l>Pulls at my Heart-strings. But resistless Fate</l>
               <l>Has fix'd its Seal, and we must part for ever,</l>
               <l>How hard soe'er it seem. Thy Youth will soon,</l>
               <l>Amidst the busy Scenes of active Greatness,</l>
               <l>Forget its Monitor: But I must bear</l>
               <l>In hopeless Solitude the Pangs of Absence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="63"/>Till Thought shall be no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>O heav'nly Powers</l>
               <l>Then there is something dreadful yet conceal'd.</l>
               <l>I cannot part from thee in Ignorance.</l>
               <l>Tell me, <hi>Aletes.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Would I could! But now</l>
               <l>It must not be.—Haste to the Banquet, Youth,</l>
               <l>Thy Duty calls thee thither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Go I cannot,</l>
               <l>Till thou assur'st me we shall meet again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>If possible we will. If not, remember,</l>
               <l>When thou shalt know thyself, that on thyself</l>
               <l>Thy Fate depends; that Virtue, Glory, Happiness,</l>
               <l>Are close connected, and their sad Reverse</l>
               <l>Is Vice, is Pain, is Infamy.—Alas!</l>
               <l>These were the Lessons of thy private Life,</l>
               <l>This I have told thee oft, but my fond Tongue</l>
               <l>Runs o'er its former Precepts, and forgets</l>
               <l>Thou now must mount a Throne; a larger Scene</l>
               <l>Of Duty opens.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Yet the tender Friend,</l>
               <l>Who should direct me, leaves me to myself.</l>
               <l>Can'st thou abandon me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Would Fate permit</l>
               <l>I would attend thee still. But oh, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whate'er becomes of me, when thou shall reach</l>
               <l>That envied Pinacle of earthly Greatness,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="64"/>Where faithful Monitors but rarely follow,</l>
               <l>Ev'n there, amidst the kindest Smiles of Fortune,</l>
               <l>Forget not thou wert once distress'd and friendless.</l>
               <l>Be strictly just; but yet, like Heaven, with Mercy</l>
               <l>Temper thy Justice. From thy purged Ear</l>
               <l>Banish base Flattery, and spurn the Wretch</l>
               <l>Who would persuade thee thou art more than Man;</l>
               <l>Weak, erring, selfish Man, endued with Power</l>
               <l>To be the Minister of public Good.</l>
               <l>If Conquest charm thee, and the Pride of War</l>
               <l>Blaze on thy Sight, remember thou art placed</l>
               <l>The Guardian of Mankind, nor build thy Fame</l>
               <l>On Rapines, and on Murders. Should soft Peace</l>
               <l>Invite to Luxury, the pleasing Bane</l>
               <l>Of happy Kingdoms, know from thy Example</l>
               <l>The Bliss or Woe of nameless Millions springs,</l>
               <l>Their Virtue, or their Vice. Nor think by Laws</l>
               <l>To curb licentious Man; those Laws alone</l>
               <l>Can bend the headstrong Many to their Yoke,</l>
               <l>Which make it present Int'rest to obey them.</l>
               <l>O Boy!—</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> PYTHIA <hi>hastily.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus!</hi> wherefore art thou here?</l>
               <l>The King expects thee, and the Banquet waits.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>I cannot go.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Thou must; thy Fate depends</l>
               <l>Upon thy Absence now. The Queen approaches.</l>
               <l>After the Banquet I again will see thee,</l>
               <l>And thou shalt know the whole. I will by Heaven.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Ilyssus.</stage>
               <l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="65"/>
                  <hi>Pythia</hi> away, and wait me in the Temple.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Pythia.</stage>
               <l>She saw them not; on her contracted Brow</l>
               <l>Sits brooding Care. She speaks! My Heart beats thick,</l>
               <l>And my Tongue trembles to perform its Office.</l>
               <l>Now Fate attend, and perfect thine own Work!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> CREUSA.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>To what have I consented!—Ha! who art thou</l>
               <l>That thus intrud'st on sacred Privacy,</l>
               <l>When the o'erburthen'd Mind unloads its Griefs,</l>
               <l>Its hoarded Miseries.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Thy better Genius!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>That Voice is sure familiar to my Ear!</l>
               <l>Who art thou, speak.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>One whom Adversity</l>
               <l>Has taught to know himself. I bring thee tidings</l>
               <l>Of an unhappy Man who wrong'd thee much,</l>
               <l>But much repented of the Wrongs he did thee;</l>
               <l>Of thy <hi>Nicander,</hi> Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nicander,</hi> say'st thou?</l>
               <l>O then thou art indeed my better Genius.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <l>Now, arm thy Soul for Wonders yet to come!</l>
               <l>Perhaps he lives.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>He lives?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Looking on him with Amazement.</stage>
            <sp>
               <pb n="59" facs="66"/>
               <speaker>ALETES.</speaker>
               <stage>After great Irresolution and Struggles with himself.</stage>
               <l>Behold him here!</l>
               <stage>She faints.</stage>
               <l>—What has my Rashness done?—The Blush of Life</l>
               <l>Has left her Cheek, the Pulse forgets to move.</l>
               <l>Where shall I turn? I cannot call for Aid,</l>
               <l>Nor can I leave her thus.—She breathes, she stirs!</l>
               <l>—Yes, yes, <hi>Creusa,</hi> thy <hi>Nicander</hi> lives,</l>
               <l>And he will catch at least this dear Embrace</l>
               <l>Tho' now thou art another's.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Gods!</l>
               <l>It is, it is <hi>Nicander,</hi> 'tis my Lord!</l>
               <l>O I am only thine, no Power on Earth</l>
               <l>Shall e'er divide us more.</l>
               <l>—It cannot be, my Senses all deceive me—</l>
               <l>And yet it is.—O let me gaze upon thee,</l>
               <l>Recall each Trace which marks thee for my own,</l>
               <l>And gives me back the Image of my Heart.</l>
               <l>How Time and Grief have chang'd thee! But my Love</l>
               <l>Can know no Change. My Lord, my Life, my Husband!</l>
               <l>Where hast thou wander'd? how hast thou been hid</l>
               <l>From Love's all-piercing Sight? the bloody Ruffians,</l>
               <l>How didst thou 'scape their Rage? or did they wreak</l>
               <l>Upon the helpless Innocent alone</l>
               <l>Their impious Vengeance?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Nor on me, nor him</l>
               <l>Did Vengeance fall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Does he too live?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>He does.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="60" facs="67"/>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <stage>Aside.</stage>
               <l>O honest <hi>Phorbas!</hi> Murder now is Virtue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>The fabled Murder was all Stratagem</l>
               <l>Contriv'd for thy dear sake; no impious Ruffians</l>
               <l>Pursued our Steps, I found that I had wrong'd thee</l>
               <l>Beyond redress, nor knew another means</l>
               <l>But by my Death to save thee from Dishonor.</l>
               <l>Despair I thought might conquer Love, and thou</l>
               <l>Once more be <hi>Athens'</hi> Pride. The precious Charge</l>
               <l>Forbad a real Death, I therefore stain'd</l>
               <l>With Blood my well-known Garments, which produc'd.—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>A curst'd Effect.—But I have nearer Fears.</l>
               <l>How cam'st thou hither? wherefore to these Shades?</l>
               <l>The Boy, where is he?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Far from hence—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Thank Heaven!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>He lives in Peace and Safety.—What disturbs thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Nothing—I dare not tell him what I feared,</l>
               <l>His honest Breast might shudder at the Guilt,</l>
               <l>Tho' now it be more needful. — The dear Boy,</l>
               <l>Say, is he brave?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>As Woman could desire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>And form'd like thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>His Person far exceeds</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="68"/>What my most vig'rous Youth could boast, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And his firm Mind is Wisdom's aged Strength</l>
               <l>With all Youth's Graces soften'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis too much.</l>
               <l>O happy Mother! Call'st thou him <hi>Nicander?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>No, <hi>Ion,</hi> 'twas the Name the Matron chose,</l>
               <l>Who gave him to my Care.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Then <hi>Ion</hi> be it.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ion</hi> shall reign in <hi>Athens.</hi> Know'st thou, Love,</l>
               <l>The curs'd Design which this <hi>Aeolian</hi> here,</l>
               <l>And the vile Maid —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>The Priestess, it should seem,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Xuthus</hi> has conspir'd to fix his Race</l>
               <l>On <hi>Athens'</hi> Throne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>But never shall his Race</l>
               <l>That Scepter wield.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>It never shall, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I have a Means —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <stage>Aside.</stage>
               <l>My Means, thank Heaven, is surer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>But I will tell thee all from first to last.</l>
               <l>Hear then and weigh my Words, for Fate is in them.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xuthus,</hi> th' <hi>Athenian</hi> King—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I think not of him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="62" facs="69"/>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Beware of that. Whate'er thou think'st, <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xuthus</hi> must still reign on, thy Lord and Husband.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xuthus</hi> my Lord! then what art thou, <hi>Nicander?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do'st thou despise me for a Crime thyself</l>
               <l>Hast forc'd me to commit? My Soul was thine</l>
               <l>Ev'n when I gave my Hand, and still remains</l>
               <l>Untainted, undefil'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>I know it well,</l>
               <l>Thou dearest, best of Women.—My torn Heart</l>
               <l>Drops Blood while I propose it, yet we must,</l>
               <l>We must for ever part.—Forbear, <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That killing Look strikes thro' me.—Think, O think,</l>
               <l>What in this Age of Absence I have borne,</l>
               <l>How combated each tender Thought, and liv'd</l>
               <l>For thy dear Sake a Victim to Despair.</l>
               <l>But now if thou consent'st, all, all is mine,</l>
               <l>And I forgive my Fate.—The dear, dear Boy,</l>
               <l>I have a Means to place him on the Throne</l>
               <l>Secure as we could wish.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Secure he shall be,</l>
               <l>I will proclaim him to the World as mine,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Athens</hi> shall with Joy receive its Sov'reign;</l>
               <l>The Tyrant <hi>Xuthus</hi> shall be taught to fear</l>
               <l>A Master's Frown.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Thy Rashness, my <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May ruin all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I will be rash, if this</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="70"/>Be Rashness, to declare to Earth, to Heav'n,</l>
               <l>A Mother's Heart-felt Joy, whose only Child</l>
               <l>Snatch'd from the Grave unhop'd for comes to claim,</l>
               <l>With every Grace and every Virtue crown'd,</l>
               <l>Th' Imperial Seat of his great Ancestors.</l>
               <l>And shall we wait a Means?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>We need not wait;</l>
               <l>For by my Care th' important Means is found</l>
               <l>Already, and no human Power but thine</l>
               <l>Can hinder our Success. I would have hid</l>
               <l>The Secret from thee till thy wish'd Consent</l>
               <l>Had giv'n my Purpose Strength, but thou defeat'st</l>
               <l>My utmost Caution, and wilt force me tell thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus</hi> is young <hi>Ion!</hi>—Ha! <hi>Creusa!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou art not mad! Good Heaven! how her Eye fixes!</l>
               <l>What have I done? what said, which could attack</l>
               <l>The Seats of Sense with this amazing Force?</l>
               <l>My Wife, my Queen, O speak?—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Off, touch me not,</l>
               <l>Thou can'st not bring Relief.—O I am curs'd</l>
               <l>Beyond all Power of Aid. Thou too art curs'd</l>
               <l>And know'st it not.—He dies, he dies, <hi>Nicander!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Amazement! who?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>O had he not been mine,</l>
               <l>His Youth, his Softness, each attracting Grace—</l>
               <l>I should have staid whole Ages ere in Thought</l>
               <l>I had consented to so damn'd a Deed.</l>
               <l>Tears, Tears, why burst ye not?—But what have I</l>
               <l>To do with Tears? those are for tender Mothers.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="71"/>The Tigress weeps not o'er her mangled Prey.—</l>
               <l>He dies, he dies, <hi>Nicander.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Who? <hi>Ilyssus?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Speak, speak, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phorbas</hi> urg'd the Deed,</l>
               <l>And I consented; at the Feast he dies</l>
               <l>By Poison.—O my Soul!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Fly then, this Instant</l>
               <l>Perhaps thou may'st prevent it, as thou cam'st</l>
               <l>He parted hence.—I knew not to his Death!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>I go, I fly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Yet stay, thy Rashness there,</l>
               <l>If Fate has sav'd him, may undo us yet.</l>
               <l>—The <hi>Pythia!</hi> true, the <hi>Pythia</hi> shall rush in</l>
               <l>To stop the fatal Banquet, and declare</l>
               <l>The Feast unhallow'd; at this lucky Moment</l>
               <l>She waits me in the Temple.—Stay, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exit</hi> Nicander.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>Pythia,</hi> no; I will myself outstrip</l>
               <l>The Lightning's Speed. Whatever be th' Event,</l>
               <l>'Tis not too late to die.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The End of the Fourth</hi> ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <pb n="65" facs="72"/>
            <head>ACT V. <hi>The Laurel Grove.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>PHORBAS and LYCEA.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>O Earth! O Heaven! O wretched, wretched <hi>Athens!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Speak on, <hi>Lycea;</hi> wherefore art thou silent?</l>
               <l>Why do'st thou lead me to this secret Shade?</l>
               <l>What mean thy flowing Tears?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>The Queen, the Queen!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Say, what of her?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>I know not, all to me</l>
               <l>Is Terror and Confusion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>What thou know'st</l>
               <l>Relate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>She sent me forth to seek thee, <hi>Phorbas;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I found thee not, but met at my Return</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creusa</hi>'s self. Despair was in her Eyes,</l>
               <l>With hasty Steps she shot impatie<gap resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters" rend="content:••">
                     <desc>illegible</desc>
                  </gap> by me,</l>
               <l>Nor listen'd when I spake. I follow'd wond'ring,</l>
               <l>And enter'd the Pavilion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="66" facs="73"/>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>The Pavilion?</l>
               <l>Why, went she to the Banquet?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Eager went,</l>
               <l>Despair and Anguish mixing on her Look.</l>
               <l>But, O good Heaven, how chang'd was that Despair</l>
               <l>To inexpressive Joy, when from the Croud</l>
               <l>She learnt <hi>Ilyssus</hi> had delay'd the Feast,</l>
               <l>And won the King once more to ask her Presence,</l>
               <l>"Where is he? let me clasp him to my Breast,"</l>
               <l>She cried; "I now no longer will resist</l>
               <l>"Heaven's high command." Imperial <hi>Xuthus</hi> rose</l>
               <l>With Transport to receive her, and loud Shouts</l>
               <l>Proclaim'd the People's Joy. When, Death to Sight!</l>
               <l>Eternal Pain to Memory! the Slave</l>
               <l>Presents the Goblets; Fill, she cried, a third,</l>
               <l>I too will hail <hi>Ilyssus</hi> King of <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But first all swear, swear by immortal <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By the far-darting God who here presides,</l>
               <l>And the chaste Guardian of our native Fanes,</l>
               <l>Swear here, swear all, and binding be the Oath,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus</hi> only shall be <hi>Athens'</hi> King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>What could she mean?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Attentive <hi>Xuthus</hi> caught</l>
               <l>With Joy the happy Omen, and all swore</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus</hi> only should be <hi>Athens'</hi> King.</l>
               <l>This done, I saw her from <hi>Ilyssus'</hi> Hand</l>
               <l>Snatch the dire Goblet, and to him resign</l>
               <l>Her own untouch'd. The Slave who mix'd the Draught</l>
               <l>Turn'd oale and trembled, I with eager Zeal</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="74"/>Press'd forward, but in vain; she firmly grasp'd</l>
               <l>The Bowl, and smiling drank it to the Dregs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>The Poison, ha?—I knew her foolish Fondness</l>
               <l>Would start at Murder's Name. But wherefore die?</l>
               <l>Why turn upon herself her impious Rage?</l>
               <l>'Twas Madness all; or else some new Contrivance,</l>
               <l>Some fresh <hi>Aeolian</hi> Fraud.—I care not what.</l>
               <l>I yet will blast their Schemes.—Yes, let her die,</l>
               <l>By her own Folly perish. <hi>Athens</hi> still</l>
               <l>Survives, and shall survive.—I must be sudden.</l>
               <l>She doubtless will betray me to the King,</l>
               <l>And cut off ev'n this last Resource. <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be secret, and thy Country shall be free.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Were it not better, <hi>Phorbas,</hi> first to see her.</l>
               <l>Perhaps some Secret unreveal'd may lurk</l>
               <l>Beneath this Show of unexampled Rashness.</l>
               <l>She left the Banquet soon, and with the <hi>Pythia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Enter'd the Temple.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>With the <hi>Pythia,</hi> say'st thou?</l>
               <l>Then there is Mischief toward.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Yet now alone</l>
               <l>We may surprize her, for I saw the Maid</l>
               <l>Quick from the Fane return with hasty Steps</l>
               <l>As if dispatch'd on some important Message,</l>
               <l>Perhaps to find thee out. Sure thou should'st see her.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>And perish, ha?—No, no, my sacred Country,</l>
               <l>Too much already have I been deceiv'd;</l>
               <l>I will not leave thee in a Woman's Power.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="75"/>—Yet hold, <hi>Lycea</hi> may inform her of them</l>
               <l>And my Designs prove yet abortive. Maid,</l>
               <l>Thy Presence may be needful.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Mine? Good Heaven,</l>
               <l>In what? <hi>Creusa</hi> will require my Aid;</l>
               <l>At least my Tears are due to my poor Queen</l>
               <l>In her last Moments.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHORBAS.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, she wants them not;</l>
               <l>I know the Poison's Force too well, <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To fear a Death so sudden. This Way, Maid;</l>
               <l>Nay, thou must go; I shall have Business for thee,</l>
               <l>Some secret Message to the Queen, <hi>Lycea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which thou alone can'st bear.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> PYTHIA <hi>and</hi> NICANDER.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas he, I saw him and <hi>Lycea</hi> with him.</l>
               <l>Sure he should be inform'd?—Thou hear'st me not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>This Action of the Queen sits near my Heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>She bade me tell thee.—But why waste we Time,</l>
               <l>Thou now may'st enter at the Postern Gate</l>
               <l>Unseen by all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Why did'st thou not rush in, and stop the Feast?</l>
               <l>Thy speedy Presence there had sav'd us all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>What could I do? The Queen was there already</l>
               <l>And all seem'd Peace and Joy; could I suspect</l>
               <l>That Poison lurk'd beneath so fair a seeming?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="69" facs="76"/>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>She breaks thro' my Designs.—Unhappy Woman!</l>
               <l>My Soul bleeds for her, and Confusion hangs</l>
               <l>On every rising Thought.—The dear, dear Boy!—</l>
               <l>Where is he, at the Banquet still?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>He is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>And where <hi>Creusa?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>I already told thee,</l>
               <l>But thou regard'st not, in the Temple's Gloom</l>
               <l>Retir'd she sits, expecting thy Approach.</l>
               <l>We there may settle all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>I fear her much.</l>
               <l>Thou seest her Passions are too near concern'd</l>
               <l>To be of use to us; thy cooler Sense</l>
               <l>Must here direct us. Does the Poison's Power</l>
               <l>Affect her yet?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Not yet; I would have tried</l>
               <l>Some powerful Antidote to quell its Force;</l>
               <l>But she refuses Life, and only begs</l>
               <l>To see her Son and thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>I will attend</l>
               <l>Upon the Instant. But first hear me, <hi>Pythia;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou seest on what a Precipice we stand,</l>
               <l>It were in vain to hope we could conceal</l>
               <l>The Truth from <hi>Xuthus,</hi> from the rest we may;</l>
               <l>'Tis thy task therefore—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="77"/>
               <speaker>PYTHIAS.</speaker>
               <l>What? to own the Fraud,</l>
               <l>And publish to the King that <hi>Delphi</hi>'s Shrine</l>
               <l>Is not oracular. Ha!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>To the King</l>
               <l>'Twere better sure to publish the Deceit</l>
               <l>Than to the World; and where's the Means but this</l>
               <l>To hide it? By <hi>Creusa</hi>'s Art thou say'st</l>
               <l>He is already bound in solemn Oaths</l>
               <l>To leave <hi>Ilyssus</hi> Heir to <hi>Athens'</hi> Throne.</l>
               <l>Can'st thou not add still stronger Oaths, or ere</l>
               <l>Thou do'st reveal the Secret of our Fate?</l>
               <l>Then who shall dare to break them? shall the King?</l>
               <l>Thou know'st his scrup'lous Piety extends</l>
               <l>Almost to Weakness. What should tempt him to it?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creusa</hi> dead can frame no Schemes against him;</l>
               <l>The Boy to him alone must owe his Greatness;</l>
               <l>And for <hi>Nicander,</hi> never more shall <hi>Greece</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hear his forgotten Name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>It must be so;</l>
               <l>And yet—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>What yet? to <hi>Phorbas</hi> thou with ease</l>
               <l>May'st own the Truth; he will not start at Fraud</l>
               <l>In sacred things.—But see, the Queen approaches</l>
               <l>Impatient of our Stay. She changes not!</l>
               <l>The Bloom of Health is still upon her Cheek!</l>
               <l>Fain would I hope—But Hopes, alas, are vain.—</l>
               <l>What hast thou done, <hi>Creusa?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>CREUSA <hi>entering.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Sav'd <hi>Ilyssus!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="71" facs="78"/>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Thou might'st have liv'd with Honor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Liv'd! good Heaven!</l>
               <l>I start, I tremble at the Thoughts of Life.</l>
               <l>Can'st thou reflect on what I had design'd,</l>
               <l>On what I am, on what, alas, I have been,</l>
               <l>And not perceive Death was my only Refuge?</l>
               <l>—Am I not <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Wife, and what art thou?</l>
               <l>O had'st thou seen the Torments of my Soul,</l>
               <l>When in one hasty Moment it ran o'er</l>
               <l>The Business of an Age, weigh'd all Events,</l>
               <l>Saw <hi>Xuthus,</hi> Thee, <hi>Ilyssus, Athens</hi> bleed</l>
               <l>In one promiscuous Carnage!—Light at length</l>
               <l>Burst thro' the Gloom, and Heaven's own Voice proclaim'd</l>
               <l>One Victim might suffice.—</l>
               <l>For <hi>Xuthus</hi> Honor strove, and mightier Love</l>
               <l>Assum'd <hi>Nicander</hi>'s Cause. Who then could fall?</l>
               <l>Could <hi>Xuthus?</hi> could <hi>Nicander?</hi>—no; <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Would thou had'st been less kind!—But, O my Queen,</l>
               <l>To blame thee now were vain.—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>To blame? 'tis Praise,</l>
               <l>'Tis Triumph I demand. He lives! he reigns!</l>
               <l>Young <hi>Ion</hi> lives! young <hi>Ion</hi> reigns in <hi>Athens!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O bring him, <hi>Pythia,</hi> bring him to my Arms;</l>
               <l>Let me but pour a last sad Blessing o'er him,</l>
               <l>And Death has lost its Terrors.</l>
               <l>How now, <hi>Lycea?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> LYCEA <hi>hastily.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>LYCEA.</speaker>
               <l>Mighty Queen, I know not</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="79"/>If thy Command would authorize th' Attempt,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Phorbas</hi> with an arm'd <hi>Athenian</hi> Band</l>
               <l>Now enters the Pavilion to destroy</l>
               <l>The King and young <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Earth and Heaven!</l>
               <l>What say'st thou, Maid?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>O let me fly to save him,</l>
               <l>Here shall their Poinards—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>Rest thou there, <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy Embaffies to-day have prov'd too fatal.</l>
               <l>My Life for his I save him from the Stroke,</l>
               <l>And on the Instant send him to thy Arms.</l>
               <l>Now, Fate, be doubly mine!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Off, let me go, I will not be restrain'd.</l>
               <l>They tear him piecemeal!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Patience, mighty Queen!</l>
               <l>What Man can do <hi>Nicander</hi> will perform.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>He is a Father only to my Child,</l>
               <l>He cannot tell them what a Mother feels.</l>
               <l>—<hi>Phorbas</hi> was born the Curse of me and mine.</l>
               <l>I might have known to what his impious Rage</l>
               <l>Would urge him on, and should have first inform'd him.</l>
               <l>—Gods! must I never know sweet Peace again,</l>
               <l>Not even in Death have Rest!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Behold who comes</l>
               <l>To bless thee ere thou diest, and cease to murmur</l>
               <l>At Heaven's high Will.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb n="73" facs="80"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> ILYSSUS.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>It is, it is <hi>Ilyssus</hi>—</l>
               <l>My Son, my Son!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>Good Heavens! and do I live</l>
               <l>To see a Parent melt in Fondness o'er me!</l>
               <l>—<hi>Aletes</hi> saved me from the Soldiers' Arms,</l>
               <l>And bade me fly to find a Mother here.</l>
               <l>Art thou indeed that Mother, mighty Queen!</l>
               <l>And may I call thee so? Thou art, thy Looks</l>
               <l>Thy Tears, thy kind Embrace, all, all proclaim</l>
               <l>The Truth—O let me thus, thus on my Knees—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Rise, rise, my Child; I am, I am thy Mother.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>O sacred Sound, <hi>Ilyssus</hi> is no more</l>
               <l>That outcast Youth. A Mother, and a Queen</l>
               <l>He finds at once.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>But art thou safe, my Child?</l>
               <l>Hast thou no Wound?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>The old grey-headed Man,</l>
               <l>Who brought this Morn the News of thy Arrival,</l>
               <l>Had rais'd against my Breast his eager Sword,</l>
               <l>Defenceless I; when good <hi>Aletes</hi> came</l>
               <l>And snatch'd me from the Stroke. I would have staid,</l>
               <l>Unarm'd with him have staid, but his Command</l>
               <l>Was absolute, that I should fly to find,</l>
               <l>What I have found, a Mother!</l>
               <stage>Embracing her.</stage>
               <l>Yet, O Queen,</l>
               <l>Why am I thus encompass'd round with Wonder?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="81"/>May I not know this Riddle of my Fate?</l>
               <l>Why first condemn'd to pass my Infant Days</l>
               <l>In this obscure Retreat? If I am thine,</l>
               <l>Thy Son, illustrious Queen, sure I was born</l>
               <l>To Thrones, and Empires?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Thou art born to Thrones,</l>
               <l>And shalt in <hi>Athens</hi> reign.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>As <hi>Xuthus'</hi> Heir.</l>
               <l>Is <hi>Xuthus</hi> then my Sire? Forgive me, Queen,</l>
               <l>I have a thousand, and a thousand Doubts.</l>
               <l>Can <hi>Xuthus</hi> be my Sire?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <stage>Forbear, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Nor press thy Fate too far. When Time permits</l>
               <l>Thou shalt know all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Shalt know it now, <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not <hi>Xuthus</hi> is thy Sire, but that brave Man</l>
               <l>Who but this Instant snatch'd thee from thy Fate,</l>
               <l>And by that Act proclaim'd himself a Father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aletes?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>Not <hi>Aletes,</hi> but <hi>Nicander,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My wedded Lord, thy Sire!—And see, he comes</l>
               <l>To bless thee, and confirm the sacred Truth.</l>
               <l>—Good Heaven, he bleeds!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> NICANDER.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>To Death, to Death, <hi>Creusa.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Amid the Fray I met the Fate I sought for.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="82"/>All else is safe, and <hi>Xuthus</hi> now pursues</l>
               <l>A scatter'd Few, who fall beneath his Sword.</l>
               <l>—Where is my Boy?—Ye Guards of Innocence!</l>
               <l>How has he been beset, and how escap'd!</l>
               <l>—Where is my Boy, for I may own him now,</l>
               <l>And clasp him to my Breast, no more <hi>Aletes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The sage Instructor of a Youth unknown,</l>
               <l>But the dear Father weeping o'er his Child.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>O Sir, what Gratitude before inspir'd</l>
               <l>Let Duty pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>I have no Time to waste</l>
               <l>In Fondness now. Hear my last Words, <hi>Ilyssus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And bind them to thy heart. Thou still must live</l>
               <l>The Son of <hi>Xuthus.</hi> The good <hi>Pythia</hi> here</l>
               <l>Will tell thee all the Story of thy Fate:</l>
               <l>And may'st thou prosper as thou do'st obey</l>
               <l>Her sacred Counsel. <hi>Xuthus</hi> too must know</l>
               <l>The fatal Tale; but to the World beside</l>
               <l>It must be hid in Darkness.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Phorbas</hi> sure</stage>
               <l>Should be inform'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>NICANDER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phorbas</hi> has breath'd his last;</l>
               <l>And the brib'd Slave who mix'd the poisonous Draught</l>
               <l>Fell by this Hand.—<hi>Ilyssus,</hi> O farewel.</l>
               <l>I will not bid Adieu to thee, <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy Colour changes, and the Lamp of Life</l>
               <l>Fades in thy Eye; we soon shall meet again. —</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ilyssus,</hi> Oh!—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="79" facs="83"/>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>How hard he grasps my Hand!</l>
               <l>My Lord, my Father! Have I learn'd so late,</l>
               <l>To call thee by that Name, and must I lose,</l>
               <l>For ever lose?—Good Heaven, she grasps me too!</l>
               <l>What means it, <hi>Pythia?</hi> the cold Damps of Death</l>
               <l>Are on her.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CREUSA.</speaker>
               <l>O my Child, enquire no farther;</l>
               <l>'Tis fitting we should part. <hi>Lycea, Pythia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Intreat of <hi>Xuthus</hi>—yet I need not fear</l>
               <l>His Goodness, tho' I wrong'd him, foully wrong'd him,</l>
               <l>He yet will prove a Father to my Child,</l>
               <l>And from the World conceal the fatal Truth.</l>
               <l>O I am cold—what Bolts of Ice shoot thro' me!</l>
               <l>How my Limbs shiver!—Nearer yet, my Child,</l>
               <l>My Sight grows dim, and I could wish to gaze</l>
               <l>For ever on thee.—Oh, it will not be—</l>
               <l>Ev'n thou art lost, <hi>Ilyssus.</hi>—Oh—Farewel.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Dies.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ILYSSUS.</speaker>
               <l>She dies, she dies. Was I then only mock'd</l>
               <l>With a vain Dream of Bliss to be plung'd back</l>
               <l>In deeper Misery? Did I but hear</l>
               <l>The tender Name of Child breath'd fondly o'er me</l>
               <l>To make me feel what 'tis to lose that Name?</l>
               <l>O I am ten times more an Orphan now,</l>
               <l>Than when I knew no Parents.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> XUTHUS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>Where is this Murd'ress, who with vile Deceit</l>
               <l>Seem'd to consent to ours, and Heaven's Designs,</l>
               <l>Only to make us a more easy Prey</l>
               <l>To her Assassins?—Ha, <hi>Creusa</hi> dead?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="84"/>And the brave Stranger who preserv'd us all?</l>
               <l>Is he too dead?—The Boy—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ilyssus</hi> lives.</stage>
               <l>And thou hast sworn, great King, that he shall reign</l>
               <l>Supreme in <hi>Athens.</hi> Say, do'st thou confirm</l>
               <l>That Oath?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>XUTHUS.</speaker>
               <l>I do, by Heaven!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PYTHIA.</speaker>
               <l>Ask here no more.</l>
               <l>The fatal Tale is for thy private Ear.</l>
               <l>Retire, and learn it all. For poor <hi>Creusa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She wrong'd not thee, upon herself alone</l>
               <l>She drew Heaven's Vengeance. And too surely proves</l>
               <l>That Murder but intentional, not wrought</l>
               <l>To horrid Act, before th' eternal Throne</l>
               <l>Stands forth the first of Crimes. Who dare assume,</l>
               <l>Unwarranted, Heaven's high Prerogative</l>
               <l>Oe'r Life and Death, with double Force shall find</l>
               <l>Turn'd on themselves the Mischiefs they design'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>The End of the Fifth ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div n="1" type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="85"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE.</head>
            <sp>
               <stage>Spoken by Miss HAUGHTON, who acted the PYTHIA.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>AT length I'm freed from Tragical Parade,</l>
                  <l>No more a <hi>Pythian</hi> Priestess,—tho' a Maid;</l>
                  <l>At once resigning, with my sacred Dwelling,</l>
                  <l>My Wreaths, my Wand, my Arts of Fortune-telling.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet superstitious Folks, no doubt, are here,</l>
                  <l>Who still regard me with a kind of Fear,</l>
                  <l>Lest to their secret Thoughts these prying Eyes</l>
                  <l>Should boldly pass, and take them by Surprize.</l>
                  <l>Nay, tho' I disavow the whole Deceit,</l>
                  <l>And fairly own my Science all a Cheat,</l>
                  <l>Should I declare, in spite of Ears and Eyes,</l>
                  <l>The Beaus were handsome, or the Critics wise,</l>
                  <l>They'd all believe it, and with dear Delight</l>
                  <l>Say to themselves at least,</l>
                  <l>"The Girl has Taste;" "the Woman's in the right."</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Or, should I tell the Ladies, so dispos'd,</l>
                  <l>They'd get good Matches, ere the Season clos'd,</l>
                  <l>They'd smile, perhaps, with seeming Discontent,</l>
                  <l>And, sneering, wonder what the Creature meant;</l>
                  <l>But whisper to their Friends, with beating Heart.</l>
                  <l>"Suppose there should be something in her Art"</l>
                  <l>Grave Statesmen too would chuckle, should I say,</l>
                  <l>On such a Motion, and by such a Day,</l>
                  <l>They would be summon'd from their own Affairs</l>
                  <l>To 'tend the Nation's more important Cares;</l>
                  <l>"Well, if I must—howe'er I dread the Load,</l>
                  <l>"I'll undergo it—for my Country's Good.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All Men are Bubbles, in a skilful Hand,</l>
                  <l>The ruling Passion is the Conjurer's Wand.</l>
                  <l>Whether we praise, foretell, persuade, advise,</l>
                  <l>'Tis that alone confirms us Fools or Wise.</l>
                  <l>The Devil without may spread the tempting Sin,</l>
                  <l>But the sure Conqueror <hi>is</hi>—the Devil within.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="86"/>
            <head>A SECOND EPILOGUE.</head>
            <sp>
               <stage>Spoken by Mrs. PRITCHARD.</stage>
               <l>STAY, Ladies—Tho' I'am almost tir'd to Death</l>
               <l>With this long Part—and am so out of Breath—</l>
               <l>Yet such a lucky Thought kind Heaven has sent,</l>
               <l>That if I die for't, I must give it Vent.</l>
               <l>The Men you know are gone. And now, suppose,</l>
               <l>Before our Lords and Masters are rechose,</l>
               <l>We take th' Advantage of an empty Town,</l>
               <l>And chuse a House of Commons of our own.</l>
               <l>What think ye, cannot we make Laws?—and then</l>
               <l>Cannot we too unmake them, like the Men?</l>
               <l>O place us once in good St. <hi>Stephen's</hi> Pews,</l>
               <l>We'll shew them Women have their public Use.</l>
               <l>Imprimis they shall marry; not a Man</l>
               <l>Past twenty-five, but what shall wear the Chain.</l>
               <l>Next, we'll in earnest set about Reclaming,</l>
               <l>For, by my Life and Soul, we'll put down Gaming.</l>
               <l>We'll spoil their deep destructive Midnight Play;</l>
               <l>The Laws we make, we'll force them to obey;</l>
               <l>Unless we let them, when their Spirits flag,</l>
               <l>Piddle with us, ye know, at Quinze and Brag.</l>
               <l>"I hope, my Dearest," says some well-bred Spouse,</l>
               <l>"When such a Bill shall come before your House,</l>
               <l>"That you'll consider Men are Men—at least</l>
               <l>"That you'll not Speak, my Dear."—Not speak?—The Beast!</l>
               <l>What, would you wound my Honour?—Wrongs like these—</l>
               <l>For this, Sir, I shall bring you on your Knees.</l>
               <l>—Or, if we're quite good-natur'd, tell the Man</l>
               <l>We'll do him all the Service that we can.</l>
               <l>Then for ourselves, what Projects, what Designs?</l>
               <l>We'll tax, and double tax their nasty Wines;</l>
               <l>But Duty-free import our Blonds and Laces,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>French</hi> Hoops, <hi>French</hi> Silks, <hi>French</hi> Cambricks, and—<hi>French</hi> Faces.</l>
               <l>In short, my Scheme is not compleated quite,</l>
               <l>But I may tell ye more another Night.</l>
               <l>So come again, come all, and let us raise</l>
               <l>Such glorious Trophies to our Country's Praise,</l>
               <l>That all true <hi>Britons</hi> shall with one Consent</l>
               <l>Cry out, "Long live the Female Parliament!</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>