<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Common-place arguments against administration: with obvious answers, (intended for the use of the new Parliament.).</title>
            <author>Tickell, Richard, 1751-1793.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K020410.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">cw3305071416</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Common-place arguments against administration: with obvious answers, (intended for the use of the new Parliament.).</title>
                  <author>Tickell, Richard, 1751-1793.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>viii,[3],10-101,[1]p ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Faulder,</publisher>
                  <date>1780.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K020410.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">cw3305071416</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By R. Tickell.</note>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Adams, 80-83a</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT915.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="halftitle">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <p>COMMON-PLACE ARGUMENTS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="3"/>
            <p>COMMON-PLACE ARGUMENTS AGAINST ADMINISTRATION, WITH OBVIOUS ANSWERS, (INTENDED FOR THE USE OF THE NEW PARLIAMENT.)</p>
            <p>LONDON: PRINTED FOR R. FAULDER, NEW BOND STREET, M DCC LXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="4"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>IN most of the Arts and Sciences, Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fessors have formed general outlines of the plan, method, and arrangement, to be followed by the pupils who study them.</p>
            <p>Some sort of analysis might be of equal service to young proficients in parliamen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tary eloquence—A multitude of words, de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>livered with rapidity and vehemence, puzzle and confuse those who are unacquainted with the technical trick of debate—It will be of use therefore to prepare for our juvenile senators, a compendious outline
<pb n="vi" facs="5"/>of such arguments as may most probably be employed at the opening of the approach<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Session.</p>
            <p>And, in order to detect the fallacy of much popular rhetoric, brief observations will be annexed to each of the <hi>Common<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>place</hi> topics; by which means, when any of the old Opposition Orators begin to flou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rish away on these <hi>trite</hi> arguments, the young members may, by recurring to the proper section in the Analysis, immediate<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly find most of the <hi>thoughts,</hi> and many of the <hi>words,</hi> that will be used, <hi>for,</hi> or <hi>against</hi> the Question; with this main difference, that each will be much shorter, and pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bably both more intelligible.</p>
            <p>The Author is aware, that nothing can be simpler than this plan; it being much
<pb n="vii" facs="6"/>of the same nature with an <hi>Exhibition Ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>talogue,</hi> which merely describes the sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jects of the several compositions presented to public criticism; and possibly some read<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ers may think it might have been well, to complete the simile, by subjoining in this instance, as well as in the former, the names of the several Artists; but, though something of that dramatic kind, was ra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther successfully attempted in a pamphlet, called <hi>Anticipation,</hi> it seems more advise-able to avoid the least appearance of perso<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nality, on the present occasion:—The ridicule that was then, with some proprie<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty, directed against the tediousness, or the pedantry, or the droll dotage, that charac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terized some individual speakers; would now be wholly unnecessary: it never was
<pb n="viii" facs="7"/>a task of difficulty to expose the folly of mock eloquence; once atchieved, the re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>petition would be as disgustful as the subject.</p>
            <p>But sophistry assumes new shapes, and acts under various disguises; like the ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>licious enchanter in romance, to be finally overcome, it must be attacked in all its transformations; yet he who engages in this war of words, can be but little exposed to any charge of presumption; it is a com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bat far more tiresome, than perilous; and however severely his patience may be exer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cised, he will have but few occasions to ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ert his strength; so that as his utmost tri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>umph can be only proportionable to so inferi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>or a contest, he may be secure at least from the imputation of vanity in undertaking it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tableofcontents">
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE late, and the new Parliament <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Complimentary Invitations to the young Members <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Prophecies of Opposition <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Annual Parliaments <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Best Officers <hi>driven</hi> from the Service <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conversation Politics <hi>46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Praise of Party <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The last Campaign, and State of the nation—Comprizing—The Captures—Rhode Island and Monsieur de Ternay—Lord Cornwallis's Victory—Danger of Ja<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>maica and Hallifax—Portuguese Perfidy—Army and Navy—Petitions and Association <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Answer <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="9"/>Miscellaneous Eloquence for the Gallery <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Change the Ministry <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Answer <hi>93</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb facs="10"/>
         <head>COMMON PLACE ARGUMENTS.</head>
         <div type="argument">
            <head>THE LATE AND THE NEW PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>THE late parliament was the most in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>famous, slavish, base, sordid, venal, mean, inconsistant, despicable parliament, that ever existed.—It betrayed the rights of the people, trampled on their privileges; violated their majesty; servilely crouched to prerogative; and wasted the blood and treasure of the public, to satiate private ambition and avarice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="11"/>Hence national resentment was universally rouzed; the elective body, to a man, despi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sed the representative, and all ranks and orders of people anxiously expected the happy mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment of the dissolution. At the approach indeed of that awful crisis, political frailty felt a sort of death-bed penitence; it was the hectic virtue of a moment: the panic however soon subsided; and, flushed with new hopes of a protracted existence: the old septennial methodist rose, like Voltaire from sickness, impatient for deeper vices, and anxious for more aggravated profli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gacy.</p>
            <p>"Such <hi>was</hi> your parliament—Look you now what follows"—A young phoenix rising from the ashes of the old!—the best of all possible parliaments!—a pure, un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>corrupt, delegation from the true source of all real power, the people: unfettered by connections; unclogged with errors; free to consult; to deliberate; to determine; for the public safety! "Such <hi>is</hi> your par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>liament."</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="11" facs="12"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>IT is difficult to give a just idea, of the a<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nimated stile of opposition invectives; particularly on such a theme as the present, where the free indulgence of them, is un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>checked by any of those awkward restraints, which some young men have of late, so un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>constitutionally thrown on them.—A de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceased parliament is one of those <hi>immaterial</hi> objects, that every one may attack with perfect impunity; and indeed, under the present restrictions, it is no small conveni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ence to the component parts of such a cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>porate body, to have in the very nature of their constitution, a safe resource for the exercise of their wildest rancour, and most fanciful asperity. It is however uncom<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monly whimsical, that almost the very same set of men, who actually composed the subject of this invective, should be themselves the auditors of it; and at the same moment that they are stigmatized in
<pb n="12" facs="13"/>their late capacity, they should receive so premature a panegyric in their new one; yet such is almost precisely the case.</p>
               <p>The last parliament and the present par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>liament being very nearly one, and the same.—It is true indeed, there have been some exchanges, and different branches of par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ticular families have taken their rotation in election honours; but <hi>still</hi> both parliaments are <hi>essentially</hi> and <hi>effectually</hi> alike: so that, with a few inconsiderable exceptions, the returns and re-elections incontrovertibly prove, that all the imputations of national odium and contempt, so industriously thrown on the last parliament, must at least have been grossly exaggerated, if not entirely false.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>penitential vote,</hi> so often, and so vauntingly relied on, it will always be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>membered, that the House <hi>at large,</hi> refu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sed to <hi>report</hi> the <hi>abstract proposition</hi> so fear<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fully passed, by a committee of inferior
<pb n="13" facs="14"/>numbers—It was indeed a florid weakness; the hectic effort of exhausted sedition; that "Like the faint offer of a latter spring, served but to usher in the fall, and withered in an affected bloom."</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="14" facs="15"/>
            <head>COMPLIMENTARY INVITATIONS TO BE SCATTERED AMONG THE YOUNG MEMBERS.</head>
            <p>AS it is scarcely possible that any gen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tleman of spirit, or independence, can support the ministry, without forfeiting all pretensions to virtue, justice, honor, and common sense, there can be still less doubt, that those, who are least hackneyed in the ways of public life, and consequently most accutely sensible of the allurements of popularity, will instantly join the present constitutional, upright, consistent, generous, just, opposition.</p>
            <p>What can be so flattering to youthful am<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bition, as being immediately enrolled in a band of genuine patriots, and registered among the only British worthies of the age! what ampler field can the world afford for the display of genius, learning and elo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quence, than that glorious contest of <hi>Ameri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ca</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> of freedom against tyran<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ny!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="16"/>In the most prosperous times, the <hi>support</hi> of ministers is an inglorious and vulgar task, compared to the <hi>control</hi> of them. There is little, or no scope for rhetoric, in plain state<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments, regular calculations, legal precision, and such other trite and plain modes, as men in office <hi>must</hi> necessarily pursue. On the contrary, <hi>opposition,</hi> has inexhaustible themes of eloquence—suspicions, alarms, menaces, and predictions, (not to mention impeachments, which cannot well recur so regularly) are rich and constant sources of popular declamation. Besides, one of the chief benefits that arise from new parlia<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments, is the accession of fresh supplies of genius and cultivated abilities. And perhaps, there never was a time, when such immense quantities of both were introduced into the House of Commons as upon the present oc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>casion—young gentlemen, not only endow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed with prodigious abilities, but who have been for many years back, in <hi>training</hi> for debate, abound on all sides.—What an in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>finite pity would it be then, were such im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>proved talents obscured and shrowded from public admiration, in the dull details of of<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficial
<pb n="16" facs="17"/>politicians!—In the moment of peril and dismay, it is happy for this nation at large to have selected men, formed, as it were, for the salvation of their country.—It is no less fortunate for those, who possess such talents, to have them called into ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, at so aweful a crisis.—Indeed, it is one of the great benefits arising from the present calamities, that gentlemen have now much finer opportunities and more numerous subjects, for displaying their talents, than they could possibly have enjoyed in more quiet times; and which too, if not imme<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diately taken advantage of, may irretrievably escape by some unlucky change, to prospe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rity abroad, or humanity at home.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="17" facs="18"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>WHAT antidote can reason provide against such potent incantations?—The cold suggestion of more temperate ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vice would feebly resist the Syren voice of popular allurement; and vainly is judgment addressed, where the subtle appeal is more fancifully made to vanity and inexperience. To examine and analize the several properties of real <hi>debate,</hi> in distinction to those of wild <hi>declamation,</hi> would appear too refined: to ridicule the prevailing passion for oratory, too trite: still less would it be proper, under this division, either to enquire into the merits of Minority, or to discuss the justice and sincerity of their claims to public confidence.</p>
               <p>To raise <hi>new levies</hi> for the service of Opposition, is so entirely the <hi>interest</hi> of that set of men who command the <hi>old troops,</hi> that it cannot fail to create some flight doubts of the perfect sincerity and pure zeal of their
<pb n="18" facs="19"/>complimentary invitations. But (without considering such an adventurous junction in the more serious light of a desertion from every solid and substantial interest of our country) it may not be wholly unuseful to suggest how impossible it is for the Opposi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, in its present state, to afford those nu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>merous and happy occasions for the display of genius and eloquence, which its advocates so speciously hold out as the strongest incen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tives to youthful ambition.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minority</hi> has long been directed, and controuled, by a few leading orators; who, after years of fatiguing service, are most justly entitled to rank as veterans in their pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fession; and are now too reasonably jealous of their established precedence, to participate in fame with the raw recruits they are so anxious to enlist—One of their leaders has expressly published <hi>the Articles of Party;</hi> with much fairness and candour, avowing the necessity of obedience to a common leader, and of acting in due subordination to his commands. With more zeal, indeed,
<pb n="19" facs="20"/>than policy, this champion of party very frankly decried and ridiculed all separate ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ertions and individual efforts, as attempts of equal inefficacy and presumption; and ra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther rashly discovered so much more of this degrading system than former politicians had thought it wise, or decent to reveal, that many men of proper pride and spirit were disgusted with the <hi>Rockingham service,</hi> and beg'd leave to <hi>resign their commissions</hi> — Others of subtler talents, laboured with more art and casuistry to explain away these dangerous <hi>articles:</hi> but still, however speciously they argued, they always had the precaution to maintain their rank in eloquence, by the ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>clusion of every new competitor, and to se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cure the <hi>credit,</hi> by monopolizing the <hi>time,</hi> of debate.</p>
               <p>—No young man of talents has, for years back, met with the patronage of Opposition; every succeeding session was the echo of the former; the same quantity of time has been annually devoted to the same tediousness and protraction of debate; even stated hours seemed almost appointed for each particular
<pb n="20" facs="21"/>orator; nor was it ever a very difficult cal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culation to imagine who was actually speak<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing, at any given time, by only looking what o'clock it was; for the daily movements of their rhetoric were as mechanically exhi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bited, by a periodical succession of figures, as those of the famous <hi>Strasburg clock;</hi> ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cept indeed, when some rough unmanage<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>able country-gentlemen <hi>would</hi> start out, like the savages of St. Dunstan's, to give a hasty stroke, or two, and then retire again, to rest in peace on their unpolished clubs.</p>
               <p>But above all, the particular stile of abi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lities, which characterize the present ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nager of Opposition, renders all inferior ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ertions in eloquence, almost useless and ri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diculous—There is a magnitude in extraor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dinary talents, that contrasts, and caricatures the comparative inequality of those who are placed in competition with them. Qualities, which, carried to an extreme, are striking from their enormity, (such as desperate ve<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hemence and outrageous acrimony) become ridiculous in imitation, and impotent by in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>feriority. They resemble theatrical thunder
<pb n="21" facs="22"/>compared with real; and serve only to bur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lesque an original, that can never be success<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fully imitated. The minor malcontents, and mimic republicans of the present day, would do well therefore to reflect, how very contemptible the petty partizans of faction have been, in all ages and countries. There were dozens of duodecimo Catilines, who buzzed conspiracy in every corner of the Forum, though history has scarcely stooped to name them; Ravaillac had his <hi>monk committees</hi> and <hi>holy associations,</hi> whose <hi>debates</hi> and <hi>resolutions</hi> have been charitably consigned to oblivion: nor has there ever been any desperate leader, from the rank of <hi>Catiline</hi> to <hi>Cade,</hi> who has not boasted a gang of followers, <hi>officious,</hi> and <hi>obscure; busy,</hi> and <hi>forgot.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="22" facs="23"/>
            <head>PROPHECIES OF OPPOSITION.</head>
            <p>IN stating contingent events, and deducing the future consequences of any mea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sure now in agitation, Opposition should al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ways be deemed infallible—They are intitled to this dependance on their <hi>present</hi> predic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions, because all their <hi>former</hi> prophecies are fully accomplished.—Lest a point of such consequence to their credit should have remained unrecorded, a copious list of these divinations was published in a periodical pa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>per devoted to their service; and, to au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thenticate more indubitably the evidence of this political foresight, any gentleman, who will be so obliging as to refer to the list, will find the date of each prediction accurately subjoined, the place of utterance in a mar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ginal note, and the full accomplishment in the opposite column. It will be equally ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>parent, that the ministry in several in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stances, received and treated these pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phecies with most irreverent scepticism: with great justice and propriety therefore,
<pb n="23" facs="24"/>no circumstance is more perpetually, and more successfully, urged, than the <hi>Prophe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cies of Opposition;</hi> and hence it is most fairly inferred, that their <hi>past</hi> sagacity, invests them with an indefeasible and perpetual in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fallibility <hi>in future.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="24" facs="25"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>THE gipsey Fortune-teller <hi>"takes a bond of Fate."</hi> and to ensure her skill, most generally <hi>perpetrates</hi> the mischiefs she predicts.—To this judicious policy it may be chiefly owing, that Egyptian divina<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion has so long surviv'd all other oracles and supernatural inspirations of antiquity—The Pythian priestess became suspected, or un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>intelligible, from evasion, or ambiguity; and was equally stigmatised by Philip's gold, or the chains of Craesus.—Even our homespun witches <hi>"palter'd in such double sense,"</hi> that, by their own equivocation more than any terrors of law, they forfeited the credulous veneration they had so long usurped.—In short, the gipsey pursues the best sys<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tem for all human prophecies. This en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>suring Sybil, boldly corrects the uncertainty of time, and chance, and with great pru<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dence relies on her own dexterity, for the securest voucher of her prescience.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="26"/>—A similar wisdom has guided the <hi>pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phets of Opposition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I pledge myself to this House (says one of them) that the confidence which Ame<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rica may justly repose in the sympathetic ardor, that inspires a very great part of this nation, will make her scorn your menaces, and fly to arms, to vindicate her rights.</q>—Here is one instance among a thousand o<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thers of a patriotic prediction, that, by the liberal encouragement it holds out, goes great lengths to effect the event it foretells, and is, in fact, the leading cause of its own ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>complishment.—<q>Away with the idle notion (says another prophet) of success in your Northern expedition! I am bold to say, (and I wish my words to be taken down) that miscarriage and ruin, will at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tend that devoted army.</q>—Not to com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment too harshly on the very extraordinary precision and accuracy of these terms, it is fair to observe thus much on all predictions of this nature, That they act with a double influence: first, by dispiriting our friends, and then by encouraging the enemy; conse<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quently,
<pb n="26" facs="27"/>if they are not condemned as <hi>prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cipals,</hi> they may at least be arraigned as active <hi>accomplices,</hi> in producing the calamity they foretell.</p>
               <p>But as many people have thought, that too large a portion of debate has been em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ployed of late years in recounting the utte<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rance, and expounding the final completion of these prophecies; it might tend to ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>breviate this article of oratory, if a commit<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tee of parliamentary prophets, invested with the ensigns of augural authority, were or<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dered forth with to <hi>prepare</hi> and <hi>bring in</hi> a kind of <hi>Political Almanack,</hi> or <hi>Patriots Ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lender,</hi> for the use of the current year; where<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>in all minor victories and defeats, should be set down as feasts, and fasts, and red-letter days set apart for more important losses.</p>
               <p>It might enrich a work of this nature, to interleave each month with pages of collate<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ral philosophy, opposite to its subjects; such as refutations of several vulgar errors too com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monly enterained, relative to some military
<pb n="27" facs="28"/>misdeeds in the late campaigns; by com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>paring them, to the retrogade motion of the planets; which every more enlightened ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>server can easily prove to be quite contrary to appearances, and merely arising from our vast distance from the objects, and the gross medium through which we view them; so too, any tediousness in crossing the <hi>Dela<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ware,</hi> or obscurity in the <hi>Saratoga</hi> business, might receive great light from the philoso<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phy of <hi>transits,</hi> and <hi>eclipses;</hi> while the doc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>trine of Comets would furnish infinite ana<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>logy to all kinds of excentricity, civil, mili<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tary, or naval.</p>
               <p>These, together with proper tables for calculating the influence of the moon on the rise and fall of stocks, would form a very compendious and handy diary in state-affairs, and, in a short time, must become as infal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lible a guide in politics, as <hi>Partridge</hi>'s <hi>pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dictions</hi> formerly were in astrology.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="28" facs="29"/>
            <head>ANNUAL PARLIAMENTS.</head>
            <p>IN the moment of most general danger to the very existence of a state, from a rebellion, and a foreign war, it becomes all wise, good, and prudent men, to devote their whole time to the concerting measures, not to overcome the common enemy, but to new model and patch up the constitution; just as, in a closely besieged town, every clever fellow should leave it to his inferiors to repell the assailants from the walls, and busy himself, and his neighbours, in drawing plans to repair, and beautify the old town-hall, the assembly-rooms, and other build<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ings of the city. And this, not from any paradoxical confusion, or ideal refinement, that the <hi>inside</hi> of the town is to all intents and purposes the <hi>outside;</hi> or that the said edifices are <hi>virtually</hi> the fortifications; but for a much simpler and more substantial reason; namely that the day of distress and danger is the true time to frighten the magistrates into receiving their terms: which, if the
<pb n="29" facs="30"/>siege is raised, will set them up for ever in fame and fortune; and if it be not, will serve at least to recommend them to the victorious enemy as very shrewd and nota<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble projectors.</p>
            <p>Now, in a state like ours, it is clear that the constitution of parliament must always form the grand subject of political theory. Hence various schemes have been propound<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed, to purify, and refine it from all corrup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions; and many tedious preparations, in the nature of chymical processes, have been occasionally invented, to exalt it to what it really should be, a kind of compound elixir of popular spirit.</p>
            <p>In the course of these experiments, some professors insisted, that its whole efficacy must depend on the ingredients, that com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose it, being brought from their several native soils, free of all charges.—Others held, that larger quantities of its most wholesome <hi>simples,</hi> should be gathered out of the rich<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>est, and best cultivated lands, and not pick<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed up, like mushrooms, from old wastes
<pb n="30" facs="31"/>and barren commons. But, however com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posed, sifted, and refined, several concurred in opinion, that it <hi>never</hi> could keep its spirit above <hi>three</hi> years, because formerly they only made it up for that time.</p>
            <p>But the last, and far most important dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>covery of all, is, that it never possibly can be fit for use, or good for any thing at all, above a <hi>twelvemonth</hi> after it is first put to<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gether.—Or (to release the metaphor be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore it's quite exhausted) that annual parlia<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments are the grand arcanum, and sovereign panacea, for all the distempers of our de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cayed and perishing constitution. And, in order to establish this important point; first, they affirm, that the virtue of that restricted duration beyond a triennial one, is very clearly proved by a converse ratio of the old homely adage, <hi>"There can never be too much of a good thing,"</hi> which, being inverted, very fairly carries the question <hi>by three to one,</hi> against triennial in favour of annual parliaments—And next, the ingenious ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vocates of this improvement, as clearly prove the undoubted <hi>use</hi> and <hi>pleasure,</hi> that would
<pb n="31" facs="32"/>naturally result both to constituents and re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>presentatives, from this annual revolution of intercourse; by shewing how infallibly it must promote the health and spirits of the former, to be under a sort of pleasing ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessity, to keep up a visiting acquaintance, with their constituents in the purer air of the country; to whom, in <hi>their</hi> turn it would prove equally beneficial and delightful, by encouraging the briskness of trade, and cheapness of provisions, at such constant re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>petitions of election festivity, and convi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vial fellowship.—But these, and many se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>condary motives, are lost in the beauty, depth, and curiosity of the main argument, that is the foundation of this plan, which is briefly this; The mysterious excellence of the number TWELVE, that limits the months in this constitutional period: a cabalistical idea, which, tho' too subtle and complex to be dwelt on minutely in this place, can<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>not fail to strike every impartial mind with sufficient force, on the mere mention of a few instances, among the millions which exist, wherein this number of TWELVE pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dominates:
<pb n="32" facs="33"/>with which short enumeration the subject shall be closed.</p>
            <p>First then, all the world knows, that the earth revolves in <hi>twelve</hi> months, round the <hi>twelve</hi> signs of the Zodiac; and this too, (as Monsieur Gebelin very critically expounds,) was typically illustrated, in Pagan mytholo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gy, by the <hi>twelve</hi> labours of Hercules; all which, like our corporate and parochial of<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fices, were performed exactly in the good, even, space of a <hi>twelvemonth.</hi> Next, all petty juries are composed of <hi>twelve,</hi> and grand ju<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ries, of twice <hi>twelve,</hi> good men and true; so too there are <hi>twelve</hi> judges; and, tho' the bishops (exclusive of the two metropolitans) are just twice that number, yet there is a relative proportion even in this difference, which was certainly designed to signify the double glory of ecclesiastical, united with tem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>poral dignities; as well as the exact increase of piety in these latter, compared to the pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mitive times; when, in truth, as every one knows, there were but <hi>twelve</hi> apostles.—Add to these therefore the <hi>twelve candlesticks</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="34"/>in the revelations, the <hi>twelve</hi> tribes of Israel, the <hi>twelve</hi> Caesars, and dozens of other duo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>decimo examples, and you will then have the very essence of all the arguments, in fa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vour of parliaments for <hi>twelve months.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="34" facs="35"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>PREVIOUS QUESTION.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="35" facs="36"/>
            <head>BEST OFFICERS <hi>DRIVEN</hi> FROM THE SERVICE.</head>
            <p>MINISTERS have the art to con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nect contrarieties of baseness; they dismiss without cause, or employ to no end, our best officers.—Examples of the former have appeared in the militia: the latter has been equally instanced both in our army, and navy.—There is something of Pagan craft in this crooked policy—The virtue and valour of <hi>Theseus</hi> were too formidable to a feeble and suspicious tyrant to be overlooked with affected contempt, or openly degraded: it was a safer, and subtler cruelty to exhaust this dangerous heroism, in remote and pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rilous enterprizes; which, if atchieved, would give credit to the wisdom of those who <hi>projected</hi> them, but, if attended with shame and disappointment, might lower, if not entirely destroy, the reputation of their conductors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="37"/>The hero of antiquity indeed, defeated this pernicious system, and returned in tri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>umph, to greet his insidious employers with unwelcome successes, and offensive victory. But, however fatally imperfect the parallel of devoted valour must appear in modern annals, every generous mind will equally abhor the same base and mean policy, which, in both instances, veiled ruin beneath its bounty, and exalted, only to destroy.</p>
            <p>Such has been the odious system of go<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vernment towards those, whose professional eminence, joined to their popular attach<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments and connections, pointed them out as the fittest objects for temporary banish<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment, at least, if not shameful captivity abroad, or more degrading impotence at home.</p>
            <p>Nor has the executive power been less busily oppressive in the domestic arrange<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments of our great internal and constituti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>onal defence, the militia.—It is the extreme of tyranny to controul the freedom of thought—Sidney lost his life for his <hi>written</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="38"/>principles.—With more cautious injustice, the patriots of the present day, are deprived of their hereditary honours, for daring to <hi>speak</hi> their independent opinions.—To re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lease the mind from the oppressive awe of of authority, the patriotic parliament of Charles the First's reign claimed, and ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ercised, their just right of appointing the Lord Lieutenants, and other officers, that array and command, our militia.—It was too well foreseen that a right of so extensive a nature might, in the hands of regal ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>price, become a convenient instrument to check the spirit of liberty, or to <hi>punish</hi> its <hi>generous exertions.</hi>—Could it have been imagined that the time would arrive, when the highest and most important ranks of that very armament should be rashly in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vaded, and revengefully violated by prero<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gative, if, on any occasion, their established possessors dared to exercise the right of thinking for themselves, it might have damped the zeal of precipitate loyalty in re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>signing so important a right to the discre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion and virtue of a monarch. Unfortu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nately however this very right was as rashly
<pb n="38" facs="39"/>surrendered by the parliament of Charles the Second, as it was manfully maintained in the reign of his tyrannical predecessor.</p>
            <p>What has been the consequence?—We have lived to see the day when a ruinous and wretched administration (that administration, which has invariably pursued the wicked system of division; that administration, which has set friend against friend, relation against relation, and connection against con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nection; that administration, which has robbed us of thirteen colonies, and plunged us in a shameful and calamitous war, with the whole world) has insolently dismissed the accomplished descendants of two of the noblest, and most ancient families, from those commands, to which their superior rank and property had most justly elevated their ancestors and themselves; for — on<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly happening to vote in opposition to the minister of the day.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="39" facs="40"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>THERE is but little necessity to con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sider the fabulous allusions, and ideal parallels, of declamation. The legendary tale of Demagogues, had its use in the de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cline of Athenian freedom: but if its boasted hero had surrendered to his worst and basest antagonist, without fighting, and, in a short time after, some happier hero had fought, and conquered the very same combatant; probably, no Grecian orator would after<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wards have much insisted on the visionary speculation of an army's being devoted to sacrifice an individual.</p>
               <p>It is necessary to treat the latter part of this argument with some degree of serious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness and solidity. Least however too much time may appear to be wasted on it, it may be prudent to premise, that objections, founded on popular notions and prejudices, are easily conveyed in few words, and, so
<pb n="40" facs="41"/>conveyed, make strong impressions; but whoever <hi>answers</hi> those objections must en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>counter all the notions to which they are allied, and to which they owe their strength; and it is well if any words find admittance to remove the first impression.</p>
               <p>The appointment of party men to places of trust, and power, was indeed a very ha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>zardous policy: it must however be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>membered, that this <hi>policy</hi> was founded on a very liberal and generous hope, that, how<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ever the forms of opposition might be kept up, and even the technical licentiousness of debate persevered in, yet that every man of honor, at so awful a period, would divest himself of all the little prejudices and pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions of party, and feel his mind actua<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted by the noblest impulse, to suspend at least all private resentment, if not to form a truly glorious coalition, founded on public principle, and national honor.—Certain<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly the accomplishment of so noble a pur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose, would have been crowned with far different success, from that which has ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tually attended its attempt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="42"/>But, to avoid these painful, and vain re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>flections; in proceeding to answer the charge of <hi>violent and unconstitutional dismission,</hi> it must first be remembered that <hi>removals</hi> are not <hi>punishments.</hi>—It would be absurd to imagine, that a meer private prejudice in political measures, however vague and fanci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>full, or even pernicious in its tendency to the general welfare of the state, can become an object of <hi>penalty:</hi> But it is indeed a very different question, with what propriety those persons, who not only avow such opinions with the fond attachment of innovation, but also disseminate them with most active zeal, should be continued in those very stations, which afford most frequent and most exten<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sive opportunities, to spread them with all the weight of influence and authority.—And next, as to the <hi>right</hi> of dismission, it is ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vious that the same power, which <hi>appoints</hi> to offices, must necessarily <hi>remove</hi> from them: both are exercises of that plain discretionary trust necessarily reposed in all governments, to the end that every delegation of their au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thority may be lodged in such hands as shall seem best affected to those who employ
<pb n="42" facs="43"/>them.—Nor is this <hi>preventive policy</hi> of guarding against dissaffecton less congenial with the <hi>spirit</hi> of our constitution.—The prerogative of appointment to offices was originally unlimited; but, at the Restoration, the parliament most expressly declared the necessity of guarding with jealous vigilance against the introduction of those persons into places of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>trust,</hi> whose opinions and prejudices rendered them dangerous ser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vants for the state to employ.</p>
               <p>Hence the <hi>corporation</hi> and <hi>test acts;</hi> which (tho', at first, they may seem rather formed to guard the mitre, than the crown) were in fact, more really directed against the <hi>civil</hi> than the <hi>religious</hi> principles of the dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>senters.</p>
               <p>These disabling statutes very clearly prove two points, both of which are material to this question.</p>
               <p>First, that it is perfectly constitutional to exercise the prerogative of appointment to
<pb n="43" facs="44"/>offices, with a strict and cautious attention to the principles of those who are to be em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ployed in them: and next, that in every other instance, except in these statutable disquali<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fications, this prerogative is entirely unlimi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted, and absolutely discretionary; for it is plain, that the very restriction in those ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cepted cases, virtually establishes its inde<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pendance in every other. But so anxious were the restoration parliament to remove all possibility of any future encroachment on the discretionary prerogative of militia ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointments, that an act was unanimously passed, expressive of the national abhorrence of that recent usurpation of them, which had fatally given arms to innovation, and over<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>turned the constitution, under the specious pretence of amending it.</p>
               <p>By the same act also, it was directly decla<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>red, that those very appointments had ever been, and for ever should continue, the unali<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>enable and uncontrouled right of the crown.</p>
               <p>Such then being both the <hi>letter</hi> and the <hi>spirit</hi> of the law on this point, it is but mere
<pb n="44" facs="45"/>matter of curiosity, to consider the plain principles, on which this power is founded, both in <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>civil</hi> society.</p>
               <p>In the former, tho' all men were origi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nally on an equality, yet the distinction of abilities set the first bounds.—It required wisdom and courage for council and arms—and it was necessary of course to exclude from each, such as were respectively defi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient in either.</p>
               <p>So far forth therefore there was a <hi>natural</hi> limitation.—But in <hi>civil</hi> society it is equally important, in all delegations of power, to connect affection to the government, with the other leading qualifications; for (as has been too often proved) a courageous man, who hates his employers, is at least as unfit to be trusted, as a coward; and wisdom, connected with enmity, would only serve to aggravate treachery in council.—The plain consequence of which, is this; that either, no government has a right to preserve itself against the disaffection of a subject; or
<pb n="45" facs="46"/>else that every government has a right to ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>clude from offfices of power and trust, such as render themselves suspected of disaffec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="46" facs="47"/>
            <head>OPINION OF THINGS IN GENERAL, OR, CONVERSATION POLITICS.</head>
            <p>EVERY thing is as bad as bad can be!—Indeed it's now my only comfort that <hi>any</hi> change, must be for the better—It can't be for the worse!—As to America, the game is up—It was always a mad, visionary, scheme; without an object, or an end—Poor Sir Robert Walpole (who, after all, was a very great man) used always to say "He would never set that stone a rolling."—France is amazingly populous!—It's nonsence to talk of a rebellion in South America—Spain has all that immense wealth under her thumb—So, we are to fight them, and all the world, for what I see!</p>
            <p>And how?—We have no men at home—And how are we to get them?—I'm sure, we have no money.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="48"/>Formerly we had friends abroad to apply to.—The old king of Prussia for one.—But surely, we can't go on, as we have, year after year, with loan upon loan and tax upon tax!—Why if a gentleman's going post now, he can't sleep in peace in his chaise—He's sure to be, woke by the turn<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pike man, hollowing for the new tickets indeed!—What will they tax next?—Not air, I hope—Then, there are these nor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thern power—I <hi>don't</hi> know what they mean—I repeat it, I haven't an idea, what they would be at—Let me tell you, it's a very black cloud, hovering over us; and bodes <hi>no good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why don't we employ new men?—We want some great original genius like a Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tham, to come forward, and <hi>act</hi>—Then we should get on—We don't get on—Such a monstrous fleet as ours, should have push'd into Brest water at once—or bombarded Cadiz—Why did not they convoy all the ships we have lost?—All I see that they are ever about, is victualling.—They are tak<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="49"/>in fresh provisions, and water, from morning till night.</p>
            <p>Yet they are always sick too.—Lord Sandwich mistook his line—I want to see a seaman at the head of the navy.—I doubt there's some mystery at the bottom of those captures—People shake their heads in the city—Depend on it, there has always been an over-ruling influence in the cabinet—A'nt every thing given to Scotch-men?—We should set the axe to the root—In short, I fairly own, things are come to such a pass, that—I really don't know what to advise.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="49" facs="50"/>
               <head>EQUIVOCAL ANSWER BY A TRIMMER.</head>
               <p>COME, come, my dear sir; now, you go too far—As long as you confined yourself to wit and humour, it was all very fair—but don't be too severe—Not that I absolutely differ from you, in what you assert; for I have, by no means made up my mind on <hi>any</hi> of these matters—I own, I wish to see, a little more, what turn things may take, before <hi>I</hi> declare myself—This country has certainly very great re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sources—But, at the same time, we are in a mighty hazardous way—Yet America is a great game—Heaven only knows tho', what should be done—It is very true, I <hi>have</hi> mostly voted with ministry—Indeed I <hi>did</hi> live in habits with a good many of them—But I never will <hi>commit myself</hi> to any set of men—I own, I always thought, the lessen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing the burthens of the landed interest a
<pb n="50" facs="51"/>very fine object—And, to be sure, it <hi>was</hi> my opinion, that our colonies should bear a part in redeeming the debts, we incurred for their defence—But I don't know, that <hi>every</hi> thing has been carried on right in America—Yet, I don't throw blame any where—Though there may have been faults—on both sides—However we shall see—I must talk with ministers about these things—But thus much I will say—I don't at all disapprove of the conduct of the States General; nor indeed of any of the northern powers; for they act only with proper precaution; and it's quite right for nations, as well as individuals, to be on their guard, and take care of themselves.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="51" facs="52"/>
            <head>THE PRAISE OF PARTY.</head>
            <p>INdependance is a wild, unsocial idea—even a monk confessed, that, to abso<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lutely enjoy this mental solitude, man must change his nature to that of angels, or de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mons.</p>
            <p>In the progress of civilization, every ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>proach to perfection is founded, on relin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quishing this solitary pride of thinking, or acting, for ourselves alone—The rudest sa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vages have their clans, and chiefs; the freest republics their heads, and statholders.</p>
            <p>From different degrees of strength, cou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rage, or abilities, subordination arises.—To the boldest, or hardiest, or wisest, the su<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>preme command in war, or in peace, is con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fided—and the natural equality of each is prudently resigned for the benefit of all—but chiefly on the spur of necessity, and the
<pb n="52" facs="53"/>pressure of complex operations, is the en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>crease of dependance originally grounded, and ultimately established—The former <hi>cre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>atea</hi> Roman dictatorship; by the latter, it was <hi>perpetuated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then, as it appears, that all natural independance has been exchanged as the bar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter for social happiness, so it is equally evi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dent, that, in the perfection of a civil state, combinations and confederacies must be en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>couraged, and perfected; and finally, that in the conflict of opposite contentions, the decisive weight and efficient force of party must depend on its disciplin'd submission to the controul of one common leader.</p>
            <p>Nor let it be objected that the avowed ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stilities of party, may, in the present times, provoke a closer union of <hi>ministerialists,</hi> than might otherwise subsist among so divided a body—It is true, indeed, there is a gloomy cloud of discord and dissention, that over<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spreads those common foes of Opposition, and of their country—Auspicious may it prove; and happy be the presage of their
<pb n="53" facs="54"/>dispersion, and their ruin!—But let it not inspire a sanguine and premature confidence, which, by relaxing the ardour of pursuit, may in the end defeat our hopes, and rob us of the glorious object of all our toils—Besides, at this crisis, there are those, who are yet free to choose their political line—And, if properly incited, what doubt can long remain, in favour of which they will decide?—Is not the support of ministry but another term for meanness and venality? Are not Opposition, and party, the very echoes of virtue and genius? The former is indeed a phalanx of baseness—the latter, the sacred league of wisdom and of honour.—If then the lists of parliamentary fame must be martialed for the combat, who is there, can a moment hesitate, what arms to wield, whence the champion should begin his bold career, or what is the enterprize his courage should atchieve, to win the immor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tal guerdon of renown?</p>
            <p>Minions of power! your's be the inglo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rious task, in tinsel pomp, and flimsey
<pb n="54" facs="55"/>pride, to wave your silken banners in the sunshine of a courtly pageant!</p>
            <p>Labour, and vigilance, and patience, are the badge of all the patriot tribe!—But re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>putation is the palm!—and if they perish in the cause of liberty, welcome be the stroke that consecrates their doom, with more than martyr's glory, and transmits their fame, from age, to age, with undiminished ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nour.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="55" facs="56"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>THOUGH nothing is more certain than that public spirit is equally abhor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rent from credulous adherence, or coward<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly indecision, yet to define the precise limits of either extreme would be to renew the <hi>commonest</hi> of all <hi>common-place</hi> theories.—It may be more useful to state a few points admitted by the disputants on both sides.—It is allowed then, that fixed principles, and general maxims, should be the established guides of all bodies of men, whose office it is, to act together.</p>
               <p>This conformity is restricted however to opinions; tho' it naturally inclines to a con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sistence in public conduct.—But leagues, and confederacies, founded on private attach<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments only, lead to mean, and degrading subservience; for more personal <hi>association</hi> is little better than conspiracy-Hence, to de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sire a body of English gentlemen, (who are chosen by the nation to consult, deliberate,
<pb n="56" facs="57"/>and then determine) to herd at once, under any individual leader, and follow, wherever he calls, is equally absurd, and insolent.</p>
               <p>It must be repeated however, that estab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lished principles and unequivocal maxims, are great, and proper guides.—To act consist<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ently with <hi>them,</hi> is sense, and honour.—How contradictory to this system are the language and the conduct of Opposition?—"I boast myself a party-man, and, therefore, will op<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose the minister," are the very words per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>petually repeated in the House of Commons by the greatest advocates of minority.—Thus the badge and livery of faction are ostenta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiously displayed on <hi>one</hi> side of the house.—On the opposite, ask one of the <hi>equivocal poli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ticians,</hi> how he means to act, and he will answer you (and with perfect honor) that "he is no party-man, but will freely tell you, his general principles, and avow his former line of conduct."—And so far forth, he acts up to the spirit of the constitution.—But if afterwards his conduct is a desertion of those principles, and totally inconsistent with what he himself declares it to have for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>merly
<pb n="57" facs="58"/>been; if, in short, it is evasive, shuf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fling, and mean; if he hangs aloof in the lobby; takes an impartial dinner in the ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>joining coffee-houses; or happens unluckily to be called out, on very particular business, just before the division; and then <hi>sails</hi> up, and down, the passages; <hi>cruises</hi> in the com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mittee-rooms; <hi>bears away</hi> for the court of requests; or <hi>steers</hi> directly home in his coach, <hi>with his light out;</hi> then indeed, the previous acknowledgment of his former principles, and conduct, is equally useless, and ridiculous; and he must be content to rank in future, with those home-hollanders or domestic dutchmen, whose cold ungrateful caution, and <hi>armed neutrality,</hi> is nearly as pernicious, and far more despicable, than the bolder hostilities of open enmity.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="58" facs="59"/>
            <head>THE LAST CAMPAIGN AND GENERAL STATE OF THE NATION.</head>
            <p>AFTER the ruinous experience of a ten year's war, the moment is arrived, when a New Parliament are to deliberate and determine on the expedi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ency of prosecuting, or relinquishing, of accomplishing, or abandoning, American subjugation.—Let the Last Campaign, and the present State of the Nation, be the fair and substantial grounds of argument to decide upon this extensive and import<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ant question.</p>
            <p>First then, As to the Latte Campaign, it is apparent to the whole world, that the daring spirit of enterprize, which once distinguished the councils, and elevated the valour of this country above her an<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient
<pb n="59" facs="60"/>enemies, is now fatally changed to cold and ignominious caution, to narrow and temporary prudence.—It is no longer conquest or death — It is lingering shame, and protracted disgrace.—That fleet, which once commanded the homage of nations, is become now, the object of pity or contempt—Those arms, that for ages snatched uncertainty from For<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tune, are at length the splendid pageant of defensive pride, and wasteful inactivity.—On the contrary, what is the situation of our enemies in both these respects?—To the accident of an epidemical disease alone, it is owing that Count D'Estaign, at the head of the combined fleets, did not drive us from the Channel—Yet the moment he had steered from Spain, by the ignorance and folly of our Admiralty, and the mise<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rable meanness of the convoys, two of the most valuable fleets, that ever sailed from this country, were instantly captur'd; to the aggrandizement and glory of our ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies, to the disgrace and ruin of ourselves—In the West Indies, such is the decided
<pb n="60" facs="61"/>superiority of the French and Spaniards, that it may be boldly predicted, Jamaica must im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mediately be the victim of Spanish avarice, and Halifax become the support and re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>source of the ambition of France. Nor have their arms been less successful by land. Monsieur de Ternay is in complete posses<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sion of Rhode Island; an acquisition, in itself fatally accommodated to impede every enterprize of England; but still more ru<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>inous by facilitating and hastening the en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tire loss of Canada.—Unlike the slight and single advantage which has been dearly ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quired by <hi>our</hi> army; and which indeed will too probably become more ruinous to this country, that its fatal surrender or cap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tivity could possibly have proved: by madly encouraging the further prosecution of destructive temerity, and by deluding the giddy unthinking multitude to a longer endurance of this accursed war.</p>
            <p>Such being the comparative state of the last campaign, let us in the next place con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sider the situation of continental politics.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="62"/>Commodore Johnstone has been driven from Portugal—That nation is crouching to Spain—There is an officer in the House of Commons, who may be appealed to, to tell his experience of the duplicity and meanness of Portugal—Indeed the con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct of Portugal is now but a proper return for our additional impositions on her trade, as well as the unparallel'd audacity of seiz<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing American vessels laden with her pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duce—It is a similar perfidy that has pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>voked the resentment of all the nothern na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions;—The Portuguese are not more our enemies, than the Russians, the Swedes, the Danes, and the Dutch—Turks, Jews, and Infidels conspire to drive us from the Mediteranean—With our trade, our pos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sessions also in those seas, must inevitably perish.—Minorca cannot long escape. Gi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>braltar was saved last year, by an experi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment, and preserved only by the indolence of Spain.—A ridiculous embassy indeed has been secretly undertaken, and the literary <hi>West Indian</hi> translated to <hi>the Spanish Fryer.</hi>—But while political credulity consults its
<pb n="62" facs="63"/>
               <hi>Delphic</hi> Oracle, or weakly trusts the vision<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ary hope of a congenial rebellion in South America, our vigilant and determined ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies are somewhat more seriously employ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed.—France has sent troops to Holland, and the Dutch must be compelled to go to war with us—In short, the whole conti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nent of Europe is united in one common and equal league against this devoted coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try.</p>
            <p>To oppose so powerful a confederacy, what are our resources?—There are none, that the ablest financier could invent, suffi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient to contend with the whole world. But the nation is already exhausted and ruined—The spirit of commerce is for ever annihilated by our recent, irrepara<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble calamities: nor can the most adventur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing industry any longer confide in the des<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>picable conductors of our naval strength, to hazard any new enterprize.—But sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posing the possibility, that added burthens of imposts and taxes could be explored, what <hi>force</hi> have we to oppose the matchless
<pb n="63" facs="64"/>superiority of our enemies?—Young, un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>disciplined regiments, must be sent to bane<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ful climates; while our old establishments are confined at home, and excellent officers are either necessarily detained with them, or insolently superseded by adventurers, without a claim, or pretension to so dan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gerous an innovation.</p>
            <p>And this too, while the Commander in Chief in America calls for new supplies of men, which it is impossible to provide, and yet without which, those already there must be totally ineffectual—Such is our mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>serable inability in arms, resources, officers and men, to continue this ruinous, de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>structive, desolating war, against America, against the world.</p>
            <p>What is our situation at home?—A set<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tled gloom of discontent!—The petitions of the people for a while gave place to more immediate and pressing objects—But let not the authors of national ruin exult in secure tranquillity—The momentary calm may yet be succeeded by tempests that shall
<pb n="64" facs="65"/>overwhelm them in misery and destruc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion—And if the most shameless corruption, if an accumulation of injuries and insults can awaken us to a just feeling of our wrongs, it will be easy to discover, and meritorious to employ, the most <hi>effectual</hi> means of redressing them—Every lenient and peaceable method has long been pur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sued in vain—Authority has been intreated with submission, haughtiness has been soothed with humility, profligacy has been tempted to reformation by allurement of pardon, and even by the prospect of praise—That weight and authority, which, from the chair of office, turned the scale of debate, and with liberal and disinterested magnanimity, supported the petitions, will now be exerted, though not with equal dignity, yet with superior force, to give <hi>effect</hi> to those principles, which it so libe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rally avowed.</p>
            <p>Our only remaining hope is, in the uni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on of disinterested and independent spirits throughout the kingdom. Such an union
<pb n="65" facs="66"/>directed to one view, and pressing to one ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ject, will not easily be resisted by the arms of power, or frustrated by the arts of cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruption.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="66" facs="67"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>SUCH is the gloomy and exaggerated picture of our national distresses—Such are the pretences for cowardly despondency, for weak contemptible desertion of all our interests and of all our hopes; and for a rash and giddy subservience to that fatal spirit of innovation, in the pursuit of im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>provements we never may obtain, and to the risque of calamities which we may never remedy—But it is not now the question, whether a season of external danger and hostility is the fittest for new arrangements of internal polity—When it was seen with what industry and activity the same set of men were busied in running from one country to another, in private intrigue and public incitement, in dictat<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing where they had no property, and can<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vassing where they had no connexious; impartial men were led to suspect, that the independent and respectable part of the
<pb n="67" facs="68"/>confederacy, far from being the real con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>trivers, were but the ostensible authors of the farce of reformation—To erect new assemblies, unknown to the constitution which they purposed to reform, and pa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ramount to the legislature, which they pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fessed to supplicate, was a system as sus<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>picious in its motive, as alarming in its tendency—A Legislature insulted and menaced, became the object of factious insolence from every desperate cabal—Even Opposition themselves, who had first in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stilled into the minds of men a contempt of order, felt, in their turn, the miseries of lawless uproar, and lamented the mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chiefs they had produced—It shall not therefore be the present enquiry, whe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther the worst and most ruinous situation, that fancy can imagine, could justify a wild licentious anarchy at home—It is a far plainer and more limited enquiry; whether the present is in any degree that ruinous crisis, which, by extirpating every present hope, throws us at once on the unprincipled and profligate violence of theoretic enterprize, and speculative de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spair:
<pb n="68" facs="69"/>or rather, whether we may not still preserve our expectations, still sustain our spirit, and confide both in our na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tional resources, and the courage of our people, to re-establish our welfare, and re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gain that respect and consequence in Eu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rope, which the generous spirit of Eng<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>land has ever entitled her to maintain, as the protectress of liberty, and the arbitress of continental freedom—It is a glaring proof of the inconsistency of Opposition, that at the same moment, when the com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plicated concerns of so extensive a system are exaggerated with every fanciful aggra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vation, the impolicy of a defensive war should be grafted on the former proposi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion—To have maintained an equality, at least, against combined hostilities, does not appear to merit the imputation of ig<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>norance, so repeatedly thrown upon that department, to which the conduct of our navy is entrusted—It is stated as a pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vidential escape, that Count D'Estaign, by the epidemical sickness of his armament, was prevented from entering the British Channel—But on the contrary, that
<pb n="69" facs="70"/>calamity was indeed in its effects a national misfortune to Great Britain—For nothing but sickness could have checked the rash presumption and impetuosity of that Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mander, from hazarding an action, for which our fleet was perfectly prepared; and which too (as it was impossible to be foreseen,) be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>came the accidental cause of those very captures, which are injuriously stated as the effects of rashness and ignorance in our Admiralty—It is clear, however, that convoys can only be protections against re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sistance of an inferior kind:—It is impos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sible to provide a convoy for every inward, and outward-bound fleet, sufficient to de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>feat the combined fleets of France and Spain—nor indeed were grand fleets ever directed against mercantile fleets, except in those cases, where, as in the present in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stance, their greater operations, had been absolutely prevented by sickness, and other accidents, equally unforeseen by both par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ties—Whether an implicit reliance must be paid to those ill-omened predic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions, which menace ruin and desolation to our foreign possessions, from the ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies
<pb n="70" facs="71"/>fleets abroad, must remain a doubt—It will always be remembered, that <hi>two years</hi> have already elapsed, since that pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riod, when the same prophets of Oppo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sition so peremptorily foretold the absolute impossibility of continuing the war for <hi>one</hi> year longer—With equal solemnity how<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ever, the loss of Canada is predicted, from the terrors of a French proclamation, joined to the evidence of Monsieur de Ternay's possession of Rhode Island—But, however mysterious the former may be, little stress can be laid on the latter: for the weakness of the Americans in the desertion of an island to their insidious protectors, is a very strange proof of English cowardice in surrendering a whole continent which they have gained with glory, preserved with humanity, and are resolute to defend to the last extremity. It must be remembered, that Admiral Graves sailed after the French squadron, and arrived at Rhode Island, much about the same time as Monsieur De Ternay had been admitted there. But since that arrival of the English fleet, the French
<pb n="71" facs="72"/>have remained totaly inactive. We have the superiority, and they haven't dared to fight. Indeed the French assistance is far more calculated to support the spirit of party there, than to form an expectation of co-operating, where they will always disagree—But if, at length, the French should determine to make North America the seat of war, we certainly may as well fight them there, as any where else—We can but lose America at last—and they them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves gain nothing but blows and losses.</p>
               <p>Yet, in contrast to this pacific resigna<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion to Monsieur De Ternay, is Lord Cornwallis's victory compared, by those who consider surrenders, glorious, and victories, ruinous.</p>
               <p>Happy had it been for this country, if military wisdom had been exerted, in this as in the last war, to justify and immor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>talize valour, not to depreciate atchieve<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments, which indeed are the decisive condemnation of those who disparage them.—If such a principle is once ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mitted, that defeat and ruin will be our
<pb n="72" facs="73"/>real advantage, it would overturn every spirited exertion to obtain a favourable peace, by demonstrating every new ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quisition to be a motive for submission, every gallant and honourable enterprize a ground of tame acquiescence to degra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dation and disgrace.—It would rob heroism of its best reward, and convert victory and triumph to a mere quibbling paradox of debasement and infamy.</p>
               <p>But with the same policy, the misfor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tunes of our continental situation are exag<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gerated and proclaimed. It is admitted to be too plain a truth, that far less hopes can be entertained from a rebellion in the Spanish colonies, than were confidently cherished in England, upon the first idea of American resistance—The Spanish co<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lonists want indeed the main force and decisive stress of insurgency and rebellion—They want a South American party in Spain, to countenance their disaffection, to exalt their profligacy, to pronounce in a Senate the eulogiums of their leaders, to distract the National Councils in their
<pb n="73" facs="74"/>support, to menace the legislature in their defence, to sympathize with their suffer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ings, and to triumph in their success.—But as to Portugal, it is a subject of double grief, that, to establish the perfidy of that state, a military officer, once glori<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ously engaged in its defence, should now be the tame witness, not the gallant avenger of ingratitude and falsehood—In fact, the the learned Commodore was very much courted by the Portuguese; nor will that people ever actually quarrel with those, whom every commercial interest has fixed their best and surest allies—The extreme of danger that political prediction can me<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nace, is the loss of Minorca; which however has always been retained, as a point of honour, rather than as a necessary possession—When we are at peace, Gibralter is suffi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient for the Mediterranean trade; and when at war, we have none at all—As to Holland, the Dutch have too great a pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perty in our funds, to assist in destroy<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing our settlements abroad.—Nor is it possible, that the northern powers of Eu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rope can consider it their interest to over<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>turn
<pb n="74" facs="75"/>a nation, to which some of them al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>most owe their existence, others their pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>servation from the jealousy of the house of Bourbon, and all have derived a generous, liberal, mediation and protection—Great Britain, that formerly established Holland, can now resist any similar confederacy: and in this glorious struggle, if she does not ultimately secure a more firm independ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ance, she has already maintained at least an equality of strength, every where; and has vanquished her enemies whenever they have ventured to contend with her—Her situa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion in point of defence is better, and be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>coming still more so, every hour—Both our army and navy are greater in number, and better in discipline and order, than ever they were—Wherever fleets and armies, have been sent, ours have pursued them.—It has always been the rule to fend the new-raised regiments abroad, in time of war, because the few we retain at home, should lead and be an example to the militia, in case of invasion. But to add new force to the national armaments, there is no boun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dary
<pb n="75" facs="76"/>to the spirit, readiness, and exer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of individuals at home, to support the dignity and the rights of this country—In one or two instances, such singular zeal has called for uncommon honors; and, in those extraordinary cases alone, for a limited time, and for a specific service, those gentlemen, who have hazarded their property, and lives, for the public safety, without any condition of rank or emolument for them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves, subsequent to such service, have been raised to <hi>temporary rank.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The complaint of our resources has con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stantly been repeated, when we have actually found them most efficient—Ten millions were raised last year almost in the course of a day. Nearly as much the year before: our revenues are improved; the sinking-fund is certainly increasing—War has hi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>therto produced no immediate distress to the state; and creates a more general cir<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culation than peace—The captures indeed are an exception—But let opposition ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plain these effects of <hi>their</hi> jealous dissatis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>faction against the profits of individual con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tractors,
<pb n="76" facs="77"/>who formerly conducted the whole business, and periods of sailing, for our mercantile fleets—But the navy-board hav<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing undertaken it of late, and in the midst of more complicated operations, the con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sequence has been, that too many of the convoys of transports, with stores, men, and provisions, have failed—The former effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted the business well, being well paid for it—The latter have done it ill, because they are not paid at all.</p>
               <p>In such a situation, the sense, the spirit of this country will still persevere, in a just and honourable cause—The happy appearance of returning loyalty in the southern colonies, with the certainty of their resources being cut off, joined to the gallantry of Lord Cornwallis's expedition up the Chesapeak Bay, give the fairest pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sage of connecting also the submission of the northern colonies—The former are most important to us, because they are more productive, and the inhabitants more na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>turally inclined to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="78"/>With such prospects therefore, the weak murmurs of domestic disaffection will be despised—The tyranny of that monster, Association, will only be a rule to its own miserable vassals—The independent coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try-gentlemen, who have seen the baneful effects of this fatal spirit, in that county where it first arose, will guard against the specious impostures of so dangerous an in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>novation—They, who in return for a hasty and misplaced confidence, received every contumelious and insulting reproach, will act with more caution, in avoiding those plausible pretences, which involve the most fatal consequences—The little ill that fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lowed in that instance, will hence be pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ductive of the greatest good. Every inde<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pendent character will now be no longer alarmed by Association, or insulted by in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>structions; but persevere in that bold, de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cided, manly firmness, that has ever been the surest guardian of the rights and li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berties of Great Britain.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="78" facs="79"/>
            <head>MISCELLANEOUS ELOQUENCE, OR, COLLATERAL RHETORIC FOR THE GALLERY.</head>
            <p>IN a mixed government like ours, public speaking has a sort of relative analogy to the compound structure of our consti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tution, and to the different orders of which it is composed. Thus the highest, and most exalted rank possesses a proud pre-eminence of phraseology, evidently characteristic of its sovereignty, and excellence: while the second degree, preserves a kind of equipoise in stile; which, by a due mixture of digni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty with plainness, denotes its intermediate balance, in the scale of legislative eloquence.—But chiefly, in the third estate, it is pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culiarly necessary, that the stream of rhe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>toric should have certain particles of popu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>larity, perpetually floating on its surface, as testimonies of the parent source, and foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain, from which it springs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="80"/>Upon this system, analogous principles might be formed, for the respective orato<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ry of the several degrees—At present, however, a few documents only shall be suggested for the particular application of this principle, to the rhetoric of the House of Commons; more especially to that truly constitutional part of it, occasionally ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dressed to the strangers in the gallery; whose "good report," as it is indeed "the brief and abstract <hi>chronicle</hi>" of parliamentary fame, it becomes peculiarly prudent, as well as honourable, to obtain.</p>
            <p>In general then, as to the mode of exer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cising this miscellaneous eloquence with most ease and efficacy; it may be fairly laid down, that all eminent and projecting sen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tences; all pointed, and epigrammatic quib<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bles; all metaphorical menaces; violent tropes; forced figures; and glaring orna<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments; are well calculated to rouse the at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tention, and hitch upon the memory, of <hi>the gallery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="81"/>These, like the emphasis of Italics in print<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing, summon the too negligent and careless mind, to pay a proper attention to many choice, and curious researches, intimately con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nected with the other matter; but which might otherwise perish from their refine<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment, or irretrievably slip bye, unnoticed.</p>
            <p>But one of the more certain, and secure resources of miscellaneous rhetoric (and which I prefer mentioning, from its double illustration of precept and example,) is that conciliating respect, which some popular ora<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tors more <hi>directly</hi> pay the <hi>gallery;</hi> in down<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>right acknowledgment of the <hi>"respectable appearance"</hi> of its company, on <hi>"important occasions."</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This condescending recognition (as it well deserves indeed) generally meets with a pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>per return; and it is pleasing to observe, how wonderfully attentive the whole body of strangers become, at the first mention of this general respectability —On some late occa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions, this idea has been carried somewhat too far: for there have not been wanting
<pb n="81" facs="82"/>certain popular orators, who politely with<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>held their arguments, after each division, and avowedly stopt all business, till the re-admis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sion of the audience.</p>
            <p>This however, tho' uncommonly hand<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>some, is dangerous; as it may give a handle to some moody, malignant mutes, for the ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>solute exclusion of all interlopers on debate.—But it will always be good, to prepare, and scatter, as occasion offers, some promis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cuous panegyrics, of nearly the same, tho' not absolutely so direct a tendency—for example—That <q>In a constitution, like ours, every thinking man, has a natural interest in public debate, which it is tyran<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nical to abridge, or violate.</q>—Or, that <q>It becomes all wise and cautious constituents to <hi>hear,</hi> in order to <hi>judge</hi> of their represen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tatives!</q>—Or again, that <q>It is no small consolation, in the present aweful crisis, to find a general diffusion of public vigilance and anxiety disseminated among all ranks, and orders of men; and more particularly in the present numerous and respectable <hi>ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pearance!</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="83"/>These, and all others of the same kind, properly accompanied by submissive tones, modulated breaks in the voice, and collateral attitudes of respectful inclination towards the gallery, scarcely ever fail of awakening the grateful attention, and sometimes, dormant curiosity of the strangers: especially at such times, as they have painfully, and patriotical<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly, persevered, to combat both fatigue and appetite, in hourly expectation of collecting some scattered scraps of mutilated eloquence, for their own private, or domestic, consump<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion at <hi>the Lycaeum,</hi> or <hi>Belle Assemblee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, in this species of miscellaneous elo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quence, the effect is comparatively weak, and contemptible, considered with others that are founded upon the same principle.</p>
            <p>Those already mentioned, can only be scattered occasionally, in the exordiums, and some episodical parts, of an oration.—The latter, and more efficient class, must take their station in the peroration, and declama<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tory close, of prolix speeches; as a <hi>corps de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>reserve,</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="84"/>to support and reinforce the main body of argument, after the harder service of the day.—These ought chiefly to consist of some very new, and deep theory; ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stract, and metaphysical; and calculated to give an idea of the originality, extent, and boldness of its author's mind; which, by connecting so many ingredients of sublimi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty, tends to inspire a sort of awe for such pre-eminence of genius, and to create a confused notion that this inventive wild<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness, if it could but be applied to the more serious business of politics, would, with equal brilliancy, strike out fresh systems of calculation, explore new resources of finance, and produce unheard of wonders and revo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lutions, in all the complicated concerns of political enterprize.</p>
            <p>As this description may serve to convey some idea of the last, and highest stile of miscellaneous rhetoric; it will be sufficient to elucidate the principle, by a single ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ample; on a subject too, not wholly un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>touched in the last session—UNIVERSAL
<pb n="84" facs="85"/>WHIGGISM—which is the better adapted for the proposed illustration from its unit<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing wildness, sublimity, invention, origi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nality, and a proper degree of extravagance; together with various other requisites, equally necessary for the perfection of this species of eloquence.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Well has it been imagined, that every human entity has universal, fixed, and in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nate ideas from the first, infused in every created soul common to <hi>all,</hi>—equal to <hi>all</hi>—perfect to <hi>all</hi>—as perfect to the savage in his cave, as to an Englishman in the se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nate!—Thus has universal nature endow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed the whole stock of human race, with equal and impartial powers, to receive and to enjoy the perfect completion of uni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>versal rights; those rights which our first thoughts inspire, and which are unalien<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ably the pride, and passion of man, the rights of UNIVERSAL WHIGGISM —To dispense, and perfect, these vast, original blessings to the whole world at large, was the great work reserv'd for our own times, and for our own country.—Now then, let
<pb n="85" facs="86"/>every nation, and people of the earth, con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>federate in one universal crusade, to rescue these sacred birth rights from barbarous violation!—The spirit of liberty is gone forth!—Her voice is the universal lan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guage of mankind—Let it be heard in the echoed thunder of the world—till UNI<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>VERSAL WHIGGISM incorporate, with human nature, and blend its essence with the soul.</q>
            </p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="86" facs="87"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>IF the form of these essays did not call for some comments on each subject, no answer would be attempted to such indis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>putable truths as are contained in the fore<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>going documents.—A very few words will be offered on this occasion, rather as addi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions, than amendments—It is apparent, that, in the several precepts for miscellane<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ous eloquence, there is least novelty in those of the first mentioned class, touching the direct or collateral appeals to the judgement, and the taste of the gallery: most of which, every judicious critic will immediately dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cover to be closely copied from the higher models of this collateral rhetoric, exhibited by the professors of our modern drama; wherein it is invariably the custom to over<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>charge particular passages, as attractive ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>peals to their gallery also; which, when properly <hi>given</hi> (as the actors phrase it) <hi>tell</hi> most surprizingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="88"/>But, it must be remembered, that much of the success in both case, depends on a curious interspersion of these brilliances, so as to relieve the heavier masses, and sustain due proportions of light and shade—For rhe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>torical flowers must be disposed and mingled with a studious delicacy of arrangement, and interweave their blended beauties in just contrast to the coarser texture of more sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stantial argument.</p>
               <p>Thus (to adapt our expressions to the sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ject) in some parts of the rhetorical ground<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>work, small seedlings of little <hi>violet</hi>-tropes should seem to fearfully revoke even the mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nuter elegance, they so faintly disclose—while, in others, more full-blown meta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phors, may diffuse their <hi>roseat</hi> luxuriance, and prodigally extend both stem and foliage among the thorny <hi>sweet-briars</hi> of irony; or entwining knots of syllogistic <hi>woodbine</hi>—with these also there should occasionally be interspersed, some brighter ornaments of wit, like the spangles of the pattern, to va<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riegate the <hi>silken</hi> sentences of perswasion,
<pb n="88" facs="89"/>and set them off with more dazzling de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>coration.</p>
               <p>As to the latter, and far more original division of miscellaneous eloquence, though something (it must be owned) of its baser kind is equally observable in the <hi>fustian<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tags</hi> and <hi>finales</hi> of our more ancient trage<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dies; and on the same plan too of leaving a good impression on the gallery; yet it is certainly, in its true nature and perfect state, most completely sublime: and in the ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>emplified instance defective only, in its un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>accountably narrow and restricted limitation to this world alone; when, with equal ease and efficacy, it might, and ought to be ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tended, not only to the inhabitants of our own moon, and other lunatic countries, but also to every nation and people in the whole planetary system: so that, in any great con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gress of astronomical worlds, <hi>universal whig<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gism</hi> should as certainly be the ruling prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple of the delegates of Jupiter's satellites, as a whig-president must be deputed by the constituents of Saturn's ring—It is only necessary therefore to add, that the respect
<pb n="89" facs="90"/>for this kind of gigantic rhetoric will be greatly enhanced, by a proportionable elocu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion and action, to justify and grace its mag<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nificence.—For here, though the figures are intentionally dilated and monstrous, and the colouring systematically overcharged, like those of <hi>cupola paintings,</hi> yet to the igno<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rant auditor above, the rhetoric of the for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mer will seem as natural and just; as the symmetry of the latter appears exact, and proportionable, to the stupid gazer below—For the eye and the ear are equally delighted and deceived, in both the one, and the other case.</p>
               <p>In the delivery therefore of these <hi>rhetori<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cal caricatures,</hi> all that can be requisite to compleat their effect, is to accompany them by congenial degrees of violence and vehe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mence, in expression, and deportment; or, in short, that the gestures and elocution of the orator, who pronounces them, may somewhat resemble those of a furious <hi>feugle<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>man,</hi> or a fanatic in a frenzy.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="90" facs="91"/>
            <head>CHANGE THE MINISTRY.</head>
            <p>AS most of the writers, who have treated of the English constitution, (particularly those of foreign countries) very ingeniously prove, that a revolution is ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessary once a century to renovate its spi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rit; so, in order to proportionably purify our interior government, the Ministry, by a fair and equable calculation, should un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dergo a change <hi>once</hi> at least, if not much oft'ner, in the course of every ten years.</p>
            <p>More or less degrees of this principle of <hi>mutability</hi> are incident to all bodies; na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tural, or politic; and universally tend to re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>new their genuine force and purity.</p>
            <p>But if this theory had never before been applied to the administrations of this coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try, surely the present ministers, and the present times, would be admitted as irre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fragable
<pb n="91" facs="92"/>arguments, in favour of that <hi>na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tional supplication,</hi> which now universally prevails, for the dismission of a ruinous Ministry, and the substitution of a virtuous Opposition.</p>
            <p>This national demand is grounded on principles as plain, as they ought to be decisive: namely, that the present Mini<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stry are the sole and original causes of that fatal source of all our miseries, the Ame<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rican war; and, on the contrary, that Opposition have from the first moment, unanimously reprobated the policy, and, with uniform consistency, ever afterwards condemned the principle of colony-taxa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Such is the plain broad basis of that na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tional supplication to change the present ruinous, and execrated Ministers—A sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plication, which every district of this coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try has not only united to enforce, but more distinctly promoted, with peculiar wisdom, in the late honourable delegation of its best and greatest supporters, the members of
<pb n="92" facs="93"/>Westminster and Surrey; unawed by the menaces, uncorrupted by the odious influ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ence of prerogative!</p>
            <p>To this national supplication for the dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mission of the present flagitious Ministers, the substitution of their virtuous Opposers, is, by necessary implication, inseparably connected.—But, if the public virtues of that patriot band have not sufficiently stamp<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed the justice of their claims on every Eng<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lish heart; let cooler, and more deli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berate judgement trace their higher title to pre-eminence of station, in unrivaled supe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riority of genius, in unparallelled excel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lence of education; let their habits, studies, and private virtues, (all exercised, with un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dissipated attention to advance the public good; all directed to the enrichment of their fellow-citizens; the diminution of national expence; and the promotion of justice, probity, and honour,) be at once the plainest, and surest proofs of their dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>interested views, as well as the best pledges of their future upright, and honest con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="93" facs="94"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>TO this great, and most important of all questions; this cause, and end of all logic, argument, and eloquence; this attractive power, to whose magnetic force, all the lightest, or weightiest bo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dies of reasoning must irresistably gra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vitate; with mixed sensations of regret, and satisfaction, we are at length ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rived.—Here should every specious de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duction, and every established proof, be equally admitted both from the advocates who attack, and the witnesses who defend, the cause of administration—Here should each slightest particle of evidence, each mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nute and shadowy distinction of opinion, be fairly and impartially deposited in that golden balance, which even-handed justice should suspend and poise, to weigh the doubtful conflict of political warfare—But, to assist at such a trial would be far too so<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lemn, too laborious, for profaner pens—
<pb n="94" facs="95"/>It is a task that may be consigned, with far greater security, to the busy zeal, and persevering patience, of polemical politi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cians—A hasty and imperfect answer to the foregoing argument, shall conclude <hi>these</hi> slighter toils—It must be owned then, that the philosophy of ministerial changes, is worthy the solidity of its fo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>reign theorists—It seems indeed very closely borrowed from the Parisian vicissitudes of fashion, dress, and even furniture, for the respective seasons—On so accommo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dating a system, many fanciful varieties might be practised, to variegate successive administrations; which, with that view, might be <hi>quarterly;</hi> and composed of more <hi>decided</hi> characters for the two greater divi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions of the year, and a kind of <hi>demi-saison</hi> statesmen for the lesser.</p>
               <p>This would give an impartial rotation to all sorts of parties, and, by a just adaption of dispositions, and tempers, analogous to their successive periods, might produce the happiest, and most extraordinary effects—For, young adventuring politicians might
<pb n="95" facs="96"/>sow the principles of a scheme in the spring administration, which, when cultivated, and matured, by coalitions of the summer and autumnal ministries, would finally pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duce the richest fruits, to be treasured, and dispensed, by the colder caution and <hi>wintry</hi> wisdom of more experienced counsellors. But after all, changes of ministry are neither as sudden, nor as easy, as changes of wea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther, or changes of scenery at a play house.—And as the principle of <hi>mutability</hi> was not much insisted on, it will be fairer to re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cur to the more serious and material sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stance of the argument.—The petitions—and the two other great points—the <hi>origin</hi> of our troubles—and the consistency of opposition.</p>
               <p>To these it may be briefly answered, that if it can possibly be prov'd, that <hi>one</hi> of the petitions was not invented, framed, and circulated, by those gentlemen, whose ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointment and elevation they severally dic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tate, the truth of them <hi>all,</hi> shall be univer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sally admitted.—But, on the contrary, if the whole pile of them was raised, fabrica<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted,
<pb n="96" facs="97"/>and supported, by one, and, the same set of men, for one, and the same purpose; the force of their evidence will not be much relied on.—Next, as to the <hi>origin</hi> of the war, it is sufficient to repeat that trite truth, "<hi>The</hi> STAMP ACT was, not the work of the present ministry!" And, in respect to the uniform resistance to the principle of American subordination, the equally self-evident proposition must al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ways be remembered "That to opposition alone are we indebted, for that absolute and universal claim to it; THE DECLARATORY LAW."—Two most trite refutations, of the two tritest of all charges! which however as indisputably disprove the imputed de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>linquency on the one side, as they abso<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lutely overthrow the ridiculous claim to consistency on the other.</p>
               <p>But, with regard indeed to the great crite<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rion of national opinion, <hi>the two popular elec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions;</hi> certainly much stress is wisely and justly laid upon <hi>that</hi> point—nor would it prove an unpleasing task for some advocate of op<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>position, to draw an exact parallel, in the
<pb n="97" facs="98"/>manner of Plutarch, between the <hi>four</hi> trium<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phant candidates; wherein it would as evi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dently appear, that the <hi>two</hi> admirals, who se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>verally share these domestic honours, are not more precisely alike in principles and con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct; than the two statesmen also of the same elections, resemble each other, in high birth, exalted genius, cultivated taste, sound reasoning, strict honour, and <hi>undamped</hi> for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>titude.—Which close, and mathematical, consideration of the several relative pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portions of merit, thus mutually com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pared, in their respective parallels, must, not only demonstrate the exact correspon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dence of their reciprocal excellencies, and therefore, by fair consequence, the truth, and justice of declaring these two elec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions a common, and equal standard of national opinion, but also at once overthrow every cavilling notion that may arise of their rediculous dissimilitude, and establish them, for the whole succeeding session of parliament, as the great political parallel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>logram of public spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="99"/>It may however be unnecessary to continue much longer the mysterious insinuation of INFLUENCE, so industriously circulated, preparatory to these boasted triumphs—at the moment, it might have been judicious, nay, possibly, necessary, to lean on this po<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pular argument—But to continue it, might now appear unworthy the gallantry and spirit of its author, if not too like the fret<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ful resource of disappointed pride.—When the tempest had dissevered the good old vessel, despair might fly to any refuge.—The gilded lion at the head, was then no longer to be upheld, by romantic enthu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>siasm, as the glittering sign and splendid presage of <hi>victory:</hi> distress and danger had destroyed all fanciful respect; and exhaus<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted, sinking, strength caught at that majestic ruin, which, faithfull even to its debaser, elevated and supported the very hand that selfishly depressed it.—It has had its use!—performed its service!—Let it be no longer exposed, and dragged about, for low mockery and insolent profanation; but generously and gratefully <hi>laid up,</hi> like a vo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive
<pb n="99" facs="100"/>tablet in the temple of Neptune, the consecrated record of unhoped-for refuge.</p>
               <p>It remains only to say a few words on the last and powerful argument for the Change of Ministry; namely, the decisive superi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ority of abilities, on the part of Opposition—this favourite <hi>common place,</hi> so perpetually, and so modestly urged, might lead to per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sonal parallels, of all others the most invi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dious, as well as disputable.—On this question, every man must judge for him<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self.—All that shall be said here— is this; that it must indeed be a much more infi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nite superiority of talent, than frequently occurs in the scale of human understand<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing, that can, at once, render the qualifica<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions of any set of men (who are compa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ratively unconversant with official business, or, at least, not equally versed of late years in political negociations, foreign, or domes<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tic;) so supremely superexcellent to those of others, some of whom have been literally educated in office, others passed the greatest part of their lives in foreign embassies of
<pb n="100" facs="101"/>complicated concern, with the ablest, and purest reputation; and all are perfectly <hi>equal</hi> to their competitors in every advan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tage of rank and situation.—To this the thousand declamatory common place re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plies of practised fraud, veteran subtlety, and professional treachery, as they may be easily imagined, shall be silently despised.—Certainly there are individuals in oppo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sition, of most extensive, and possibly un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>equalled understanding, the accession of whose abilities would give lustre to public council, and be indeed almost a national blessing.—But if the miserable appendages of party must for ever fix their ponderous and oppressive influence on talents formed for free, and bold aspiring; then may their perverted excellence be justly pronounced the ruin of their country; and while, to vul<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gar observation, this luminous and malig<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nant prodigy, this splendid, but baneful por<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tent, scatters terror and amazement; by every more thinking mind, it will at once be wondered at, and lamented; admired, and deplored.—For pre-eminence of genius becomes doubly pernicious by the abuse of
<pb n="101" facs="102"/>its own superiority, and the contaminating degradation of the faculties of others; and is indeed, both in effect, and by example,—The decay of a whole age.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>