<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Short sketch of temporary regulations: (until better shall be proposed) for the intended settlement on the grain coast of Africa, near Sierra Leona.</title>
            <author>Sharp, Granville, 1735-1813.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K020428.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3305646380</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Short sketch of temporary regulations: (until better shall be proposed) for the intended settlement on the grain coast of Africa, near Sierra Leona.</title>
                  <author>Sharp, Granville, 1735-1813.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4],88p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed by H. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <date>1786.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K020428.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3305646380</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Granville Sharp.</note>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT935.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>SHORT SKETCH OF TEMPORARY REGULATIONS (UNTIL BETTER SHALL BE PROPOSED) FOR THE INTENDED SETTLEMENT ON THE GRAIN COAST OF AFRICA, NEAR <hi>SIERRA LEONA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> PRINTED BY H. BALDWIN, FLEET-STREET. M DCC LXXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb facs="2"/>
         <head>A SHORT SKETCH OF TEMPORARY REGULATIONS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </head>
         <div type="part">
            <head>FRANKPLEDGE.</head>
            <p>THE most certain and effectual mode of securing peace, right, and mutual protection, for any community, is the old English system of mutual <hi>Frankpledge,</hi> or <hi>free suretyship,</hi> given by all <hi>the house<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>holders,</hi> for themselves and each other, in exact numerical divisions of <hi>tens</hi> and hundreds; which, in the English law<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>books, is called <hi>"Maxima securitas"</hi>—<hi>"the greatest security,"</hi> though it is now unhappily neglected, and consequently crimes abound and increase; so that,
<pb n="2" facs="3"/>notwithstanding the horrible increase also of <hi>bloody laws</hi> to intimidate offenders, yet there is <hi>no effectual security</hi> from vio<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lence and robbery, either in our streets or roads, or even in our chambers; since the houses of the rich and great, nay of the first officers of the state, are not ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>empted from the nocturnal intrusion of housebreakers, insomuch that even the Lord Chancellor and Honourable Speaker of the House of Commons have lately experienced the common danger, and the deplorable want of the antient <hi>"Maxima securitas."</hi> That funda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mental system of <hi>English polity</hi> is so little known among us at present, that many well-meaning persons are induced, by their fears, to wish for <hi>security,</hi> on a much less eligible plan, formed on the model of the arbitrary system of govern<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment in France, commonly called <hi>police,</hi> the introduction of which would be an utter perversion of the first principles of
<pb n="3" facs="4"/>
               <hi>legal</hi> government in England. The inha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bitants even of the most distant settle<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments under the crown of Great-Britain must not adopt any <hi>polity</hi> that is essen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tially <hi>inconsistent</hi> with the <hi>Maxima secu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ritas,</hi> ordained and required by the common law of England.</p>
            <p>The community of free African set<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tlers, however, have already adopted (as I am informed) a small variation from the old English model of numerical di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>visions, by forming themselves into di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>visions of <hi>dozens,</hi> instead of <hi>tithings</hi> or <hi>tens;</hi> but as this little change is by no means <hi>inconsistent</hi> with the true princi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ples and intention of our legal English <hi>frankpledge,</hi> I am at liberty to acknow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ledge a most hearty approbation of it, as being an arrangement far more con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>venient and effectual for securing perfect subordination, peace, and good govern<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment, even than the antient legal divi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions
<pb n="4" facs="5"/>into <hi>tens</hi> or <hi>decenaries,</hi> because each <hi>dozen</hi> will have one <hi>chief</hi> or <hi>headborough,</hi> and one <hi>assistant headborough,</hi> to govern and lead a compleat complement of ten <hi>deciners;</hi> so that the division may still with propriety retain the old <hi>legal</hi> name of a <hi>tithing</hi> or <hi>decenary;</hi> and the <hi>hundred division</hi> may be rendered literally and strictly an <hi>hundred</hi> families, by appoint<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing one <hi>hundreder,</hi> two <hi>chiefs</hi> of <hi>fifties,</hi> and one town clerk (or clerk of the hundred) over every <hi>eight dozens;</hi> whereby the legal <hi>hundred,</hi> in its civil capacity (for the maintenance of <hi>peace, justice,</hi> and <hi>common right,</hi> according to the first principles of our constitutional <hi>polity,</hi> the most effectual for all the purposes of good government) will consist of—
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Hundreder,</hi> or centurion
<note place="bottom" n="*">Who in the common law is a <hi>high constable</hi> and <hi>"justiciarius,"</hi> or justice of the peace.</note>,—</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Chiefs</hi> of <hi>fifties—superior constables,</hi> and presiding <hi>justices</hi> in the weekly Tithing-courts
<note place="bottom">† Or rather, in the courts or four tithings, or dozens, collected together.</note>;</item>
                  <item>1 <hi>Town-clerk,</hi> or Clerk of the hun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dred
<note place="bottom" n="‡">With a proper salary, to register all judgments and debts, and to be allowed two or more assistants, if necessary, from the best qualified of the deciners, with suitable salaries also for their trouble.</note>,</item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Headboroughs</hi> being constables in ordinary.</item>
                  <item>8 <hi>assistant Headboroughs</hi> or consta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bles extraordinary.</item>
                  <item>80 <hi>Deciners</hi>—masters of families or householders
<note place="bottom" n="§">Who, jointly with the chiefs of their several divi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions, pledge each other, and their respective families or dependants for the publick peace and common right, and are termed in law, <hi>boni et legales homines, "Good and true men."</hi>
                     </note>, viz.</item>
                  <item>100 <hi>Householders</hi> in all, who must
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
                     <hi>equally</hi> contribute to support all the burthens of the state, and of course must be entitled to an <hi>equal</hi> voice in the <hi>"common council,"</hi> or parliament, of their settlement; which on the African coast is called <hi>Palaaver;</hi> and if the whole body of householders should hereafter, by God's blessing, become too numerous for a <hi>personal</hi> attendance in their <hi>common council</hi> they will be all equally entitled to elect a proper number of deputies from their respective divisions to represent them in the supreme council; and that, in a due and <hi>equal</hi> proportion to their numbers; for otherwise their representa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion would be rendered most banefully <hi>delusive</hi> and <hi>corrupt!</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="8"/>And in a military capacity the same hundred house<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>holders will form a corps of <hi>militia</hi> consisting of
<list>
                  <item>1 Captain</item>
                  <item>2 Lieutenants</item>
                  <item>1 Muster master and commissary</item>
                  <item>8 Serjeants</item>
                  <item>8 Corporals</item>
                  <item>80 <hi>Milites</hi> or men of arms</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Amounting altogether to 100 free militia men or armed de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciners.</p>
            <p>To these must also be added the sons, apprentices, and in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dentured servants of the deci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners, viz. all the males of 16 years of age and upwards, who by the <hi>common law</hi> are required to be armed, and of course to be disciplined in the use of arms. The average of males above 16 years of age may be stated, I believe, at three to each family, includ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing all the persons above de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>scribed: so that in a few years, if the settlement suc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceeds, there may probably be added to the 100 armed de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciners at least 200 Privates or rank and file.</p>
            <p>In all 300 militia men in each hundred division, a corps that may be rendered sufficiently effectual to support the executive justice of a free, legal government, within any extent of
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>land which an <hi>hundred families</hi> can fairly occupy, and amply sufficient to supply a roster or rotation of very easy service in the necessary <hi>watch</hi> and <hi>ward</hi> of the settlement.</p>
            <p>N. B. This average number of males would be rather too large, were not ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>prentices and <hi>indentured servants</hi> in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cluded; but in a new settlement, where <hi>ordinary labour</hi> is chiefly wanted, there is a great probability that the <hi>indentured servants</hi> will far exceed the number I have estimated.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="10"/>
            <head>WATCH AND WARD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Rotation.—Exercise.—Discipline, preserved by Fines of Labour.—Watch Duty of Indentured. Servants to be allowed and deducted from the Term of their Indentures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>hundred deciners</hi> should serve, three at a time at least, with six privates, in due rotation, as the nightly guard of the <hi>hundred division;</hi> which guard being divided into three parties of one deciner and two privates each, one party may patrole, whilst the other two are sta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tioned at the gate-house, or watch<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tower, alternately watching and resting every four hours; but the patroling and watching party must relieve each other every two hours, until it is their turn to rest four hours in the inner guard room; by this means the watch duty may be
<pb n="10" facs="11"/>rendered very easy and <hi>equal</hi> to all ranks of persons in the hundred; and even if the captain and four of the <hi>oldest</hi> de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciners, together with eight of the <hi>youngest</hi> privates be excused the nightly duty, the rotation of this easy service to each individual will be only once in thirty-two nights, viz. less than twelve nights in a year, which cannot interfere with their ordinary employments: but for the sake of keeping up proper disci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pline, triple the number ought to assem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble in rotation, every evening and morn<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing, to set and to discharge the guard, after the performance of a short military exercise all together, under the inspec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of the captain, or one of the lieute<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nants, (being previously trained or drilled in small squads under the inspection of their respective serjeants) and this at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tendance may be rendered perfectly <hi>equal</hi> and regular to all ranks, by a proper roster of service, duly distinguishing the
<pb n="11" facs="12"/>courses of <hi>Watch and Ward</hi> from the rotation of attendance for mere exer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cise.</p>
            <p>Want of punctuality in musters, or absence, should be punished in propor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion to the time lost, by <hi>equal</hi> fines on all ranks of men, estimated at so many <hi>days</hi> or <hi>hours labour</hi> (as hereafter ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plained) towards the support of the public Exchequer.</p>
            <p>Disobedience of orders on service, and inattention or carelessness in exercise, and all such other misdemeanors, should be likewise punished by <hi>fines of labour</hi> for publick profit.</p>
            <p>The watch duty of an indentured ser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vant should be rewarded by a deduction of one day's service from <hi>his indentures</hi> for each night that he attends on mili<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tary
<pb n="12" facs="13"/>duty, which will encourage his vigilance, and win his attention to the interests of the settlement; and by his being entered on the same roster with the whole body of <hi>deciners,</hi> and by serv<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing in due rotation with them, he will soon perceive the facility and happiness of becoming a <hi>deciner</hi> himself, by proper diligence in fulfilling his contract of la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bour; especially as the regulations, here<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>after to be mentioned, will insure him from the imposition of more service than is due, and from the fraud or oppression of an unjust master; and he will acquire still further security by being known, and by becoming acquainted with other deciners (besides his master) in the mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>litia service.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="13" facs="14"/>
            <head>FREE LABOUR.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Free Labour to be the Standard or Medium of Traffick instead of Cash.—Times of Labour (publick or hired) to be general and uniform.— Evening Prayer and the Advantages of it.— Limitation of Labour per Day to eight Hours.—Six Hours on Saturdays.—That the People may attend the Courts and Folkmotes to improve their Decernment of Good and Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>HUMAN Labour</hi> is more essential and valuable than any other article in new settlements, which chiefly depend on the cultivation and produce of the earth for their subsistence and commer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cial profit. On this account, though the price of provisions is generally lower in new settlements than in communi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ties of long standing, yet the price of <hi>Free Labour</hi> is always much higher; and higher still, or rather infinitely <hi>more
<pb n="14" facs="15"/>expensive</hi> (however slaveholders may reckon) is <hi>the labour of slaves,</hi> besides the abominable injustice, the corruption of manners, the danger, and other <hi>curses,</hi> which <hi>always attend</hi> the tolera<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of slavery! <hi>Free labour,</hi> therefore, in all new settlements, ought to be made the <hi>standard,</hi> or <hi>medium,</hi> whereby to rate the value of all the necessaries of life, as well as of all articles of com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>merce in the settlement: a cow, sheep, or hog, or a bushel of corn, should each be valued at a proportionable number of <hi>day's labour,</hi> estimated at eight hours actual labour per day; and a pig, rabbit, or fowl, at so many <hi>hours labour,</hi> ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cording to their respective sizes; and for the fractional estimation of smaller arti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cles, the hours may be reduced to <hi>minutes,</hi> and thereby afford an excellent substitute for money as a medium of traffic and exchange, whereon a <hi>paper currency</hi> may be established, which will
<pb n="15" facs="16"/>always bear an <hi>intrinsic value,</hi> without diminution, as hereafter explained under the head of <hi>Publick Revenue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The daily commencement of publick labour and of hired labour, and all the necessary cessations from labour for rest and refreshment, should be limited to stated periods of time, rendered uniform and general, throughout the settlement, by the periodical summons of a publick bell, as in our <hi>dock yards</hi> and great ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nufactories, for the more effectual pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vention of imposition by the employer or employed.</p>
            <p>By the limitation of labour to eight hours per day, the rateable or legal days work (instead of continuing from six in the morning to six in the evening, as with us) will end at four in the after<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>noon, including two whole hours for necessary refreshment and rest; unless it
<pb n="16" facs="17"/>should be thought more convenient in general to begin at five in the morning, and to work three hours till eight, and then, after resting half an hour at break<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fast, to work three hours and an half more till noon, when a moderate and temperate meal, suitable to the heat of the climate, may be rendered more re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>freshing and healthful to the labourer by a <hi>general sestoo,</hi> or sleeping time, during the meridean heat till half past one; which rest of one hour and an half, at one time, will be amply sufficient to recruit them for the remaining burthen of the rateable labour, or legal day's work, viz. one hour and an half more, ending at three o'clock in the afternoon, when the <hi>evening</hi> of the antients com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>menced, and the appointed hour of <hi>even<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing sacrifice</hi> in the patriarchal times. If, therefore, the new society would agree to assemble at <hi>that hour,</hi> in whatever place they shall afterwards appropriate
<pb n="17" facs="18"/>to religious worship, and there join toge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther in a very short <hi>general form of prayer and evening sacrifice of thanks</hi> (in which, to remove all objections about the value of time, they need not be detained much longer than about five minutes, to ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>press all that may be absolutely neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary for every good purpose of prayer and thanksgiving, at least as a <hi>daily</hi> ser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vice) they will soon be convinced that no human measure is so well calculated to add real dignity to the ordinary la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bourer, as well with respect to his own <hi>internal</hi> improvement, as in the out<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward esteem and consideration which it will necessarily insure to him from others, by continually reminding the rich and higher ranks of men that the daily la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bourer is their brother and their <hi>equal</hi> in the sight of God, and that all men ought to be <hi>equally</hi> servants to <hi>the same Lord!</hi> I could wish that a short daily morning prayer might also be adopted at
<pb n="18" facs="19"/>nine o'clock, after breakfast, but I pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose with diffidence, lest publick prayers even <hi>only once</hi> a day should be obtained with difficulty.</p>
            <p>As some of the <hi>out lots</hi> will be distant about two miles from the centre of the township, it may perhaps be more expe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dient to commence the rateable daily labour even half an hour sooner still, than I have last proposed, viz. at half past four in the cool of the morning, where<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>by all <hi>publick labour</hi> will end at half past two in the afternoon, which will allow time for labourers in the distant lots to repair to the general assembly of the township, at <hi>evening prayer.</hi> And an officer from every dozen may be ordered to be prepared, by a previous examina<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, at the publick bank of all the in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dents in course for each day's labour; that after being discharged in the pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick books, they may be cancelled, and
<pb n="19" facs="20"/>most expeditiously returned to those who have fulfilled them; all which, by the happy system of <hi>Frankpledge,</hi> may be most easily effected with very little loss of time; so that the labourers may return from the centre of the township to their own private lots, and have near five hours of leisure to themselves to cul<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tivate their own land, even if they work no later than eight at night, which will allow them ample time for rest, espe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cially as the mid-day <hi>sestoo</hi> will render less sleep necessary at night.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="21"/>A seventh part of the year shall be appropriated more particularly to God's service, and shall be duly observed and kept holy, on the pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nalty of seven weeks, or forty-two days labour in the publick lots for every breach of this universal law of God, either in buying, selling, or <hi>working for pecuniary profit;</hi> or for <hi>travelling,</hi> unless a very urgent necessity can be proved: and this penalty to be doubled on a repeti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion or continuance of the offence. 52 Sundays or days of our Lord.</p>
            <p>Two more days shall be appro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>priated to a religious commemora<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of our Lord's birth and expia<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tory death, at the usual seasons; and a third day to the great annual <hi>view of Frankpledge,</hi> to be ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointed at some convenient season, after the greatest and most general harvest of the year, the remem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>brance of which shall also be so<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lemnized on that day by religious thanksgiving both at the opening and conclusion of the <hi>view of Frankpledge;</hi>—so that the 365 days of the year will be further reduced by the deduction also of 3 Holidays.</p>
            <p>The abovementioned Sundays and holidays, amounting to fifty<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>five days, being deducted from the year, there will remain only 310 Days of labour.</p>
            <p>365</p>
            <p>The days of labour shall be rated throughout the new settlement only at
<pb n="21" facs="22"/>eight hours actual labour each day, in all agreements or contracts for labour, as well of apprentices and indentured servants, as of those who are hired by the day; that all labourers may have some leisure hours every day to culti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate their own private lots of land. And only six hours labour are to be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quired by law on Saturdays, without any deduction from the labourer's profit for the deficiency, because it is for the pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick benefit that the people should have leisure to attend the courts and folkmotes (to be held on Saturdays) in order that they may gradually improve that natural faculty of <hi>reason</hi> or <hi>knowledge</hi> which is inherited by all men from our first pa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rents, and may <hi>"have their understand<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ings exercised by habit to discern both good and evil."</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="22" facs="23"/>
            <head>FREEDOM AND PROTECTION TO STRANGERS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Limitation of Indentured Service.—An injured Indentured Servant to be turned over to the Publick Exchequer.—Fugitive Slaves to be protected, and allowed to purchase Land by Labour, and after due Time of Probation to be admitted to the Rank of Deciners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS soon as a slave shall set his foot within the bounds of the new settlement, he shall be deemed a <hi>free man,</hi> and be equally entitled with the rest of the in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>habitants to the protection of the laws, and to all the natural rights of humanity. And the service even of <hi>indentured ser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vants</hi> shall be strictly limited, viz. no person to be bound for a longer term than five years after the age of twenty<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>one, or of seven years if bound after the age of fourteen years, or of ten years if
<pb n="23" facs="24"/>bound after the age of eleven years. And if any indentured servant shall have just cause to complain of his master's beha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>viour to him, he shall be turned over to the care of the <hi>general asylum for males;</hi> and his <hi>labour,</hi> for the limited term of his indentures, shall be turned over to the <hi>publick Exchequer,</hi> which shall purchase of the master all the re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>maining term of service. If any slave shall <hi>escape from his master</hi> in any part of the neighbouring country where the abominable traffic in human beings is tolerated, and shall apply at any town<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ship within the free settlements for an asylum, he shall be received and pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tected in the publick asylum; for this is required by an indispensable moral law of God, and, of course, by the laws of England—<q>Thou shalt not deliver unto his master the servant</q> (or <hi>slave,</hi> for all <hi>slaves</hi> are servants)
<q>which is es<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>caped
<pb n="24" facs="25"/>from his master unto thee; he shall dwell with thee, even among you, in that place which he shall choose, in one of thy gates, where it liketh him best: Thou shalt not oppress him,</q> Deut. xxiii. 15, 16. The stranger, how<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ever, shall be required to promise obe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dience to the laws of the settlement, and due legal submission to the chiefs of the division, wherein he is admitted and pledged; and also to enter himself on the publick roster of equal service in <hi>Watch and Ward,</hi> when of proper age. And in order to obtain his livelyhood, independently of individuals, he shall, if he is above twenty years of age, be al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lowed to purchase, of the publick Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chequer, one quarter of a lot of land, for one year's service, consisting of 310 days service of eight hours each, (and a proportionable addition to the term, if under that age) for which quarter of a
<pb n="25" facs="26"/>lot, he shall be taxed only one quarter part of a deciner's contribution to paro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chial and publick exigences and expences; which proportionable contribution of labour for <hi>taxes</hi> shall commence from the time he receives the land; but the Exchequer shall give him credit for the <hi>labour of purchase</hi> until the second year after he receives the land; in the course of which only <hi>half of the labour,</hi> viz. 155 days, may be demanded, and the remainder in the course of the third year, whereby the stranger will have <hi>spare days of labour</hi> to enable him (by giving indents for it) to purchase neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>saries for his farm: And he shall be al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lowed a separate chamber in the publick asylum or inn, until he is able to build an house or cottage upon his own lot. After he has faithfully discharged his debt of service according to his first con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tract with the Exchequer, and also his
<pb n="26" facs="27"/>other contract debts with private indivi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duals (for all such private debts should be entered in the publick Exchequer, in order to give <hi>intrinsic value to the in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dentures for labour,</hi> as the state of <hi>every man's</hi> credit and circumstances will then appear on the publick books) he shall be allowed another quarter of a lot on the same terms, and so on till he has acquired a compleat lot; when, if he has by his good and faithful behaviour proved himself worthy of the rank and trust of a <hi>deciner,</hi> he shall be admitted to all the privileges and civil rights of the community as a free member and <hi>equal proprietor</hi> of the whole settlement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="28"/>
            <head>REDEMPTION FROM SLAVERY.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Redemption from Slavery.—Price to be repaid by a short limited Service to the Publick Exche<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quer.—Profit by Redemption infinitely superior to the Profits of the Slave Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THOUGH it is a fundamental prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple of the settlement, that all <hi>slaves</hi> shall be deemed <hi>free</hi> as soon as they enter it, so that no person can retain, or sell, or employ, <hi>a slave</hi> within the bounds of the settlement, yet there can be no impropriety in providing a means of re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>paying the expence of <hi>redeeming slaves,</hi> on the condition of a <hi>short limited service,</hi> as an apprentice or indentured servant, provided that the actual prices given for redemption can be sufficiently authenti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cated, that no more may be repaid, except, perhaps, a limited profit, not exceeding ten per cent. by way of in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terest,
<pb n="28" facs="29"/>for advancing the price; and pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vided also that the said <hi>limited service</hi> of the contract be not claimable by any <hi>individual,</hi> but by the <hi>publick Exchequer only,</hi> after the redeemed person has con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sented to work out the price; whereby all possibility of <hi>domestic slavery,</hi> or <hi>pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate oppression,</hi> will be excluded; and the Exchequer will give an ample equi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>valent to the redeemed person, to insure his voluntary consent to a contract for a <hi>limited time of labour,</hi> not only by the protection it will afford him, but also by putting him in possession of a portion of land, equal to the quarter part of a <hi>de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciner's</hi> lot, to be increased as he discharges his debt of labour; and by finding him provisions until he shall be able to raise provisions from his own land. The publick Exchequer will be enabled, by the consent of a majority of the set<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tlers, thus to dispose of land, because all the <hi>unoccupied</hi> land in the settlement
<pb n="29" facs="30"/>is to be deemed as <hi>common,</hi> in which the whole body of settlers, sent out from England, if above sixteen years of age, whether indentured or not, shall be en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>titled to an <hi>equal share,</hi> and therefore no land must be appropriated, but by <hi>com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon</hi> consent. Suppose the redemption of a man should cost ten pounds (which I believe is about the average price on the coast) and suppose the labour of such a stranger be estimated only at sixpence ster<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ling per day (though it is certainly worth much more, perhaps three or four times as much) a limited service, by the re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>deemed person, of five years to the pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick Exchequer, as an equivalent for the purchase of a full lot of protected land, with a gradual introduction to all the privileges of a free English settlement, will amount, at 310 working days per annum (fifty-two sundays and three holi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>days being deducted for the reasons al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ready mentioned under the head <hi>of Free
<pb n="30" facs="31"/>Labour)</hi> will amount, I say, to 38l. 15s. out of which, after paying 10l. the price of redemption, and 10 per cent for the advance of money, viz. 1l. more, there will remain in the publick Exchequer (towards supplying food and necessaries to the labourer, till he can provide for himself, and for risque of loss by sick<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness or death) the sum of 27l. 15s. the surplus of which, if the redeemed per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>son lives and does well, becomes the <hi>property of the publick,</hi> in which he <hi>himself</hi> enjoys an equal share of pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fit; so that the <hi>purchase of a slave,</hi> un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>der so equitable a regulation, will be really and truly a <hi>Redemption from Sla<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>very</hi> to a state of <hi>freedom</hi> and protection. And if the <hi>voluntary labour of a man</hi> should really be worth three times what I have estimated (as I really believe it is) the profit for redemption, for 11l. dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bursed, will amount to 105l. 5s. which is 956 9/11l. per cent. in favour of the
<pb n="31" facs="32"/>publick Exchequer! Nay, the profit may be fairly estimated at a much higher rate! for if the <hi>free labour,</hi> which the redeemed person pays for his lot of land, be employed by the elected trustees of the Exchequer in the <hi>publick lots</hi> of land, they may expect to receive at least the <hi>or<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dinary production of land,</hi> for the labour bestowed upon it; which even in our northern climate may be rated at a <hi>triple amount</hi> (and much more may certainly be expected in the fertile and productive climate of Africa) so that the <hi>ordinary profit</hi> may fairly be stated at 315l. 15s. for 11l. disbursed, which is at the rate of 2870 5/11;l. per cent. in favour of the <hi>publick Exchequer</hi> in which the redeemed person himself would have an <hi>equal pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perty</hi> with the rest of the community. Let the advocates for slavery shew, if they can, that <hi>involuntary servitude</hi> is equally profitable! The intolerable ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pence of all kinds of labour wherever
<pb n="32" facs="33"/>slavery is permitted, when compared with the price of labour in <hi>free</hi> countries, will sufficiently confute them. But more shall be said of the great profits of <hi>Free Labour,</hi> under the head of <hi>Publick Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>venue, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>AGRARIAN LAW.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Money for purchasing Land, to be invested in Presents for the African Chiefs.—Chiefs to be previously acquainted with some necessary Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ditions.—All the Settlers to be restrained from purchasing Land for</hi> private Property, <hi>until the Bargains for the</hi> Publick <hi>Land are con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cluded.—The Presents to be deemed Publick Stock.—All the Settlers above sixteen Years of Age to be</hi> equally <hi>entitled to the Land.—Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cautions for fixing on the Spot for the first Township.—Settlers to be obedient to the Agent and how long.—Reserve of Land.— Limitation of Land.—Limitation of landed
<pb n="33" facs="34"/>Possession.—Manner of laying out a tenth Lot for the Conductor.—Also two more Lots for Publick Uses.—Likewise ten other</hi> Publick <hi>Lots for every hundred</hi> private <hi>Lots.—How to be appropriated. General Asylum for Males and Females, and for married Persons.—Hos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pital for Sick.—Penitentiary Let.—Glebe Land.—No Layman to have Benefit from the Glebe.—Limitation of the Cure of Souls.— Lot for Parish Clerks and Beadles.—Under Beadles or Trumpeters.—Lot for a Town Clerk.—Let for two Assistant Clerks of the Hundred.—One reserved Lot to make good Deficiencies.—Allowance of Land to Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>prentices and indentured Servants.—Sons of Settlers how to purchase Land.—Indentured Servants allowed to redeem the Terms of Ser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vice and how.—And to purchase Land by Labour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE money which has been paid into the hands of the trustees to procure land for the settlement shall be vested in such articles of merchandize, as are deemed
<pb n="34" facs="35"/>most proper for presents to the petty chiefs or Cabo-sieurs, on the African coast, and shall be disposed of among them to the best advantage, to engage their peaceable consent to admit the new settlers, and to give up to them a suffi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient tract of uninhabited land, border<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing on the sea, or on some navigable river or creek where fresh water also may be procured, with every other natu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ral accommodation suitable and necessary for a proper settlement. But in treating for the land, the Cabo-sieurs or chiefs shall be informed, as a necessary part of the agreement, that the land which they are requested to give up to the new set<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lers, is intended to be dignified with the title and privileges of a <hi>land of freedom,</hi> like England, where no man can be a slave; for as soon as a <hi>slave</hi> sets foot on English ground, he immediately be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>comes free, provided he conforms him<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self
<pb n="35" facs="36"/>to the laws of the state. And there<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore, if any <hi>slave who has escaped from his master,</hi> (in the neighbouring coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try, where slavery is allowed,) should fairly get within the boundary of the new settlement, he is afterwards to be considered as <hi>a free man.</hi> And no man must pursue him to take him away by force, nor be offended with the new settlers for refusing to deliver him up: because they are indispensably required by the laws of God, and of England, to <hi>protect the slave that has escaped from his master.</hi> (See this further explained un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>der the head of <hi>freedom.</hi>) This previous declaration is absolutely necessary to be made, as one means of avoiding future dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>putes with the neighbouring inhabitants. And in order that as much land as possi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble may be procured for the new settle<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment by the abovementioned presents, the agent or agents, for the settlers, and
<pb n="36" facs="37"/>every individual among them, shall be restrained from purchasing or making any agreement whatever for separate <hi>pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate</hi> property in land (on pain of forfeit<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing all right to a share in the profits of the settlement) until an agreement is made and concluded for the <hi>whole com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon stock of land:</hi> and until the bounds of it are actually marked out and made known to the whole body of settlers. An invoice shall be made of all the ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ticles for presents, in which the money intended for the purchase of land was invested; so that if any articles remain more than are necessary for the purpose, they shall be deemed a part of the <hi>com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon stock,</hi> and shall be registered ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cordingly. The whole body of original settlers that go together from England above the age of sixteen years, whether male or female, apprentice, or in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dentured servant, shall be <hi>equally</hi> entitled to <hi>all the land</hi> within the bounds of the
<pb n="37" facs="38"/>settlement; subject, however, to the rules hereafter expressed for the appropriation of it, from time to time when wanted: and all unappropriated land shall be deemed <hi>common.</hi> No land shall be ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>propriated but by the free consent of a majority of the settlers, after a full dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cussion of the reasons in the common council, or folkmote.</p>
            <p>When the agent-conductor shall have carefully viewed and considered the tract of country thus vested in the community of settlers, he shall recommend to them a proper situation for the first encamp<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment and principal township, as nearly in the center of their territory as the necessary accommodations of a constant supply of fresh water, and a navigable communication with the sea will permit: and he shall lay before the community his reasons for the choice, and if any other person or persons should propose
<pb n="38" facs="39"/>different situations of equal propriety, the <hi>elected</hi> heads of dozens, or a sufficient deputation from them must carefully examine all the proposed situations; and after duely weighing the reasons assign<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed for each proposal, they shall make their report to the <hi>common council;</hi> and the opinion of the majority shall decide the question; for it is absolutely neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary that the majority of the settlers should be well satisfied and contented with the situation of their principal township, whether it be better or worse than was first proposed. But in all other points they must be obedient to the advice of the agent-conductor, and fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>low his directions in clearing the ground, marking out and entrenching the first encampment, building temporary bar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racks, and store-houses, for the accom<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>modation of the whole community, and in digging, sowing, and planting, in the publick grounds, for the common sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>port
<pb n="39" facs="40"/>of the whole body of settlers; and no man shall separate himself to work for private emolument, until a small portion of land for a <hi>town lot,</hi> and a larger portion for an <hi>out lot</hi> agreeable to a plan annexed (No. 2) shall be marked out, and sufficiently cleared by <hi>publick</hi> labour for <hi>every settler;</hi> nor until the said portions of land are equally and in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>differently appropriated to each person <hi>by lot,</hi> to avoid disputes, and shall be duly registered with the names of the re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spective proprietors. Whether or not the <hi>separate private houses</hi> should be built by joint and <hi>publick</hi> labour, may be afterwards discussed and determined in the <hi>common council.</hi> Land shall be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>served in the township for such new set<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tlers as may afterwards arrive, which may in the mean time be cultivatad for public benefit, but it shall <hi>not be appropriated</hi> until it is really wanted for such addi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tional settlers as may afterwards join
<pb n="40" facs="41"/>themselves to the community: for no man ought to be the proprietor of more than <hi>one town lot,</hi> with its proportional <hi>out lot,</hi> according to the limitation here-after mentioned. And therefore if any additional land, either of town lots or out lots, or both, should be acquired by mar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riage or by inheritance, or legacy, or by any other lawful means, the inheritor shall be allowed three years to dispose of them: but in any other case, if it should be found out, that one individual possesses more than one town lot, or more land in out lots, than is declared in the fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lowing table, such land and lots shall be forfeited to the community.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>EXCEPTION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>N. B.</hi> The agent or first conductor of the settlement is excepted in the above regulation, because he is to be allowed every tenth lot that is laid out for private property, on account of his extraordinary
<pb n="41" facs="42"/>care and trouble in agreeing for the land, and for laying out the lots
<note place="bottom" n="*">Memorandum. Mr. Smeathman the agent, and first proposer of the settlement, having unfortunately caught a putrid fever of which he died, July 1, 1786, the gentlemen of the committee must now determine whether this exception ought to be made in favour of any other agent; or whether this tenth lot ought not rather to be reserved for such publick purposes as the committee may hereafter think proper to direct. As more money than what is allowed by government will probably be wanted, the reserved <hi>tenth lots</hi> may enable the settlers to repay whatever money may be necessary for them to borrow for the first exigencies of their little community.</note>. And also such <hi>publick officers</hi> are to be excepted who hold <hi>publick lots,</hi> hereafter men<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tioned, in right of their respective offi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ces, as the chaplain, clerk of the hun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dred, two assistant clerks of the hundred, and the three beadles, each of whom may be allowed to possess one separate lot, in their <hi>private</hi> capacity, besides their <hi>official publick</hi> lots.</p>
            <p>If any man should be dissatisfied with the situation of the first township, and
<pb n="42" facs="43"/>can find eleven other deciners of the same opinion, they may afterwards dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose of their registered lots, and agree with the <hi>community</hi> (to whom all the <hi>un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>occupied land</hi> within the bounds of the settlement doth jointly and equally be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>long) for sufficient land to form a pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portional township in some distant part, as proposed in the general scheme of the settlement (plate No. 2.) according to the following limitation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>LIMITATION OF LANDED POSSESSIONS.</head>
            <p>NO person shall possess in his or her own right, more land (exclusive of the Town lot where the person dwells) than the number of acres expressed against the following descriptions of places, viz.
<list>
                  <item>Within 3 miles of the principal town not more than 20 Acres.</item>
                  <item>Within 3 miles of the sea, navi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gable river, creek, or haven in any other part of the settlement not more than 40 Acres.</item>
                  <item>Within 7 miles of Do. not more than 100 Acres.</item>
                  <item>Within 12 miles of Do. not more than 200 Acres.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="44"/>Whenever nine lots are laid out, a tenth of equal size, shall be laid out closely adjoining to them, which shall be numbered and registered as the property of <hi>the conductor;</hi> or for a <hi>reserve to pay publick debts</hi> (the first conductor to whom the promise of <hi>every tenth lot</hi> was made, having lately died the com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mittee are at liberty to dispose of this <hi>re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>served land,</hi> as they shall think most just and right) and an account shall be kept of whatever odd number of lots are laid out at the same time, <hi>more</hi> than the ten last appropriated, and <hi>less</hi> than the amount of another nine; that as other new lots are demanded, the con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ductor may have a tenth lot of equal size close adjoining to any of the last appropriated lots which he shall chuse: but, for every ten lots thus marked out for <hi>private property,</hi> two lots of equal size, shall be also marked out adjoining to them, for <hi>publick uses,</hi> to be registered
<pb n="44" facs="45"/>as such, which under the care of an elected committee, in every district, controlled by the common council of the state, shall be cultivated by <hi>publick labour</hi> (hereafter more fully explained) and the produce be appropriated to a <hi>publick fund</hi> for religious instruction, schools, poor, hospitals, salaries of pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick officers, and all such just and rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sonable expences besides as ought to be defrayed by a publick exchequer. And also to every hundred lots <hi>laid out for</hi> PRIVATE <hi>property ten additional publick lots
<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>N. B.</hi> The <hi>publick lots</hi> are <hi>not</hi> to be reckoned with those that are <hi>tithed</hi> in favour of the con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ductor, but only the lots which are laid up for <hi>private property.</hi>
                  </note> shall be laid out</hi> closely adjoining: viz. One lot for a <hi>general asylum for poor males,</hi> under the care and direction of the <hi>oldest</hi> and most prudent deciners in <hi>the hun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dred,</hi> elected as a committee, expressly for that trust.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="46"/>Secondly, One lot for a <hi>general asylum of poor females,</hi> under the care of the <hi>elderly widows,</hi> or of such other pru<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dent matrons as shall be elected to the charge.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, One lot for a <hi>general asylum of poor families,</hi> of both sexes together, that the branches of a family may not be separated through misfortunes or poverty; but that each family may be allowed a distinct and separate habitation to them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves at the publick expence, until they can be otherwise provided, and more comfortably established, under the care and patronage of the committee of elder deciners above mentioned. Spare cham<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bers shall also be prepared to accommo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>date strangers and travellers, as at an inn, but separately in the said three lots, according to their respective descriptions of <hi>male, female,</hi> or <hi>family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="47"/>Fourthly, One lot for the support of an <hi>hospital for the sick and hurt,</hi> divided into separate wards, for males and fe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>males, subject respectively to the visita<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion and direction of the two separate trusts abovementioned.</p>
            <p>And Fifthly, One <hi>penitentiary lot</hi> to be strongly fenced (with palisades, ditch, and parapet, having all the defences re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>versed or facing inwards) for the secure confinement of all felonious offenders, and to be divided into three distinct compartments; two for the separation of the two sexes; and a third for the mar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ried persons of either sex, that they may not be separated from their spouses, or families, in case they should desire to attend them. And</p>
            <p>Sixthly, One lot to be registered as <hi>glebe</hi> land; and to be reserved for the chaplain of the hundred, whenever a
<pb n="47" facs="48"/>clergyman duly qualisied shall be elected by the majority of the <hi>deciners</hi> or <hi>house<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>holders</hi> in the <hi>hundred;</hi> but no layman, during the vacancy, may receive any profit from <hi>the glebe,</hi> though he may of<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficiate gratis, as far as a layman may lawfully be allowed to interfere in the sacred office. And no chaplain shall be inducted to a legal charge or cure of souls over more than <hi>one hundred families of deciners</hi> and <hi>their dependants,</hi> at one time; with due exception, however, to clergymen of episcopal authority, in case God's blessing on the settlement should hereafter render the appointment of bishops necessary.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, One lot, half of which to be appropriated to the use of a <hi>parish clerk,</hi> who shall also act as a <hi>head beadle</hi> in all assemblies of the hundred; and the other half in equal parts to <hi>two in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ferior beadles,</hi> for his assistants; who, as
<pb n="48" facs="49"/>soon as they can be taught, shall have an additional salary as <hi>trumpeters,</hi> to summon the people to the courts of justice, and to assemble the militia at the head quarters in case of publick danger.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, One lot for a <hi>town clerk,</hi> or <hi>recorder of the hundred,</hi> who shall keep an exact register of all the appro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>priations of land in his division, the ros<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ters of service, both civil and military, the judgements of the courts for <hi>fines of labour;</hi> and the due registering of all private contracts for <hi>labour,</hi> in which duty he shall be subject to the control and accompt of the publick Exchequer in the principal township.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, One lot for two <hi>assistant clerks of the hundred</hi> to be elected from the body of deciners, the most prudent and best qualified to acquire a general
<pb n="49" facs="50"/>knowledge of the principles and max<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ims of the <hi>common law,</hi> as well as of the regulations of the settlement, that they may be able to advise the head<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>boroughs on all occasions. And</p>
            <p>Tenthly, One publick lot reserved to make good the deficiencies of any of the rest, or to be applied to any other <hi>public use</hi> that the Hundred Court shall think proper to direct. And if any of these <hi>publick lots,</hi> or any parts thereof, remain uncultivated, the directors of the nearest bank, with the consent of the Hundred Court, may cause the su<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perfluous land to be cleared and culti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vated for the increase of the publick stock, and revenue.</p>
            <p>Every <hi>apprentice,</hi> or <hi>indentured male,</hi> above the age of sixteen years, that shall afterwards be introduced into the settle<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment from Europe, and every male bred<pb n="50" facs="51"/>in the settlement, as they arrive at that age, shall be allowed by the publick as many acres of land to himself, adjoin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing to the out lot of his parent, or of his master, as will amount to <hi>an eighth part of a lot,</hi> in order that he may em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ploy his leisure hours to his own profit; and as soon as he is twenty-one years of age, he shall have an addition from the publick of one-eighth more, amounting in all to <hi>one quarter of a lot, gratis:</hi> and the son of a settler, when arrived at that age, shall be allowed to <hi>purchase</hi> three-fourths of a lot more, to compleat his proportion for a deciner, at the rate of <hi>half a year's service</hi> for each <hi>fourth part</hi>—that is in all for 465 days labour to the publick: half of which to be demanded before the end of the second year, and the remainder gradually before the end of the third year. But with re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spect to an indentured servant or appren<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tice, if he shall be able, even before he
<pb n="51" facs="52"/>is of age, to purchase out his indentures, either by the produce of his private por<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of land, or by entering himself at the town bank, for such a proportion of his extra hours, or evening's labour, as shall be deemed equal to his strength, without injury to the labour due to his master, but not exceeding two hours (making ten hours labour in all per day:) the master must consent to the redemp<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, and the late indentured person, even though he is not of age, shall be al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lowed to <hi>purchase</hi> one quarter of a lot in whatever township he shall chuse, for <hi>one year's service</hi> (viz. 310 days labour paid by installments as above) to the Exche<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quer of the township; but on condition however that if he does not chuse to settle in the township of his late master, he shall give up the land which he there held, on being allowed <hi>the value</hi> of it, by the Exchequer; and that he shall
<pb n="52" facs="53"/>previously apply to the headborough or chief of the division wherein his desired lot is situated, in order to obtain the assent of the inhabitants to his admission among them; which being granted, he shall make a publick declaration in open court of his sincere intention to comply with the laws of the settlement, and to behave himself consistently with the ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessary peace and good order of a civi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lized society. And after he has ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>proved himself to the vicinage of his new settlement by good behaviour, and by a faithful discharge of the stipulated service or price, he shall be admitted (if he is twenty-one years of age, or as soon as he attains that age) to all the civil rights of the community, provided that he solemnly <hi>renews</hi> the said declaration at the next publick court or folkmote of the district which he inhabits; and he shall then be allowed to purchase at the publick Exchequer as much more land
<pb n="53" facs="54"/>as will amount to a compleat lot. And every indentured <hi>European,</hi> above the age of twenty-one, shall be allowed <hi>gra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tis,</hi> half a lot of land adjoining to his master's <hi>out lot;</hi> and as soon as the li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mited demand of labour, due to his master, shall be faithfully discharged, either by service or by redemption, he shall be allowed to <hi>purchase</hi> half a lot more for two years service (with rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sonable credit or allowance of time to perform it in) to <hi>the Exchequer</hi> or pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick bank and shall be admitted to all the civil rights of a deciner, as soon as the stipulated service is faithfully dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>charged: or sooner, if the <hi>Hundred Court</hi> shall be satisfied that he is worthy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="54" facs="55"/>
            <head>PUBLICK REVENUE AND PAPER CUR<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>RENCY OF INTRINSIC VALUE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Tax on Day's Work required from all Males above eighteen Years of Age.—Number of Indentures to be given by every Male.—In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dentures how to be certified.—Every Man to have an Accompt of Labour open at the Exchequer, certified by the proper Officers of his Division.—Apprentices and Indentured Servants to be registered.—Publick Labour to be deducted from the Terms of all Inden<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tured Servants.—Accompts of Labour how to be settled and discharged.—Estimation of La<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bour.—Additional Tax on the Rich, and on those who have more profitable Employments than ordinary Labour.—The Payment of Tithes of Property always grievous and in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>convenient.—Tax on Pride and Indolence. The Advantages of making</hi> Ordinary Labour <hi>the Medium of Traffic.—That poor Men will never want Employment, nor lose Time in searching for it.—Will obtain Credit for Ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessaries,
<pb n="55" facs="56"/>and for the Assistance of Artificers. —Indentures how to be certified, entered, and put in Circulation.—Indentures will be</hi> ready Cash <hi>to the Merchant, Tradesman, or Arti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficer, and will enable them to redeem their own more valuable Labour, and to draw on the Bank for Paper Cash to circulate, or for Labour to accommodate Planters, who will repay in Produce; that the Indentures will be really as intrinsically valuable as ready Cash. —The Author's Doubts.—A few Objections removed.—Debts of Labour to be demanded only by the publick Banks.—Applications ei<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther for Labourers or Labour to be made at the publick Banks.—Planters to pay a small Commission per Cent. to the Bank for supply<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Labourers.—Labourers to be summoned in due Rotation some every Day, with due previous Notice, according to the Dates of their Indentures not balanced.—Guard against Bankruptcy, and against Oppression of indentured Labourers.—In case of Death, Debts of Labour due</hi> to the Exchequer <hi>to be made good out of the</hi> real <hi>and</hi> personal <hi>Estate of the Debtor.—The System of</hi> Frankpledge
<pb n="56" facs="57"/>
               <hi>the chief Security of this Revenue.—Publick Fines and Forfeitures.—The peculiar Im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>provement which even</hi> Frankpledge <hi>will ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain by Fines of Labour.—Even</hi> Neglect <hi>of</hi> publick <hi>Labour may be turned to the</hi> pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick <hi>Advantage.—The Revenue of</hi> Fines <hi>re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>served to make up all Deficiences in this Cal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culation as it would probably amount to</hi> a Third <hi>of what is already reckoned, and the Profits of the Sale of Land probably even more than the Fines.—The</hi> Savings <hi>by this Ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rangement would be almost as extraordinary as the</hi> Gains.</p>
            <p>IN order to establish an efficient pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick revenue, and at the same time to render industry and honest daily labour honourable, or at least <hi>creditable</hi> by being <hi>general.</hi>—All contributions to the state, and all publick fines, (except those laid on persons convicted of felony within the settlement, which are to be worked out in the <hi>penitentiary lots,</hi> (before de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>scribed) shall be levied in <hi>day labour,</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="58"/>estimated (whatever a man's calling, art, or ability may be) at the rate of eight hours work per day of an <hi>ordinary la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bourer;</hi> so that persons who have money, or more valuable employments, may compound, or find a sufficient substitute accustomed to <hi>ordinary labour:</hi> but the substitute must be a <hi>free man;</hi> because no slave, nor even an apprentice or in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dentured servant, if bound for a longer term than what is limited under the general head of freedom, shall be per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mitted to work within the bounds of the settlement, lest any discredit should thereby be thrown on <hi>honest labour.</hi> And for the same reason the fines of days work laid on persons convicted of fe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lony, within the settlement, shall not be entered on the same books of the Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chequer which contain the names of the rest of the community, but shall be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gistered in a distinct book, as a separate
<pb n="58" facs="59"/>branch of the revenue, and shall be worked out in the penitentiary lots.</p>
            <p>All written contracts or indentures for labour, publick or private, shall be en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tered in the books of the Publick Exche<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quer, to which shall be made compleat indexes of reference, that the state of every man's engagements may easily be known, whereby no man will have it in his power to dispose of indentures for more labour than such a reasonable pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portion of his leisure as he may be sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posed capable of fulfilling and discharging in due time.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="60"/>A <hi>truth part</hi> of the 310 days of labour shall be appropriated to the support of Religious instruc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, schools, widows, poor, and other paro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chial exigencies. 31 Days.</p>
            <p>And also another <hi>tenth</hi> for other <hi>general</hi> expences of the community or state 31 Days.</p>
            <p>This publick contribution of <hi>two-tenths,</hi> or one-fifth of the <hi>work-days</hi> in a year, shall be equally required of all males above the age of eighteen years, and shall be estimated at the value only of <hi>ordinary labour in cultivating the earth,</hi> amounting for each person, per annum, to sixty<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>two days of ordinary labour 62 Days.</p>
            <p>For which every male of the above description shall annually sign indentures for the undermentioned portions of his labour, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Days Work.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 Indenture for</cell>
                     <cell>20 Days Work 20</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>10 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>5 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4 Indentures for</cell>
                     <cell>2 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>1 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. Do.</cell>
                     <cell>4 Hours work or ½ a day each</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>2 Do. or ¼ do.</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16 Do.</cell>
                     <cell>1 Do. or ⅓ do.</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51 Indentures.</cell>
                     <cell>Days work of ordinary labour</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The small portions of time are necessary to form a rateable medium for the prices
<pb n="60" facs="61"/>of all kinds of small articles in traffick, and to afford a convenient exchange when the indentures are circulated like bills in lieu of cash; and for such arti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cles as may require a still smaller frac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion to express any gradual rising or fall of price, the proper fraction of an hour into sixty minutes, will be sufficiently small for all purposes; and if any species of so small a value as <hi>one minute</hi> (or even as five or fifteen minutes) should be thought necessary, small pieces of copper or other cheap metals, amber, or parti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cular kinds of shells or beads, may be substituted for it. But if <hi>indentures,</hi> (for the sake of uniformity in the currency) should be preferred, an indenture for <hi>ten minutes,</hi> the sixth part of an hour, will amount exactly to <hi>one farthing,</hi> at the lowest price of <hi>ordinary labour,</hi> i. e. one shilling per day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="62"/>In the indentures must be express'd the name of the township, or of <hi>the hundred,</hi> and <hi>the number,</hi> or other denomination of the <hi>tithing</hi> or <hi>dozen,</hi> wherein the signer lives; and when the indenture is cut at the figured tally, the signer of it shall keep the checque in his own possession, but shall deliver the full number and value of his signed indentures into the Exchequer, in the presence of the chief of the dozen to which he belongs. If he himself is an <hi>headborough,</hi> or chief of a dozen, he shall deliver his inden<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tures in the presence of his <hi>hundreder,</hi> or of three other <hi>headboroughs,</hi> of the same hundred, and the <hi>hundreder himself</hi> in the presence of four <hi>headboroughs</hi> of his own division.</p>
            <p>The entry or counter checque in the publick treasury of every man's accompt of indentures, for which he is a debtor
<pb n="62" facs="63"/>to the publick, shall be carefully exa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mined and certified by the <hi>Hundreders,</hi> or their assistants, or at least by four of the Headboroughs, of the particular division to which each debtor respectively belongs, which will be very little trouble to each <hi>chief,</hi> as the highest will certify only for 100 families; and the regula<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rity of the frankpledge, and the <hi>certain knowledge</hi> of each individual in a divi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sion, which every chief obtains by it, will effectually secure every individual from forgeries; so that no man will be liable to answer any demands for labour, but what may be amply proved and au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thenticated by comparing the checques in his own hands with the certified entry in the Exchequer.</p>
            <p>Masters of <hi>apprentices,</hi> and also of <hi>in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dentured strangers,</hi> brought by them into the settlement, shall be obliged to register the said indentured persons in the
<pb n="63" facs="64"/>publick Exchequer of the township where he lives, together with the terms of their indentures, on the penalty of 310 days labour for every wilful failure herein; and he shall be obliged to deduct from the limited time of indentured service, all the time that the apprentices or servants have worked for the publick benefit.</p>
            <p>When a man has worked out, or otherwise redeemed any of the paper<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>money, for which he is nominally re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sponsible, and shall have received back the indenture, after the service, he may produce it at the Exchequer, together with its corresponding checque, that it may be cancelled in the publick ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>compt; whereby the discharge of pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick debts may be as regularly proved and authenticated as the just demands abovementioned; and the state of a man's publick debt may always be known at
<pb n="64" facs="65"/>the publick Exchequer by the balance of indentures in his accompt; and thereby all frauds and impositions may be easily traced and detected.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Labour</hi> in all new settlements where land is cheap, is, of course, much higher and more valuable than in old established states, the intrinsic value of the labour, in the proposed new settlement, might fairly be estimated <hi>at double the price</hi> of labour in England; but at present I will rate it only at <hi>one shilling per day,</hi> on ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>count of the limitation of eight hours instead of ten, commonly required in England. About 300 males have already entered their names; which number multiplied by sixty-two, the tax of days work due from each per annum, by this regulation, will produce 18,600 days of labour in a year, due to the publick; which, estimated at the low average rate of only 1s. per day, will amount to 930l.
<pb n="65" facs="66"/>per annum. And as the value or ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pence of labour, when applied <hi>to land,</hi> (at the ordinary estimation of increase by the products of the earth in return for labour and care) is expected to pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duce <hi>at least triple the amount</hi> of the disbursement, even in our northern cli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mates, so the value of 930l. bestowed in labour on the publick lots of land in the fertile and productive climate of Africa, where very little labour is necessary, might certainly be estimated much higher: but even at the ordinary rate it will amount to 2790l. per annum, which is a very great publick revenue, if it be remembered that it is calculated on the very small number of 300 males, reckon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing rich and poor together, which are only the ordinary average number of males in an <hi>hundred division,</hi> or 100 families of a well established settlement, at the rate of three males to a family!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="67"/>The general contribution, which I have proposed, is <hi>equally</hi> laid on the poor as on the rich, the former being <hi>equally</hi> capable of paying it, and that certainly with more ease to themselves, by being accustomed to <hi>ordinary labour.</hi> Nevertheless the rich (it may be said) ought to contribute more than the poor, on account of the superior advantages which accrue to them by their associa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion with the poor in one well regulated political body. The superior advantages I speak of are—1st, The <hi>personal ease</hi> or exemption from labour, which their riches may always procure to them in such a society—and secondly the effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tual security of their property, or wealth, <hi>procured in Frankpledge,</hi> or <hi>"Maxima securitas,"</hi> by the equal exertion of persons, who have <hi>no property,</hi> and by an <hi>equal</hi> risque, also <hi>of their lives,</hi> in case of actual danger. So that it seems clearly reasonable and just, that the rich
<pb n="67" facs="68"/>and higher ranks of citizens should contribute <hi>more to the publick revenue,</hi> than the poor;—but in what proportion is rather difficult to determine; though it may be readily answered, that the quantity of riches should, in due pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portion, determine the quantity of con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tribution; yet this cannot be done with<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>out a general <hi>tax on property,</hi> which, as experience teaches us, is liable to many inconveniences; so that even the antient and ordinary tax of <hi>tithes</hi> to the clergy is deemed grievously inconvenient, on account of the difficulties, disputes, quarrels, and vexations, which too fre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quently happen, as well in compound<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing for them as in the collection of them <hi>in kind.</hi> The only expedient, therefore, which I am able to devise, at present, for procuring a larger contribution from the rich, is a <hi>tax on pride and indolence;</hi> a tax which, though it will not produce in exact proportion to the property of
<pb n="68" facs="69"/>the wealthy, will nevertheless most cer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tainly obtain from the wealthy and luxurious a contribution exactly pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portionate to whatever <hi>pride and indo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lence</hi> may be occasioned by the super<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fluous wealth of the community: and in aid to this tax on <hi>superfluous wealth,</hi> the <hi>affluence</hi> likewise of the more useful members of society, whose employments procure them a more profitable reward than they could obtain by ordinary la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bour, might be made to yield a reason<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>able addition to the revenue in conside<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ration of their superior abilities to con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tribute, which men of this respectable class certainly have.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="69" facs="70"/>
            <head>TAX <hi>on</hi> PRIDE <hi>and</hi> INDOLENCE, <hi>and on Persons who have superior Emoluments above the ordinary Class of Labourers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THOUGH <hi>labour</hi> is the common lot of man, according to the divine sentence, or penal judgment, denounced against our first <hi>male</hi> parent,—<q>In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread, till thou return into the ground,</q> &amp;c. Gen. iii. 19. and though an apostle also has de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>clared, that
<q>if any would not work neither should he eat,</q> yet many persons there are, in every community, who by some means or other seem to be exempted from the necessity of <hi>personal labour,</hi> the ordinary condition of human life! How this may be accounted for, and reconciled with the divine decree, is stated more at large in my tract on the Law of Nature, and Principles of Action
<pb n="70" facs="71"/>in Man, p. 21—30. Nothing, there<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore, according to <hi>natural religion,</hi> can be more <hi>reasonable</hi> and <hi>just,</hi> or more consistent also, according to the second foundation of law, with the <hi>revealed will of God</hi> in the holy scriptures, than that all persons who have wealth sufficient to purchase an exemption from this <hi>ordi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nary lot of man,</hi> should be required to contribute in a larger proportion to the exigencies of the community, than persons who depend on their <hi>daily labour</hi> for their <hi>daily bread.</hi> And this additional contribution may very easily be levied, without making any other ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ditional object of taxation than what I have already proposed to be the <hi>single article</hi> of general contribution, viz. <hi>the two tenths of ordinary labour:</hi> let a re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>demption of the general tax of sixty-two days' contribution, viz. two tenths of <hi>ordinary labour</hi> be required at the rate of a <hi>double,</hi> or, if necessary, of a <hi>triple</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="72"/>value of the service, from all persons who, having no real bodily infirmity or incapacity, shall decline a <hi>personal</hi> attendance for the general contribution, either through <hi>pride,</hi> by setting them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves up above their brethren in their own estimation, as superior to the com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon lot of <hi>ordinary labour,</hi> or else by having a better and more reasonable mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive, that of a more profitable occupa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion for the employment of their time, which will equally render them capable of paying, without any actual hardship, the additional tax for the <hi>ease, indulgence,</hi> and <hi>superior profit,</hi> which they enjoy by the purchase.</p>
            <p>Suppose there be ten men in an hun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dred, or thirty males in <hi>one hundred fa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>milies,</hi> whose pride, or wealth, or indo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lence, would induce them to decline personal labour: such men ought surely to redeem their exemption at a <hi>triple
<pb n="72" facs="73"/>value,</hi> which cannot amount to any real hardship or oppression; as the alterna<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive, and only hardship to those who may <hi>love too well their wealth, and deem the tax too heavy,</hi> is to submit to the ordi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nary lot of their brethren, in complying with a short limited service for the pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick benefit, in which they themselves have an <hi>equal</hi> profit. And suppose there be also double that number of persons in an hundred division, who have useful arts and more profitable trades and occu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pations to induce their redemption of <hi>personal service:</hi>—The produce of the tax will be as follows—the first class of thirty gentlemen, or idle men, taxed at triple the value of the sixty-two days of ordinary labour, will pay all together the sum of 279l. but as the sixty-two days of labour from each is already in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cluded in the former general calculation, one third must be deducted from the esti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mated
<pb n="73" facs="74"/>value of this additional tax, where by it is reduced to
<table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">l.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">s.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>186</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The second class of 60 merchants, tradesman, or useful artificers, who will be induced by more profitable occupa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions to redeem their <hi>personal labour,</hi> will each pay a <hi>double tax,</hi> viz. the value of 124 days ordinary labour at 1s. per day which all together is <hi>only</hi> 6<hi>l.</hi> 4<hi>s. per ann. each man;</hi> but as they are already charged half that sum, in the general estimate of contribution, the other half alone must here be reckoned, viz. 3l. 2s. which multiplied by 60 amounts to</cell>
                     <cell>186</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Total additional tax on the 2 classes abovementioned in one hundred families</cell>
                     <cell>372</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Which addition, if laid out on the cultivation of land in the publick lots, would produce <hi>three times that value,</hi> according to the ordinary increase of land, for the labour bestowed on it. The risque, indeed, of a misapplica<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of the labour, or of a defalcation of the increase, may reasonably be objected, according to the ordinary mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>conduct of persons intrusted with the care of farms, at present in this coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try; but the same objection will not hold where <hi>Frankpledge</hi> is duly established, because the eye of every neighbour would be a watchful guard against fraud, all being equally interested in the pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick profit. I will therefore multiply this additional tax by 3, the ordinary rate of increase to be expected from the land which is cultivated by it</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>1116</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To which add the general contribu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion before estimated at</cell>
                     <cell>2790</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The total amount of revenue for one single division of an hundred families</cell>
                     <cell>3906</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="75"/>Thus an ample source is opened not only of <hi>publick credit</hi> but also of <hi>private security,</hi> or trust, in traffick, by the same easy means; whereby poor labouring men may be enabled to obtain all the necessary articles of merchandize, though they have no ready money to advance. For, as <hi>ordinary labour</hi> is rendered the <hi>medium of traffic,</hi> instead of cash, the first advantage to a poor industrious man, ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>customed only to <hi>ordinary labour,</hi> is, that he will, at all times, have it in his power to obtain employment; in the search of which, with us, many honest men, in all the three kingdoms, are ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>liged to leave their native country. And the second material advantage to him is, that he can always obtain an immediate credit, proportionable to the value of his unengaged time, for any articles of trade that he may want, by giving the <hi>mer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chant,</hi> or <hi>tradesman,</hi> in return for them, an indenture for as many <hi>days labour</hi> as
<pb n="75" facs="76"/>the purchase is worth; and he is also enabled to employ a <hi>blacksmith, car<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>penter,</hi> or other useful <hi>artificer</hi> (in case he should want their assistance on his own lot) by giving them, in like manner, an indenture, for as many days of <hi>or<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dinary labour,</hi> as will amount to the value of the work. These indentures (as before proposed for the indentures of general contribution) should express the names of the <hi>hundred,</hi> and of the <hi>dozen</hi> in which the signer is associated, and should be previously carried by him to be entered at the public Exchequer, or bank, of the hundred, and be there properly certified, as before proposed; after which the labourer may cut off the indentures from his checques, at the printed tally, and pay them to the <hi>mer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chant</hi> or <hi>tradesman,</hi> for the article pur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chased; or to the <hi>artificer</hi> for his job, retaining the checques in his own custody, that he may always know the
<pb n="76" facs="77"/>amount of his <hi>debt of labour.</hi> On the other hand, the <hi>merchant, tradesman,</hi> or <hi>artificer,</hi> who receives such an indenture from a poor labourer, can immediately <hi>realize</hi> the value of it in his own favour, by paying it into the public Exchequer, or bank of the township; where, of course, it will be posted to the credit of his accompt of labour, and will enable him to redeem a part of his <hi>own inden<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tures,</hi> without his <hi>own personal labour,</hi> which, of course, is much more valuable than <hi>ordinary labour;</hi> and in like manner he will proceed with all other indentures for <hi>ordinary labour,</hi> that he has procured by his traffic, or more valuable occupa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, always paying them to the credit of his account at the bank, until the amount exceeds his own debt for public service: when, from the balance of labour in his favour, according to the amount of it, he will always be at liberty to draw on the bank for <hi>indentures of days
<pb n="77" facs="78"/>work,</hi> either for <hi>circulation,</hi> as ready cash, or for <hi>labourers,</hi> to cultivate his own lot of land, or else occasionally to accom<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>modate planters who want labourers, and are willing to pay the value of them, in <hi>produce,</hi> &amp;c. whereby <hi>private credit</hi> (as well as <hi>public credit,</hi> already provided for) will be amply supported: and the indentures for <hi>labour,</hi> by which this most essential <hi>public</hi> and <hi>private</hi> service is effected, will be, in fact, A PAPER CURRENCY OF INTRINSIC VALUE, an<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>swering all the purposes of <hi>ready cash,</hi> as a medium of traffic, as well as all the necessary purposes of <hi>negociable bills,</hi> to support <hi>public</hi> and <hi>private</hi> credit; and yet they cannot be, at all, liable to de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>preciation!</p>
            <p>The advantages appear to me so great and extraordinary, that I can hardly give credit, as I proceed, to my own estima<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of them; and am inclined to suspect
<pb n="78" facs="79"/>that I am, in some way or other, <hi>enor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mously mistaken;</hi> but as I cannot yet find out my error, I must leave my censure to some more able head. A few obvious objections, however, I am prepared to remove by a timely proposal of adequate remedies. As for instance—Whatever might be deemed troublesome, or dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>agreeable, in exacting the payment of these <hi>debts of labour,</hi> may be effectually withdrawn <hi>from individuals,</hi> by investing the <hi>public bank of each township</hi> with the sole authority of demanding the <hi>labour</hi> for the indentures, that have been re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spectively entered and certified therein. And that the several banks may be enabled to realize the value of these indentures, all applications either for <hi>labourers,</hi> or <hi>labour,</hi> shall be made at the several <hi>town banks;</hi> where planters may be sure of a supply of labourers, and the labourer equally sure of a constant supply of work, without danger of op<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pression,
<pb n="79" facs="80"/>or non payment of wages, being secured from both by the media<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of the bank, which employs him, and disposes of his service. And both parties, or at least the <hi>planters,</hi> ought to pay some small allowance per cent. to the bank, by way of commission, or profit for the negociation. And each bank should regularly summon, (with <hi>due previous notice</hi> for every day) a suf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficient number of the indentured la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bourers that are entered on their books, not only to cultivate <hi>the public lots of land</hi> under their care, but also to supply the current daily demand of labour that may be wanted by planters and other private individuals; but all persons sum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>moned to labour, shall work on the <hi>public lots,</hi> until such demands are made, by which means <hi>the labourers will lose no time in waiting for work.</hi> The daily sum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monses to labour, issued from the bank, should be made <hi>in due rotation, according
<pb n="80" facs="81"/>to the dates of the indentures entered on the books,</hi> and according to the quantity of debt which each individual has to work out. And, that no man may run deeper in debt, by disposing of his labour to a greater amount than he may be able to discharge in due time, all indentures whatsoever for the labour either of ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>prentices or servants, should be entered at the bank of the township, where the parties reside, whereby not only the state of every labourer's debt may be always known, and, of course, likewise his ability to discharge it, but also, on the other hand, the labourers, apprentices, and servants themselves, will be thereby more easily protected from the oppression of such avaritious masters, as might other<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wise be inclined to exact more service than is due by the terms of their contract.</p>
            <p>If any person should die before his indentured service is discharged to the
<pb n="81" facs="82"/>
               <hi>public</hi> bank, his land, stock, and effects shall be answerable to the amount of his deficiency to the <hi>publick,</hi> in preference to all other debts: whereby the <hi>paper currency,</hi> will always preserve a <hi>standard value;</hi> and, at the same time, afford a most convenient medium for traffic and exchange. If any further difficulties, more than I have foreseen and guarded against, should still be objected, I flatter myself that the salutary establishment of Frankpledge will be sufficient to obviate them all. For this <hi>maxima securitas,</hi> renders every individual completely re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sponsible for all debts or demands that can justly be made upon him, and for all charges against him whatever, because the residence of the meanest member of society can be most expeditiously known by the public books; so that he may be immediately traced at any time to his very chamber, and no individual in <hi>Frankpledge</hi> can resist the united power
<pb n="82" facs="83"/>of a free people—for if any one should neglect or despise the summons of the public bank, his <hi>tithing</hi> or dozen may be compelled (on the penalty of a heavy fine for neglect) to produce him: and should the tithing or dozen neglect, the hundred is summoned to enforce satis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>faction, and so on with respect to higher divisions, until the strength of the whole community is united, as one man, to render executive justice, to <hi>fine,</hi> or other<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wise punish all contumacious delinquents against common sense, and to enforce obedience to the determined justice of the majority. This occasional mention of <hi>misdemeanors</hi> and <hi>fines,</hi> reminds me that I have omitted to add to the amount of my calculation of <hi>Revenue,</hi> the profit of the <hi>public fines</hi> and <hi>forfeitures,</hi> which must always be very considerable where <hi>Frankpledge</hi> is established; not only, because the regularity and order of the system renders the levying of <hi>fines</hi> and
<pb n="83" facs="84"/>
               <hi>forfeitures</hi> extremely easy, expeditious, and free from expence, but also, because the penalties of <hi>fines</hi> and <hi>forfeitures</hi> are, in Frankpledge, extended to the <hi>minutest immoralities,</hi> and <hi>negligences,</hi> in order to render the peace and regularity of society as perfect as possible. Add to this a very particular advantage, which the ancient mode of punishing by <hi>fines</hi> and <hi>forfeitures,</hi> will acquire by the applica<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of my proposal of universal calcula<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion by <hi>days labour</hi>—an advantage which could never before be obtained; viz. that the <hi>poorest man</hi> has, thereby, <hi>some<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thing to forfeit,</hi> even sometimes very considerable, because his <hi>personal labour</hi> is <hi>equally valuable,</hi> and probably <hi>more so,</hi> than the labour of a man of superior rank; so that even the happy system of <hi>Frankpledge itself</hi> is very materially im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>proved, and rendered much <hi>more effectual,</hi> as well as more <hi>profitable,</hi> by the pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posed addition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="85"/>All contempts of legal summonses to <hi>labour,</hi> would, of course, be <hi>finable;</hi> as also <hi>apparent sloth,</hi> or <hi>remissness in work<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing;</hi> both of which would thereby be made <hi>effectual to increase the value of the paper currency,</hi> instead of diminishing it, as might be expected. Likewise all con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tempts of court, neglects of summons to attend juries; want of punctuality in attending the duties of Watch and Ward, in the rotation of the public roster; and all inattention or disobedience while on duty; all breaches of the sabbath, swear<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing, drunkenness, and immodesty, as well as <hi>fornication</hi> and <hi>adultery</hi> (both of which should be very strictly, and very severely mulcted, for the more effectual promotion of <hi>honourable marriage</hi>) giving or accepting a challenge to fight, even though no mischief should ensue; all unnecessary wrangling, fighting, or striking, and even every wilful provoca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion by word or gesture, and every other
<pb n="85" facs="86"/>misbehaviour that is inconsistent with the peace, order, and quiet of a happy so<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciety, would be punished by a suitable <hi>fine of days' work,</hi> in proportion to the offence, by which altogether this essential article of <hi>fines</hi> and <hi>forfeitures</hi> (which, in England, through <hi>neglect of Frankpledge,</hi> are hardly an object of consideration) would necessarily occasion a much larger addition to the <hi>public revenue</hi> than I can venture, at present, to estimate; and, therefore, I must beg leave to <hi>reserve</hi> this valuable article of <hi>fines,</hi> to make up any deficiencies, which, perhaps, may be afterwards discovered in my other cal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culations; to which must also be added, as a further reserve, the profits arising from the <hi>sale of land</hi> for <hi>day labour,</hi> not yet estimated, though it would probably amount even to more than the fines.</p>
            <p>I have already, without these profitable articles, carried my estimation of the
<pb n="86" facs="87"/>
               <hi>public Revenue</hi> nearly to the amount of 4000l. per annum, for every 100 families, including equally both rich and poor, which far exceeds the proportionable revenue, I believe, of any kingdom on earth; for indeed, the same means are <hi>not practicable</hi> in any country or nation, unless the most excellent system of <hi>Frankpledge</hi> be previously established, which I must frequently repeat. But, for the sake of comparison, let us apply this scheme to the computed average number of taxable houses or families in England and Wales. The one million families (as they are commonly esti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mated) would raise, by merely taking on themselves the very moderate and equal burthen of only a 5th part of their <hi>most ordinary</hi> labour, estimated at the low rate of one shilling per day, together with the additional <hi>tax on pride,</hi> and the easy levy <hi>on profitable occupations,</hi> with the due increase of the whole profit, when applied
<pb n="87" facs="88"/>to <hi>the cultivation of public land,</hi> would raise (I say) at the rate of 3906l. for every hundred families, before calculated, the amazing revenue of 39 millions, and 60 thousands of pounds sterling, per annum. If I am questioned on the pos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sibility of raising a sum so enormously great, that it far exceeds the whole annual produce of all our accumulated taxes, customs, and other means of revenue, I must confess, that I am at a loss how even to satisfy my own doubts about it; and that I know not what reasons to assign for such an incredible accumulation of wealth, arising from so <hi>trifling a burthen</hi> laid upon the people, unless it may be attri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>buted to the <hi>effectual employment of all the labouring poor;</hi> and of others capable of labour, and also to the <hi>effectual</hi> means of which the proposition seems to pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mise of rendering that general employ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment <hi>of ordinary labour</hi> profitable, not only in the circulation of the indentures
<pb n="88" facs="89"/>as <hi>bills</hi> and <hi>cash;</hi> but also in the increase which may be naturally expected from <hi>the actual labour, when applied to the earth.</hi> But there are other advantages attending the proposal, which are not yet reckoned.</p>
            <p>The previous re-establishment of <hi>frankpledge,</hi> without which the raising of such an increased revenue could not be practicable, would, at the same time, render absolutely <hi>unnecessary</hi> the greatest part of our most expensive establishments both <hi>civil</hi> and <hi>military.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that, upon the whole the gain might fairly be estimated at nearly triple the <hi>effective,</hi> or neat amount of all the other deviseable "<hi>Ways and Means,</hi> &amp;c. &amp;c."— That this is not an exaggerated statement of our publick burthens, will be allowed, I believe, by all parties. I wish they were equally agreed in opinion about the necessary remedy!</p>
         </div>
         <closer>
            <signed>GRANVILLE SHARP.</signed>
            <dateline>Old Jewry, <date>3d <hi>July,</hi> 1786.</date>
            </dateline>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>