<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thoughts on civil liberty: on licentiousness, and faction. By the author of Essays on the characteristics, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Brown, John, 1715-1766.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K020305.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3303806837</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thoughts on civil liberty: on licentiousness, and faction. By the author of Essays on the characteristics, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Brown, John, 1715-1766.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>167,[1]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>Newcastle upon Tyne :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed by J. White and T. Saint, for L. Davis and C. Reymers, London,</publisher>
                  <date>1765.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K020305.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3303806837</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author of Essays on the characteristics, &amp;c = John Brown.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT789.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>THOUGHTS ON CIVIL LIBERTY, ON LICENTIOUSNESS, AND FACTION. By the AUTHOR of ESSAYS on the CHARACTERISTICS, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Sed in Vitium Libertas excidit, et Vim</l>
               <l>Dignam Lege regi.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>NEWCASTLE UPON TYNE:</hi> Printed by J. WHITE and T. SAINT, For L. DAVIS and C. REYMERS, against <hi>Gray's-Inn-Gate, Holborn, London;</hi> Printers to the ROYAL SOCIETY. MDCCLXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tableofcontents">
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <pb facs="3"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SECT. I. <hi>The Design.</hi> Page 9.</item>
               <item>SECT. II. <hi>Of the Nature of civil Liberty.</hi> p. 11.</item>
               <item>SECT. III. <hi>Of Licentiousness and Faction.</hi> p. 14.</item>
               <item>SECT. IV. <hi>Unassisted Laws no permanent Foundation of civil Liberty.</hi> p. 15.</item>
               <item>SECT. V. <hi>Virtuous Manners and Principles the only permanent Foundation of civil Liberty.</hi> p. 26.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="4"/>
SECT. VI. <hi>An Objection considered.</hi> Page 36.</item>
               <item>SECT. VII. <hi>A Confirmation of these Principles, drawn from the History of free States. 1st of Sparta.</hi> p. 42.</item>
               <item>SECT. VIII. <hi>Of the Republic of Athens.</hi> p. 61.</item>
               <item>SECT. IX. <hi>Of the Commonwealth of Rome.</hi> p. 67.</item>
               <item>SECT. X. <hi>How far these Facts can properly be ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ply'd to the political State of Great Bri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain.</hi> p. 78.</item>
               <item>SECT. XI. <hi>Of the general State of Manners and Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples, about the Time of the Revolution.</hi> p. 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="5"/>
SECT. XII. <hi>Of the Changes in Manners and Principles, through the succeeding Times.</hi> Page 94.</item>
               <item>SECT. XIII. <hi>Among what Ranks, Licentiousness and Fac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion may most probably be expected.</hi> p. 108.</item>
               <item>SECT. XIV. <hi>Of the most effectual Means of detecting Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>centiousness and Faction.</hi> p. 115.</item>
               <item>SECT. XV. <hi>Of the characteristic Marks of Liberty.</hi> p. 118.</item>
               <item>SECT. XVI. <hi>Of the first characteristic Mark of Licen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiousness and Faction.</hi> p. 120.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="6"/>
SECT. XVII. <hi>A second Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</hi> Page 124.</item>
               <item>SECT. XVIII. <hi>A third Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</hi> p. 126.</item>
               <item>SECT. XIX. <hi>A fourth Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</hi> p. 127.</item>
               <item>SECT. XX. <hi>A fifth Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</hi> p. 131.</item>
               <item>SECT. XXI. <hi>A sixth Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</hi> 134.</item>
               <item>SECT. XXII. <hi>Some Objections obviated.</hi> p. 137.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="7" facs="7"/>
SECT. XXIII. <hi>Of the Remedies against Licentiousness and Faction. The first Remedy.</hi> Page 140.</item>
               <item>SECT. XXIV. <hi>A second Remedy.</hi> p. 142.</item>
               <item>SECT. XXV. <hi>Some concomitant Remedies.</hi> p. 149.</item>
               <item>SECT. XXVI. <hi>Of the chief and essential Remedy.</hi> p. 156.</item>
               <item>SECT. XXVII. <hi>The Conclusion.</hi> p. 160.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Errat. p. 63, for "imbibed, read "imbued."</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="8"/>THOUGHTS ON CIVIL LIBERTY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>SECTION I. <hi>The</hi> DESIGN.</head>
            <p>THERE are two Causes, essentially distinct, though often interwoven, by which a free State may perish. These are, <hi>external</hi> and <hi>internal</hi> Violence: <hi>Invasions</hi> from Abroad, or <hi>Dissentions</hi> at Home: The Rage of foreign <hi>War,</hi> or do<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mestic <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After a dangerous and exhausting War, Victory hath at length restored Peace to our bleeding Country. But in vain the
<pb n="10" facs="9"/>
Sword of War is sheathed, if in Time of Peace the Poignard of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction</hi> is drawn, and madly level'd by many of our Countrymen, at the Breasts of their Fellow-Subjects.</p>
            <p>To prevent the fatal Consequences of this deluded or deluding Spirit, is the Purpose of this Essay: In which the Writer will endeavour to trace the present State of Things to its general Foundations: By pointing out the real Basis and genuine Characteristics of true Liberty; by unmas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quing the Pretences, and laying open the secret <hi>Sources</hi> and distinctive <hi>Marks</hi> of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the political Principles here laid down and inforced, will be found strictly connected with Religion and Morals; no Apology will be made for endeavouring to establish the public Happiness of Mankind on the solid Basis of <hi>Virtue,</hi> which is the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Religion itself.—</hi>In this Point the Writer confirms himself on the Authority of an excellent and learned Prelate, whose
<pb n="11" facs="10"/>
political Researches were of like Tendency. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"As the Sum of human Happiness is sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posed to consist in the Goods of Mind, Body, and Fortune, I would fain make my Studies of some Use to Mankind, with Regard to each of these three Par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ticulars; and hope it will not be thought faulty or indecent in any Man, of what Profession soever, to offer his Mite to<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wards improving the <hi>Manners</hi> (I will add, the <hi>Religion) Health,</hi> and <hi>Prospe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rity</hi> of his Fellow-Creatures. <note place="bottom" n="*">Dr. <hi>Berkley</hi>'s Misc. p. 118.</note>"</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>SECT. II. Of the Nature of Civil Liberty.</head>
            <p>TO some it will doubtless appear a superfluous Labour, to fix the true Idea of <hi>civil Liberty,</hi> in a Country which boasts itself <hi>free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="11"/>
Yet the Writer esteems it a necessary though obvious Task: Not only that he may appeal to his Idea of it, thus estab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lished; but also, because in the <hi>Conduct</hi> (at least) if not in the <hi>Writings</hi> of his Countrymen, it seems to have been some<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>times mistaken.</p>
            <p>The <hi>natural Liberty</hi> of Man, considered merely as a solitary and savage Individual, would generally lead him to a full and unbounded Prosecution of all his Appe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tites. Some Savages there are, though few, who live nearly, if not altogether, in this <hi>brutal</hi> State of <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These last Expressions, it must be con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fessed, are inadequate to their Subject: For such a State of Man is worse than that of Brutes, and in the strict Sense, is also <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Nature.</hi> For Brutes are en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dowed with unerring Instincts, which Man possesseth not: Therefore such a solitary and wretched State is strictly <hi>unnatural;</hi> because it prevents the Exertion of those Powers, which his <hi>Nature</hi> is <hi>capable</hi> of <hi>at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>taining:</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="12"/>
But those <hi>Powers Society</hi> alone can <hi>call forth</hi> into <hi>Action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man is therefore formed for <hi>Society:</hi> That is, Man is formed for Intercourse with Man: Hence, through the natural Deve<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lopement of the human Powers, a Variety of new <hi>Wants,</hi> a Necessity for mutual <hi>Aids</hi> and distinct <hi>Properties,</hi> must arise: From these, a new <hi>Accession,</hi> as well as a frequent <hi>Disagreement</hi> and <hi>Clashing</hi> of <hi>Desires</hi> must inevitably ensue. Hence the Necessity of <hi>curbing</hi> and <hi>fixing</hi> the <hi>Desires</hi> of Man in the social State; by such <hi>equal Laws,</hi> as may compel the <hi>Appetites</hi> of each <hi>Individual</hi> to yield to the <hi>common Good</hi> of <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this salutary <hi>Restraint, civil Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty</hi> is derived. Every natural Desire which might in any Respect be inconsist<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ent with the general Weal, is given up as a voluntary Tax, paid for the higher, more lasting, and more important <hi>Benefits,</hi> which we reap from <hi>social Life.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="14" facs="13"/>
            <head>SECT. III. Of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>FROM the Nature of civil Liberty, thus delineated, the Nature of <hi>Licen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiousness</hi> will easily be fixed: Being indeed no other than <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Every Desire carry'd into Action, which in any Respect violates those equal Laws, established for the common Benefit of the Whole."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, an <hi>unlimited Indulgence</hi> of Appe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tite, which in the <hi>savage</hi> State is called <hi>natural Liberty,</hi> in the <hi>social</hi> State is stiled <hi>Licentiousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Licentiousness,</hi> when its immediate Object is That of <q rend="inline margQuotes">"thwarting the Ends of civil Liberty,"</q> is distinguished by the Name of <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="15" facs="14"/>
            <head>SECT. IV. Unassisted Laws no permanent Foundation of Civil Liberty.</head>
            <p>THESE Remarks are obvious; and clear to every Man possessed of the common Degrees of Understanding. Let us now consider, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"What are the <hi>perma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nent Foundations</hi> of civil Liberty:"</q>That is, in other Words, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"What are the effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tual Means by which every Member of Society may be uniformly sway'd, im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pelled, or induced, to sacrifice his pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate Desires or Appetites, to the Welfare of the Public."</q>—This is a Subject, which deserves a particular Elucidation, because in our own Country, and our own Times, it seems to have been <hi>much</hi> and <hi>dangerously</hi> mistaken.</p>
            <p>It hath been affirmed as a first Principle by certain Writers, and hath been artfully or weakly suggested by others, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that the
<pb n="16" facs="15"/>
coercive Power of human Laws is suffi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient to sustain itself: That the Legislator or Magistrate hath properly no Concern with the private Opinions, Sentiments, or Operations of the Mind: And that <hi>Actions</hi> alone fall under the legal Cog<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nizance of those in Power."</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>Fable of the Bees</hi> hath boldly laid down this; which, as a ruling Principle, pervades his whole Work. He professes himself the Friend of Liberty: He derides private Virtue, as the Offspring of Flattery, begotten upon Pride: He discards Religion, as a political Fable; he treats the Principle of Honour, as an empty Chimera; he recommends private Vices as public Be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nefits; <note place="bottom" n="*">
                  <hi>Fable of the Bees,</hi> passim.</note> and having thus level'd the whole Fabric of <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Principles;</hi> what, do you think, is the grand Arcanum of his Policy, for the Prevention of such Crimes as would indanger the Grandeur and Stability of the State? Why;—<q rend="inline margQuotes">"se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vere
<pb n="17" facs="16"/>
Laws, rugged Officers, Pillories, Whipping-Posts, Jails, and Gibbets."</q> 
               <note place="bottom" n="*">Essay on Charity Schools.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This Principle, of the Sufficiency of hu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>man Laws to sustain their own Efficacy and Power, without Regard to the Opi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nions or Principles of Men, hath been, at least, indirectly held forth by other Writers.</p>
            <p>An Author, who although a <hi>sincere,</hi> was certainly an <hi>imprudent</hi> Friend of Liberty, speaks in the following ambigu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ous Stile; which, if not designed to im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>press the Principle here called in Question, is at least very liable to be interpreted into it. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"It is foolish to say, that Govern<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment is concerned to meddle with the <hi>private Thoughts</hi> and Actions of Men, while they injure neither the Society, nor any of its Members. Every Man is in Nature and Reason, the <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>poser</hi> of his own <hi>domestic Affairs;</hi> and according to the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="17"/>
                  <hi>Equity,</hi> every Man must carry <hi>his own Conscience:</hi> So that neither has the Magi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>strate a Right to <hi>direct</hi> the <hi>private Be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>haviour</hi> of Men; nor has the Magistrate, or any Body else, any Manner of Power to <hi>model</hi> People's <hi>Speculations,</hi> no more than their <hi>Dreams.</hi> Government being intended to <hi>protect</hi> Men from the <hi>Injuries</hi> of one another, and not to direct them in <hi>their own Affairs;</hi> in which <hi>no one is interested but themselves,</hi> it is plain, that their <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>domestic Concerns</hi> are <hi>exempted</hi> entirely from its Jurisdic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion: In Truth, Men's <hi>Thoughts</hi> are not subject to <hi>their own Jurisdiction."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>—"Let People alone,</hi> and they will <hi>take Care of themselves,</hi> and do it <hi>best:</hi> And if they do not, a sufficient <hi>Punishment</hi> will <hi>follow</hi> their <hi>Neglect,</hi> without the <hi>Magistrate's Interposition</hi> and <hi>Penalties.</hi> It is plain, that such busy Care and offi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cious <hi>Intrusion</hi> into the <hi>personal Affairs,</hi> or <hi>private Actions, Thoughts,</hi> and <hi>Imagina<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions</hi> of Men, has in it more <hi>Craft</hi> than
<pb n="19" facs="18"/>
                  <hi>Kindness:—</hi>To <hi>quarrel</hi> with any Man for his <hi>Opinions, Humours,</hi> or the Fashion of his Cloaths, is an <hi>Offence</hi> taken without being given."</q>—<q rend="inline margQuotes">"True and impartial Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty is therefore the Right of every Man, to pursue the <hi>natural, reasonable,</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> Dictates of his own Mind: To <hi>think what he will,</hi> and <hi>act as he thinks,</hi> provided he <hi>acts not</hi> to the <hi>Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>judice</hi> of another. <note place="bottom" n="*">
                     <hi>Cato</hi>'s Letters, No. 62.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>These Expressions are crude, inaccurate, and ambiguous; leaving the thoughtful Reader at a Loss for the Author's precise and determined Meaning. For, first, they may possibly imply, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that the Magistrate hath no Right to violate the Laws of what is commonly called <hi>religious Tole<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ration</hi> or <hi>christian Liberty;</hi> but that every Man hath an unalienable Right to wor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ship God in that <hi>Manner</hi> which accords to the Dictates of his own Conscience."</q>—In this Sense they are rational and true:
<pb n="18" facs="19"/>
               <gap extent="1 page" rend="content:〈1 page duplicate〉">
                  <desc>duplicate</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="20"/>
               <gap extent="1 page" rend="content:〈1 page duplicate〉">
                  <desc>duplicate</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="21"/>
And to this Truth the Writer hath more than once born public Testimony. <note place="bottom" n="*">See Vol. of Sermons, Serm. 4, 5, 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But, secondly, they may imply, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that Thoughts, Speculations, Opinions, Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples, however received and imbibed by the Mind of Man, have no Connexion with his Actions; at most, no Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nexion so necessary and strong as to give the Magistrate a Right to <hi>regulate</hi> them by <hi>any Means</hi> whatever. That no Di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rection is to be given either to the <hi>grown</hi> or the <hi>infant Mind;</hi> that as every Member of Society hath a Right to hold what Opinions and Principles he plea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>seth, so he hath the same Privilege to communicate them to his <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Children:</hi> That they are to think what they will, because Thoughts and Opi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nions are a private and personal Affair: That the Magistrate is only concerned to regulate their Actions."</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="22"/>
This is not only a possible Interpretation, but in all Appearance, the more natural of the two. For it is not here once sug<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gested by this Author, that <hi>Opinions</hi> have any <hi>Influence</hi> on <hi>Actions;</hi> but rather, that they concern <hi>nobody</hi> but <hi>Him</hi> who <hi>holds</hi> them. 'Tis true, he speaks of them as being <hi>reasonable,</hi> and <hi>religious:</hi> But if they be the mere Result of private and fortui<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tous Thought, unaided by the Regulations of civil Policy, I see not why they may not more probably be <hi>unreasonable</hi> and <hi>irreli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gious:</hi> Because they are more likely to be model'd by <hi>ruling Appetites</hi> than <hi>rational Deduction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the same Time, it is but Justice to this Author to say, that he certainly meant not (like the Author of the <hi>Fable of the Bees)</hi> to discard all <hi>moral</hi> Principles as groundless and chimerical; whatever his Intentions were with Regard to <hi>Religion.</hi> But his Expressions are <hi>ambiguous,</hi> and have been laid hold of by Men of the most libertine Opinions: Therefore in
<pb n="22" facs="23"/>
whatever Sense they were <hi>written,</hi> it is necessary to oppose them, in that Sense in which they have been <hi>received.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And farther, this is certain: That the Principle implied in this second Interpreta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion hath passed into a general Maxim in this Kingdom, among those who pique themselves on <hi>unlimited Freedom</hi> of <hi>Thought.</hi> These Men have long and openly derided every <hi>Regulation</hi> of <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Principle;</hi> have discarded all <hi>moral</hi> and <hi>religious In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>struction,</hi> under the despised Idea, of <hi>Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>judice of Education;</hi> have laid it down as their fundamental Maxim, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that you are to think what you will: Only to act ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nestly."</q> Not attending to that essential Connexion which subsists between <hi>Thoughts, Opinions, Principles,</hi> and ACTIONS.</p>
            <p>Doubtless, any Society of Men, aiming at the Establishment of civil Liberty, have a Right to unite themselves on what Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ditions they please. But it is the Purpose of this Essay, to prove, by Reasonings confirmed by Facts, that a free Commu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nity
<pb n="23" facs="24"/>
built on the Maxims above delivered, cannot be of <hi>long Duration:</hi> That the mere <hi>coercive Power</hi> of <hi>human Laws</hi> is not suf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficient to <hi>sustain itself:</hi> That there is a strong and unalterable <hi>Connexion</hi> between <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Actions:</hi> That a certain <hi>Regu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lation</hi> of Principles is necessary to check the selfish Passions of Man; and prevent <hi>Liberty</hi> from degenerating into <hi>Licentious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness:</hi> And that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"a certain System of Manners and Principles, mutually sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>porting each other, and pervading the whole Community, are the only perma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nent Foundation on which true civil Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty can arise."</q>
            </p>
            <p>The natural Appetites, Passions, and Desires of Man, are the universal Foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain of his Actions: Without the Impulse which he receives from <hi>those,</hi> he would be at once unfeeling and inactive. Conse<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quently, according to the State and Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter of his Desires, his Actions will <hi>natu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rally</hi> be good or evil; innocent, useful, or destructive.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="25"/>
Were these Desires universally coincident with the Welfare and Happiness of others, no coercive Power would be wanting, as the Means of producing and securing perfect Liberty.</p>
            <p>But the acknowledged Necessity of penal Laws affords an incontestable Proof, that the <hi>unbridled Desires</hi> of Man are utterly inconsistent with the Welfare and Happi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness of his Fellow Creatures.</p>
            <p>Whatever Means, therefore, are most effectual in curbing and <hi>subduing</hi> the selfish <hi>Desires</hi> of Man, are the most effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tual Means of <hi>regulating</hi> his <hi>Actions,</hi> and establishing civil Liberty on its most per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>manent Foundations.</p>
            <p>The mere coercive Power of human Laws, without an assistant Regulation of the Passions and Desires, is utterly inade<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quate to the great Ends either of <hi>private</hi> Happiness or <hi>public</hi> Liberty.</p>
            <p>It cannot produce <hi>private</hi> Happiness to the Individual, because while it leaves his Mind open to be <hi>infested</hi> by every <hi>unruly</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="26"/>
               <hi>Passion</hi> that may arise, it <hi>forbids</hi> him the <hi>Gratification:</hi> Thus it sets the distracted Soul at Variance with itself. The best Consequence that can be hoped for, is a continued Conflict of <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Appetite;</hi> of a <hi>Dread</hi> of human <hi>Laws,</hi> warring with inordinate and <hi>selsish Passions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot be a <hi>permanent</hi> Foundation of public Liberty; because while the Passions are thus left without an inward Controul, they will often be too strong for <hi>Fear,</hi> even where a legal Punishment is the cer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain Consequence: For as they are suffered to subsist in their full Vigour, and when kindled in the Soul are blind and head<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>long, they will often carry away the whole Man; will bear him down in their Gratification, even to unavoidable De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>struction.</p>
            <p>Still farther, and chiefly: Human Power cannot penetrate the secret Recesses of the Soul, nor reach the dark Intentions of the Heart of Man, nor always be of Weight to combat the Strength of Indi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>viduals:
<pb n="26" facs="27"/>
Hence <hi>Cunning</hi> will often <hi>evade,</hi> and <hi>Force</hi> will often <hi>defy,</hi> the coercive Power of the best-formed Laws. Thus <hi>public Wisdom</hi> must give Way to <hi>pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate Gratification,</hi> the <hi>Innocent</hi> must be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>come a <hi>Prey</hi> to the <hi>Guilty;</hi> that is, in other Words, <hi>Liberty</hi> must be <hi>destroyed,</hi> and <hi>Licentiousness</hi> must <hi>triumph.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>SECT. V. Virtuous Manners and Principles the only permanent Foundation of civil Liberty.</head>
            <p>WHAT, then, are the <hi>permanent Foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dations,</hi> on which perfect Liberty can arise?—I answer, it can only arise on the Power of such a System of <hi>Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> effectually impressed on the human Mind, as may be an <hi>in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward Curb</hi> to every inordinate Desire; or rather, such as may so frame and model the Human Heart, that its ruling Desires
<pb n="27" facs="28"/>
may correspond, coincide, or coalesce, with all the great and essential Appoint<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments of public Law.</p>
            <p>The Nature of Man admits of this Im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>provement, though not in a perfect, yet in a considerable Degree. He is born with Appetites suited to his own Preser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vation, and the Continuance of his Spe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cies: Beyond this, he is by Nature at once <hi>selfish</hi> and <hi>social; compassionate</hi> and <hi>resentful; docile,</hi> either to <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil;</hi> and hence, capable of acquiring <hi>new Ha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bits,</hi> new Passions, new Desires, either to the <hi>Welfare</hi> or <hi>Destruction</hi> of his Fellow-Creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virtuous Manners</hi> I call such acquired Habits of Thought and correspondent Action, as lead to a steady Prosecution of the general Welfare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virtuous Principles</hi> I call such as tend to confirm these Habits, by superinducing the Idea of <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Virtuous Manners are a permanent Foundation for civil Liberty, because they
<pb n="28" facs="29"/>
lead the Passions and Desires themselves to coincide with the Appointments of public Law. The infant Mind is preg<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nant with a Variety of Passions: But it is in the Power of those who are in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>trusted with the Education of Youth, in a considerable Degree, to determine the Bent of the nascent Passions; to fix them on salutary Objects, or let them loose to such as are pernicious or destructive.</p>
            <p>Here, then, lie the first Foundations of civil Liberty: In forming the Habits of the youthful Heart, to a <hi>Coincidence</hi> with the <hi>general Welfare:</hi> In checking every rising Appetite that is contrary to This, and in forwarding every Passion that may promote the Happiness of the Community: In implanting and improv<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Benevolence, Self-Controul, Humility, Integrity, and Truth; in preventing or suppressing the contrary Habits of Selfish<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness, Intemperance, Pride, Dishonesty, and Falsehood: In teaching the young Mind to <hi>delight,</hi> as far as is possible, in
<pb n="29" facs="30"/>
every Virtue for its own Sake: In a Word, in so forming the Pleasures and Displeasures of the opening Heart, that they may coalesce and harmonize with the Laws of public Freedom.</p>
            <p>Above all, <hi>This</hi> will give Stability to civil Liberty, if the social Passions of In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dividuals can be so far extended, as to include the Welfare of the <hi>whole</hi> Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>munity, as their <hi>chief</hi> and <hi>primary</hi> Ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ject. This Affection is distinguished by the Name of <hi>public Spirit,</hi> or the <hi>Love</hi> of our <hi>Country;</hi> the highest Passion that can sway the human Heart, considered as a permanent Foundation of true Liberty.</p>
            <p>But in some Minds the selfish Passions are strong, and the social ones weak or wanting: And in the best formed Heart incidental Temptations may arise, and overturn its pre-established Habits: There<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore it is a necessary Measure for the Se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>curity of private Virtue and public Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom, that <hi>virtuous Principles</hi> be likewise implanted in the Heart. Such Principles,
<pb n="30" facs="31"/>
I mean, as may <hi>strengthen</hi> the good Ha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bits of Thought and Action already con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tracted, by superinducing the Idea of <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of these there are but <hi>three,</hi> which can sway the Manners of Men, and confirm the Foundation of civil Liberty. These are <hi>Religion, Honour,</hi> and natural <hi>Conscience.</hi> The first has the <hi>Deity</hi> for its Object; the second, the <hi>Applause</hi> of <hi>Men;</hi> the third, the <hi>Approbation</hi> of our own <hi>Heart.</hi> The Frame and Situation of Man admits of no other <hi>Principle,</hi> from whence the Idea of <hi>Duty</hi> can arise.</p>
            <p>The Principle of <hi>Religion</hi> tends to this End of confirming civil Liberty, as it in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duces the Idea of <hi>Duty;</hi> and urges the Per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>formance of it, on the Belief of a just, omnipotent, and all-seeing GOD; who approves and condemns, will reward or punish, according as our Thoughts and Actions are Good or Evil.</p>
            <p>But, as the Means of rendering <hi>Reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gion,</hi> a firm <hi>Ally</hi> and <hi>Support</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="32"/>
it is necessary that their <hi>Dictates</hi> should be <hi>coincident:</hi> That is, that the Thoughts and Actions which Religion prescribes as Duties, and forbids as Sins, should coin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cide with the Dictates and Appointments of public Law. In free Countries, this is the natural State of Religion; which commonly either bends to the established Laws of the Community, or moulds them into its own Genius and Complexion.</p>
            <p>The Principle of <hi>Honour</hi> affords a con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>comitant Support of civil Liberty, when properly directed. It works by a power<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ful and universal Passion, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"our Fondness for the Applause of Men:"</q> But in free Countries, this Principle is much more liable to abuse than that of Religion: Because it is apt be be warped by the fashionable and ruling Manners of the Times: For whatever is fashionable is apt to draw Respect and Applause: Whatever is unfashionable is for the present intitled only to Contempt. Hence the Principle of <hi>Honour</hi> becomes <hi>fluctuating</hi> and <hi>uncer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="33"/>
in its Nature, and therefore in its <hi>Effects:</hi> A <hi>Regulation</hi> of this Principle, therefore, is of the most important Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sequence; because, if left to its own fan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tastic Dictates, it will often <hi>endanger</hi> in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stead of <hi>strengthening</hi> the Foundations of public Freedom.</p>
            <p>The third Principle, that of natural <hi>Conscience,</hi> which tends to confirm the Establishment of Liberty, is founded in the Approbation of our own Heart. This Principle is in one Respect independent on the other two, but in another Respect seems to stand intimately related to them. It is independent of them, as it neither looks out for the Approbation of God, nor the Applause of Men: It seems inti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mately related to them, because on a strict Examination of the human Frame, as well as the History of Mankind, it ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pears generally to be the Result of the <hi>one,</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> or <hi>both.</hi> We transplant the acknowledged <hi>Approbation</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and the <hi>Applause</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> into our own <hi>Heart;</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="34"/>
and from this, through the fertile Power of <hi>Association,</hi> springs a new Principle of <hi>Self-Approbation</hi> and <hi>Self-Reproof,</hi> as an additional <hi>Regulator</hi> of our Thoughts and Actions.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, many Writers have resolved the <hi>particular</hi> Dictates of natural Consci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ence into an <hi>unchangeable</hi> Principle of Right and Wrong, arising universally in the human Heart. There is no Doubt, but the <hi>general</hi> Principle of Self-Appro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bation or Self-Rebuke ariseth in an <hi>uni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>versal</hi> Manner, in some Degree or other: But as it appears from the History of human Nature, that the <hi>particular</hi> Dic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tates of this Conscience <hi>vary</hi> with the other received Principles of the Mind, it is not necessary to debate or dwell on this speculative Point: We may take it as a Truth confirmed by Facts, that the <hi>particular</hi> Dictates of natural <hi>Conscience</hi> will generally be founded on those of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="35"/>
Hence, then, it appears, that this Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple of Conscience stands in Need of a <hi>Guide,</hi> in the same Degree as those Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples on which it is founded. If it be founded on the <hi>Religion</hi> of a free State, it will generally <hi>coincide</hi> with the Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples of <hi>Freedom:</hi> If its Foundations are laid in the mere Principle of <hi>Honour,</hi> its Dictates will be <hi>fantastic</hi> as those of its Parent; and will therefore require a pa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rallel <hi>Regulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Each of these Principles, singly taken, is of Power, in <hi>some</hi> Degree or other, to strengthen the Basis of civil Liberty. On their <hi>united</hi> Influence, added to the Force of pre-established Habits of Thought and Manners, public Freedom might seem to arise on immoveable and everlasting Foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dations.</p>
            <p>But as the Nature of Man, even in his most virtuous State, is <hi>imperfect</hi> and <hi>in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>consistent;</hi> so, in Spite of the most salutary Institutions, some <hi>Defects</hi> will intrude. Hence, from an unavoidable Alloy of
<pb n="35" facs="36"/>
Vice, civil Liberty must ever be <hi>imper<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fect:</hi> A certain Degree of Licentiousness (that is, of private Will, opposing the Public) will always mix itself, and in some Degree contaminate the Purity of every Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>Yet, while virtuous Manners and Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples clearly predominate in their Effects, a State may still be justly called <hi>free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in Proportion as these Manners and Principles decay, and their Contraries rise into Power and Action, public Freedom must necessarily decline. For in that Case, the Passions and Powers of the human Mind are all set in Conspiracy against the Dictates of public Law. Hence un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bridled Passions will have their Course; every Man's Heart and Hand will be set against his Brethren; and the general Cement of Society, which bound all to<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gether, being thus dissolved; even with<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>out any external Violence offered, the Commonwealth through its <hi>internal Cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruption</hi> must fall in Pieces.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <pb n="36" facs="37"/>
            <head>SECT. VI. An Objection considered.</head>
            <p>DOubtless, it will be objected (nay, it <hi>hath</hi> been objected) by the Patrons of unlimited Freedom of Thought, that This is indeed a System of <hi>Slavery;</hi> that it is building civil Liberty on the <hi>Servi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tude</hi> of the <hi>Mind,</hi> and shackling the in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fant Soul with <hi>early Prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Answer to this plausible Objection, the Writer replies (what he hath else<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>where advanced <note place="bottom" n="*">Sermons on Education, &amp;c. p. 62, &amp;c.</note> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"That a Prejudice doth not imply, as is generally supposed, the Falsehood of the Opinion instilled, but only that it is taken up, and held, without its proper Evidence. Thus the infant Mind may be prejudiced in Favour of <hi>Truth</hi> as well as <hi>Falsehood;</hi> and neither can the one or the other, thus instilled, be properly called more than an <hi>Opinion."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="38"/>
Farther: The infant Mind cannot re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>main in a State of Indifference and In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>action, either with Regard to Habits of Conduct, or Principles and Opinions. Ha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bits, Impressions, Beliefs, Principles, of one Kind or other, the growing Mind will inevitably contract, from its Communica<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion with Mankind: If therefore rational Habits and Principles be not infused, in order to preclude Absurdities; it is Odds, but Absurdities will get the Start, and preclude all rational Habits and Opi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nions. The Passions and the Reason of a Child will put themselves in Action, however wretched and inconsistent; in the same Manner, as his Limbs will make an Effort towards <hi>walking,</hi> however awk<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward and absurd. The same Objection, therefore, that lies against instilling sa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lutary Habits and Principles, will arise against teaching him to <hi>walk erect:</hi> This being indeed a Violation of the natural <hi>Freedom</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> as the other is of the natural <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Passions and
<pb n="38" facs="39"/>
the <hi>Mind.</hi> The Consequences, too, are of the same Nature: For sure, a Child left to the Direction of his own Appetites and Reason would stand the same Chance to grovel in Absurdities, as to crawl on Hands and Knees, and wallow in the Mire.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any Difference, with Respect to the real and internal Freedom of the Mind, between <hi>Opinions instilled,</hi> and <hi>Opinions caught by Accident.</hi> For in Truth, the Mind cannot be <hi>compelled</hi> to receive any Habit of Thought, Principle, or Opinion. These may indeed be offered to the infant Mind, but the Reception of them is its own voluntary Act; and is e<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>qually so, whether they be presented by fortuitous Incidents, or designed Instruc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion. All the Difference is, that in the first Case such a System of Habits and Opinions will certainly arise, as tend to the Destruction of Society: In the second, such a System of Habits and Opinions may be infused into the free Mind, as
<pb n="39" facs="40"/>
will lay a sure and lasting Foundation of public Liberty and Happiness.</p>
            <p>Nay, if any Difference could arise, with Respect to the true <hi>Freedom</hi> of the <hi>Mind;</hi> surely, <hi>That Mind</hi> ought, in the Eye of Reason, to be adjudged <hi>most free,</hi> which adopts a System of Thought and Action, founded on the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of the agreeing <hi>Society;</hi> rather than <hi>That</hi> which is suf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fered to be incurably tainted with the <hi>vague</hi> and <hi>random</hi> Conceptions of <hi>untu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tor'd Infancy.—</hi>This, at le<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter" rend="content:•">
                  <desc>illegible</desc>
               </gap>st, is conso<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nant with the old Stoic Principle, that <q rend="inline">"The wise Man alone is free. <note place="bottom" n="*">Solus Sapiens liber.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Much hath been said in our Times, indeed, concerning the Force of <hi>unassisted</hi> human <hi>Reason:</hi> The Writer would not willingly either flatter or degrade its Powers. But to Him it appears, that they are superficially informed of the Frame and Tenor of the human Mind, who think that <hi>mere Reason</hi> (as it exists in Man) is more than a Power of dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cerning
<pb n="40" facs="41"/>
and chusing the <hi>properest Means</hi> for obtaining his <hi>desired Ends,</hi> whether these Ends be <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil.</hi> The Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions, pre-established Habits, and infused Principles of the Soul are the universal Motives to human Action. Where these point not to an <hi>End desired,</hi> Reason may indolently exercise its Eye; but can never find nor create an Object, of Force suf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficient to put the Powers of the Soul and Body in Motion. Hence, human Reason must always receive its particular Cast and Colour from the pre-established Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions, Habits, and Principles; will ever form its ruling Ideas of Good and Evil, Right and Wrong, Just and Unjust, from these great Fountains of human Action.</p>
            <p>The History of human Nature con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>firms this Truth: Hence it is, that this boasted human Reason is indeed so poor and unprofitable a Possession; being warped and moulded into that particular Form, which the varying Accidents of Cli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mate, Soil, established Manners, Religion,
<pb n="41" facs="42"/>
Policy, bodily Frame, or prevailing Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions and Principles, chance to give it.</p>
            <p>Hence, then, it appears, that the private Freedom of the infant Mind is not <hi>vio<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lated</hi> but only <hi>directed</hi> to its <hi>best End,</hi> by early and salutary Instruction. Hence it appears to be the proper Destination of Man, that he shall not be left to the Fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lies of his own weak Understanding and nascent Passions; that he shall not be left <hi>fortuitously</hi> to imbibe the Maxims of corrupt Times and Manners; Maxims which, setting aside all Regard to their speculative Truth or Falsehood, do lead to the Dissolution of Law and Freedom: But that he shall be conducted voluntarily to adopt those Habits and Principles, which have been consecrated by the Approba<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of the best and wisest Men, in every Age and Nation; such, in particular, as are suitable to the Laws, the Customs, the Genius, of his own free Country; such, in a Word, as are a <hi>secure Foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dation</hi> of <hi>public Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="42" facs="43"/>
            <head>SECT. VII. A Confirmation of these Principles, drawn from the History of free States.</head>
            <head>1st. Of Sparta.</head>
            <p>THESE Reasonings, founded on the Nature and Constitution of Man, will receive a strong and unanswerable Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>firmation from the History of free States. Hence we shall obtain the clearest Evi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dences of Fact, that while virtuous Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners and Principles retained their Efficacy and Power, civil Liberty remained un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>shaken: That as these decayed, Liberty declined: That as soon as these were lost, Liberty was no more; Licentiousness crept in; Faction triumphed; and overwhelmed these degenerate States in one common Ruin.</p>
            <p>To this Purpose I shall briefly analyze the Genius of the three most eminent
<pb n="43" facs="44"/>
               <hi>Republics</hi> that are recorded in Story: Those of SPARTA, ATHENS, and ROME. The Events are sufficiently known to those who are conversant in ancient History: But the fundamental and leading <hi>Causes</hi> of these Events deserve a particular Inves<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tigation: They will form a concurrent Proof of the Principles here given.</p>
            <p>The Republic of SPARTA claims the first Place; both on Account of its Antiquity, and Perfection. By its Perfection is meant, not the moral Perfection of its <hi>particular Institutions,</hi> but of the <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> by which <hi>These</hi> Institutions were secured.</p>
            <p>The leading Institutions which LYCUR<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>GUS fixed as the Essence of his Common<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wealth, were these which follow.</p>
            <p>1. He established a Senate of <hi>twenty-eight,</hi> as an <hi>intermediate Power</hi> between that of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People...</hi> 2. He made an equal Partition of Lands and Goods, among the free Members of the Community... 3. He introduced the Use of Iron Money, instead of Gold and Silver... 4. He banished or
<pb n="44" facs="45"/>
prevented all the Arts of Commerce, Ele<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gance, and Luxury... 5. He ordained, that all the Members of the Society should eat together, and partake alike of the same coarse Fare... 6. He established an occasional Community of Wives: So that a Wife was not so much the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perty of her Husband, as of the Repub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lic, to the End of Population... 7. With a parallel View, he ordained a Kind of Community of Children: By This, no Father had the Care of his own Child; which, on its Birth, was immediately de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>livered over to the Officers of the State; and was either preserved or destroyed ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cording to their Decree... 8. A conti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nued Attention to the Preservation of the State, and an unremitted Preparation and Readiness for defensive War, formed the chief Employment of the <hi>Spartan</hi> State... 9. He committed the Cultivation of their Lands to a large Body of Slaves, who dwelt in the surrounding Country, were deprived of all the natural Rights
<pb n="45" facs="46"/>
of Men, and were often laid in Wait for, and butchered in cold Blood by the young Men of SPARTA. <note place="bottom" n="*">This Enormity, practised with Impunity by the young Men of Sparta, hath been held unaccountable: But seems to have been allowed on the same warlike Principle with That other Allowance <q rend="inline">"of stealing Vic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tuals."</q> Both were probably established as the Means of preparing them for the Exercise of <hi>Stratagem</hi> in War.</note>
            </p>
            <p>These were the public and essential In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stitutions of the Spartan Republic: Many of them strange in their Nature: Yet formed for long Duration, through the Means and Principles on which they were established: Which we shall find to be consistent with, and corroborative of the Principles of civil Liberty above laid down.</p>
            <p>The first and best Security of civil Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty, hath been shewn to consist <q rend="inline margQuotes">"in impressing the infant Mind with such Habits of Thought and Action, as may correspond with and promote the Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointments of public Law."</q>—This Se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>curity was laid by LYCURGUS, in the
<pb n="46" facs="47"/>
deepest and most effectual Manner, by the Mode of <hi>Education</hi> which he pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>scribed to the <hi>Spartan</hi> Youth.</p>
            <p>No Father had a Right to educate his Children according to the Caprice of his own Fancy. They were delivered to pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lic Officers, who initiated them early in the Manners, the Maxims, the Exercises, the Toils, in a Word, in all the mental and bodily Acquirements and Habits, which <hi>corresponded</hi> with the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>State.</hi> Family Connexions had no Place: The first and leading Object of their Af<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fection, was the general Welfare. This Tuition was carefully continued, till they were enrolled in the List of <hi>Men:</hi> To secure the Manners thus acquired, they were prohibited from travelling into other Countries, lest they should catch Infection from ill Example: On the same Founda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, all Visits from Strangers were for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bidden. <note place="bottom" n="*">Plutarch: in Lycurgo.</note> Thus were they strongly and
<pb n="47" facs="48"/>
unalterably possessed with the <hi>Love</hi> of their <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These severe Manners were confirmed by all the Principles that could strengthen them in the Mind of Man.</p>
            <p>The Principle of <hi>Religion</hi> laid at the very Foundation of the State: For LY<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>CURGUS expressly modeled his Common<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wealth on the Pretence of a divine Au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thority. He declared to the People, that its essential Institutions were given him by the Oracle of DELPHI, which he went on Purpose to consult. <note place="bottom" n="*">Plutarch: in Lycurgo.</note> Again, after he had modeled his Republic, he repaired once more to the sacred Tripod; and en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quired, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"whether the God approved of the Laws he had established."</q> The An<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>swer was in the Affirmative: And this Reply LYCURGUS sent to SPARTA. <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This Principle was so intimately blen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ded with that of the State, that their <hi>Kings</hi> were at the same Time the <hi>High Priests</hi> of the Community. <note place="bottom" n="‡">Ib.</note>—The Reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gion
<pb n="48" facs="49"/>
and Power of an Oath was so strongly impressed on their Minds, that LYCURGUS trusted the future Execution of his Laws, to <hi>That</hi> Oath which the People took, on his last Departure from the City: <note place="bottom" n="*">Plutarch: in Lycurgo.</note>—An Oath, which proves, that the Religion of the Country was not at Variance with the Appointments of the State; because it obliged them never to depart from the Institutions of LYCURGUS.</p>
            <p>The Principle of <hi>Honour</hi> was not at Variance, but <hi>co-operated</hi> with and <hi>sus<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tained</hi> That of <hi>Religion.</hi> PLUTARCH is very particular, on their early and con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tinued Encouragement of this Principle. Their Songs (which made a Part of their Education) tended to inflame their Minds with honest Ambition. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Their Subject was generally the <hi>Praise</hi> of such Men as had dy'd in Defence of their Coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try; or in <hi>Derision</hi> of Those who had shrunk from the public Service. The <hi>old</hi> Men talked high of what they had
<pb n="49" facs="50"/>
done: The <hi>younger</hi> Part echo'd back their Song; declaring their Resolution, not to disgrace the Valour of their Forefathers. <note place="bottom" n="*">Plutarch: in Lycurgo.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Principle of natural <hi>Conscience</hi> was so intimately interwoven with those of their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> that it affords a striking Proof how far natural Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>science depends on these other Principles. If natural Conscience were in itself a well-regulated and <hi>sufficient Guide;</hi> could any Thing have been more odious to its Dic<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tates, than <hi>Prostitution, Adultery, Thieving,</hi> and <hi>Assassination?</hi> Yet all these did the severe <hi>Spartans</hi> practise, not only <hi>without Remorse,</hi> but with <hi>Self-Approbation;</hi> the infant Mind being before-hand modeled to this <hi>preposterous</hi> System of <hi>imagined Duty.</hi> For, on the very ruling Principles of the State, their Daughters were de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bauched, their Wives were common, their Victuals were stolen, their Slaves were murdered. <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="51"/>
Thus was the famed Republic of <hi>Sparta</hi> strongly fortify'd, by the united and con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>current Power of <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Principles,</hi> all pointing to the <hi>same</hi> End, the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Duration</hi> of the <hi>State:</hi> Of Manners and Principles, which in their particular Application, seemed to sacrifice the Hap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>piness of Individuals to the Preservation of the Whole: And while they were most <hi>abhorrent</hi> from the Maxims of <hi>improved</hi> human Nature, <hi>secured</hi> the Institutions of a <hi>savage</hi> Policy.</p>
            <p>From this View of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monwealth, these farther Remarks may naturally arise.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It hath been Matter of Surprize to those who have written on this famed Republic, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"by what Means LYCURGUS should be able to perswade the <hi>Spar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tans,</hi> not only to change the Form of their Government, but to quit their pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate Possessions, their Manner of Life, the Use of Money, the Advantages of Commerce, the Property of their Wives,
<pb n="51" facs="52"/>
the Care of their Children; and adopt a contrary System, so abhorrent from the Desires of civilized Man."</q> And in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>deed, supposing the <hi>Fact,</hi> it should seem a Paradox utterly unaccountable.—The true Solution seems of a quite different Nature.—PLUTARCH leads me to it.—<q rend="inline margQuotes">"There is so much Uncertainty (saith he) in the Accounts which Historians have left us of LYCURGUS, that scarce any Thing is asserted by one, which is not contradicted by others. Their Senti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments are quite different as to the Fa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mily he came of, the Voyages he un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dertook, the Place and Manner of his Death: But most of all, when they speak of the Laws he made, and the Common<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wealth he founded.—They cannot be brought to agree, as to the very <hi>Age</hi> when he lived.—TIMAEUS conjectures, that there were two of his Name, and in different Times; but that the one being more famous than the other, Men gave to Him the Glory of both their Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ploits.
<pb n="52" facs="53"/>
                  <note place="bottom" n="*">Plutarch: in Lycurgo.</note>"</q>—Hence it appears, that the true History of this Lawgiver was lost in the Darkness of fabulous and obscure Ages: And that, as to the Beginnings of this Commonwealth, we have nothing to depend on, but the traditionary Rumours of a barbarous and lying Period. Now this seems to be fairly weighed down by the internal Evidence arising from the Na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture of the Establishment itself. For it was indeed <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the Establishment of bar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>barous Manners, carried into Perma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nency by political Institutions."</q> That Mankind should be <hi>carry'd back</hi> to <hi>This,</hi> from a State of <hi>Humanity</hi> and <hi>Civiliza<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion;—</hi>that they should quit private Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perty, Money, Commerce, Decency, do<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mestic Comforts, Wives and Children, and give them up to the Possession of the Public, is a Contradiction to all the known Powers and Passions of the human Mind. To effect a <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>Government only,</hi> is a Work sufficient for the Abilities of
<pb n="53" facs="54"/>
the greatest Legislator: But to overturn all the pre-established Habits of the Head and Heart, to destroy or reverse all the fixed Associations, Maxims, Manners, and Principles, of a whole civilized Commu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nity; were a Labour, which might well be ranked among the most extravagant Legends of fabulous GREECE.</p>
            <p>On the other Hand, to <hi>bring forward</hi> a Tribe of untaught Savages <hi>one Degree</hi> towards <hi>Civilization,</hi> and <hi>there</hi> to <hi>fix</hi> them;—to assign equal Portions of Land to those among whom Lands laid in Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon;—to introduce Iron Money, where <hi>no Money</hi> had been in Use;—to prohibit Commerce, where Commerce was almost unknown;—to make the Girls dance naked in Public, where they had never known the decent Use of Cloaths;—to allow of Theft and Homicide under cer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain Limitations, where <hi>Both</hi> had been practised without Limitation;—to make Wives at Times a public Property, where promiscuous Concubinage had prevailed;
<pb n="54" facs="55"/>
to give Children a public Education, where no Education had taken Place;—These might all seem the natural and practicable Efforts of a <hi>Pagan</hi> Legislator.</p>
            <p>Thus, the Formation of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Republic seems clearly accounted for. A Tribe of untaught Savages, were brought forward by LYCURGUS one Degree to<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wards Civilization and Humanity, and There fixed by severe Institutions.</p>
            <p>The Fate of AGIS, their patriot King, confirms this Solution. He, with a De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gree of public Virtue seldom seen in any Station, attempted to bring back the cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rupt State to its first rigorous Instituti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ons. But That which LYCURGUS could establish among untaught Savages, AGIS found impracticable, among a corrupted People. He was seized, imprisoned, and murdered by a Faction, in his Attempt to restore Freedom to a degenerate Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>public.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Argument here alledged be just, concerning the first Institution of this
<pb n="55" facs="56"/>
Republic; it follows (what, indeed, seems probable in its own Nature) that the strongest political Institutions may be formed on the savage State of Man. In this Period the Legislator hath few or no prior Institutions to contend with; and therefore can form a System of Legisla<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion consistent with itself in all its Parts. While the Lawgiver who reforms a State already modeled and corrupted, must con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tent himself with such partial Regulations, as the Force of prior Establishments and public Habits will admit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The long united State of this Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>public afford a Proof against a political Maxim commonly received, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"That Divi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions are necessary to a free State; and that inward Tranquillity is a certain Symptom of its approaching Ruin."</q> For, from the History of SPARTA, it appears, that during the Space of at least five hundred Years, intestine Divisions were unknown. This common and mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>taken Maxim (adopted by almost all poli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tical
<pb n="56" facs="57"/>
Writers <note place="bottom" n="*">Among others, by MACHIAVEL and MONTES<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>QUIEU.</note>) hath been founded on a Supposition, that where Opinion is <hi>free,</hi> it must ever be <hi>divided.</hi> The <hi>Spartan</hi> Commonwealth presents a clear Proof of the Reverse: That Opinion may be <hi>free,</hi> yet still <hi>united.</hi> But this <hi>free Union</hi> can only be the happy Effect of an early and rigorous Education; by which the grow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Minds of the Community are volun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tarily led, by public Institutions, into <hi>one common Channel</hi> of <hi>Habit, Principle,</hi> and <hi>Action. . .</hi> PLUTARCH tells us, that the Effect of this entire Union was so conspi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cuous in SPARTA, that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the Common<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wealth resembled <hi>one</hi> great and power<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ful Person, <hi>actuated by one Soul,</hi> rather than a State composed of <hi>many</hi> Indivi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duals. <note place="bottom" n="†">In Lycurgo.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It appears, that the Institutions of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Republic were admirably cal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culated for each other's Support, while
<pb n="57" facs="58"/>
their perfect Union was maintained: And further, that when an Inroad was made into any one of them, the Ruin of the Whole was inevitable.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Its Institutions were admirably cal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culated for each other's Support, while their perfect Union was maintained."</q> Because they tended strongly to prevent the <hi>first Inroads</hi> of <hi>Temptation</hi> to the <hi>Mind,</hi> the very <hi>first Impulses</hi> of <hi>selfish Passion.</hi> The equal Partition of Lands and Goods took away all Hope of Superiority in Wealth: The Introduction of Iron Money rendered Wealth cumbersome and untrac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>table: The Prohibition of Commerce pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vented the Materials of Luxury: The Ba<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nishment of elegant Arts prevented the first Conception of them. Their public Meals eaten in common, cut off the Hope, nay, prevented the Desire of all private In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dulgence of the Palate, the Disorders of Intemperance. To secure these rigid In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stitutions, the public Education of their Children was ordained, lest private Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sion
<pb n="58" facs="59"/>
should mix its Alloy, with the rigo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rous Appointments of the State. Thus the Republic was so round and compact in all its Parts, that it might seem to defy the Attacks of the most powerful Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"But supposing an Inroad made into any one of its capital Institutions, the Ruin of the Whole was inevitable."</q> For its several Parts receiving their Strength from each other, were therefore mutually <hi>dependent;</hi> and the Whole being an au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stere Contradiction to the natural Appe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tites of Man, the least Inroad of Indul<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gence naturally led on to more forcible Temptations. Thus, <hi>Inequality</hi> of Posses<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions brought in <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Poverty. Wealth</hi> brought in <hi>Luxury: Poverty</hi> gave Birth to <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Avarice.</hi> Licentious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness and Faction thus crept in; and the Fall of SPARTA was <hi>inevitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet even amidst the <hi>Decays</hi> of this Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>public, the Force of a rigorous Education essentially mixed with the Principles of
<pb n="59" facs="60"/>
the State, was still conspicuous. The Power of Manners and Maxims thus im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bibed was so untractable, even in the declining Periods of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Common<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wealth, that PHILOPAEMEN, after many fruitless Attempts to annihilate its Influ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ence, declared, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that the only effectual Method of destroying SPARTA, must be in <hi>dissolving</hi> the <hi>Education</hi> of their <hi>Youth.</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="*">Plutarch: in Philopaem.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Analysis is clearly confirmed by PLUTARCH in the following Passages. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Since we may blame the Legislators of common Rank, who, through Want of Power or Wisdom, commit Mistakes in the Formation of fundamental Laws; how much more may we censure the Conduct of NUMA, who for the Repu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tation of his Wisdom only, being called by the general Voice of an unsettled People to be their King, did not in first Place constitute Laws for the Edu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cation of Children, and Discipline of
<pb n="60" facs="61"/>
Youth? For Want of which, Men be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>come seditious and turbulent, and live not peaceable in their Families and Tribes: But when they are inured from their Cradle to good Principles, and im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bibe from their Infancy the Rules of Morality, they receive such Impressions of Virtue, as convinces them of that Advantage which mutual Concord brings to a Commonwealth. This, with many others, was one of the Policies of LY<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>CURGUS: And was of singular Force in the Confirmation and Establishment of his Laws:"</q>— <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Hence the <hi>Spartans</hi> having sucked in these Principles with their Milk, were possessed with a most reverend Esteem of all his Institutions: So that the Fundamentals of his Laws continued in Force for above five hun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dred Years, without any Violation. <note place="bottom" n="*">Comparison of NUMA and LYCURGUS.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such then was the Force of concurrent Manners and Principles, all centering on one Point, impressed on the infant Mind,
<pb n="61" facs="62"/>
and continued by a Variety of rigorous Institutions.—Thus, the Strength of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Republic, like the firm-compacted Weight of the <hi>Macedonian Phalanx,</hi> bore down every opposing Power.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VIII. Of the Republic of Athens.</head>
            <p>WE have seen the Force of Manners Principles in the strong Forma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, the <hi>Unanimity,</hi> and <hi>Continuance</hi> of the <hi>Spartan</hi> State. We shall now see the Ef<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fects of the <hi>Want</hi> of Manners and Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples, in the weak Establishment, the un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceasing <hi>Factions,</hi> and early <hi>Dissolution</hi> of the Commonwealth of ATHENS.</p>
            <p>It appears above, that LYCURGUS, pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bably forming his People in the first and earliest Period of Civilization, was thus enabled to establish a perfect Republic. SOLON, on the contrary, having a <hi>cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rupted</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="63"/>
People to <hi>reform,</hi> could only insti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tute such a Kind of Government, as their <hi>pre-established</hi> Habits, Vices, and Forms of Polity could admit.</p>
            <p>Here we discover the Foundation of that striking Remark of SOLON himself. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"That he gave not the <hi>Athenians</hi> the <hi>best</hi> Laws that could be <hi>given,</hi> but the <hi>best</hi> they were <hi>capable</hi> of <hi>receiving.</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="*">Plut. Solon.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>The first and ruling Defect in the In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stitution of this Republic seems to have been <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the total Want of an established Education, suited to the Genius of the State."</q> There appears not to have been any public, regular, or prescribed Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointment of this Kind, beyond what Custom had accidentally introduced. 'Tis true, that the Parents often had Mas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ters to instruct their Children in the <hi>gym<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nastic</hi> Arts, and in <hi>Music.</hi> Which last, in the ancient Acceptation of the Word, included <hi>Poem</hi> as well as <hi>Melody:</hi> 'Tis farther true, that the Poems thus taught
<pb n="63" facs="64"/>
their Children, included often the great Actions, but withal, the Vices of Gods and ancient Heroes. <note place="bottom" n="*">See a Dissertation on Music and Poetry, Sect. v.</note> Yet in this first and ruling Circumstance, in the Institu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of a free State, the Parents were much at Liberty, to do as seemed good to them. Hence, a dissimilar and discor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dant System of Manners and Principles took Place; while some youthful Minds were imbibed with proper and <hi>virtuous</hi> Principles, some with <hi>no</hi> Principles, and some with <hi>vicious</hi> Principles; with such as must, therefore, on the Whole, tend to shake the Foundations of true Freedom.</p>
            <p>The second ruling Defect in the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stitution of this Republic, was the Estab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lishment of an unmixed and absolute Democracy. This naturally arose from the <hi>licentious</hi> State of <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ples,</hi> which SOLON found already preva<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lent among the <hi>People.</hi> A <hi>virtuous</hi> Peo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ple would have been content to have
<pb n="64" facs="65"/>
               <hi>shared</hi> the legislative Power with the higher Ranks of the Commonwealth. But a <hi>licentious</hi> People naturally grasped the Whole, as the likliest Means (in their de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>luded Eye) of gratifying their own un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bridled Passions. From this partial Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tribution of Power, the State was blindly ruled by the Dregs of the Community. For <hi>All</hi> who were of Ability to maintain a <hi>Horse,</hi> were admitted to the Rank of <hi>Magistracy:</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="*">Plut. in Solon.</note> And all who were <hi>admitted</hi> to the Rank of <hi>Magistracy</hi> were <hi>excluded</hi> from any Share in the <hi>legislative Power.</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib.</note> Hence it followed, that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"All they who possessed the <hi>Legislative Power,</hi> were such as were <hi>not</hi> of <hi>Ability</hi> to <hi>maintain</hi> a <hi>Horse."</hi>
               </q>—<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Do not you despise (said SOCRATES to his Pupil ALCIBIADES, who was afraid to speak in Presence of the <hi>Athenian</hi> People) do not you despise That <hi>Cobler?</hi> I do, reply'd the Youth. Do not you (rejoyned the Philospher) equally contemn that <hi>Cryer,</hi> and yon
<pb n="65" facs="66"/>
                  <hi>Tent-Maker?</hi> ALCIBIADES confessing that he did; then said SOCRATES, "Is not the Body of the <hi>Athenian People</hi> com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posed of Men <hi>like these?</hi> And therefore, when you <hi>despise</hi> the <hi>Individuals,</hi> why should you fear the <hi>Whole?</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="*">Aeliani Var: Hist. L. ii. C. 1.</note>"</q>—A hope<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ful Tribe of <hi>Legislators!</hi> and such as might naturally be supposed to give Rise to that Licentiousness, Discord, and Ruin, in which they were soon swallowed up.</p>
            <p>From this weak and imperfect Estab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lishment, founded on the Caprices of an ignorant, unprincipled, and <hi>licentious Po<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pulace,</hi> all the subsequent <hi>Factions,</hi> which ended in the <hi>Ruin</hi> of this <hi>Republic,</hi> are clearly derived.</p>
            <p>Even SOLON, the original Legislator, outlived the Commonwealth he had form<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed. On his Departure from ATHENS, <hi>Factions</hi> immediately arose. PISISTRA<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>TUS, the first ruling Demagogue, <hi>led</hi> the <hi>People;</hi> obtained a Guard; seized the Castle; and <hi>established</hi> a <hi>Tyranny.</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="†">Plut: in Solon.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="67"/>
We need go no farther into the His<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tory of this Republic, for a Discovery of the Causes of its final Ruin. It is true, that an imperfect Semblance of Liberty often appeared, amidst the Factions of succeeding Times: It is true, that Wealth and Luxury contributed to hasten the Fall of ATHENS: It is true, that PERI<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>CLES and ALCIBIADES, in their Turn, while they seemed to polish the Manners, inflamed the Vices of the Populace; and led them on to the certain Destruction of the State. But for the Ruin of this Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monwealth, we need not have Recourse to the Inroads of Wealth or Luxury, as the Causes of its Dissolution. It resem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bled a beautiful <hi>Edifice</hi> founded in <hi>Sand</hi> and <hi>Rubbish:</hi> Where an <hi>uneducated,</hi> an <hi>unprincipled,</hi> a <hi>licentious Populace,</hi> ruled the State; That State was destined to the convulsive Struggles of <hi>Faction</hi> while it lived, and then to a <hi>speedy Death.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <pb n="67" facs="68"/>
            <head>SECT. IX. Of the Commonwealth of Rome.</head>
            <p>LET us now pass to a Review of the Commonwealth of ROME: In the History and Fate of which, we shall find most abundant Proof of the Truths here laid down, concerning the Power of Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners and Principles, in the Preservation or the Dissolution of public Freedom.</p>
            <p>MONTESQUIEU remarks finely, in his Discourse on this Republic, that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"more States have perished, thro' a Violation of Manners, than thro' a Violation of Laws <note place="bottom" n="*">Grandeur, &amp;c.</note>"</q> The Reason (though he does not assign it) appears evident on the Principles here given. He who violates established <hi>Manners,</hi> strikes at the general <hi>Foundation;</hi> he who violates <hi>Law,</hi> strikes only at a particular Part of the <hi>Superstruc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture</hi> of the State.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="69"/>
In the Republic of SPARTA, we have seen the original State of Manners and Principles conspiring strongly to the <hi>Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>servation</hi> of the Republic: In that of ATHENS, we have seen the original State of Manners and Principles tending no less clearly to its <hi>Dissolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In analysing the original State of Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners and Principles in the <hi>Roman</hi> Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monwealth, we shall find a different and <hi>intermediate</hi> State of Things; mixing the <hi>Strength</hi> of the <hi>Spartan,</hi> with the <hi>Weakness</hi> of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Institutions; tending first to <hi>enlarge</hi> and <hi>aggrandize</hi> the Republic, and in the End to <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>destroy</hi> it.</p>
            <p>The Manners and Principles of early ROME, which tended to enlarge and aggran<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dize the Republic, were 1. A <hi>Love</hi> of their <hi>Country</hi> instilled into their rising Youth: Formed chiefly on the Power of <hi>Custom;</hi> and more particularly on the <hi>warlike</hi> Ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nius of the State. Their Annals abound with so many Instances of this grand Passion, that present Times stand amazed, and with Difficulty credit their Story.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="69" facs="70"/>
2. This Passion, founded on an <hi>early,</hi> though <hi>not</hi> a <hi>prescribed</hi> Education, was so strengthened by their <hi>religious</hi> System, that till the fatal Entrance of the Doctrine of EPICURUS, no <hi>Roman</hi> was ever known to have violated his Oath. <note place="bottom" n="*">See Montesq. Grand. des Rom. C. x. Polyb. L. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Their Principle of <hi>Honour</hi> coincided with that of their Religion. It was so strong, at the Time of the first Formation of the Republic, that the Punishment of <hi>Disgrace</hi> was judged sufficient to deter the People from a Violation of the Laws. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"When a Delinquent was cited before the People (saith LIVY) the <hi>Valerian</hi> Law ordained only, that he should be branded as <hi>in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>famous.</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="†">Liv. Hist. L. 10.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. From the Truths laid down above, it appears, that the Principle of natural <hi>Conscience</hi> must of Course co-operate with these, for the Confirmation of civil Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom. The Force of this Principle is no less conspicuous in the early Periods of
<pb n="70" facs="71"/>
               <hi>Roman</hi> Liberty: It arose even into a fero<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cious Pride of Virtue, independent of all outward Testimony, which hath distin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guished the great Names of ancient ROME, from Those of every other People upon Earth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To these we must add the <hi>Equality</hi> of Property, the <hi>Mediocrity</hi> of Possession, the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of Life, which prevailed in early ROME; all these were the Outworks that guarded the internal Strength of Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners and Principles; and seemed, like the Institutions of SPARTA, to promise an Eternity of Freedom.</p>
            <p>But in Spite of all these Foundations of civil Liberty, there were three fatal Cir<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cumstances, admitted into the very Essence of the Republic, which contained the <hi>Seeds</hi> of <hi>certain Ruin:</hi> While the <hi>Tree</hi> seemed to <hi>flourish</hi> in its full Growth and Vigour, <hi>These,</hi> like <hi>Canker-Worms,</hi> lay <hi>eat<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing</hi> at the Root.</p>
            <p>The first of these was the Neglect of instituting public Laws, by which the
<pb n="71" facs="72"/>
               <hi>Education</hi> of their Children might have been <hi>ascertained.</hi> This is justly charged by PLUTARCH, as a capital Defect in NUMA's Legislation: <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, Sect. vii.</note> This Defect, when once admitted into the Essence of the State, could not easily be rectify'd in succeeding Times: The Principle could only have been effectually infused, at the general Formation of the whole Mass. In Consequence of this Error in the first Concoction, the supporting Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples of Freedom were vague and fluc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tuating: For Want of this <hi>preventing</hi> Power, the incidental Vices of a Parent were naturally transmitted to his Chil<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dren, and thence to future Ages. The rigorous Education of SPARTA was a strong Check to the Proneness of human Nature towards Degeneracy and Corrup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion: Through This, every incidental Vice dy'd with its first Possessor: While the more lax Institution of the <hi>Roman</hi> Repub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lic, suffered every original Taint in Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners
<pb n="72" facs="73"/>
and Principles to be transfused into, and to contaminate succeeding Times.</p>
            <p>The second of these was <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Their Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple of <hi>unlimited Conquest."</hi>
               </q> Their early Passion for War arose from their <hi>Necessi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ties.</hi> On their first Establishment, they had neither <hi>Territory</hi> nor <hi>Commerce:</hi> They lived by <hi>Plunder:</hi> Hence, the <hi>ruling Ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nius</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> was <hi>warlike:</hi> Their war<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>like Genius was <hi>unchecked</hi> by any other Principle: Hence, unremitted Exercises, unceasing Improvements in Discipline, in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>creasing Valour and Ferocity arose. Thus they attempted to subdue, and thus they subdued the World.</p>
            <p>But such an Empire is utterly <hi>untena<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble: Valour</hi> may <hi>acquire,</hi> but cannot <hi>main<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain</hi> it. The <hi>Body</hi> of such a State is too enormous to be effectually animated by the <hi>Soul.</hi> This is a Cause of Ruin so clear, that it hath met every Writer's Observation; and therefore needs no far<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther Proof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="74"/>
The third Principle of inevitable De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>struction, which seems to have been in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wrought into the very Essence of the <hi>Ro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>man</hi> Republic, was the fatal Principle of <hi>Change:</hi> This is a Cause not so obvious; and therefore may require a farther Inves<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tigation.</p>
            <p>MONTESQUIEU hath justly observed, that one Cause of the <hi>Roman Greatness</hi> was <q rend="inline margQuotes">"their <hi>adopting</hi> any Institution or Custom of other Nations whom they conquer'd, provided it was better than their own. <note place="bottom" n="*">Grandeur, &amp;c. C. i. ii.</note>"</q> It seems to have escaped the Observation of this great Writer, that the same Princi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ple of <hi>Adoption,</hi> carried through every Pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riod of the Republic, led the Way to its final <hi>Ruin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For altho' in the early Periods, when Manners were simple, and concurrent Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples were strong, this Spirit of <hi>Adoption</hi> was confined to Customs that were <hi>better</hi> than their own; yet in the succeeding Pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riods,
<pb n="74" facs="75"/>
when Manners grew more relaxed, and Principles were weakened, the same Spirit of <hi>Adoption</hi> opened a Door for the Admission of <hi>Customs</hi> that were <hi>pernicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Admission of <hi>Change,</hi> which in the virtuous Ages led to the <hi>Greatness,</hi> in succeeding Times brought on the <hi>Destruc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion</hi> of the Republic.</p>
            <p>The sagacious Romans soon found the Consequences of this Defect: They saw, that through a Want of original, <hi>preven<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive,</hi> and salutary Institutions, bad Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners were creeping insensibly on the State. Hence the Creation of the <hi>Censors</hi> had its Rise: An Office, which immediately took Cognizance of the Manners of the <hi>Ci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tizens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this high Office was ineffectual in its End; because it had not Power univer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sally to <hi>prevent, but</hi> only in Part to <hi>remedy</hi> the Evil. Hence, while <hi>particular</hi> and <hi>detected Offences</hi> only, could be punished by the <hi>Censor,</hi> the <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> of the People were laid open to a <hi>general Cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruption,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="76"/>
from the fatal Principle of <hi>No<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>velty</hi> and <hi>Adoption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Danger arising from this Principle manifestly increased with the increasing Empire: That <hi>Identity</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> of Manners and Principles, which is the Soul and Security of every free State, gave Way to Manners and Principles wholly <hi>dissimi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lar.</hi> New Maxims of Life, new Principles of Religion and Irreligion, of Honour and Dishonour, of Right and Wrong, picked up indiscriminately among the Nations which they conquered, by Degrees infused themselves into the Heads and Hearts of the <hi>Roman</hi> Citizens.</p>
            <p>Here, then, we see the original Founda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of all the Misery and Ruin which ensued. On the Conquest of the <hi>luxu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rious, immoral,</hi> and <hi>unprincipled</hi> Tribes of GREECE, the <hi>Romans,</hi> having no <hi>preven<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive Remedy</hi> in the Essence of their State, of Course <hi>adopted</hi> the <hi>Luxury,</hi> the <hi>Immora<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lities,</hi> the <hi>Irreligion,</hi> of the conquered People.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="77"/>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"It seems to me (says the excellent MONTESQUIEU) that the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Sect, which made its Way into ROME towards the Close of the Republic, con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tributed much to corrupt the Hearts of the <hi>Romans.</hi> The <hi>Greeks</hi> had been in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fatuated with it before them; accord<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ingly, they were sooner corrupt. PO<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>LYBIUS tells us, that in His Time, no <hi>Greek</hi> could be trusted, on the Se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>curity of his Oath; whereas, a <hi>Roman</hi> was inevitably bound by it. <note place="bottom" n="*">Grandeur, &amp;c. C. x.</note>"</q>—He adds, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"CYNEAS having discoursed on the <hi>Epicurean</hi> System at the Table of PYRRHUS, FABRICIUS wished that all the Enemies of ROME might hold the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>such a Sect.</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, as in the early Periods of the Commonwealth, they had adopted the <hi>Virtues,</hi> in the later Times they assumed the <hi>Vices</hi> of the conquered Nations. Thus, by unperceived Gradations, the same Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <pb n="77" facs="78"/>
"The Admission of <hi>Change,</hi> first led to the <hi>Greatness,</hi> and then to the <hi>Ruin</hi> of the Republic."</q>
            </p>
            <p>All the particular Consequences that followed, were <hi>occasional</hi> and <hi>inevitable.</hi> The Rapacity, the Factions, the civil Wars; the enormous Profligacy of Indi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>viduals, the horrible Calamities of the State;—All these are finely pursued by MONTESQUIEU; and were no more than the natural and incidental Effects of this general Cause, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Loss of Manners and Principles."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, the <hi>Progress</hi> and <hi>Retreat</hi> of the <hi>Roman Power</hi> resembled the <hi>Flow</hi> and the <hi>Ebb</hi> of a vast Ocean; which, rowzed from its Bed by central Concussions, <hi>over<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>whelmed</hi> and <hi>forsook</hi> the <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <pb n="78" facs="79"/>
            <head>SECT. X. How far these Facts can properly be ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ply'd to the political State of Great Britain.</head>
            <p>THOUGH the Study of History be of<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ten instructive and useful, yet, in one Respect, it becomes the Source of fre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quent Error, even when it is written with Impartiality and Truth. This ariseth from a mistaken Application of historical Facts. Errors of this Kind are apt to creep in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>to all Reasonings, on every Subject, where Men and Manners are concerned: But they are liable to infect <hi>political</hi> Reason<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ings, above all others.</p>
            <p>As the political Interests of Men form the principal Subject of History, the Rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>soner on this Subject hath Recourse to Facts, as the best Support of his Ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gument. Yet, the Politician seems, of all others, most liable to be mistaken in the Application of History to his own
<pb n="79" facs="80"/>
Purpose; because the political Connex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ions and Interests of Men are, above all others, <hi>complicated</hi> and <hi>various.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, as no two political Constitutions were ever the <hi>same</hi> in <hi>all</hi> their Circum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stances, though <hi>similar</hi> in <hi>many;</hi> so, all Arguments drawn from a <hi>partial</hi> Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>semblance, must be inadequate and incon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>clusive; unless when it appears, that no other Circumstances took Place, by which That <hi>partial</hi> Resemblance might be <hi>coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>teracted,</hi> and its Effects destroyed.</p>
            <p>Yet, it hath been a Practice too com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon among political Reasoners, from a <hi>partial</hi> Resemblance between two States, to infer a <hi>total</hi> one; and because they have been <hi>like</hi> in <hi>some</hi> Respects, to draw Conclusions, as if they had been <hi>like</hi> in <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much Caution, therefore, is necessary, in the Application of historical Facts: Without This, we shall run into perpe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tual Error. Let us, then, remark some of the most <hi>essential</hi> Circumstances, in which the Constitution of the <hi>British</hi> State
<pb n="80" facs="81"/>
differs from those of SPARTA, ATHENS, and ROME; and then draw such Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>clusions, as may be consistent with these Distinctions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may lay it down as a funda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mental Truth generally acknowledged, that the <hi>political</hi> Constitution of GREAT BRI<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>TAIN, in its <hi>main Outline,</hi> is <hi>better modeled</hi> than those of SPARTA, ATHENS, or ROME. The legislative and executive Powers are more equally balanced, and more clearly distinguished. Now, if Laws could support themselves, it would follow, that this political State must <hi>therefore</hi> be of <hi>longer Duration.</hi> But as it hath been made appear, that the Duration of free States depends not so much on their mere <hi>Form,</hi> as on the <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> which support them; so, nothing can be decided concerning the <hi>Duration</hi> of the <hi>British</hi> State, from its mere <hi>external Model.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Christian</hi> Religion, established in BRITAIN, is, in its own Nature, far
<pb n="81" facs="82"/>
superior to that of these ancient Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>monwealths. The absolute Perfection and glorious Attributes of the Deity; the great Principle of universal Charity; the parti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cular Duties of Man to Man, thence re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sulting; the Sanctions of future Reward and Punishment; all these tend to purify and exalt the Soul, far beyond the Rites of ancient Paganism: For This, even in its best Forms, was ever built on the History and Examples of deify'd Men, whose Lives had often been blotted with the most flagrant Crimes; and therefore, could never exalt the Heart of Man, be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>yond this weak Principle of Elevation.—But as the <hi>Power</hi> of a <hi>Religion</hi> depends, not only on its <hi>excellent Genius,</hi> but on its being <hi>effectually impressed</hi> on the Mind; so, no Consequence can be justly drawn, from the mere <hi>un-apply'd</hi> Excellence of its Nature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Self-Consistence,</hi> and perfect <hi>Unity</hi> of Parts which distinguished the Repub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lic of SPARTA, cannot be expected nor
<pb n="82" facs="83"/>
found in that of BRITAIN. For the first was the entire Work of a single Legisla<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tor, struck out at one Heat; all its In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stitutions conspiring to one End, and centering (like the Radii of a Circle) in one single Point: To This, the outward Form of Government, the internal State of Education, of Religion, Manners and Principles, were uniformly subordinate. But at the Time of the <hi>Revolution,</hi> which was the first Aera of BRITAIN'S Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom, many prior Institutions and Estab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lishments, both in Religion and Policy, Manners and Principles, had taken Place: These had been formed on the fortuitous Events of Time; and had resulted from a Variety of contending Parties; of <hi>Power,</hi> fluctuating at different Periods, between the <hi>Kings,</hi> the <hi>Nobles,</hi> the <hi>Priesthood,</hi> and the <hi>People.</hi> All these it was impossible for human Art to remove and new-model, without shaking the State to its Founda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions: Hence, though the Form of the <hi>Bri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tish</hi> Constitution, civil and religious, be of
<pb n="83" facs="84"/>
unrivaled Excellence; yet in its very Birth it came attended with unalterable Weak<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness.—It wanted that general Self-Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sistence, that entire Unity of Parts, as well as of established Habits, Manners and Principles, suited to the Genius of the State, which was the very Spirit and Sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>port of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Commonwealth. In this Circumstance, it appears likewise in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ferior to the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth; yet, perhaps, superior to that of <hi>Athens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>British</hi> System of Polity and Religion, perfect in its leading Parts, but imperfectly united and supported, is not upheld in its native Power (like that of SPARTA) by correspondent and effectual Rules of Education. The Fundamental Laws of our Country, the Principles and Duties of Christianity, are indeed occasi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>onally explained and taught, in a certain Manner and Degree: But it is in the Power of every Private Man to educate his Child, not only without a Reverence for These, but in an absolute Contempt
<pb n="84" facs="85"/>
of them. It is much in every Parent's Option, whether he will impress his Chil<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>drens Hearts with such Habits and Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples as accord to the Genius of the State, or with Impunity suffer them to contract such Manners and Opinions as tend to its Dissolution. A Circumstance pregnant with Danger to this free State: For hence, Manners and Principles, its chief Support, are liable to be incurably perverted in the Heart, at that Time of Life, in which alone they can be effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tually impressed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the important Circumstance of <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the Admission of <hi>Change,"</hi>
               </q> or the <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple of <hi>Adoption,"</hi>
               </q> the <hi>British</hi> Consti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tution is contrary to That of SPARTA; and nearly on a Level with Those of ATHENS and ROME.—Foreign Commerce, foreign Travel, new Manners, new Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples, new Modes of Dress, of Amuse<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment, of Luxury, are here adopted with a Degree of Avidity almost unbounded.—Happy would the Writer esteem his
<pb n="85" facs="86"/>
Labours; if this Principle, which <hi>in some Respects</hi> hath tended so much to the <hi>Improvement</hi> of his Country, could in any Degree be checked by his weak Admo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nitions, from <hi>degenerating</hi> into a <hi>Cause</hi> of its <hi>Destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The last Circumstance of Note, here to be remarked, is <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Difference of Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter among the several <hi>Ranks</hi> of the Community in these ancient free States, and That of <hi>Britain."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In Point of <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Ability,</hi> the Difference was great between the <hi>Nobles</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> in these ancient States: In BRITAIN, the <hi>Nobles</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> (in their <hi>legislative</hi> Capacity) are fairly on a <hi>Level.</hi> When ALCIBIADES addressed the legislative Body of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Peo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ple, he addressed <hi>Coblers, Brasiers, Tanners, Tent-Makers.</hi> When the People of ROME retired in Discontent to the sacred Moun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain, they were appeased by the Fable of the <hi>Belly, Head,</hi> and <hi>Hands.</hi> A <hi>Lord</hi> of Parliament would make but a sorry Fi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gure,
<pb n="86" facs="87"/>
who should come armed with <hi>such</hi> an <hi>Apologue,</hi> for the <hi>Conviction</hi> of a <hi>British</hi> House of <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again: In each of these ancient Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>publics, the collective Body of the <hi>Peo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ple</hi> were much of one uniform Character; being Inhabitants of the same City, and nearly on a Level with Respect to Em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ployment and Property. In ATHENS, they were all <hi>Artisans</hi> or <hi>Tradesmen:</hi> In SPARTA and ROME, they were all <hi>Soldiers.</hi> A low Degree of Knowledge was their ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>neral Lot: For much Knowledge can only be acquired by much Leisure; which their Occupations did not allow. The People of SPARTA were intentionally virtuous: Those of ATHENS were corrupt: Those of ROME were of a mixed Character. As these free States voted not by Representatives, the Presence of the People was necessary, in all Decisions of a public Nature: Hence, such a People from their Ignorance, Wants, collective Presence, and Pride of Power, must ever and suddenly be
<pb n="87" facs="88"/>
swayed by the Eloquence of public De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>magogues.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>collective</hi> Body of the People of BRITAIN are of a Nature and Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter less uniform, and essentially diffe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rent. They may properly be divided into two Classes; <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;"</hi>
               </q> and <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the <hi>Populace</hi> of its <hi>Cities."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Populace</hi> of its <hi>Cities</hi> resemble Those of ATHENS in most Things; except only, that they are not possessed of the <hi>legisla<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive Power.</hi> For the <hi>People</hi> of ATHENS were <q rend="inline margQuotes">"a Body of <hi>Labourers</hi> and <hi>Mechanics,</hi> who earned their Bread with the Sweat of their Brows; too generally ignorant and ill-educated; too generally prosligate in Manners, and void of Principle."</q>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>People</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in their <hi>collective</hi> Body, are upon the Whole, of a quite different Character. For under this Title are properly comprehended <q rend="inline margQuotes">"all Those who send Representatives for the Counties to Parliament."</q> This Catalogue
<pb n="88" facs="89"/>
will include the landed <hi>Gentry,</hi> the bene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficed Country <hi>Clergy,</hi> many of the more considerable <hi>Merchants</hi> and Men in <hi>Trade,</hi> the substantial and industrious <hi>Freeholders</hi> or <hi>Yeomen:</hi> A collective Body of Men, with all their incidental Failings, as <hi>different</hi> in Character from the <hi>Populace</hi> of any great <hi>City,</hi> as the <hi>Air</hi> of RICHMOND HILL from that of BILLINGSGATE or WAPPING.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XI. Of the general State of Manners and Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples, about the Time of the Revolution.</head>
            <p>AT this famed Period, it is evident, that the Manners and Principles of the Nation did, upon the Whole, tend to the Establishment of <hi>Liberty;</hi> otherwise, Liberty had not been established. This Revolution was perhaps the noblest public <hi>Reform</hi> that ever was made in any State: And such a Reform, nothing but the <hi>Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>valence</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="90"/>
of <hi>upright Manners</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> could have <hi>effected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>religious</hi> Principle of <hi>Protestant Christianity</hi> seems to have taken the Lead, even of the Love of civil Freedom. The Dread of <hi>Popery</hi> was, at least, equal to That of <hi>arbitrary Power:</hi> The national <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> (on the whole) co<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>incided with, and confirmed the <hi>Christian</hi> Principle: These three united Powers raised Liberty to the brightest Throne she ever sat on: A Throne which nothing but their <hi>Contraries</hi> can <hi>shake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding the unrivaled Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cellence of this civil and religious Estab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lishment, there could be little Hope of its immediate and perfect Efficacy. De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>claimers may express their Wonder, that a System so perfect should not at once attain its End: But they who take a nearer View of the Manners and Principles of those Times, will rather say, that the Tumults and Dissentions which instantly arose, were in their own Nature <hi>inevitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="91"/>
The Manners of the Times, tho' in the Main favourable to Liberty, were mixed with a gross Alloy of <hi>private Licentious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness:</hi> And hence, factious Measures of Course arose, from the Prospect of Power or Gain. <note place="bottom" n="*">See <hi>Estimate,</hi> V. i. Part 2.</note> The preceding Age had caught a strong Tincture of <hi>Vice,</hi> from the pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>valent Example of a debauched Court. The <hi>Education</hi> of Children was still left in an <hi>imperfect</hi> State: This great Revo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lution having confined itself to the Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>form of <hi>public</hi> Institutions; without as<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cending to the first great Fountain of political Security, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the private and effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tual Formation of the <hi>infant</hi> Mind."</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>religious</hi> Principle, though chiefly consonant with the new Constitution, and indeed its leading Support, was in <hi>Part</hi> at <hi>Variance</hi> with it.—A numerous Body of <hi>Papists</hi> held a whole System of Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples diametrically opposite to its most essential Dictates.—Another Body of Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>testant
<pb n="91" facs="92"/>
               <hi>Jacobites</hi> were at War with the Principles of the State: For they held an hereditary and unalienable Right of Kings, founded on certain <hi>mistaken</hi> Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sages of the sacred Scriptures.—A third Body of Men, though they allowed the Necessity and Justice of the Revolution, on the Principle of an <hi>Abdication,</hi> yet still retained an Opinion at Variance with the State: They asserted an <hi>independent Hierarchy,</hi> vindicated a religious <hi>Intole<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rance,</hi> and on some misconstrued Passages of Scripture, affirmed the Duty of a <hi>pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sive Obedience</hi> without Limitation.—A fourth Body was That of some bigoted <hi>Dissenters,</hi> who not content with a reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gious Toleration which had been justly granted them, aimed, on a mistaken Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple of Religion, to erect their own Sys<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tem upon the Ruins of the established Church.—All these Parties held <hi>religious Principles</hi> at <hi>Variance</hi> with the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Freedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="93"/>
The Principle of <hi>Honour,</hi> tho' in many, and great Instances, co-operating with that of Religion; yet when not founded on it, was often at <hi>Variance</hi> with it. This Principle, as it hath appeared in modern Times, was in its Origin chiefly <hi>Military.</hi> Hence it hath generally taken Cognizance of Actions, not as they are <hi>just</hi> or <hi>unjust,</hi> but merely as they are <hi>splen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>did</hi> or <hi>mean, brave</hi> or <hi>cowardly:</hi> Thus, it overlooks all Laws, both human and di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vine: Hence unbounded Contempt of Ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies, furious Party-Rage, unlimited Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sentment and Revenge, <hi>were</hi> and still <hi>are</hi> its favourite Dictates. Thus it hath come to pass, that Honour often forbids what Religion approves; and approves what Religion forbids. This uncontrouled and dangerous Principle mixed itself with the licentious Manners of the Times: Hence, Attachments, Resentments, and Party-Rage, arose and were persisted in, essentially con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tradictory to the Principles of Freedom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="94"/>
Consonant with what hath been above delivered, the Principle of <hi>Conscience</hi> did not <hi>correct,</hi> but <hi>followed</hi> one or other of these various Principles, according to their Predominance and Power. And <hi>These</hi> being incurably discordant among them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves, the national Ideas of Right and Wrong, Just and Unjust, which were formed on <hi>These,</hi> could not but prove themselves of the like <hi>motley</hi> and <hi>disagree<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing</hi> Complexion.</p>
            <p>Here, then, we behold the natural and unavoidable Source of all the Dissentions that disgraced the Reigns of King WIL<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>LIAM and Queen ANNE. And while some affect to wonder, how so generous a System of Religion and Polity, so no<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble a Constitution in Church and State, could fail to produce private Virtue and public Happiness; we now obtain an additional Proof of the irresistable Power of <hi>pre-established Manners</hi> and <hi>Principles,</hi> when at <hi>Variance</hi> with the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom:</hi> We may see, even to Demonstration,
<pb n="94" facs="95"/>
that the <hi>Animosities</hi> of <hi>Those Times</hi> were <hi>not incidental,</hi> but <hi>inevitable.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XII. Of the Changes in Manners and Principles, through the succeeding Times.</head>
            <p>THE Accession of GEORGE the First seemed the Aera of perfect Freedom. And if an excellent King, at the Head of an unrivaled Constitution, could have secured Liberty; it had now been fixed on immoveable Foundations.</p>
            <p>The Alloy of <hi>licentious Manners</hi> and <hi>contradictory Principles</hi> which had tarnished the preceding Reign, still maintained their Influence: But the declared and zealous Advocates for Liberty now assumed the Reins of Power, and began more effectu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ally to combat those <hi>false Principles</hi> which were at <hi>Enmity</hi> with the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="96"/>
Would to God, these intentional Friends of public Liberty had been as much the Friends of private Virtue and Religion! They would not, then, have undermined the Foundations, while they were building the Superstructure of civil Freedom.</p>
            <p>The Seeds of Irreligion had for some Time been privately fermenting: But they did not break forth into open Growth till about this Period.—'Tis remarkable, that BURNET, <note place="bottom" n="*">Conclusion of his History.</note> enumerating the Dangers by which the State was threatened in the Year 1708, makes no Mention of <hi>Irre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ligion,</hi> as an Evil worth being obviated. But soon after, this Pestilence came on, with a terrible Swiftness and Malignity.</p>
            <p>The slavish Principle of absolute <hi>Non-Resistance,</hi> and an <hi>independent Hierarchy,</hi> were still prevalent in Part, especially among the <hi>Clergy.</hi> To combat <hi>these,</hi> and expose them to the public Contempt, cer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain Writers were encouraged by Those
<pb n="96" facs="97"/>
in Power. A vigorous and effectual At<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tack was made on the Advocates for Des<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>potism. But in their Zeal against Ty<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ranny, these Writers supplanted Freedom.</p>
            <p>They assailed <hi>Superstition</hi> with such Wea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pons as destroyed <hi>Religion:</hi> They opposed <hi>Intolerance</hi> by Arguments and Ridicule which tended to sweep away all public <hi>Establishments:</hi> While they only aimed (perhaps) to contend for <hi>Freedom</hi> of <hi>Thought,</hi> they unwarily sapped the Foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dation of all salutary <hi>Principles.</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="*">See the Div. Leg. of Moses. Dedication Vol. ii. p. 6, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>CATO's <hi>Letters,</hi> and the <hi>Independent Whig,</hi> among many other Tracts of less Note, seem palpable Instances of this Truth: The one was written in Defence of <hi>civil,</hi> the other, of <hi>religious</hi> Liberty. Yet both tended, in their general Tour, to relax those Principles by which alone Freedom, either civil or religious, can be sustained: By their intemperate Insults on religious Institutions; by their public and
<pb n="97" facs="98"/>
avowed Contempt of all Opinions, Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples, (or, if you please) Prejudices, in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stilled into the infant Mind, as the neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary Regulators of human Conduct: By exalting unaided human Reason, far be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>yond the Rank she holds in Nature: By debasing all those Assistances which the Wisdom of Ages had prescribed and con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>secrated, as the necessary Means of correct<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing her vague and wandering Dictates.</p>
            <p>While These Authors made this ill<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>judged, and perhaps undesigned Attack, on the Foundations of civil Liberty; others made a still bolder and more fatal Inroad; and opened a wider Door for <hi>Licentious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness,</hi> by an Attack on <hi>Christianity</hi> itself.</p>
            <p>In this List of Enemies to their Coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try, it must be a Mortification to every Friend of Virtue and Liberty, to find the noble Author of the <hi>Characteristics.</hi> His Morals were unblemished, his Love of Virtue and Freedom indisputable: But by confounding two Things, which he saw <hi>accidently united,</hi> though in their Nature
<pb n="98" facs="99"/>
               <hi>essentially distinguished,</hi> he polluted his <hi>Ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guments</hi> against <hi>Intolerance,</hi> with the grossest <hi>Buffoonries</hi> on <hi>Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Doubt, but that the cur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rent Reasonings of the Times had brought him to a Habit of Belief, that all This was harmless Pastime. To this Purpose he seems to speak himself. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"'Tis certain, that in Matters of Learning and Philo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sophy, the Practice of <hi>pulling down</hi> is <hi>pleasanter,</hi> and affords more <hi>Entertain<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment,</hi> than that of <hi>building</hi> and <hi>setting up.—</hi>In the literate warring World, the <hi>springing</hi> of <hi>Mines,</hi> the <hi>blowing up</hi> of Towers, Bastions, and Ramparts of Philosophy, with <hi>Systems, Hypotheses, Opinions,</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> into the Air, is a <hi>Spectacle</hi> of all other the most natu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rally <hi>rejoicing.</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="*">Miscell. iii. Chap. 1.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>These intemperate Sallies of Gaiety may serve as a Comment on the Passage already cited from CATO's <hi>Letters.</hi> They are a clear and concurrent Indication of the
<pb n="99" facs="100"/>
ruling Principle of the Times; when <hi>Opi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nions</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> began to be derided as Things <hi>indifferent.</hi> The noble Writer was naturally led to embrace this grow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Error of the Times, by a too flat<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tering Opinion which he had imbibed concerning unassisted human Nature; as being sufficient of itself to establish the unerring Practice of Virtue, unless before<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hand sophisticated by servile Institutions.</p>
            <p>The noble Writer, indeed, attempts a Vindication of this licentious Conduct, by an Appeal to the Practice of ancient GREECE and ROME. There, he tells us, <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"Philosophy</hi> had a free Course, and was permitted as a <hi>Balance</hi> against <hi>Super<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stition.</hi> And while some Sects, such as the <hi>Pythagorean</hi> and latter <hi>Platonic,</hi> joined in with the Superstition and Enthusiasm of the Times; the EPICU<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>REAN, the <hi>Academic,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> were allowed to use all the Force of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Raillery</hi> against it. <note place="bottom" n="*">Letter on Enthusiasm.</note>"</q>—This hath a plau<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sible
<pb n="100" facs="101"/>
Appearance: Yet I am perswaded, the noble Author would have looked grave, had he been put in Mind of the Remark which FABRICIUS made on the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Sect, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"that he wished <hi>such Principles</hi> to all the <hi>Enemies</hi> of ROME. <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, p. 76.</note>"</q> Or had he recollected, that when the <hi>irreligious</hi> System of EPICURUS prevailed in GREECE and ROME, these <hi>unprinci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pled</hi> and <hi>profligate</hi> States were on the <hi>Eve</hi> of their <hi>Destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after the Author of the <hi>Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racteristics,</hi> another more dissolute Writer appeared on the public Stage. I mean, the Author of <q rend="inline">"The Fable of the Bees."</q> This Gentleman, as hath been observed above, leveled his Artillery on the whole Fabric of <hi>Morals</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> His Sys<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tem was diametrically opposite to that of Lord SHAFTESBURY: The one was founded on the <hi>unaided Excellence,</hi> the other on the <hi>incurable Depravity</hi> of <hi>human Nature.</hi> But now the vagrant Spirit of Irreligion
<pb n="101" facs="102"/>
was Abroad; and the most inconsistent Productions were greedily swallowed, pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vided only they <hi>disgraced</hi> CHRISTIANITY.</p>
            <p>The Avidity with which these Compo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sitions were received, soon emboldened a succeeding Writer, to make a formal At<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tack on the Religion of his Country: <hi>Christianity as old as the Creation</hi> now ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>peared: In which the Gospel was grosly misrepresented, insulted, and disgraced; and in Compliance with the ruling Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lady of the Times, that <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>sickly</hi> Creature, <q rend="inline">"unassisted <hi>Human Reason,"</hi>
               </q> was vainly exalted to the <hi>Throne</hi> of ETER<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>NAL TRUTH!</p>
            <p>Other inferior Workmen in this patriot Amusement of blowing up the Religion of their Country, such as WOOLSTON, and MORGAN, I pass unnoticed.</p>
            <p>In a succeeding Period, and down to the present Time, the Evil hath increased, and been compleated. For now, not only <hi>revealed</hi> but <hi>natural</hi> Religion hath been publicly attacked, in the Writings
<pb n="102" facs="103"/>
of Lord BOLINGBROKE: An Author who stands convicted of designed Profligacy, even on his own Confession. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Some Men there are, <hi>the Pests</hi> of <hi>Society I think them,</hi> who pretend a great Regard to Religion in general, but who take every Opportunity of declaiming pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>licly against that System of Religion, or at least that Church Establishment, which is received in BRITAIN. <note place="bottom" n="*">Dissert. on Parties. Let. xii.</note>"</q>—You See, this patriot Writer proclaims his Ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>horrence even of Those who assault the <hi>Out-Works</hi> of Religion: And then, with Modesty unparallel'd, proceeds to blow up the <hi>Citadel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The last of these patriot Worthies, by which the present Age stands distinguish<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed, is the Author of <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Essays philoso<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phical and moral:"</q> Who, disdaining the vulgar Practice of a particular Attack, <hi>undermines</hi> all the <hi>Foundations</hi> of <hi>Reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gion, revealed</hi> and <hi>natural;</hi> and with a Pen truly <hi>Epicurean,</hi> dissolves at once all
<pb n="103" facs="104"/>
the <hi>Fears</hi> of the <hi>Guilty,</hi> the <hi>Comforts</hi> of the <hi>Afflicted,</hi> and the <hi>Hopes</hi> of the <hi>Virtuous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such, then, hath been the Progress of this public Evil; which hath proceeded almost without <hi>Cognizance</hi> from the Magi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>strate: Instead of <hi>That,</hi> it is well known, that some of these public Enemies of their Country and Mankind were formerly pen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sioned, and others privately encouraged by Those in Power. How This came to pass, and aggravated the growing Evil, it is now necessary to point out.</p>
            <p>We have seen above, that a Foundation was laid for this, in an ill-conducted Op<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>position to the Enemies of Freedom. They who were employed to sweep away <hi>false Principles,</hi> imprudently struck at <hi>all Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beyond This, a famous Minister as<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sumed, and long held the Reins of Power. There seems not the least Foundation for the Charge laid against him by his Ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"That his Design was to inslave his Country."</q> Neither had he any
<pb n="104" facs="105"/>
natural Inclination to corrupt Practices: Yet he rather chose to rule by These, than to resign his Power. Nay, perhaps he thought this corrupt System the only one, which, under the Circumstances of Those Times, could support that illu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>strious Family, which was brought in, as the happy Support of Liberty. Far<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther, perhaps, he judged This the only possible Expedient for prolonging a <hi>Peace,</hi> which He thought <hi>necessary,</hi> till Time should wear out the false Principles, on which the expelled Family still held their Influence in the Minds of the People.—From <hi>some</hi> or <hi>all</hi> of these Motives, He not only <hi>gave Way</hi> to Corruption, but <hi>encouraged</hi> it. To this End, <hi>Religion</hi> was <hi>discountenanced:</hi> And <hi>Christian Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciple,</hi> which would have been the firmest <hi>Friend</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> was <hi>discarded,</hi> as the <hi>Enemy</hi> of <hi>Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean Time, <hi>Trade, Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> increased: These, in their <hi>Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>treme,</hi> having an unalterable Tendency
<pb n="105" facs="106"/>
to a Dissolution of Manners and Princi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ples, went Hand in Hand with the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gress of Corruption; which, in its most improved State, this mistaken Minister left, as a lasting Legacy to his Country. <note place="bottom" n="*">See an Estimate, &amp;c. Vol. ii. p. 204, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Effects of this established System of Corruption did not immediately appear: But about the Year fifty-seven, they came to their <hi>Crisis;</hi> advancing with the Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pearances even of <hi>public Ruin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That powerful Correctress, NECESSITY, gave a <hi>temporary Union</hi> to all Parties, and a <hi>temporary Restoration</hi> to the <hi>State.</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="†">See ib. Vol. i. p. the last.</note> But from the Deduction of Causes here given, it was natural to expect, that as soon as <hi>Danger</hi> ceased, <hi>Faction</hi> would arise.</p>
            <p>It follows also, that it must arise on Foundations widely different from Those in the Reigns of WILLIAM and ANNE. For the Dissentions of these <hi>past</hi> Times were chiefly founded in <hi>false Principles:</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="107"/>
Those of the <hi>present</hi> Age, on a <hi>Want of Principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the false Principles which disgra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ced the Protestants of the last Age, are vanished. The mistaken Interpretations of Scripture, on which the <hi>Jacobite,</hi> the <hi>Tory,</hi> the <hi>bigoted Dissenter,</hi> founded their various Pretensions and Attempts, are <hi>now</hi> held in general Derision: A Preacher, of whatever religious Congregation, who should <hi>now</hi> advance these obsolete State-Heterodoxies, would be the Contempt of his wiser Audience.</p>
            <p>Nay, what is more, these false Princi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ples tending to Despotism, are generally banished, even from the Breasts of the Clergy; except only a very few of the most aged. For the Bishops being ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointed by the Patrons of Liberty, have been such, as held Principles consistent with the Freedom of the State: And much Caution having been required of them, and used by them, in the Appoint<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments of their Clergy, the general Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plexion
<pb n="107" facs="108"/>
of this Body hath changed from That of being the <hi>Enemies,</hi> to That of being the <hi>Friends</hi> of Freedom.</p>
            <p>Much it were to be wished, that along with the <hi>Tares,</hi> the <hi>Wheat</hi> had not also perished. But the general System of <hi>Manners</hi> being <hi>relaxed</hi> though <hi>refined;</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="*">See the Estimate, Part i.</note> and <hi>Education</hi> still left more and more <hi>imper<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fect;</hi> the Principle of <hi>Religion</hi> being unhap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pily <hi>destroyed</hi> among certain Ranks, and <hi>weakened</hi> among <hi>others;</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib.</note>—That of <hi>Ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nour</hi> being thus left to its own <hi>false</hi> and <hi>fantastic</hi> Dictates; <note place="bottom" n="‡">Ib.</note>—and <hi>Conscience</hi> natu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rally following the <hi>Whims</hi> of its <hi>untutored</hi> Parent;<hi>—Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> found<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed on a <hi>Want</hi> of <hi>Principle,</hi> cannot but arise, and stand among the <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"leading Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racters</hi> of the <hi>present Times."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="section">
            <pb n="108" facs="109"/>
            <head>SECT. XIII. Among what Ranks, Licentiousness and Fac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion may most probably be expected.</head>
            <p>THOUGH this Want of Principle must naturally infect every Rank of Men, in a certain Degree; yet some Ranks stand more exposed to it than others.</p>
            <p>And, that we may give as little Offence as possible, while we speak the Truth; let it be observed, that all Orders of Men being born with an equal Tendency to Virtue or Vice; their adopting the One, or falling into the Other, depends chiefly on the Temptations to which their <hi>Rank</hi> exposes them.</p>
            <p>Let us consider the Temptations to Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>centiousness and Faction, to which the <hi>leading Ranks</hi> stand exposed.</p>
            <p>Wealth and Power give Opportunities of Indulgence; Indulgence naturally in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>flames Appetite.—Flattery awakens con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tempt; and Contempt weakens the Fear
<pb n="109" facs="110"/>
of Offence or Shame.—Laws which bind little Men, are often too weak for Great ones.—Leisure, when not dignify'd by suitable Accomplishments, ends in Idleness; and Idleness is the Parent and the Nurse of licentious Folly. To such Tempta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions do the <hi>Great</hi> stand exposed, in the important Article of <hi>Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Respect to the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gion,</hi> their present Situation is no less unfa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vourable. Dissolute Opinions flatter their disordered Passions: Nor will they ever want Sycophants, to present this alluring Bait to their Desires.—The Maxims of Irreligion are now so generally established among Those with whom the young Men of Fashion converse, that they must be peculiarly fortunate, if they es<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cape the <hi>Infection.</hi> Wherever This Taint is given, the Principles of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> become vague and ineffectual, if considered as the Supports of Liberty. Certain <hi>Delicacies</hi> of <hi>personal</hi> Conduct they may produce; but can never rise to an
<pb n="110" facs="111"/>
unbiassed and steady Prosecution of the <hi>public Welfare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Circumstance unfavourable to the <hi>public</hi> Virtue of the higher Ranks presents itself. Their Situation leads them to <hi>expect,</hi> and to <hi>claim,</hi> the great and <hi>lucrative Offices</hi> of the State. I need not <hi>here</hi> point out, how strongly This tends to betray them into the Extremes of selfish Views, Ambition, Party-Rage, Licentiousness, and Faction. <note place="bottom" n="*">See the Estimate, &amp;c. Vol. i. Part 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Add to all these Considerations, their frequent and long-continued Meetings in the Capital: A Circumstance which, from the powerful Effects of <hi>free Communication,</hi> cannot but inflame all these Causes of political Dissention.</p>
            <p>If we next examine the State of the <hi>Populace</hi> of the great Cities, we shall find that Their Situation naturally ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>poses them to such Temptations as lead to factious Conduct, when not early for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tify'd by a virtuous Education. They
<pb n="111" facs="112"/>
are often urged by <hi>Want;</hi> of which, <hi>Discontent</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> are the inevitable Effects. They are let loose to every Im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pulse of Appetite, by frequent Opportu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nity and Secrecy of Action: They are tempted by wicked Examples; inflamed by evil Communication and intoxicating Liquors: And though the industrious Mechanic may sometimes escape the In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fection; yet the Life of the <hi>uninstructed Poor</hi> in great Cities, is too commonly a horrid Compound of Riot and Distress, Rapacity and Thieving, Prostitution and Robbery, Wickedness and Despair.</p>
            <p>Now if this Body of Men be indeed, what Candour itself cannot deny, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"too generally ignorant and ill-educated; too generally profligate in Manners, and void of Principle;"</q> it follows, that like <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the <hi>Athenian Populace</hi> of old, they must be liable to the <hi>Seduction</hi> of artful Men;</q> the ready <hi>Tools</hi> of every unprincipled <hi>Leader,</hi> who may choose to misguide them, to the Ends of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="112" facs="113"/>But 
<q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"The</hi> PEOPLE <hi>of</hi> GREAT BRI<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>TAIN, as above distinguished, <note place="bottom" n="*">See p. 87, 88.</note> are of a Character essentially different from both These. The landed <hi>Gentry,</hi> the Country <hi>Clergy,</hi> the more considerable <hi>Merchants</hi> and Men in Trade, the sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stantial and industrious <hi>Freeholders</hi> and <hi>Yeomen,"</hi>
               </q> possess a <hi>middle</hi> State of Life, which guards them from many of those Temptations that surround the <hi>higher</hi> and the <hi>lower</hi> Ranks. Their <hi>imaginary</hi> Wants are <hi>fewer</hi> than those of the <hi>Great:</hi> Their <hi>real</hi> Wants are <hi>fewer</hi> than those of the <hi>Poor:</hi> Hence Their Appetites are less in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>flamed to Evil.—Their Education gene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rally seconds this happy Situation, in a certain Degree: Though imperfect, it is commonly more consistent with the main Outlines of public Law, than that of the superior or inferior Ranks.—Their Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples of Religion confirm this Educa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion: They stand not generally exposed to the Infection of dissolute Opinions.
<pb n="113" facs="114"/>
Their Sentiments of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Consci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ence</hi> are most commonly built on the <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>Christianity.—</hi>Their <hi>Numbers</hi> and their <hi>Station</hi> conspire to <hi>exclude</hi> them from a <hi>general Claim</hi> to the lucrative Of<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fices of the State. Their <hi>collective Know<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ledge</hi> is of sufficient Reach to prevent their <hi>general Seduction</hi> to the Purposes of <hi>Licentiousness:</hi> Their <hi>Dispersion,</hi> and rural Life, prevent those continued and unre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>strained Communications, which are alike fatal to private and public Virtue.</p>
            <p>Let not the Writer be misunderstood. There are Examples of Integrity and Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>honour, of Virtue and Vice, among all De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>grees of Men. He only points out the Circumstances which naturally tend, upon the Whole, to form the several Ranks into these distinct Characters.</p>
            <p>From this View of the several Ranks, it follows, that although <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The <hi>People</hi> of this Kingdom"</q> must inevitably partake of the various Manners and Principles of the <hi>Great</hi> and the <hi>Populace,</hi> with which
<pb n="114" facs="115"/>
they at Times communicate; though they be subject to the common Failings of Men, and to the <hi>incidental</hi> Inroads of Licentiousness from <hi>higher</hi> and <hi>lower</hi> Life;—yet upon the Whole, and consi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dered as one <hi>collective Body,</hi> they stand comparatively clear of many Temptations to Vice; and therefore must naturally be least exposed to the Influence of <hi>Licen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Consequence, arising from their <hi>Dispersion,</hi> must not pass unnoticed. It not only prevents the general Depravation of their Manners and Principles, but like<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wise prevents their <hi>uniting</hi> in large <hi>Bodies,</hi> upon all <hi>slight</hi> Occasions. Hence, though they are apt to <hi>doubt,</hi> nay to be <hi>alarmed,</hi> on the <hi>factious Clamours</hi> of the <hi>Capital;</hi> yet they are not rowzed into <hi>Action,</hi> but on <hi>singular</hi> and <hi>important</hi> Emergencies.</p>
            <p>To conclude: They are a <hi>great,</hi> but <hi>quiescent</hi> Power; on whose <hi>collective Know<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ledge</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi> the Freedom and Fate of this Nation must <hi>finally</hi> depend. In
<pb n="115" facs="116"/>
the last Age, through the Influence of <hi>false Principles,</hi> pre-established or infused, they had well-nigh shaken the Founda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions of Liberty: <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, p. 91.</note> In the present, <hi>these</hi> mistaken Principles being <hi>no more,</hi> They are now <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the firmest <hi>Bulwark</hi> of BRI<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>TAIN's <hi>Freedom."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XIV. Of the most effectual Means of detecting Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>centiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>WHERE Faction is founded on false <hi>Principles,</hi> it is easily <hi>detected,</hi> be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cause it is generally <hi>avowed.</hi> It im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plies no moral <hi>Depravity,</hi> but only an <hi>Error</hi> of the Mind: And he who holds this <hi>Error,</hi> is not naturally <hi>ashamed</hi> of it, because he holds it as a <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where Faction is founded on Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>centiousness and Want of Principle, it
<pb n="116" facs="117"/>
cannot be so easily detected: For as it implies a moral Depravity, it will natu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rally attempt to <hi>veil</hi> itself; and to this End, will assume the <hi>Garb</hi> and <hi>Appear<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ance</hi> of <hi>Freedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The favourite Subject of its Clamours will be the <hi>Misconduct</hi> of Those who <hi>go<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vern.</hi> And in a Country where Liberty is justly ranked among the greatest na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tional Blessings, the most plausible Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tence of Faction will be, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"to load the executive Power with the Charge of Despotism."</q>
            </p>
            <p>In every free State there will frequently occur certain Subjects and Measures, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"of <hi>doubtful Expediency."</hi>
               </q> These, in the wide Field of political Contention, may justly be stiled <q rend="inline">"the <hi>debateable Grounds."</hi>
               </q> On these doubtful Points, even the Friends of Liberty may sometimes differ: There<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore the Patrons of Faction will naturally lay hold on these, as the most successful and effectual Means of State Distraction: Because Thus they may hope to mingle
<pb n="117" facs="118"/>
with, and to pass for the Friends of Freedom.</p>
            <p>When therefore such doubtful Measures become the Subject of political Conten<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion; it may be difficult to determine, from the mere Circumstance of <hi>Opinion, who</hi> are the Friends of Liberty, and <hi>who</hi> the Abettors of Faction: Because, in these Points, there may be an incidental Dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ference of Opinion, even among the Friends of Liberty themselves.</p>
            <p>A much surer Determination may be formed on the <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of the <hi>dissenting Party:</hi> For the Friend of Liberty, having no selfish Views, will be rational, honest, equitable, in the Prosecu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of his Wishes. He who is actuated by the Spirit of Licentiousness and Faction, will be irrational, dishonest, iniquitous.</p>
            <p>Let us, then, endeavour to particula<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rize these distinctive <hi>Marks</hi> or <hi>Characters:</hi> Thus shall we best be able to determine, <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"who</hi> are the <hi>Friends</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>who</hi> the <hi>Abettors</hi> of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="section">
            <pb n="118" facs="119"/>
            <head>SECT. XV. Of the Characteristic Marks of Liberty.</head>
            <p>THESE which follow, are perhaps some of the clearest <hi>Characteristics</hi> of the Spirit of <hi>Liberty:</hi> By which the Friends of public Freedom, though dissen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tient from any Measure of Government, will be evidently distinguished.<hi>—Each</hi> of these Marks may seem <hi>decisive,</hi> even when <hi>separately</hi> viewed: But to do Justice to this Argument, it will be necessary to consider and <hi>weigh</hi> them in <hi>Union;</hi> be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cause as they in Part <hi>depend</hi> on <hi>each other,</hi> they will <hi>illustrate each other,</hi> and at once <hi>receive</hi> and <hi>give</hi> additional <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Friend of Liberty will endea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vour to preserve that just Balance of divided Power, established by Law, for the Security of Freedom."</q>—Because the <hi>public Welfare</hi> is the leading Object of his Wishes; and can only be effectually
<pb n="119" facs="120"/>
obtained by the Preservation of such a Balance.</p>
            <p>This will be the general Aim and End of the true Friend of Liberty: This <hi>End</hi> will be prosecuted by <hi>suitable Means;</hi> and its <hi>Reality</hi> will be <hi>confirmed</hi> and <hi>illustrated</hi> by these which follow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"He will be attached to Measures, without respecting Men."</q>—Because the Passions and Interests of Individuals ought to yield to the public Weal.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"He will be generally self-consistent, both in Speech and Action."</q>—Because, the public Welfare being the uniform Object of his Pursuits, This can only be steadily and effectually promoted, on clear and uniform Principles.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"He will not attempt to inflame an ignorant Populace against their legal Governors."</q>—Because an ignorant Po<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pulace are, in all Cases, unqualify'd to decide on the Measures of Government.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"His Debates, either in the Senate, or from the Press, will be void of un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>distinguishing
<pb n="120" facs="121"/>
and injurious Imputati<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ons on any whole Bodies of Men, who may differ from him in Opinion."</q> Because, Truth and the public Welfare being his desired End, he will clearly seé, that <hi>others</hi> have the same Right of <hi>ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>proving,</hi> as <hi>Himself</hi> hath of <hi>disapproving,</hi> the Measures of Government.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"He will not industriously and in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>discriminately defame the private Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racters of the Individuals who differ from him in Opinion."</q>—Because Calumny thrown on Individuals is a still more ag<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gravated Crime, than That which is pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>miscuously aimed at Bodies of Men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XVI. Of the first characteristic Mark of Licentious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness and Faction.</head>
            <p>THOUGH we have seen, that the Patrons of Faction will attempt to mix and confound themselves with the
<pb n="121" facs="122"/>
Friends of Liberty; yet, in Spite of their Pretences, they will be detected by the following characteristic Marks, which will stand in <hi>clear Opposition</hi> to Those of <hi>Freedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These, like the former, may seem suf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficiently decisive, even when <hi>separately</hi> viewed: But to do Justice to this Argu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment, it will in the same Manner be ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessary to <hi>consider</hi> and <hi>weigh</hi> them in <hi>Union:</hi> Because, as they in Part <hi>depend</hi> on <hi>each other,</hi> they will <hi>illustrate each other,</hi> and at once <hi>receive</hi> and <hi>give</hi> ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ditional <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Leaders of Faction (being na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>turally of the higher Ranks <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, Sect. xiii.</note>) would aim to establish an <hi>aristocratic Power;</hi> and <hi>inslave</hi> both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> to their own Avarice and Ambition."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, if any Set of Men had in <hi>for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mer</hi> Times been in Power; and while in Power, had oppressed embarrassed Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jesty;
<pb n="122" facs="123"/>
had threatened the Prince with a general Resignation; had thus intimidated him to their own Purposes; had by these Means usurped the <hi>legal Prerogatives</hi> of the <hi>Crown;</hi> and apply'd them rather to the Support of their own <hi>Influence,</hi> than to the <hi>public Welfare:—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>legal Privileges</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> had fared no better in their Hands:—If These, too, had been swallowed up, in the great Gulph of aristocratic Power:—If the Members of the lower House, while they seemed to be the free Representatives of the People, had been in Truth, a great Part of them, no more than the <hi>commissioned Deputies</hi> of their <hi>respective Chiefs,</hi> whose Sentiments they declared, and whose In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terests they pursued:—</p>
            <p>If such a Set of Men, as soon as they had lost their Influence, should now rail at the Privileges of the Crown, as the En<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gines of Despotism, though they had been formerly allowed by the Wisdom of the State, as the occasional Securities of Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom:—</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="123" facs="124"/>
If they should now absurdly magnify and exalt the Privileges of the lower House, beyond the Limits prescribed by a free Constitution:—If their Pretence should be the Vindication of the People's Rights; while their real Motive was <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the <hi>Restoration</hi> of their own <hi>exorbitant Power,</hi> founded on an <hi>expected Majority</hi> of their own <hi>Dependents:"</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If this Conduct was pursued by any Set of Men, they would stand convicted of a <hi>clear Mark</hi> of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such</hi> would be their main <hi>End</hi> or <hi>Pur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose:</hi> And this <hi>End</hi> would be pursued by <hi>suitable Means:</hi> These Means, consi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dered in <hi>Union,</hi> would still farther con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>firm and illustrate the End they aimed at: And these Means would be such as follow.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="section">
            <pb n="124" facs="125"/>
            <head>SECT. XVII. A second Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">"THE Patrons of Faction would be attached to Men, to the Neglect of Measures."</q>
            </p>
            <p>If the same Men, when formerly in Power, should have obstinately adhered to each other in every public Debate and Opinion; should have execrated every Man, as the Enemy of his Country, who dissented even in the slightest Article of political Belief:—</p>
            <p>If on any sudden Change in the Foun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain of Power, a more generous System of Government should have taken Place:—If the <hi>Sovereign</hi> had aimed to unite all <hi>honest Men</hi> of <hi>all Parties,</hi> and had invited them to co-operate for the Welfare of their Country:—</p>
            <p>If these Men, determined still to en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gross all public Power, should threaten the Sovereign (as they had effectually
<pb n="125" facs="126"/>
threatened his royal Predecessor) with a general Resignation:—</p>
            <p>If their Leaders should be taken at their Word, and unexpectedly stripped of all Power and Influence:—</p>
            <p>If on This, the Clamours of their at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tendant Populace should arise; <note place="bottom" n="*">See Sect. xix.]</note> and for the Sake of the public Tranquillity, Over<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tures should be made by the Prince to the Discontented:—If the <hi>same Principle</hi> should still predominate, and <hi>Demands</hi> in Favour of <hi>Men</hi> should be the <hi>leading Ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ject</hi> of <hi>Accommodation:—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If these Demands should be not only irrational in their Kind, but exorbitant and oppressive in their Degree; requiring a <hi>general Restoration</hi> of All the Discon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tented, and a <hi>general Dismission</hi> of all who were in Power, tho' of known Fide<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lity to their King and Country:—</p>
            <p>If such should be the Conduct of any Set of Men, they would stand evidently convicted of Licentiousness and Faction.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="section">
            <pb n="126" facs="127"/>
            <head>SECT. XVIII. A third Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">"THE Patrons of Faction would be <hi>self-contradictory</hi> and <hi>inconsistent,</hi> not only on <hi>different,</hi> but on <hi>parallel</hi> Oc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>casions."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, if the <hi>Exercise</hi> of a <hi>Privilege</hi> should be quietly <hi>allowed</hi> to <hi>one</hi> Offi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cer of State, and by the <hi>same Persons</hi> should be <hi>clamoured against</hi> in his <hi>Suc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessor:</hi> The Persons thus <hi>acquiescing</hi> and <hi>clamouring</hi> by <hi>Turns,</hi> would stand con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>victed of a <hi>self-contradictory</hi> and <hi>inconsistent</hi> Conduct: And without deciding on the Propriety or Impropriety of the Privilege in Question, would carry upon them a clear Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</p>
            <p>Again, if a certain Mode of political <hi>Influence</hi> on <hi>Dependents</hi> was generally ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ercised among all the Ranks of a free Country:—If the same Persons already
<pb n="127" facs="128"/>
characterized, should <hi>now condemn</hi> This as a <hi>despotic</hi> Measure in the <hi>Servants</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> which They themselves <hi>for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>merly</hi> exercised when in <hi>Power,</hi> and still <hi>continue</hi> to exercise towards their <hi>private Dependents:—</hi>These Gentlemen would be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tray a very notable Inconsistence in their Conduct: And therefore, without any De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cision on the <hi>Rectitude</hi> of such a general <hi>Practice,</hi> would stand convicted of an undeniable Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XIX. A fourth Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">"THE Patrons of Faction would en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>deavour to delude and inflame an ignorant and licentious Populace against their legal Governors."</q>
            </p>
            <p>A blind and unprincipled Populace have ever been the most effectual Engines of Sedition: And above all, Those of the
<pb n="128" facs="129"/>
               <hi>Capital,</hi> being near to the grand Scene of political Contention, must ever be a ready and dangerous Engine in the Hands of Licentiousness and Faction.</p>
            <p>But in a Nation like this, to make the <hi>Populace</hi> of the <hi>Capital</hi> a more successful Instrument of Sedition, a Degree of Art would be necessary. For it appears above, that the <hi>People</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Populace</hi> of its <hi>Cities,</hi> are of a Character essentially <hi>opposite</hi> to each other: That the <hi>one</hi> is collectively <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>upright;</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> collectively <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>immo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ral.</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, Sect. xiii.</note>—The first Step, therefore, that <hi>Fac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion</hi> would take, as the surest Method for Success, would be to <hi>confound</hi> the <hi>one</hi> with the <hi>other;</hi> and dignify <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the <hi>Clamour</hi> of the <hi>Populace,"</hi>
               </q>by stiling it <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"the</hi> VOICE <hi>of the</hi> PEOPLE."</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Fury of such a Populace, thus awakened by Vanity, Vice, and Igno<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rance, would arise in a Variety of Shapes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="129" facs="130"/>
If an Order of the Senate should be given for the Burning of a <hi>Paper</hi> legally declared seditious; such a <hi>Populace</hi> would be incited to rescue it from the Fire: And they who had thus incited them would boast, that it was rescued by the Hands of <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>"the</hi> PEOPLE."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Every talking Demagogue, who should oppose the Measures of Government, would be artfully and indiscriminately obtruded on such an ignorant <hi>Populace,</hi> as a <hi>Pa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>triot</hi> or a <hi>Heroe.</hi> And They who had thus obtruded him would boast, that he was the <hi>Favourite</hi> of <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>"the</hi> PEOPLE."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Every distinguished Friend to the Mea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sures of Government would be artfully obtruded on such a Populace, as the Enemy of his Country: And They who had thus obtruded him would boast, that he was the <hi>Detestation</hi> of <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>"the</hi> PEOPLE."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Every Act of the Legislature, which contradicted the Passions or partial Inte<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rests of such a <hi>Populace</hi> or their <hi>Leaders,</hi> would be branded by them, as arbitrary
<pb n="130" facs="131"/>
and oppressive: And they would boast, that it was branded by the <hi>Voice</hi> of <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"the</hi> PEOPLE."</q>
            </p>
            <p>If daily or periodical Papers of Intel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ligence were circulated from the Capital through the Nation, and These were open to the Admission of every Thing which private Pique, Passion, or Interest, might suggest; they would of Course become the general Repositories of popular Slan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>der: And as <hi>Malice</hi> is always more eager to <hi>accuse,</hi> than injured <hi>Innocence</hi> to <hi>defend,</hi> these Slanders would often seem to <hi>pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ponderate</hi> in the public Ear: And hence, would be boasted by Those who raised them, as the prevailing <hi>Voice</hi> of <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                  <hi>"the</hi> PEOPLE."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>hatched</hi> by <hi>Licentiousness,</hi> FAC<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>TION would attain to its <hi>enormous Growth:</hi> The <hi>unprincipled</hi> among the <hi>Great</hi> would form the <hi>Head,</hi> the <hi>unprincipled</hi> among the <hi>Populace</hi> would form the <hi>Body,</hi> of this <hi>rapacious Monster.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="section">
            <pb n="131" facs="132"/>
            <head>SECT. XX. A fifth Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">"THE Abettors of Faction would throw injurious and undistinguish<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Imputations on every Body of Men who differed from them in Opinion."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus gained an ignorant and licentious Populace, as the Trumpets of Sedition; the Patrons of Faction would leave no Means untry'd to load their Adversaries with the most envenomed Calumny.</p>
            <p>Thus if any mistaken Principle had formerly been maintained, but was now generally forsaken and derided; a Fac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion could not be detected by any clearer Mark, than by its Attempt to conjure up the Ghost of this <hi>departed</hi> Principle, in order to alarm and terrify not only the <hi>Populace,</hi> but the PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="132" facs="133"/>
If on This Pretence, any Men should attempt to revive Animosities which Time had bury'd;—should attempt to divide and distract the Subjects of an <hi>united</hi> Kingdom, whose <hi>common Welfare</hi> depended on their <hi>Union;—</hi>should revile all Men without Distinction, who were born in a <hi>certain District;</hi> and indiscriminately en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>deavour to exclude them from a Partici<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pation of those public Trusts, Honours, and Emoluments, to which, with the rest of their Fellow-Subjects, they might stand intitled by their <hi>Capacity</hi> or <hi>Virtue:—</hi>Who would not discover, in this <hi>unequal Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct,</hi> a clear and distinctive Mark of Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>centiousness and Faction?</p>
            <p>Again: If ever there had been a Time, when All who presumed to <hi>dissent</hi> in any Degree from those in Power, were in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>discriminately and unjustly branded with the Name of <hi>Jacobite</hi> or <hi>Tory;—</hi>and if These very Men who had bestowed such Appellations should <hi>now</hi> deal them as freely round, on All who <hi>assent</hi> to Those
<pb n="133" facs="134"/>
in Power:—This were surely a clear In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dication, that the Spirit of Faction were abroad.</p>
            <p>But if, in the Course of political Revolu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions, some of these Men's <hi>former Adherents</hi> should <hi>now</hi> be their <hi>Adversaries;</hi> and some <hi>former Adversaries</hi> should <hi>now</hi> be their <hi>Adherents;</hi> another <hi>characteristic</hi> Circum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stance would arise: For Those whom they had once <hi>reviled,</hi> they would now <hi>applaud,</hi> as being the <hi>Friends</hi> of <hi>Liberty;</hi> and Those whom they had formerly <hi>ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plauded,</hi> they would now <hi>revile,</hi> as hav<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing become <hi>Jacobites</hi> or <hi>Tories.—</hi>Such a Conduct, and such <hi>Names</hi> thus <hi>arbitrarily imposed,</hi> however speciously coloured over by the <hi>Pretence</hi> and <hi>Cry</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> might seem to stand, with all impartial Judges, as a clear <hi>Mark</hi> of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Views of such Men would be still more apparent, should they insinuate, that the <hi>Prince</hi> received Those very Men as his Ministers and Favourites, whose Principles
<pb n="134" facs="135"/>
tended to the <hi>Subversion</hi> of his <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Family.</hi> This Insinuation, indeed, would not so much merit <hi>Detestation,</hi> as <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Ridicule.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XXI. A sixth Mark of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">"THE Abettors and Instruments of Faction would promiscuously ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lumniate the private Characters of the principal individuals of the opposing Party."</q>
            </p>
            <p>It was the just Observation of an an<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient Writer, that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the Wicked is an Abomination to the Righteous, and the Righteous an Abomination to the Wick<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed."</q>—Yet the Measures which these two Parties take, in their Treatment of each other, are essentially different.—The <hi>good</hi> Man never maliciously <hi>stabs</hi> the <hi>Reputa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion</hi> of his Neighbour: The <hi>wicked</hi> Man,
<pb n="135" facs="136"/>
on the contrary, delights in this <hi>most practicable,</hi> but <hi>most atrocious</hi> of all <hi>Mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chiefs.—</hi>Invenomed Hints, ambiguous Im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>putations, private Crimes darkly alledged, but void of all Foundation:—These are the deadly Weapons of the abandoned but cunning Defamer.</p>
            <p>Here then is a secure and ample Field for every profligate Minister of Faction: Here <q rend="inline margQuotes">"he tosseth about Arrows, Fire<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>brands, and Death; and cries, am I not in Sport?"</q>
            </p>
            <p>If a Prince, whose Words and Actions might justly be given, as an Example of Integrity to all his Subjects, should be ambiguously accused of such Things as his Honour would abhor:—</p>
            <p>If such a Prince should be indirectly charged with Ignorance, for not distin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guishing in a Point of Law, which even some of the ablest Lawyers in his King<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom had not attended to:—</p>
            <p>If neither the Virtues nor the Condes<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cension of a Queen could protect her
<pb n="136" facs="137"/>
from the Insults of Those whom she had never injured:—</p>
            <p>If any other Branch of a royal Family should be basely traduced, by the grossest and most audacious Calumnies, studiously contrived to inflame an ignorant and un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bridled Populace:—</p>
            <p>If the Servants of the Crown, and Mem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bers of the Legislature, who had legally exerted themselves in Defence of their in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jured Sovereign, should in their private Character be impudently vilify'd, misre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>presented, and abused; and even their un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>offending Families traduced with study'd and unexampled Virulence:—</p>
            <p>If neither Age nor Virtue should be a Security against the Arrows of public Ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lumny:—If a MAN of the most distin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guished Worth in private Life, a known and zealous Friend of public Liberty, one of the Ornaments of his Age and Coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try, should be overwhelmed by a Load of the most unprovoked and malicious Slan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>der; merely because he had dared to as<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sert
<pb n="137" facs="138"/>
his own Right of private Judgment, in Opposition to the Opinion of another:—</p>
            <p>If these Outrages should be publicly <hi>committed</hi> by <hi>some;</hi> and <hi>winked</hi> at or <hi>countenanced,</hi> or <hi>patronized</hi> by <hi>others;—</hi> surely, all honest Men ought to joyn, in declaring their Abhorrence of such atro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cious Acts of Licentiousness and Faction, perpetrated in Defiance of All <hi>Laws,</hi> both <hi>human</hi> and <hi>divine.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XXII. Some Objectious obviated.</head>
            <p>SHOULD it be objected to the Writer, that while he blames the Practice in others▪ He indiscriminately characterizeth whole Bodies of Men who dissent from public Measures; he would reply, that the Accusation is groundless: For he hath ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pressly distinguished Those who <hi>dissent</hi> on <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> from such as
<pb n="138" facs="139"/>
               <hi>dissent</hi> on <hi>Motives</hi> of <hi>Licentiousness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should it be objected, that he hath attacked even <hi>private</hi> Characters, in the Way of indirect Description: This Accusation would be equally ill-founded. For all personal Peculiarities are avoided, save only the single Facts alluded to, as the Proofs of his Allegations: These were essentially necessary for the Support of the Argument; and relate not to <hi>private</hi> Life, but to <hi>public</hi> and <hi>political</hi> Conduct.</p>
            <p>Should it be objected, that he hath indirectly censured Those, whose Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct he had formerly applauded: He replies, that he never was attached to <hi>Men,</hi> but <hi>Measures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should it be objected, that some of these characteristic Marks may seem to involve Men of good Morals in private Life: He would reply, that the Affections of <hi>good</hi> Men in <hi>private</hi> Life may not <hi>al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ways</hi> extend to the <hi>Public.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="139" facs="140"/>
Should it be objected, that some of these characteristic Marks may seem to involve Men, who have been eminently serviceable to their Country in public Stations: He would reply, that He ever hath been, and ever will be proud to do Justice to Merit, when exercised in any public Station.</p>
            <p>Should it be objected, that he ques<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions the Conduct of Those only who are now out of Power: He would reply, that he formerly questioned their Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct with the same Freedom, when in the Fulness of their Power: And that his Rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sons in both Instances were the same; because in both Instances he judged their general Conduct to be <hi>essentially</hi> ill-found<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed, narrow, selfish, reprehensible.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="section">
            <pb n="140" facs="141"/>
            <head>SECT. XXIII. Of the most effectual Means of checking the Growth of Licentiousness and Faction.</head>
            <p>THUS the Writer hath endeavoured to lay open the Foundations and Characters of Licentiousness and Faction: He now proceeds to consider the most effectual Means of checking them in their Progress; of restoring internal Uhanimity; and securing public Freedom.</p>
            <p>In every national Malady of this Nature, there are two Kinds of Remedies essen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tially distinct: The one is palliative, and temporary; the other is radical, and lasting.</p>
            <p>The palliative Remedies ought to be first apply'd; because it will appear, that they are the only Means by which we can come at Those which are radical.</p>
            <p>'Tis evident, then, that the first Ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vance towards a Cure of this national
<pb n="141" facs="142"/>
Evil must arise from the steady Conduct of the Prince. For Faction, unopposed, and led on by the higher Ranks, will never cease in its Demands, till it termi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nates in the Possession of an unbounded aristocratic Power: This is a Power, which nothing but the Courage and Steadiness of the Prince can possibly contend with: Be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cause the final Object of such a Faction will always be, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Those high and lucra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive Offices of State, which are in <hi>His</hi> sole <hi>Disposal."</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If a Sovereign once gives Way to the Storms in which such a Faction will in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>volve him, his Peace and Freedom, toge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther with Those of his People, are inevita<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bly destroyed. On the contrary, if amidst all the Tumults of Sedition, he discovers an unalterable Firmness and Fortitude, founded in upright Intentions and real Virtue; the Rage of hopeless Faction will by Degrees subside; and a Prospect of better Times will open upon <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>People.</hi> This general Truth <hi>might</hi>
               <pb n="142" facs="143"/>
be <hi>commented</hi> on: But at present, the Writer can with Satisfaction leave it to the impartial <hi>Public,</hi> to find a <hi>more instruc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive</hi> and LIVING COMMENT.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XXIV. Of a second Remedy.</head>
            <p>THE next Remedy, which can effec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tually aid the Firmness of the Prince, must be the Steadiness of the Minister, in discouraging, as far as in him lies, the Inroads of <hi>Venality</hi> and <hi>Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a large Topic, and fitter for a Book than a Section: However, what is most essential to the present Subject may be briefly touched on.</p>
            <p>A plausible Objection, then, is here to be obviated: For a late Writer hath very calmly and systematically attempted to prove the universal and unconditional Ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessity of political Corruption, in all free Governments. <note place="bottom" n="*">See a free Inquiry into the Nature and Origin of Evil, Let. v.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="143" facs="144"/>
What follows is the Foundation of his Argument. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"All human Government is the Offspring of Violence and Corrup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion; and must inherit the Imperfection of both its Parents. <note place="bottom" n="*">Origin of Evil, p. 128.</note>"</q> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"All Govern<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ments must be administered by the same Violence and Corruption, to which they are indebted for their Origin. <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib. p. 129.</note>"</q> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruption <hi>(therefore)</hi> must always increase in due Proportion to the Decrease of ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bitrary Power; since where there is less Power to command Obedience, there must be more Bribery to purchase it; or there can be no Government carry'd on at all. <note place="bottom" n="‡">Ib. p. 135.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such is the Sum of this Gentleman's Argument: To which, the following Ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>servations are offered, as a Reply.</p>
            <p>There have been two different Pictures given of <hi>Man,</hi> by different Writers, dia<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>metrically opposite to each other. By some, the human Species hath been re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>presented
<pb n="144" facs="145"/>
as a natural Society of Angels; by others, as a Crew of Devils. Both these Representations have arisen from a partial View of Mandkind▪ One Party re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>garding his <hi>social</hi> Qualities only; the other overlooking These, and fixing on the Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>petites which are commonly called the <hi>felfish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were Mankind of the first of these Characters, they would need no Law! Were they of the latter, no Law could unite or bind them. The Truth is, they are a Mixture of Both. As they have the several Modes of Self-Love, for the Preservation of the Individual; so, by <hi>proper Culture,</hi> they gain Habits of Bene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>volence, Religion, social Prudence, the Love of honest Reputation, and sometimes even a Regard for the general Welfare of the Society to which they belong. As these social Passions and Regards are strong or weak, frequent or uncommon; the Character of a Nation is good or bad, honest or corrupt, upright or profligate.
<pb n="145" facs="146"/>
A Variety of Proofs hath been given of these different Degrees of moral Charac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter, in the preceding Parts of this Essay. <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, Sect. vii, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But that we may not seem to build on a Principle which this Author admits not, we hear him virtually declaring all This himself in another Part of his Book. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Here <hi>He (Man)</hi> has an Opportunity given him of <hi>improving</hi> or <hi>debasing</hi> his Nature, in such a Manner as to render himself <hi>fit</hi> for a Rank of <hi>higher Per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fection</hi> and Happiness; or to <hi>degrade</hi> himself to a State of <hi>greater Imperfec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion</hi> and Misery. <note place="bottom" n="†">Origin of Evil, p. 93.</note>"</q> Again, he speaks of a <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Manners,</hi> as a Thing <hi>practicable:</hi> And recommends it, as the only Remedy for political Evil. <note place="bottom" n="‡">Ib. 149.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But while he treats of the absolute <hi>Neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sity</hi> of political Corruption, all the <hi>better Part</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>hid;</hi> his <hi>Imperfections</hi> and <hi>Vices</hi> alone are <hi>set</hi> in <hi>View.</hi> During the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gress of this Argument, if it deserves that
<pb n="146" facs="147"/>
Name, we hear of nothing but <q rend="inline margQuotes">"such imperfect and <hi>vicious</hi> Creatures as <hi>Men, tyrannizing</hi> over <hi>others</hi> as imperfect and <hi>vicious</hi> as themselves: <note place="bottom" n="*">Origin of Evil, p. 126.</note>"</q> We have no<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thing presented to us, but <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Pride, Ava<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rice, and Cruelty on one Side; Envy, Ignorance, and Obstinacy on the other; Injustice and Self-Interest on both. <note place="bottom" n="†">Ib.</note>"</q> In a Word, Mankind are represented as an <hi>abandoned</hi> and <hi>incurable</hi> Race, ut<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terly <hi>void</hi> of all <hi>good</hi> Qualities; and such as <q rend="inline margQuotes">"must be always bribed or beat into Obedience. <note place="bottom" n="‡">Ib. p. 130.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here, then, this Maxim of the absolute and unconditional Necessity of Political Corruption appears in all its Nakedness and Deformity: For it is founded on <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the supposed incurable Wickedness of Man:"</q> An Error too glaring to need a Confutation; and which there is still the less Occasion to confute, because this Au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thor himself admits the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="147" facs="148"/>It follows then, that his leading Proposi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion is as false in itself, as it is pernicious to Society, that 
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Corruption must always increase in due Proportion to the De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>crease of arbitrary Power:"</q> Because Vir<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tue and Religion, upright Manners and Principles, properly instilled, may much better supply Corruption's Place. <note place="bottom" n="*">Were it necessary to pursue this Gentleman through all the Windings of his political Labyrinth, and trace him to the End of his Course, where he suddenly starts up in the Form of a severe Moralist; there could not, perhaps, be exhibited a more striking Instance of Self-Contradiction, in the whole Compass of literary Debate.—At present I shall only remark, that this Essay was published in the Year 1757, at a Time when the System of political Corruption much needed some Kind of Apology, because its fatal Effects began to gla<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter" rend="content:•">
                     <desc>illegible</desc>
                  </gap>e too strongly upon the Nation to be longer doubted. Hence, though we should not inquire <q rend="inline margQuotes">
                     <hi>"who</hi> the Author is,"</q>we may give a <hi>shrewd Guess,</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes"> "what <hi>political School</hi> he was <hi>bred</hi> in."</q>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>On this Foundation, therefore, it ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pears, that every upright Minister ought, as far as possible, to check the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gress of Corruption: And tho' at Times he may be embarassed, and under a <hi>po<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>litical</hi>
               <pb n="148" facs="149"/>
               <hi>Necessity</hi> of yielding; 'tis clearly both his Duty and his Interest to oppose this dangerous and encroaching Spirit, in the leading Outlines of his public Conduct.</p>
            <p>It is his Duty; both because Corrup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion can only flourish on the Ruins of Virtue and Religion, good Morals and Principles, without which public Liberty is essentially destroy'd; and because Cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruption tends inevitably and invariably to weaken the public Administration of Government, by filling every high De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>partment with the Venal, the Ignorant, the Selfish, the Dishonest. <note place="bottom" n="*">See Estimate, Part ii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is both his Duty and Interest; be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cause <hi>Licentiousness,</hi> and its Attendants, <hi>Venality</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> are of an <hi>insatiable</hi> Appetite. The more the Venal are fed, they grow more importunate: If you gorge one of These to the full, and thus lay him to sleep; ten will rise in his Place, every one more clamourous than the first.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="149" facs="150"/>
The Minister, therefore, both in Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sideration of his own Peace, and the pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lic Welfare, ought as far as possible, to obviate this Evil in its <hi>Beginnings;</hi> for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tify <hi>Himself,</hi> as well as the <hi>State,</hi> with the <hi>Honest,</hi> the <hi>Firm,</hi> and the <hi>Capable;</hi> resist, to the utmost, the exorbitant Demands of <hi>Venality:</hi> Thus <hi>Faction</hi> will either <hi>bark</hi> itself <hi>asleep;</hi> or <hi>die despairing.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XXV. Of some concomitant Remedies.</head>
            <p>LET us now consider, what might be in the Power of the <hi>Legislature</hi> and the <hi>Magistrate</hi> immediately to effect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis generally acknowledged, that Power naturally follows Property. There<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore exorbitant Property in Individuals must always be unfavourable to civil Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty; must always tend to produce Licen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiousness and Faction; because it throws
<pb n="150" facs="151"/>
exorbitant Power into the Hands of In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dividuals: And the greater the <hi>Inequality</hi> between the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi> the more the <hi>one</hi> will ever be under the <hi>Influence</hi> of the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It should seem, then, to be the <hi>parti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cular</hi> Interest even of the most <hi>Wealthy,</hi> if they be the real Friends of Liberty,—'tis certainly the <hi>general</hi> Interest of a <hi>free Community;</hi> that some legal Limita<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of Property should take Place. I speak not of the Probability, but the Expediency of such a Measure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It follows, that some <hi>Regulation</hi> in Respect to <hi>Boroughs</hi> would be of great Importance. For in Boroughs, contrary to all sound Policy, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Power is lodged without annexed Property."</q>The na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tural Consequence is, that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"this ill-placed Power will be seized by Those who are possessed of exorbitant Property."</q> Thus Power settles on its natural Foundation: But a Foundation, in this Instance, most dangerous to Freedom; as it leads to the
<pb n="151" facs="152"/>
Establishment of an Aristocracy. In This Instance, too, I speak not of the Probabi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lity, but the Expediency of the Measure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Limitation of extended Conquest and Empire might seem an Object worthy the Attention of the highest Powers.—ROME perished by its Avidity of un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bounded Empire. Colonies, when peopled beyond a certain Degree, become a Bur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>then to the Mother Country: They exhaust her Numbers; they distract her Attention; they divide her compacted Strength. Such Extent of Colonies, as may be necessary to maintain the Empire of the Seas, will al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ways be a just Object of <hi>British</hi> Regard. More than this, sound Policy perhaps could hardly dictate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Limitation is of more Impor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tance, as it would naturally set Bounds to another Excess: I mean, That of Trade and Wealth. This, the Writer knows, is of all other Topics the most unpopular: Notwithstanding which, he presumes to persist in what appears to Him a demon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>strative
<pb n="152" facs="153"/>
Truth, that <q rend="inline margQuotes">"exorbitant Trade and Wealth are most dangerous to private Virtue and therefore to public Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom."</q> The Topic is too large, to be here insisted on. He therefore refers to what he hath already written on this Sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ject; <note place="bottom" n="*">See Estimate, Part iii. passim.</note> which hath been much clamoured against, indeed; but never confuted. <note place="bottom" n="†">For the Conviction of Those who chuse rather to attend to <hi>present</hi> than <hi>future</hi> Consequences, the follow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Circumstance may deserve Notice. Much hath been said <q rend="inline margQuotes">"on the Cause of the present exorbitant Price of Provisions, and general Distress of the Poor:"</q>Every Cause hath been assigned except the true one, which seems to be <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the sinking Value of Money, arising necessarily from the exorbitant Increase of Trade and Wealth."</q> If this be so, it follows, that the Evil is incurable, excepting only by a general Augmentation of the Wages of the Poor.—Now This, which is the neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary Effect of the Exorbitancy of Commerce, naturally tends (by the increased Price of Manufactures) to the Destruction of Commerce. If the Exorbitancy of Trade should still run higher, this Evil will be aggravated in Proportion. The Consequences which must follow, are such as the Writer chuseth not to enlarge on; because he knows, the Spirit of the Times would not bear it.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="153" facs="154"/>
5. The immediate Care of upright Manners and Principles might seem an Object worthy the strictest Attention both of the Legislature and Magistrate.</p>
            <p>To this End, if the growing Spirit of <hi>Novelty</hi> and <hi>Adoption</hi> could by any Means be checked, it would be a Work attended with the most salutary Consequences. The Writer would not willingly be thought chimerically to adopt all the Rigours of the <hi>Spartan</hi> State: But could wish to see a Law enacted, parallel to That of LACEDAEMON, by which their raw and unexperienced Youth were prohibited from bringing Home the new Follies and Vices of foreign Countries, picked up in a premature and too early Travel. <note place="bottom" n="*">See Estimate, Vol. ii. Part i. Sect. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He would by no Means discourage the <hi>Freedom</hi> of the <hi>Press:</hi> Yet, sure, its <hi>Licen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiousness</hi> might seem an Object of the Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gistrate's Regard. The Search of Truth is good: But to search for This in the
<pb n="154" facs="155"/>
Hoards of <hi>Irreligion,</hi> is like searching for <hi>Hope</hi> in PANDORA'S <hi>Box;</hi> where the sole Reward of Industry can only be <hi>Pestilence, Despair</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi> National Virtue ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver was maintained, but by national Religion: He, therefore, who shakes the essential Principles of Religion, undermines the Virtue of his Fellow-Subjects; and therefore deserves to feel the Rigour of the Law, as a determined <hi>Enemy</hi> of his <hi>Coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try.—</hi>This may seem a practicable Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>medy: But how to destroy those irreligious Writings, which already lie exposed on Stalls and Counters, or deposited in private Libraries, like so many Heaps of Poison, for the Gratification of Vice, and the De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>struction of Virtue:—Or how to pluck from the Minds of Men those poisoned Arrows, which these Authors have already planted there!—That were a <hi>Task indeed!—</hi>The Shaft is already flown; and cannot be recalled: And this Nation, thro' suc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceeding Times will have Cause to say,<q rend="inline">—"Haeret Lateri lethalis Arundo."</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="155" facs="156"/>
               <hi>Immoral Writings</hi> should seem no less the Object of the Magistrate's Attention. Tho' These may not shake the <hi>Principles,</hi> yet they inevitably corrupt the <hi>Manners</hi> of a Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Personal Defamation,</hi> or Calumny thrown on <hi>private</hi> Characters, is another Evil, which seems rising at present with unheard-of Aggravations. Two <hi>slagrant</hi> Instances of This Enormity the Writer will pass unnoticed, lest he should seem to insult over the <hi>Exiled</hi> or the <hi>Dead.</hi> 
               <note place="bottom" n="*">In these two Kinds of modern Profligacy, <hi>immoral Writings,</hi> and <hi>personal Calumny,</hi> there is one professed Author, now said to be living in this Kingdom with Impunity; who, in a better policed State would ere this have felt the full Weight of that public Punishment and Infamy which is due to an Enemy of Mankind. This Man, supposed to be one <hi>C—,</hi> first writ a Volume of execrable <hi>Memoirs,</hi> for the Corruption of Youth and Inno<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cence: Since That, a <hi>Reverie,</hi> or <hi>Dream,</hi> which <hi>Hun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ger</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> probably conspired to suggest; replete with the most impudent Falsehoods, and injurious Calum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nies on Individuals, for the Entertainment of <hi>base</hi> and <hi>envious</hi> Minds.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="section">
            <pb n="156" facs="157"/>
            <head>SECT. XXVI. Of the chief and essential Remedy.</head>
            <p>ALL these may be regarded as tempo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rary and concomitant Supports of Freedom. But the chief and essential Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>medy to Licentiousness and Faction, the fundamental Means of the lasting and se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cure Establishment of civil Liberty, can only <q rend="inline margQuotes">"lie in a general and prescribed Im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>provement of the Laws of Education."</q>
            </p>
            <p>We have seen above, that upright Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ners and Principles are the only Basis of true Liberty; that the infant Mind, if left to its own untutored Dictates, inevitably wanders into such Follies and Vices, as tend to the Destruction of itself and others. We have seen, that the early and continued Culture of the Heart can alone produce such upright Manners and Principles, as are necessary to check and subdue the selfish Passions of the Soul; and that Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty
<pb n="157" facs="158"/>
can only arise from a general Subor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dination of These, to the public Welfare. We have seen these Truths confirmed, by an Appeal to the State of three famed Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>publics, which by Turns <hi>arose</hi> and <hi>fell,</hi> on the very Principles here delivered. We have seen the Defects, as well as Excellen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cies, of our own public Constitution, both <hi>civil</hi> and <hi>religious:</hi> That its Form is excel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lent and unrivaled; but that the practical <hi>Application</hi> of this unrivaled Excellence is attended with Defects incurable: That it hath all along been inevitably counterwork<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed by Manners and Principles discordant with its Genius, and discordant with each other: That for Want of a prescribed Code of Education, to which all the Members of the Community should legally submit, the Manners and Principles on which alone the State can rest, are ineffec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tually instilled, are vague, fluctuating, and self-contradictory.</p>
            <p>Nothing, then, is more evident, than that some Reform in this great Point, is
<pb n="158" facs="159"/>
necessary, for the Security of public Free<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom. Till this be effected, in Spite of all temporary Remedies, Licentiousness and Faction, tho' checked for a Time, will ever be gathering new Strength, and return<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing to the Charge with redoubled Fury.</p>
            <p>This Reform, to some, may appear easy to effect: By others it will be de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rided, as wholly impracticable. Perhaps the Truth may lie between these two Opinions: To throw the Manners and Principles of a Nation into any new Chan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nel, is certainly a Work of no small Dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficulty.—On the other Hand, we seem to have many Materials lying round us, ready to be converted into the Means of this great Work. A pure and rational Religion; a generous System of Policy, founded on that Religion; Manners, tho' apparently degenerating, yet by no Means generally profligate; much true Religion, Integrity, and Honour among the <hi>middle</hi> Ranks; many Instances of <hi>domestic Worth</hi> among the <hi>higher;</hi> and in Spite of the
<pb n="159" facs="160"/>
Temptations that surround the <hi>Great,</hi> true <hi>Piety,</hi> and the <hi>moral Virtues</hi> adorning the <hi>most exalted Station.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, without dreaming of the perfect Republic of PLATO;—and fairly acknowledging the incurable Defect of our political State, in not having a cor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>respondent and adequate Code of Educa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion inwrought into its first Essence;—we may yet hope, that in a secondary and inferior Degree, something of this Kind may be still <hi>inlaid:</hi> It cannot have that perfect Efficacy, as if it had been originally <hi>of the Piece:</hi> Yet, if well con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ducted, it may strengthen the weak Parts; and <hi>alleviate</hi> Defects, though not com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pleatly <hi>remove</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Among <hi>what Ranks,</hi> in the Writer's Opinion, these <hi>Defects</hi> in <hi>Education</hi> chiefly <hi>lie,</hi> may be sufficiently collected from some of the preceding Sections. But as to the most <hi>effectual Methods</hi> of <hi>relieving</hi> these <hi>Defects,</hi> he pretends not at present to attempt so great a Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="160" facs="161"/>
This, however, he is well perswaded of; that till something of the Kind be attempted and performed; all the la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>boured Harangues that can be given from the <hi>Bench,</hi> the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> or the <hi>Press,</hi> will be of little Avail: They may tend <hi>occa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sionally</hi> to <hi>obviate</hi> some of the <hi>Evils</hi> of <hi>Licentiousness;</hi> but never can <hi>radically cure them.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XXVII. The Conclusion.</head>
            <p>THESE Remedies, however <hi>just</hi> in their <hi>Nature,</hi> can only be <hi>effectual</hi> through a proper Application: And this can only lie <q rend="inline margQuotes">"in a zealous and unfeigned Union of the <hi>Honest</hi> among all <hi>Ranks</hi> and <hi>Parties,</hi> for the <hi>Accomplishment</hi> of <hi>these Ends,</hi> against the Patrons and Instruments of Licentiousness and Fac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion."</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="161" facs="162"/>
This Union, at first View, seems of such a Nature as could hardly need to be inforced: Yet it is frequently retarded by several Circumstances.</p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Great,</hi> this rational Union is often counteracted by the Ties of false Honour; a dangerous Principle, which we have already noted, as being produc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tive of Party-Rage and Faction. <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, p. 92.</note> This Principle, even in honest Minds, will sometimes prevail over the Dictates of Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ligion and private Virtue. On this false Foundation, political Connexions are often maintained, in Defiance of a just Sense of public Utility: While the unhappy Man who acts on this mistaken Motive, is inwardly rent by two contrary and con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tending Powers. Severe Moralists may perhaps discard such a Character from the List of the <hi>Honest:</hi> But it should seem, that he is rather an Object of Clemency than Indignation. Remove but the unhappy Prejudice from his Breast;
<pb n="162" facs="163"/>
And such a Character would press for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward among the first, towards the <hi>Goal</hi> of <hi>public Virtue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again: This rational and salutary Union may be retarded by Connexions of <hi>Friend<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ship, Gratitude,</hi> or <hi>Blood.</hi> This Cause tends to confirm and extend the Influence of the former. <hi>Fathers, powerful Friends,</hi> and <hi>Patrons,</hi> connect themselves with Par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ties, and cleave to them on a mistaken Principle: <hi>Sons, obliged Friends,</hi> and <hi>De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pendents,</hi> are naturally inlisted in their Party; and are rivetted in it, not only by <hi>false Honour,</hi> but <hi>Education, Gratitude, Affection.</hi> How peculiarly unfortunate is this Circumstance; that the <hi>generous Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions</hi> should ever become the <hi>Adversaries</hi> of <hi>public Virtue!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same false Attachment to Friends, Patrons, and Relations, naturally prevails, in a certain Proportion, among the mid<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dle Ranks of the Kingdom. Their In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terests, Passions, and Prejudices, are not so immediately concerned as Those of the higher Ranks; and therefore 'tis natural
<pb n="163" facs="164"/>
to suppose, that their mutual Attachments of mistaken Honour or private Affection, will upon the Whole be more moderate and less culpable. Yet still, while these false Attachments are prevalent among the <hi>Great,</hi> the <hi>People</hi> must in some De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gree catch the Infection, from the various Relations which they bear to their Supe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riors. Hence untractable Prejudices arise, and are maintained: While <hi>Measures</hi> are less regarded, than the <hi>Party</hi> which <hi>adopts</hi> them.</p>
            <p>But besides This, another Circumstance ariseth, which inevitably tends to <hi>disunite,</hi> and <hi>distract</hi> the <hi>Honest</hi> among the <hi>People;</hi> even when their personal Attachments are conquered by their Integrity. Their <hi>Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>persion</hi> in the Country hath already been remarked, as a Circumstance worthy of At<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tention. Here it meets us again, as a Cause of their frequent <hi>Disunion.</hi> We have seen how naturally (under the present State of Things) every factious Clamour that ri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>seth in the Capital, is transmitted with aggravated Circumstances, through the
<pb n="164" facs="165"/>
whole Kingdom. <note place="bottom" n="*">See above, Sect. xix, p. 130.</note> And the People of the Villages being easy of Belief, because not suspecting the abandoned Profligacy of these <hi>Town-Defamers,</hi> are apt to receive every insinuated <hi>personal Slander,</hi> as a <hi>Truth.</hi> These Calumnies being seldom contradicted by the injured Party, take Root in the Minds of the less knowing. Hence Doubts arise; Surmises and Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>likes are spread; Facts, though void of all Foundation, are alledged and persisted in; the more credulous Part are misled: Thus an honest People are divided; and not only a <hi>Province</hi> or a <hi>Village,</hi> but even an <hi>House</hi> often set at Variance with<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>in itself.</p>
            <p>These Contentions <hi>sometimes</hi> arise to a Degree which is ridiculous: And have for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>merly been so described <hi>without Exception,</hi> by the Tools of Faction. Notwithstanding This, every Friend of Liberty ought to grieve, if a <hi>free,</hi> an <hi>honest,</hi> and a <hi>sensible</hi> PEOPLE should ever desist (were it possi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble)
<pb n="165" facs="166"/>
to debate on Affairs of Government. Tho' they may be occasionally alarmed and misled on slight Occasions, yet their mature and collective Judgment on im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portant Subjects, will <hi>seldom</hi> be <hi>erroneous.</hi> On this Foundation, MONTESQUIEU'S Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mark is solid: <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Tell me not, that such a People will sometimes <hi>reason ill:"</hi>
               </q> 'Tis sufficient, <q rend="inline">"that <hi>they reason.</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom" n="*">L'Esprit des Loix.</note>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Guilt and ill Consequences, then, arise from the malevolent Clamours of the Capital, transmitted thence to the Provinces. These Clamours, though not of Power to seduce an <hi>honest</hi> PEOPLE into actual Sedition, are yet often suffi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cient to <hi>alarm</hi> and <hi>divide</hi> them. <note place="bottom" n="†">See above, Sect. xiii. p. 114.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Much Caution, therefore, ought to be used by the Inhabitants of the <hi>Country,</hi> how they give Credit to the <hi>political</hi> Ru<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mours of the <hi>Town;</hi> which are seldom spread without Design; and are in ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>neral spread most industriously by the Malevolent. They who act on good Prin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples,
<pb n="166" facs="167"/>
are apt to trust to the native Force of Truth: The Patrons of False<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hood are conscious of a Defect <hi>here;</hi> and therefore endeavour to supply it by a misapply'd Diligence and Cunning.</p>
            <p>One Mark of Licentiousness and Fac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion is peculiarly applicable to these Cla<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mours from the Metropolis: If they are fraught with <hi>personal Calumny,</hi> and at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tack private Characters, they assuredly come from the <hi>Enemies</hi> of <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Freedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All These, therefore, a <hi>sensible</hi> and <hi>ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nest</hi> PEOPLE will learn to <hi>suspect</hi> and <hi>de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ride.</hi> This Foundation once laid, they will not be far from a <hi>general Union</hi> against the <hi>hidden Designs</hi> of <hi>Licentious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Conclusion, therefore, let the <hi>Honest</hi> among every <hi>Rank</hi> and <hi>Party</hi> recollect; that their first and highest Obligations are to God, their King, and Country. That every <hi>subordinate</hi> Connexion ought to <hi>yield</hi> to <hi>These:</hi> That true <hi>Honour</hi> can never be at <hi>Variance</hi> with the Laws of <hi>Religion</hi> and
<pb n="167" facs="168"/>
               <hi>Virtue:</hi> That if any <hi>Desertion</hi> be <hi>shameful,</hi> it is the <hi>Desertion</hi> from <hi>Truth</hi> and the Welfare of their <hi>Country:</hi> If any <hi>At<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tachment</hi> be <hi>honourable,</hi> it is an impartial <hi>Attachment</hi> to the <hi>public Weal,</hi> unbiassed by private Affections and Regards. If any <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> be the certain Mark of a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ingenuous</hi> Mind, it is the <hi>Ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>knowledgment</hi> of <hi>its own Errors,</hi> or those of a <hi>Patron, Friend,</hi> or <hi>Ancestor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These Remarks the Writer submits to the Impartiality and Candor of his Coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>trymen; desiring that they may be regard<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed as his Mite, thrown in towards the Ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>complishment of the Sovereign's Wish, on his Accession to the Throne; that of <q rend="inline margQuotes">"found<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing the Liberty and Happiness of this Kingdom on the solid Basis of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> and uniting ALL HONEST MEN in the steady Prosecution of this great Purpose.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishersadvertisement">
            <pb facs="169"/>
            <p>By the same AUTHOR, With all Convenient SPEED, <hi>Will be Publi&amp;s;hed,</hi> PRINCIPLES OF CHRISTIAN LEGISLATION.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>