<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Achilles: An opera. As it is perform'd at the Theatre-Royal in Covent-Garden. Written by the late Mr. Gay. With the musick prefix'd to each song.</title>
            <author>Gay, John, 1685-1732.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K020978.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3314258361</idno>
            <idno type="ecll">0783200300</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Achilles: An opera. As it is perform'd at the Theatre-Royal in Covent-Garden. Written by the late Mr. Gay. With the musick prefix'd to each song.</title>
                  <author>Gay, John, 1685-1732.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8],68,[4]p. : ill.,music. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Watts,</publisher>
                  <date>1733.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K020978.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3314258361</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll">0783200300</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a half-title and 3 pages of advertisements.</note>
                  <note>At foot of titlepage: Price one shilling and six pence.</note>
                  <note>Variant: no price on titlepage.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT1728.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="halftitle">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>ACHILLES. AN OPERA.</p>
            <p>By the late Mr. <hi>GAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Price One Shilling and Six Pence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <p>ACHILLES. AN OPERA. As it is Perform'd at the
Theatre-Royal in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—deceperat omnes</l>
               <l>(In quibus Ajacem) sumptae fallacia vestis.</l>
               <bibl>Ovid. Metam. Lib. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Naturam expellas furcâ licet, usque recurret.</q>
            <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
            <p>Written by the late Mr. <hi>GAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the MUSICK prefix'd to each SONG.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for J. WATTS at the Printing-Office in
<hi>Wild-Court,</hi> near <hi>Lincoln's-Inn-Fields.</hi>
               <abbr>MDCCXXXIII.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Price One Shilling and Six Pence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tableofsongs">
            <pb facs="3"/>
            <head>A
TABLE of the SONGS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <item>AIR 1. What's Life? No Curse is more severe. <hi>Page</hi> 2</item>
               <item>AIR 2. Why thus am I held at Defiance? <hi>p.</hi> 3</item>
               <item>AIR 3. The Woman always in Temptation. <hi>p.</hi> 4</item>
               <item>AIR 4. When a Woman sullen sits. <hi>p.</hi> 6</item>
               <item>AIR 5. Man's so touchy, a Word that's injurious. <hi>p.</hi> 7</item>
               <item>AIR 6. Must then, alas, the fondest Mother. <hi>p.</hi> 8</item>
               <item>AIR 7. How your Patience had been try'd. <hi>p.</hi> 10</item>
               <item>AIR 8. Whene'er my Looks have spoke Desire. <hi>p.</hi> 11</item>
               <item>AIR 9. Observe the wanton Kitten's Play. <hi>p.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>AIR 10. When a Woman's censorious. <hi>p.</hi> 14</item>
               <item>AIR 11. As you, Sir, are my Husband, no doubt you're
prone. <hi>p.</hi> 15</item>
               <item>AIR 12. Then must I bear eternal Strife. <hi>p.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>AIR 13. O <hi>Love,</hi> plead my Pardon, nor plead it in vain. <hi>p.</hi> 17</item>
               <item>AIR 14. To what a Pitch is Man profuse. <hi>p.</hi> 18</item>
               <item>AIR 15. Reputations hack'd and hew'd. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>AIR 16. Though Woman's glib Tongue, when her Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions
are fir'd. <hi>p.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>AIR 17. O guard your Hours from Care. <hi>p.</hi> 22</item>
               <item>AIR 18. All Hearts are a little frail. <hi>p.</hi> 23</item>
               <item>AIR 19. Let Jealousy no longer. <hi>p.</hi> 24</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <item>AIR 20. Such Homage to her Beauty. <hi>p.</hi> 25</item>
               <item>AIR 21. Shou'd the Beast of the noblest Race. <hi>p.</hi> 26</item>
               <item>AIR 22. What, must I remain in Anguish? <hi>p.</hi> 28</item>
               <item>AIR 23. If my Passion want explaining. <hi>p.</hi> 30</item>
               <item>AIR 24. How unhappy are the Great. <hi>p.</hi> 31</item>
               <item>AIR 25. When the Fort on no Condition. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>AIR 26. Why such Affectation? <hi>p.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>AIR 27. What Heart hath not Courage by Force assail'd. <hi>p.</hi> 33</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="4"/>AIR 28. No more be coy. <hi>p.</hi> 34</item>
               <item>AIR 29. What give o'er! <hi>p.</hi> 36</item>
               <item>AIR 30. The Slips of a Husband, you Wives <hi>p.</hi> 37</item>
               <item>AIR 31. Ah! shou'd you ever find her. <hi>p.</hi> 38</item>
               <item>AIR 32. First let him for Honour roam. <hi>p.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>AIR 33. Think what Anguish tears my Quiet. <hi>p.</hi> 41</item>
               <item>AIR 34. Know that Importunity's in vain. <hi>p.</hi> 42</item>
               <item>AIR 35. How happy my Days, and how sweet was my
Rest. <hi>p.</hi> 43</item>
               <item>AIR 36. Your Dress, your Conversations. <hi>p.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>AIR 37. Ah, why is my Heart so tender! <hi>p.</hi> 45</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <item>AIR 38. What are the Jests that on Marriage you quote? <hi>p.</hi> 47</item>
               <item>AIR 39. Soldier, think before you marry. <hi>p.</hi> 48</item>
               <item>AIR 40. What is all this idle Chat? <hi>p.</hi> 50</item>
               <item>AIR 41. Oh, then it seems you want a Wife! <hi>p.</hi> 51</item>
               <item>AIR 42. What means all this Ranting? <hi>p.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>AIR 43. In War we've nought but Death to fear. <hi>p.</hi> 54</item>
               <item>AIR 44. We may resolve to resist Temptation. <hi>p.</hi> 56</item>
               <item>AIR 45. Think of Dress in ev'ry Light. <hi>p.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>AIR 46. In Dress and Love by like Desires <hi>p.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>AIR 47. Thy Fate then, O <hi>Troy,</hi> is decreed. <hi>p.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>AIR 48. Beauty weeps.—Ah, why that Languish? <hi>p.</hi> 62</item>
               <item>AIR 49. Why this Pain? <hi>p.</hi> 63</item>
               <item>AIR 50. O, what a Conflict's in my Breast! <hi>p.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>AIR 51. Was ever a Lover so happily freed! <hi>p.</hi> 66</item>
               <item>AIR 52. How short was my Calm! in a Moment 'tis past. <hi>p.</hi> 67</item>
               <item>AIR 53. Nature breaks forth at the Moment unguarded. <hi>p.</hi> 68</item>
               <item>AIR 54. Thus when the Cat had once all Woman's Graces. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <byline>Written by Mr. <hi>GAY.</hi>
            </byline>
            <byline>Spoken by Mr. <hi>QVIN.</hi>
            </byline>
            <lg>
               <l>I Wonder not our Author doubts Success,</l>
               <l>One in his Circumstance can do no less.</l>
               <l>The Dancer on the Rope that tries at all,</l>
               <l>In each unpractis'd Caper risques a Fall:</l>
               <l>I own I dread his ticklish Situation,</l>
               <l>Critics detest Poetic Innovation.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Ic'rus</hi> been content with solid Ground,</l>
               <l>The giddy vent'rous Youth had ne'er been drown'd.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pegasus</hi> of old had Fire and Force,</l>
               <l>But your true Modern is a Carrier's Horse,</l>
               <l>Drawn by the foremost Bell, afraid to stray,</l>
               <l>Bard following Bard jogs on the beaten Way.</l>
               <l>Why is this Man so obstinate an Elf?</l>
               <l>Wall he, alone, not imitate himself?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Scene now shews the Heroes of old <hi>Greece</hi>;</l>
               <l>But how? 'tis monstrous! In a Comic Piece.</l>
               <l>To Buskins, Plumes and Helmets what Pretence,</l>
               <l>If mighty Chiefs must speak but common Sense?</l>
               <l>Shall no bold Diction, no Poetic Rage,</l>
               <l>Fome at our Mouths and thunder on the Stage?</l>
               <l>No 'tis <hi>Achilles,</hi> as he came from <hi>Chiron,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Just taught to sing as well as wield cold Iron;</l>
               <l>And whatsoever Criticks may suppose,</l>
               <l>Our Author holds, that what He spoke was Prose.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatispersonae">
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <list>
               <head>Dramatis Personae.</head>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <head>MEN.</head>
                     <label>Lycomedes,</label>
                     <item>MR. <hi>Quin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Diphilus,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Aston.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Achilles,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Salway.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Ulysses,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Chapman.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Diomedes,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Laguerre.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Ajax,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Hall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Periphas,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Walker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Agyrtes,</label>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Leveridge.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <list>
                     <head>WOMEN.</head>
                     <label>Thetis,</label>
                     <item>Mrs. <hi>Buchanan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Theaspe,</label>
                     <item>Mrs. <hi>Cantrel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Deidamia,</label>
                     <item>Miss <hi>Norsa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Lesbia,</label>
                     <item>Miss <hi>Binks.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Philoe,</label>
                     <item>Miss <hi>Oates.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>Artemona,</label>
                     <item>Mrs. <hi>Egleton.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Courtiers, Guards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <stage>SCENE, <hi>SCYROS.</hi>
            </stage>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="7"/>
            <head>ACHILLES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT I. SCENE I.</head>
                  <head type="sub">SCENE, The Palace.</head>
                  <stage>THETIS, ACHILLES.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THETIS.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EFORE I leave you, Child, I must insist up<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on
your Promise, that you will never disco<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver
yourself without my Leave. Don't look
upon it as capricious Fondness, nor think (be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cause
'tis a Mother's Advice) that in Duty to
yourself you are oblig'd not to follow it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>But my Character! my Honour!—
Wou'd you have your Son live with Infamy?—On
the first Step of a young Fellow depends his Character for
Life.—I beg you, Goddess, to dispense with your Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you then no Regard to my Presentiment? I can't
bear the Thoughts of your going, for I know that odious Siege
of <hi>Troy</hi> wou'd be the Death of thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Because you have the natural Fears of a Mother, wou'd
you have me insensible that I have the Heart of a Man? The
World, Madam, must look upon my absconding in this Man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ner,
and at this particular Juncture, as infamous Cowardise.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="2" facs="8"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR I. A Clown in <hi>Flanders</hi> once there was.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>What's Life? No Curse is more severe,</l>
                              <l>Than bearing Life with Shame.</l>
                              <l>Is this your Fondness? this your Care?</l>
                              <l>O give me Death with Fame.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>Keep your Temper, <hi>Achilles</hi>:—'Tis both im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pious
and undutiful to call my Prescience in question.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon me, Goddess, for had you, like other Mothers,
been a meer Woman only, I shou'd have taken the Liberty of
other Sons, and shou'd (as 'tis my Duty) have heard your Ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vice,
and follow'd my own.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>I positively shall not be easy, Child, unless you give
me your Word and Honour.—You know my Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>My Word, Madam, I can give you; but my Honour
is already sacrific'd to my Duty. That I gave you when I sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mitted
to put on this Womans Habit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>Believe me, <hi>Achilles,</hi> I have a tender Regard for your
Honour, as well as Life.—By preventing your running
head-long to your Destiny, I preserve you for future Glory.
Therefore, Child, I once more insist upon your solemn Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mise.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Was I a Woman (as I appear to be) I cou'd without
Difficulty give you a Promise to have the Pleasure of breaking
it; but when I promise, my Life is pledg'd for the Performance.
—Your Commands, Madam, are sacred.—Yet I intreat
you, Goddess, to consider the ignominious Part you make me
act.—In obeying you, I prove my self unworthy of you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>My Will, <hi>Achilles,</hi> is not to be controverted. Your
Life depends upon your Duty; and positively, Child, you shall
not go to this Siege.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="3" facs="9"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR II. <hi>Gudgeon</hi>'s Song.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Why thus am I held at Defiance?</l>
                              <l>A Mother, a Goddess obey!</l>
                              <l>Will Men never practise Compliance,</l>
                              <l>Till Marriage hath taught 'em the Way?</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>But why must I lead the Life of a Woman? Why
was I stolen away from my Preceptor? Was I not as safe
under the Care of <hi>Chiron</hi>?—I know the Love he had
for me; I feel his Concern; and I dare swear that good Crea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture
is now so distress'd for the Loss of me, that he will quite
founder himself with galloping from Place to Place to look af<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter
me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll hear no more. Obey, and seek to know no fur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther.
—Can you imagine that I wou'd have taken all this
Trouble to have lodg'd you under the Protection of <hi>Lycomedes</hi>;
if I had not seen the absolute Necessity of it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Were I allow'd to follow my Inclinations, what wou'd
you have to fear?—I shou'd do my Duty, and die with Ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nour.
—Was I to live an Age, I cou'd do no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>You are so very obstinate, that really, Child, there's
no enduring you.—Your Impatience seems to forget that I
am a Goddess: Have I not degraded my self into the Charac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter
of a distress'd <hi>Grecian</hi> Princess? 'Tis owing to my Artifice
and Insinuation that we have the Protection of the King of
<hi>Scyros.</hi> Have I not won <hi>Lycomedes</hi> his Friendship and Hospi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tality
to that degree as to place you, without the least Suspi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cion,
among his Daughters?—And for what, dear <hi>Achilles</hi>?
—Your Safety and future Fame requir'd it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis impossible, Madam, to bear it much longer.—
My Words, my Actions, my aukward Behaviour, must one
Day inevitably discover me.—I had been safer under the
Tuition of <hi>Chiron.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>Hath not the Prophet <hi>Calchas</hi> persuaded the Confede<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rates
that the Success of their Expedition against <hi>Troy</hi> depends
<pb n="4" facs="10"/>
upon your being among 'em? Have they not Emissaries and
Spies almost every where in search of you? 'Tis here only,
and in this Disguise, that I can believe you out of the Reach of
Suspicion.—You have so much Youth, and such a Bloom,
that there is no Man alive but must take you for a Woman.
What I am most afraid of is, that when you are among the La<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dies
you shou'd be so little Master of your Passions as to find
your self a Man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR III. Did you ever hear of a galant Sailor.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l> The Woman always in Temptation,</l>
                              <l>Must do what Nature bids her do;</l>
                              <l>Our Hearts feel equal Palpitation,</l>
                              <l>For we've unguarded Minutes too.</l>
                              <l>By Nature greedy,</l>
                              <l>When lank and needy,</l>
                              <l>Within your Fold the Wolf confine;</l>
                              <l>Then bid the Glutton</l>
                              <l>Not think of Mutton;</l>
                              <l>Can you persuade him not to dine?</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>Now, dear Child, let me beg you to be discreet.—I
have some Sea-Affairs that require my Attendance, which
(much against my Will) oblige me for a time to leave you to
your own Conduct.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="5" facs="11"/>
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>Thetis, Achilles, Artemona.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>The Princesses, Lady <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> have been sitting at their
Embroidery above a Quarter of an Hour, and are perfectly mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>serable
for want of you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pyrrha</hi> is so very unhandy, and so monstrously auk<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward
at her Needle, that I know she must be diverting. Her
Passion for Romances (as you must have observ'd in other
Girls) took her off from every Part of useful Education.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>For the many Obligations I have to the Princesses, I
should (no doubt) upon all Occasions shew my self ready to be
the But of their Ridicule.—'Tis a Duty that all great People
expect from (what they call) their Dependants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>How can you, Lady <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> misinterpret a Civility? I
know they have a Friendship, an Esteem for you; and have a
Pleasure in instructing you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heaven's sake, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> let not your captious Tem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>per
run away with your Good-manners. You cannot but be
sensible of the King's and their Civilities, both to you and me.
—How can you be so horridly out of Humour?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>All I mean, Madam, is; that when People are sensi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble
of their own Defects, they are not the proper Objects of
Ridicule.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>You are so very touchy, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> that there is no en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>during
you.—How can you be so unsociable a Creature as to
deny a Friend the Liberty of laughing at your little Follies and
Indiscretions? For what do you think Women keep Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pany
with one another?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Because they hate one another, despise one another, and
seek to have the Pleasure of seeing and exposing one another's
Faults and Follies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>Now, dear <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> tell me, is Work a thing you
pique yourself upon? Suppose too they shou'd smile at an Ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>surdity
in your Dress, it cou'd not be such a Mortification as if
(like most Women) you had made it the chief Business of your
Life?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't they treat one another with equal Familiarity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>But a Reply from me (whatever was the Provocation)
might be look'd upon as impertinent. I hate to be under the
Restraint of Civility when I am ill-us'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="6" facs="12"/>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you allow me, Madam, to make your Excuses to
the Princesses?—The Occasion of your Highness's leav<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
her, I see, troubles her.—Perhaps I may interrupt Conver<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis astonishing, Child, how you can have so little
Complaisance. This sullen Behaviour of yours must be disa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>greeable.
I hope, Madam, she is not always in this way?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Never was any Creature more entertaining! Such Spi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rits,
and so much Vivacity! The Princesses are really fond
of her to Distraction.—The most chearful Tempers are liable
to the Spleen, and 'tis an Indulgence that one Woman owes to
another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>The Spleen, Madam, is a Female Frailty that I have no
Pretensions to, nor any of its Affections.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR IV. Si vous vous moquez de nous.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>When a Woman sullen sits,</l>
                              <l>And wants Breath to conquer Reason.</l>
                              <l>Always these affected Fits</l>
                              <l>Are in Season:</l>
                              <l>Since 'tis in her Disposition,</l>
                              <l>Make her be her own Physician.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nay, dear Madam, you shall not go without me.—Though
I have my particular Reasons to be out of Humour, I cannot
be deficient in Good-manners.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>I know they would take it mortally ill if they thought
your Complaisance had put yourself under the least Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>straint.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I can't forgive myself for my Behaviour.—You must
excuse me, Madam; for Absence in Conversation is an Incivi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lity
that I am but too liable to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>You know we all rally you upon your being in Love,
as that is one of its most infallible Symptoms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="7" facs="13"/>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>I charge you, upon my Blessing;—as you expect Fame,
Glory, Immortality, obey me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[To <hi>Achilles. Thetis</hi> kisses him. Exeunt <hi>Achilles</hi> and <hi>Artemona.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thetis.</speaker>
                     <p>As for his Face, his Air, his Figure, I am not under the least
Apprehension; all my Concern is from the Impetuosity of his
Temper.—Yet, after all, why <hi>shou'd</hi> I fear a Discovery?
for Women have the same Passions, though they employ 'em
upon different Objects.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR V. A Minuet.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Man's so touchy, a Word that's injurious</l>
                              <l>Wakes his Honour; he's sudden as Fire.</l>
                              <l>Woman kindles, and is no less furious</l>
                              <l>For her Trifles, or any Desire.</l>
                              <l>Man is <gap resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters" rend="content:••">
                                    <desc>illegible</desc>
                                 </gap>sty,</l>
                              <l>Or sour, or resty,</l>
                              <l>If balk'd of Honours, or Pow'r, or Pelf.</l>
                              <l>Woman's Passions can no less molest ye,</l>
                              <l>And all for Reasons she keeps to her self.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                     <p>He is sudden, he is impatient. What then? Are Women less
so? Ask almost all Servants what they know of their Mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tresses.
—He is wilful, testy, and untractable. Can't
<pb n="8" facs="14"/>
Thousands of Husbands say as much of their Wives? Then as
for his Obstinacy—that can never shew him less a Woman.
But he hath not that Command of his Tongue I cou'd wish
him: He is too vehement, too severe in his Expressions. In this
Particular, indeed, few Women take equal Liberties to one a<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nother's
Faces, but they make ample Amends for it behind each
other's Backs; so that, with all these Infirmities of Man, he may
with the least Conduct very well pass for a fine-spirited Woman.
—This Reflexion hath cur'd my Anxiety, and will make me
believe him secure.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>Thetis, Lycomedes.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis with the utmost Gratitude that I return your Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jesty
Thanks for the Honours and hospitable Favours shewn to
me and my Daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>You wou'd oblige me more, Madam, if your Af<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fairs
wou'd allow you to accept 'em longer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>I have presum'd, Sir, to trespass further on your Ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nerosity,
in leaving my Daughter under your Protection.—I
hope <hi>Pyrrha</hi>'s Behaviour will deserve it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR VI. To you, my Dear, and to no other.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <l>Must then, alas, the fondest Mother</l>
                              <l>Desert her Child?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l> — Ah, why this Tear?</l>
                              <l>She'll in <hi>Theaspe</hi> find another;</l>
                              <l>In me paternal Love and Care.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Had you taken her with you, my Daughters wou'd have
<pb n="9" facs="15"/>
been miserable beyond Expression. Theirs and her Education
shall be the same.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>I beg you, Sir, not to regard my Gratitude like the com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon
Obligations of Princes; for neither Time nor Interest can
ever cancel it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Affairs of Consequence may require your Presence.
Importunity upon these Occasions is troublesome and unhospi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>table.
—I ask no Questions, Madam, because I choose not
to pry into Secrets.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thet.</speaker>
                     <p>I can only thank, and rely upon your Majesty's Good<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness.
—My Duty to the Queen, Sir, calls me hence to own
my Obligations, and receive her Commands.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Diphilus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lyc.</speaker>
                     <p>The Princess <hi>Calista</hi> hath taken her Leave; she is but
just gone out of the Room.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>That <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> Sir, was a most delicious Piece.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>With all her little vixen Humours, to my Taste she
is infinitely agreeable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Your parting with her, Sir, in this easy manner, is a<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stonishing.
One too so excessively fond of you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Parting with her, <hi>Diphilus!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>But no Prince alive hath so great a Command of his
Passions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear <hi>Diphilus,</hi> let me understand you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>To my Knowledge you might have had her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Can I believe thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>I really thought the Queen began to be a little uneasy,
and, for the Quiet of the Family (since she is gone) I must
own I am heartily glad of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="10" facs="16"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR VII. <hi>John</hi> went suiting unto <hi>Joan.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>How your Patience had been try'd,</l>
                              <l>Had this haughty Dame comply'd!</l>
                              <l>What's a Mistress and a Wife?</l>
                              <l>Joy for Moments; Plague for Life.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not so unhappy, <hi>Diphilus.</hi>—Her Mother hath
left her to my Care.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Just as I wish'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd she had taken her with her!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>It might have been better. For beyond dispute, Sir,
both you and the Queen wou'd have been easier.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Why did she trust her to me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>There cou'd be but one Reason.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot answer for myself.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas upon that very Presumption you was trusted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd I could believe thee!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis an apparent manifest Scheme, Sir, and you
wou'd disappoint both Mother and Daughter if your Maje<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sty
did not betray your Trust.—You love her, Sir, you
say.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>To Distraction, <hi>Diphilus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>And was the betraying a Trust ever as yet an Obstacle
to that Passion? What wou'd you have a Mother do more
upon such an Occasion? Ladies of her Rank cannot transact
an Affair of this kind, but with some <hi>Decorum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>But you can never suppose <hi>Pyrrha</hi> knows any thing
of the Matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Why not, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>From me she cannot; for I have never as yet made
any downright Professions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>There lies the true Cause of her Thoughtfulness; 'tis
nothing but Anxiety, for fear her Scheme shou'd not take place;
for, no doubt, her Mother hath instructed her not to be too for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward,
to make you more so.—Believe me, Sir, you will have
<pb n="11" facs="17"/>
no Difficulties in this Affair, but those little ones that every Wo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>man
knows how to practise to quicken a Lover.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Be it as it will, <hi>Diphilus,</hi> I must have her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Had I been acquainted with your Pleasure sooner, your
Majesty by this time had been tir'd of her.—How happy shall
I make her, if I may have the Honour of your Majesty's Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mands
to hint your Passion to her!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Never did Eyes receive a Passion with such Coldness,
such Indifference!</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR VIII. Groom's Complaint.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Whene'er my Looks have spoke Desire,</l>
                              <l>I sigh'd, I gaz'd in vain;</l>
                              <l>No Glance confess'd her secret Fire;</l>
                              <l>And Eyes the Heart explain.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Though 'tis what she wishes, what she longs for, what
she sighs for, Respect and Awe are a Restraint upon her Eyes
as well as Tongue. I have often told you, Sir, she dares not
understand you; she dares not believe herself so happy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>This Ring, <hi>Diphilus.</hi>—I must leave the rest to
your Discretion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>There may be a manner in giving it her, a little Hint
or so—but the Present will speak for itself; 'tis the most
successful Advocate of Love, and never wants an Interpre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Say every thing for me, <hi>Diphilus</hi>; for I feel I cannot
speak for myself.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Cou'd I be as successful in all my other Negotiations!
Yet there may be Difficulties, for, if I mistake not, the Lady
hath something of the Coquette about her; and what Self-Denial
will not those Creatures suffer to give a Lover Anxie<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty!</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="12" facs="18"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR IX. O'er Bogie.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Observe the wanton Kitten's Play,</l>
                              <l>Whene'er a Mouse appears;</l>
                              <l>You there the true Coquette survey</l>
                              <l>In all her flirting Airs:</l>
                              <l>Now pawing,</l>
                              <l>Now clawing,</l>
                              <l>Now in fond Embrace,</l>
                              <l>Till 'midst her Freaks,</l>
                              <l>He from her breaks,</l>
                              <l>Steals off, and bilks the Chase.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear <hi>Diphilus,</hi> what do you mean? I never saw a
Woman so little of that Character.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon me, Sir; your Situation is such that you can
never see what Mankind really are. In your Presence every
one is acting a Part; no one is himself, and was it not for the
Eyes and Tongues of your faithful Servants how little wou'd
your Subjects be known to you! Though she is so prim and
<pb n="13" facs="19"/>
reserv'd before you, she is never at a Loss for Airs to draw all
the young flirting Lords of the Court about her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Beauty must always have its Followers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>If I mistake not, General <hi>Ajax</hi> too (who is sent to so<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>licit
your Quota for the <hi>Trojan</hi> War) hath another Solicitation
more at heart.—But suppose she had ten thousand Lov<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ers;
a Woman's prevalent Passion is Ambition, which must an<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>swer
your Ends.—The Queen is coming this way, and her
Commands may detain me.—I go, Sir, to make <hi>Pyrrha</hi> the
happiest Creature upon Earth.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Theaspe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I think the Princess <hi>Calista</hi> might as well have taken
her Daughter with her.—That Girl is so intolerably forward,
that I cannot imagine such Conversation can possibly be of any
great Advantage to your Daughter's Education.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>You seem of late to have taken an Aversion to the
Girl. She hath Spirit and Vivacity, but not more than is be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>coming
the Sex; and I never saw any thing in her Behaviour
but what was extremely modest.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heaven's sake, Sir, allow me to believe my own
Eyes. Her Forwardness must give the Fellows some Encou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ragement,
or there wou'd not be that intolerable Flutter about
her.—But perhaps she hath some Reasons to be more upon
her Guard before you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>How can you be so unreasonably censorious?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I can see her Faults, Sir. I see her as a Woman sees
a Woman. The Men, it seems, think the aukward Creature
handsome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="20"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR X. <hi>Dutch</hi> Skipper. First Part.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>When a Woman's censorious,</l>
                              <l>And attacks the meritorious;</l>
                              <l>In the Scandal she shews her own malicious Thought.</l>
                              <l>If real Guilt she blames,</l>
                              <l>Then Pride her Heart inflames;</l>
                              <l>And she fansies she's better for another's Fault.</l>
                              <l>Thus seeking to disclose</l>
                              <l>The Slips of Friends and Foes,</l>
                              <l>By her Envy she does herself alone expose.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Nay, dear Child, your attacking her in this peevish way can
be nothing but downright Antipathy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, dear Sir, your defending her in this feeling
manner can be nothing but downright Partiality.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I own my self partial to Distress, and I see her in
that Circumstance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>But there are other Reasons that may make a Man
partial.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="15" facs="21"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XI. <hi>Dutch</hi> Skipper. Second Part.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>As you, Sir, are my Husband, no doubt you're prone</l>
                              <l>To turn each new Face</l>
                              <l>To a Wife's Disgrace;</l>
                              <l>And for no other Cause but that she's your own;</l>
                              <l>Nay, Sir, 'tis an evident Case.</l>
                              <l>'Tis strange that all Husbands should prove so blind,</l>
                              <l>That a Wife's real Merits they ne'er can find,</l>
                              <l>Tho' they strike all the rest of Mankind.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>How can you be so ridiculous? By these Airs, Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dam,
you would have me believe you are jealous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thes.</speaker>
                     <p>Whence had you this contemptible Opinion of me?
Jealous! If I was so I have a Spirit above owning it. I wou'd
never heighten your Pleasure by letting you have the Satisfac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion
of knowing I was uneasy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me beg you, my Dear, to keep your Temper.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Since I have been so unguarded as to own it; give me
leave to tell you, Sir, that was I of a lower Rank it wou'd
keep you in some Awe, because you wou'd then know I cou'd
take my Revenge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>You forget your Duty, Child.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>There is a Duty too due from a Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>How can you give way to these Passions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Because you give way to yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>But to be so unreasonably jealous!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Unreasonably! Wou'd it were so!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="22"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XII. Black Joke.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Then must I bear eternal Strife,</l>
                              <l>Both Night and Day put in mind of a Wife,</l>
                              <l>By her Pouts, Spleen, and passionate Airs!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                              <l>D'ye think I'll bear eternal Slight,</l>
                              <l>And not complain when I'm robb'd of my Right?</l>
                              <l>Call you this, Sir, but whimsical Fears?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Can nought then still this raging Storm?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                              <l>Yes. What you promis'd if you wou'd perform.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <pb n="17" facs="23"/>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Pr'ythee teaze me no more.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                              <l>I can never give o'er,</l>
                              <l>Till I find you as fond and as kind as before.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Will you ne'er ask</l>
                              <l>A possible Task?</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Wou'd you have me so unhospitable as to deny her my Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tection?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not, Sir, that I presume to controul you in your
Pleasures.—Yet you might, methinks, have shew'd that Ten<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>derness
for me to have acted with a little more Reserve. Wo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>men
are not so blind as Husbands imagine.—Were there no
other Circumstances,—your Coolness to me, your Indifference.
—How I despise my self for this Confession!—Pardon me,
Sir, Love made me thus indiscreet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XIII. Ye Shepherds and Nymphs.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>
                                 <stage>
                                    <hi>Theaspe</hi> weeping.</stage>
                              </l>
                              <l>O <hi>Love,</hi> plead my Pardon, nor plead it in vain;</l>
                              <l>'Twas you that was jealous, 'twas you was in Pain;</l>
                              <l>Yet why should you speak? To what Purpose or End?</l>
                              <l>I must be unhappy if Love can offend.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yet was ever a Design of this kind so manifest, so bare-fac'd!</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="18" facs="24"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XIV. The Goddesses.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>
                                 <stage>
                                    <hi>Theaspe</hi> angry.</stage>
                              </l>
                              <l>To what a Pitch is Man profuse,</l>
                              <l>And all for ostentatious Pride!</l>
                              <l>Ev'n Misses are not kept for Use,</l>
                              <l>But for mere Show, and nought beside.</l>
                              <l>For might a Wife speak out,</l>
                              <l>She cou'd prove beyond all doubt,</l>
                              <l>With more than enough he was supply'd.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Princess <hi>Calista</hi> hath shewn an uncommon Confidence
in your Majesty. The Woman, no doubt, depends upon it,
that her Daughter's Charms are not to be resisted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, dear Child, don't be scandalous.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XV. <hi>Joan</hi>'s Placket.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Reputations back'd and hew'd,</l>
                              <l>Can never be mended again;</l>
                              <l>Yet nothing stints the tattling Prude,</l>
                              <l>Who joys in another's Pain.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="19" facs="25"/>
Thus while she rends</l>
                              <l>Both Foes and Friends,</l>
                              <l>By both she's torn in twain.</l>
                              <l>Reputations hack'd and hew'd,</l>
                              <l>Can never be mended again.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>You are in so particular a manner oblig'd to her, that
I am not surpris'd at your taking her Part.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>But, dear Madam, why at present is all this violent
Fluster?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Ask your own Heart, ask your own Conduct. Those
can best inform you.—'Twou'd have been more obliging if
<hi>Pyrrha</hi> and you had kept me out of this impudent Secret.—
You know, Sir, I have Reason.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>If one Woman's Virtue depended upon another's
Suspicions, where shou'd we find a Woman of common Mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>desty!
Indeed, Child, I think you injure her; I believe her
virtuous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>When a Man hath ruin'd a Woman, he thinks him<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self
oblig'd in Honour to stand up for her Reputation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>If you will believe only your own unaccountable
Suspicions, and are determin'd not to hear Reason, I must leave
you to your perverse Humours.—What wou'd you have me
say? What wou'd you have me do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Shew your Hospitality (as you call it) to me, and put
that Creature out of the Palace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I have a greater Regard to yours and my own Quiet,
than ever to comply with the extravagant Passions of a jealous
Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>You have taken then your Resolutions, I find; and I
am sentenc'd to Neglect.—Did ever a Woman marry but
with the Probability of having at least one Man in her Power?
—What a wretched Wife am I! </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Weeps.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Jealousy from a Wife, even to a Man of Quality, is
now look'd upon as Ill-manners, though the Affair be never so
publick.—But without a Cause!—I beg you, Madam, to
say no more upon this Subject.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Though you, Sir, may think her fit Company for
you; methinks the very same Reasons might tell you that
she is not so very reputable a Companion for your Daugh<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Since a passionate Woman will only believe herself,
I must leave you, Madam, to enjoy your Obstinacy. I know
but that way of putting an end to the Dispute.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="20" facs="26"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XVI. We've cheated the Parson, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Though Woman's glib Tongue, when her Passions are fir'd,</l>
                              <l>Eternally go, a Man's Ear can be tir'd.</l>
                              <l>Since Woman will have both her Word and her Way,</l>
                              <l>I yield to your Tongue; but my Reason obey.</l>
                              <l>I obey,</l>
                              <l>Nothing say,</l>
                              <l>Since Woman will have both her Word and her Way.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>Theaspe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd I had been more upon the Reserve! But Hus<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bands
are horridly provoking; they know the Frailty of the
Sex, and never fail to take the Advantage of our Passions to
make us expose our selves by Contradiction.—<hi>Artemona.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
                  <stage>Theaspe, Artemona.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that Creature, that (what do you call her) that
Princess gone?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Why did not she take that awkward Thing, her
Daughter, with her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="21" facs="27"/>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>The Advantages she mighr receive in her Education,
might be an Inducement to leave her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Might <hi>that</hi> be an Inducement?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Besides, in her present Circumstance, it might be in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>convenient
to take her Daughter with her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Can't you find out any <hi>other</hi> Reason for leaving
her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Courtesy, Madam; your Hospitality.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>No <hi>other</hi> Reason!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>No other Reason?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd I cou'd believe there was no other!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not for me to pry into your Majesty's Secrets.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I hate a Girl that is so intolerably forward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>I never observ'd any thing but those little Liberties that
Girls of her Age will take, when they are among themselves.
—Perhaps those particular Distinctions the Princesses shew her,
may have made her too familiar.—I am not, Madam, an Ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vocate
for her Behaviour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>A Look so very audacious! Now the filthy Men,
who love every thing that is impudent, call that Spirit.—
But there are, <hi>Artemona,</hi> some particular Distinctions from a
certain Person, who of late hath been very particular to me,
that might <hi>indeed</hi> make her too familiar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Heaven forbid!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>How precarious is the Happiness of a Wife, when it
is in the Power of every new Face to destroy it!—Now,
dear <hi>Artemona,</hi> tell me sincerely, don't you, from what
you yourself have observed, think I have Reason to be un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>easy?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>That I have observ'd!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear <hi>Artemona,</hi> don't frighten thyself.—I am not
accusing you but talking to you as a Friend.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="22" facs="28"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XVII. Fairy Elves.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <sp>
                                 <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                                 <l>O guard your Hours from Care,</l>
                                 <l>Of Jealousy beware;</l>
                                 <l>For she with fancy'd Sprites,</l>
                                 <l>Herself torments and frights.</l>
                                 <l>Thus she frets, and pines, and grieves,</l>
                                 <l>Raising Fears that she believes.</l>
                              </sp>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I hate myself too for having so much Condescension
and Humility as to be jealous. 'Tis flattering the Man that
uses one ill; and 'tis wanting the natural Pride that belongs to
the Sex. What a wretched, mean, contemptible Figure is a
jealous Woman! How have I expos'd myself!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majesty is safe in the Confidence repos'd in me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>That is not the Case, <hi>Artemona. Lycomedes</hi> knows
I am unhappy. I have own'd it, and was so unguarded as to
accuse him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon mere Suspicion only?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="23" facs="29"/>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Beyond Dispute he loves her. I know it, <hi>Artemona</hi>;
and can one imagine that Girl hath Virtue enough to withstand
such a Proposal?</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XVIII. <hi>Moll Peatly.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>All Hearts are a little frail</l>
                              <l>When Temptation is rightly apply'd.</l>
                              <l>What can Shame or Fear avail</l>
                              <l>When we sooth both Ambition and Pride?</l>
                              <l>All Women have Power in view;</l>
                              <l>Then there's Pleasure to tempt her too.</l>
                              <l>Such a sure Attack there's no defying,</l>
                              <l>No denying;</l>
                              <l>Since complying</l>
                              <l>Gives her another's Due.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                     <p>—I can't indeed (if you mean that) positively affirm that he hath
yet had her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Then it may be still only Suspicion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I have trusted too my Daughter <hi>Deidamia</hi> with my
Weakness; that she, by her Intimacies and Friendship with
<hi>Pyrrha,</hi> may get into her Secrets. In short, I have plac'd her
as my Spy about her.—That Girl (out of Good-nature, and
to prevent Family-disputes) may deceive me. She insists upon
it that I have nothing to fear from <hi>Pyrrha</hi>; and is so positive in
this Opinion, that she offers to be answerable for her Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then, Madam, will you still believe your own
Jealousies?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="24" facs="30"/>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>All I say is, that <hi>Deidamia</hi> may deceive me; for
whatever is in the Affair, 'tis impossible but she must know
it; I have order'd it so that she is scarce ever from her;
they have one and the same Bed-Chamber; yet such is my
Distemper, that I suspect every Body, and can only believe
my own Imaginations.—There must be some Reason that
<hi>Deidamia</hi> hath not been with me this Morning.—I am im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>patient
to see her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XIX. <hi>John Anderson</hi> my <hi>Jo.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                              <l>Let Jealousy no longer</l>
                              <l>A fruitless Search pursue;</l>
                              <l>You make his Flame the Stronger,</l>
                              <l>And wake Resentment too.</l>
                              <l>This self-tormenting Care give o'er;</l>
                              <l>For all you can obtain</l>
                              <l>Is, what was only Doubt before,</l>
                              <l>To change for real Pain.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>The End of the First Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <pb n="25" facs="31"/>
                  <head>ACT II. SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Diphilus, Achilles.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I Am very sensible, my Lord, of the particular Honours
that are shewn me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Honours, Madam! <hi>Lycomedes</hi> is still more
particular. How happy must that Woman be whom he re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spects!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you mean, my Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Let this speak both for him and me: The Present is
worthy him to give, and you to receive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I have too many Obligations already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis in your Power, Madam, to return 'em all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus I return 'em. And, if you dare be honest, tell
him this Ring had been a more <hi>honourable</hi> Present to <hi>Theaspe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XX. Abroad as I was walking.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <l>
                              <stage>[Offering the Ring a second time.]</stage>
                           </l>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                              <l>Such Homage to her Beauty,</l>
                              <l>What Coyness can reject?</l>
                              <l>Accept, as 'tis your Duty,</l>
                              <l>The Tribute with Respect.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="26" facs="32"/>
What more can Beauty gain thee?</l>
                              <l>With Love I offer Power.</l>
                              <l>What Shame can ever stain thee,</l>
                              <l>Restrain thee,</l>
                              <l>Or pain thee,</l>
                              <l>When blest with such a Dower?</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis but an Earnest, Madam, of future Favours.—
When <hi>Lycomedes</hi> his Power is yours, I intreat your Highness
not to forget your Servant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I shall remember thee with Contempt and Abhorrence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>I beg you, Madam, to consider your present Situa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion.
—This uncommon Distinction requires a softer Answer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I shall give no other, my Lord.—I dare say, <hi>Diphilus,</hi>
you think yourself highly honour'd by your present Negotia<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion.
—Is there no Office too mean for Ambition?—Was you
not a Man of Quality, was you not a Favourite, the World,
my Lord, wou'd call you a Pimp, a Pandar, a Bawd, for this
very honourable Proposal of yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>What an unmerciful Weapon is a Woman's Tongue!—
I beg your Highness to confine yourself within the Bounds of
common Civility, and to consider who I am.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I do consider it, <hi>Diphilus,</hi> and that makes thee a thou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sand
times the more contemptible.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XXI. Butter'd Pease.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Shou'd the Beast of the noblest Race</l>
                              <l>Act the Brute of the lowest Class;</l>
                              <l>Tell me, which do you think more base,</l>
                              <l>Or the Lion or the Ass?</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="27" facs="33"/>
Boast not then of thy Rank or State;</l>
                              <l>That but shews thee the meaner Slave.</l>
                              <l>Take thy due then of Scorn and Hate,</l>
                              <l>As thou'rt but the greater Knave.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Though the Sex have the Privilege of unlimited Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pression,
and that a Woman's Words are not to be resented;
yet a Lady, Madam, may be ill-bred. Ladies too are generally
passionate enough without a Provocation, so that a Reply at
present would be unnecessary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Are such the Friends of Power?—How unhappy are
Princes to have their Passions so very readily put in Execution,
that they seldom know the Benefit of Reflexion! Go, and for
once make your Report faithfully and without Flattery.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>Diphilus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>This Girl is so excessively ill-bred, and such an ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rant
Termagant, that I cou'd as soon fall in love with a Tigress.
She hath a handsom Face, 'tis true, but in her Temper she is
a very Fury.—But <hi>Lycomedes</hi> likes her; and 'tis not for me to
dispute either his Taste or Pleasure.—Notwithstanding she is
such a Spit-fire, 'tis my Opinion the thing may still do: Things
of this Nature shou'd be always transacted in Person, for there
are Women so ridiculously half-modest, that they are asham'd
in Words to consent to what (when a Man comes to the
Point) they will make no Difficulties to comply with.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Diphilus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, <hi>Diphilus,</hi> in what manner did she receive my
Present?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis my Opinion, Sir, that she will accept it only
from your Hands. From me she absolutely refuses it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="34"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXII. Come open the Door sweet <hi>Betty.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>What, must I remain in Anguish?</l>
                              <l>And did not her Eyes consent?</l>
                              <l>No Sigh, not a Blush, nor Languish</l>
                              <l>That promis'd a kind Event!</l>
                              <l>It must be all Affectation,</l>
                              <l>The Tongue hath her Heart bely'd;</l>
                              <l>That oft hath withstood Temptation,</l>
                              <l>When ev'ry thing else comply'd.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>How did she receive you? Did you watch her Eyes?
What was her Behaviour when you first told her I lov'd her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>She seem'd to be desperately disappointed that you had
not told her so your self.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>But when you press'd it to her—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>She had all the Resentment and Fury of the most com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plying
Prude.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>But did not she soften upon Consideration?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>She seem'd to take it mortally ill of me, that my
meddling in the Affair had delay'd your Majesty's Application.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>What no favourable Circumstance!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, I was not in the least surpris'd at her Behaviour.
Love at second-hand to a Lady of her warm Constitution! It was
a Disappointment, Sir; and she cou'd not but treat it accord<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ingly.
—Whatever was my Opinion, 'twas my Duty, Sir, to
obey you, but I found just the Reception I expected. Apply
to her your self, Sir; answer her Wishes, and (if I know any
thing of Woman) she will then answer yours, and behave her<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self
as she ought.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>But, dear <hi>Diphilus,</hi> I grow more and more impa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tient.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="29" facs="35"/>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>That too by this time is her Case—To save the Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pearances
of Virtue, the most easy Woman expects a little
gentle Compulsion, and to be allow'd the Decency of a little
feeble Resistance. For the Quiet of her own Conscience a
Woman may insist upon acting the Part of Modesty, and you
must comply with her Scruples.—You will have no more trou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble
but what will heighten the Pleasure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pyrrha!</hi>—This is beyond my Hopes.—<hi>Diphilus,</hi>
lay your Hand upon my Breast. Feel how my Heart flutters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Did <hi>Pyrrha</hi> feel these Assurances of Love she wou'd
not appear so thoughtful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deidamia</hi> too not with her!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>She is with the Queen, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>My other Daughters, who seem less fond of her, are
in the Garden; so all's safe.—Leave me, <hi>Diphilus,</hi> and let
none, upon Pain of my Displeasure, presume to intrude.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Achilles.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> my dear Child, why so thoughtful?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoughts may not be so respectful; they may be too
familiar, too friendly, too true: And who about you presumes
to communicate 'em? Words and Forms only are for your
Ear, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>You know, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> you was never receiv'd upon
the Foot of Ceremony, but Friendship; so that it wou'd be more
respectful if you was less shy and less reserv'd.—'Tis your Be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>haviour,
<hi>Pyrrha,</hi> that keeps me at a Distance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>If I was wanting, Sir, either in Duty to you or my self,
my own Heart wou'd be the first to reproach me.—Your Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jesty's
Generosity is too solicitous upon my Account; and your
Courtesy and Affability may even now detain you from Affairs
of Importance.—If you have no Commands, Sir, the Princesses
expect me in the Garden.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, positively, my dear <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> you shall not go.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>But why, Sir?—For Heaven's Sake, what hath set
you a trembling?—I fear, Sir, you are out of Order.—Who
waits there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I did not call, <hi>Pyrrha.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me then, Sir, know your Commands.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="36"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXIII. Altro Giorno in compagnia.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>If my Passion want explaining,</l>
                              <l>This way turn and read my Eyes;</l>
                              <l>These will tell thee, without feigning,</l>
                              <l>What in Words I must disguise.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Why do you fix your Eyes so intensely upon me?—Speak
your Pleasure, speak to me then.—Why am I seiz'd?—
Spare me, Sir, for I have a Temper that can't bear Provocation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I know there are a thousand necessary Affectations
of Modesty, which Women, in Decency to themselves, practise
with common Lovers before Compliance.—But my Passion,
<hi>Pyrrha,</hi> deserves some Distinction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I beg you then, Sir, don't lay violent Hands upon me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>The Present you refus'd from <hi>Diphilus</hi> accept from
me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Why will you persist?—Nay, dear Sir, I can't answer
for my Passions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not <hi>Diphilus,</hi> but I give it you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>That <hi>Diphilus,</hi> Sir, is your Enemy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis I that offer it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Your very worst Enemy, your Flatterer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>You shou'd strive, Child, to conquer these extrava<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gant
Passions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>How I despise that Fellow! that Pimp, that Pandar!</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="31" facs="37"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XXIV. Trip to the Landry.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>How unhappy are the Great,</l>
                              <l>Thus begirt with servile Slaves!</l>
                              <l>Such with Praise your Reason cheat.</l>
                              <l>Flatt'rers are the meanest Knaves.</l>
                              <l>They, in Friendship's Guise accost you;</l>
                              <l>False in all they say or do.</l>
                              <l>When these Wretches have ingross'd you,</l>
                              <l>Who's the Slave, Sir, they or you?</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this reproachful Language, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> befitting my
Presence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, dear Sir, don't worry me. By <hi>Jove,</hi> you'll pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>voke
me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Affectation, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> is intolerable. There's
enough of it.—Those Looks of Aversion are insupportable.—
I will have no struggling.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Then, Sir, I must have no Violence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXV. As I walk'd along <hi>Fleetstreet.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>When the Fort on no Condition</l>
                              <l>Will admit the gen'rous Foe,</l>
                              <l>Parley but delays Submission;</l>
                              <l>We by Storm shou'd lay it low.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="32" facs="38"/>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I am in earnest, Lady.—I will have no trifling, no
coquetting; you may spare those little Arts of Women, for my
Passion is warm and vehement enough without 'em.—Do you
know, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> that Obedience is your Duty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I know my Duty, Sir; and, had it not been for that
Sycophant <hi>Diphilus,</hi> perhaps you had known yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not, Lady, to be aw'd and frighten'd by stern
Looks and Frowns.—Since your obstinate Behaviour then
makes Violence necessary—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>You make Self-preservation, Sir, as necessary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I won't be refus'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXVI. The Lady's New-Year's Gift.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Why such Affectation?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Why this Provocation?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Must I bear Resistance still!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Check your Inclination.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Dare you then deny me?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>You too far may try me.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>Must I then against your Will!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Force shall never ply me.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Never was such a Termagant!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>By <hi>Jove,</hi> never was such an Insult!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you?—Dare you?—Never was such
Strength!—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Achilles</hi> pushes him from him with great Violence, and
throws him down.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Desist then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Audacious Fury, know you what you have done?—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="39"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXVII. Puppet-Show Trumpet Tune.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <stage>[<hi>Achilles</hi> holding <hi>Lycomedes</hi> down.]</stage>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>What Heart hath not Courage, by Force assail'd,</l>
                              <l>To brave the most desperate Fight?</l>
                              <l>'Tis Justice and Virtue that hath prevail'd;</l>
                              <l>Power must yield to Right.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Am I so ignominiously to be got the better of!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>You are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>By a Woman!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>You now, Sir, find you had acted a greater Part, if (in
Spite of your Flatterers) you had got the better of your own
Passions.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Achilles, Diphilus, Courtiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>An Attempt upon the King's Life!—The Guards!
where are the Guards?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>Such an open, bare-fac'd Assassination!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They seize <hi>Achilles,</hi> and raise <hi>Lycomedes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>And by a Woman too!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>Where are your Wounds, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>Take the Dagger from her, that she do no farther
Mischief.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>The Dagger! Where? What Dagger?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Court.</speaker>
                     <p>You will find it some where or other conceal'd;
examine her, search her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Save your Zeal, Sirs, for times of real Danger. Let
<hi>Lycomedes</hi> accuse me.—He knows my Offence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="34" facs="40"/>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>How have I expos'd my self!—<hi>Diphilus,</hi> bid these
over-officious Friends leave me, and, as they value my Favour,
that they say nothing of what they have seen.— <stage>[<hi>Diphilus</hi>
talks apart with the Courtiers, who go out.]</stage> Though the Insult
from any other Person had been unpardonable; there are ways
that you, Madam, might still take to reconcile me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Self-defence, Sir, is the Privilege of Mankind. I know
your Power, but as I have offended no Law I rely upon your
Justice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twou'd be safer, Madam, to rely on your own
future Behaviour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Who was the Aggressor, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Beauty, Inclination, Love. If you will merit Fa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vour
you know the Conditions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XXVIII. Old King Cole.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>No more be coy;</l>
                              <l>Give a Loose to Joy,</l>
                              <l>And let Love for thy Pardon sue.</l>
                              <l>A Glance cou'd all my Rage destroy,</l>
                              <l>And light up my Flame anew.</l>
                              <l>For though a Man can stand at Bay</l>
                              <l>Against a Woman's Will;</l>
                              <l>And keep, amid the loudest Fray,</l>
                              <l>His Resolution still:</l>
                              <l>Yet when consenting Smiles accost,</l>
                              <l>The Man in her Arms is lost.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <pb n="35" facs="41"/>
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Achilles, Diphilus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>If your Resentment wants only the Show of Justice;
let this <hi>honourable</hi> Man here be my Accuser; it may be neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary
for him to trump up a horrid Conspiracy to skreen his own
infamous Practices.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majesty hath had too much Confidence in this
Woman. The Lives of Kings are sacred, and the Matter (tri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vial
as it seems) deserves further Inquiry.—There must be
some secret villainous Design in this Affair.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>And are not you, <hi>Diphilus,</hi> conscious of that secret vil<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lainous
Design?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis an Offence, Sir, that is not to be pardon'd. Your
Dignity, Sir, calls upon you (notwithstanding your Partiality
to her) to make her an Example. There must be Things of
Consequence that we are still ignorant of; and she ought to
undergo the severest Examination.—My Zeal for your Ser<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vice,
Sir, was never as yet at a loss for Witnesses upon these
Occasions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[To <hi>Lycomedes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't you see the Queen coming this Way? Have
done with this Discourse, dear <hi>Diphilus,</hi> and leave me.—
Wou'd I cou'd forget this ridiculous Affair! For the present;
<hi>Pyrrha,</hi> I trust you to return to the Ladies; though (consider<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
your passionate Temper) I have little Reason to rely on
your Discretion.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Theaspe, Deidamia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I thought I had heard <hi>Pyrrha</hi>'s Voice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>A jealous Woman's Thoughts are her own and her
Husband's eternal Plague; so I beg you, my Dear, say no
more of her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>And have I no reason but my own Thoughts, my
Liege?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="42"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXIX. Dicky's Walk in Dr. <hi>Faustus.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                              <l>What give o'er!</l>
                              <l>I must and will complain.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>You plague us both in vain.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                              <l>You wont then hear a Wife!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>I must, it seems, for Life.</l>
                              <l>Teaze no more.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                              <l>Nay, Sir, you know 'tis true,</l>
                              <l>That 'tis to her I owe my Due.</l>
                              <l>No Thanks to you!</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <p>It behoves Kings, Sir, to have the severest Guard upon their
Actions; for as their great ones are trumpeted by Fame, their
little ones are as certainly and as widely convey'd from Ear
to Ear by a Whisper.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>These chimerical Jealousies, Madam, may provoke
my Patience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Chimerical Jealousies!—And do you really, Sir,
think your ignominious Affair is still a Secret?—Am I to be
ignorant of a Thing that is already whisper'd every where?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="43"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXX. Puddings and Pyes.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                              <l>The Slips of a Husband you Wives</l>
                              <l>Will never forget:</l>
                              <l>Your Tongue for the Course of our Lives</l>
                              <l>Is never in debt.</l>
                              <l>'Tis now funning,</l>
                              <l>And then dunning;</l>
                              <l>Intent on our Follies alone,</l>
                              <l>'Tis so fully employ'd that you never can think of your own.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>My Suspicions have, <hi>indeed,</hi> wrong'd <hi>Pyrrha.</hi>—How I
respect and honour that Girl!—<hi>Deidamia,</hi> that honourable,
that virtuous Creature <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> well deserves both your Friend<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ship
and mine.—As soon as you have found her bring her
to me, that I may acknowledge the Merits she hath to me.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
                  <stage>Lycomedes, Theaspe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>After the Repulse and Disgrace you have very justly
met with, you might with Reason censure me for want of Duty
and Respect shou'd I upbraid you.—'Tis past; and if you
will never again put me in mind, I choose to forget it.—Yet,
wou'd you reward Virtue, and had you any Regard for my
Quiet.—</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="38" facs="44"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XXXI. My Dilding, my Dalding.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Ah! shou'd you ever find her</l>
                              <l>Complying and kinder;</l>
                              <l>Though now you have resign'd her;</l>
                              <l>What then must ensue!</l>
                              <l>Your Flame, though now 'tis over,</l>
                              <l>Again will recover;</l>
                              <l>You'll prove as fond a Lover,</l>
                              <l>As I'm now of you.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>What wou'd you have me do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I wou'd have you distrust your self and remove the
Temptation.—I have long had it at Heart to find a Match
for my Nephew <hi>Periphas,</hi> and I really think we can never meet
with a more deserving Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Whatever Scheme you have for her, <hi>I</hi> shall not in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terfere
with you.—I have had enough of her termagant Hu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mours;
she hath not the common Softness of the Sex.—
'Tis my Opinion, that <hi>Periphas</hi> will not find himself much
oblig'd to you; for the Man that marties her must either con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quer
his own Passions, or hers, and one of 'em (according to
my Observation) is not to be conquer'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Marriage, Sir, hath broke many a Woman's Spirit;
and that will be only his Affair.—When he takes her with
him, your own Family at least will be easy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Presence just now wou'd be shocking.—I cou'd
not stand the Shame and Confusion.—I see her, and <hi>Deida<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mia</hi>
with her.—Do with her as you please; you have my
Consent.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="scene">
                  <pb n="39" facs="45"/>
                  <head>SCENE IX.</head>
                  <stage>Theaspe, Deidamia, Achilles.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>The Character <hi>Deidamia</hi> hath given of you, and your
own Behaviour, Child, have so charm'd me, that I think I ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver
can sufficiently reward your Merits.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deidamia</hi>'s Friendship may make her partial.—My
only Merit, Madam, is Gratitude.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>To convince you of the Opinion I have of you—But
I must first ask you a Question—Don't you think, Lady
<hi>Pyrrha,</hi> that my Nephew <hi>Periphas</hi> is very agreeable?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>That Impatience of his, to serve as a Volunteer with the
Troops of <hi>Lycomedes</hi> at the Siege of <hi>Troy,</hi> is becoming his
Birth.—So much Fire, and so much Spirit!—I don't wonder
your Majesty is fond of him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>But I am sure, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> you must think his Person
agreeable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>No Woman alive can dispute it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't know, every way, so deserving a young Man;
and I have that Influence upon him, and at the same time that
Regard for him, that I would have him happy.—Don't think,
Child, that I wou'd make him happy at your Expence; for,
knowing him, I know you will be so.—Was the Princess <hi>Ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lista</hi>
here, 'tis a Match she cou'd not disapprove of; therefore let
that be no Obstacle, for every thing, in regard to her, I take up<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on
my self.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd you make me the Obstacle to his Glory? Par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>don
me, Madam, I know my self undeserving.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="40" facs="46"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XXXII. How happy are you and I.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>First let him for Honour roam,</l>
                              <l>And martial Fame obtain:</l>
                              <l>Then (if he shou'd come Home)</l>
                              <l>Perhaps I may explain.</l>
                              <l>Since then alone the Hero's Deeds</l>
                              <l>Can make my Heart give way;</l>
                              <l>'Till <hi>Ilion</hi> falls and <hi>Hector</hi> bleeds,</l>
                              <l>I must my Choice delay.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> I won't take these romantick Notions
of yours for an Answer.—<hi>Deidamia</hi> is so much your Friend,
that, I am sure, she must be happy with this Alliance; so, while
I make the Proposal to my Nephew, I leave you two to talk
over the Affair together.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE X.</head>
                  <stage>Deidamia, Achilles.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Was there ever a Man in so whimsical a Circumstance!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Was there ever a Woman in so happy and so unhappy
a one as mine!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Why did I submit? why did I plight my Faith thus in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>famously
to conceal my self?—What is become of my
Honour?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah <hi>Pyrrha, Pyrrha,</hi> what is become of mine!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>When shall I behave my self as a Man!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd you had never behav'd yourself as one!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="47"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXXIII. Fy gar rub her o'er with Straw.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Think what Anguish tears my Quiet,</l>
                              <l>Since I suffer'd Shame for thee:</l>
                              <l>Man at large may rove and riot,</l>
                              <l>We are bound but you are free.</l>
                              <l>Are thy Vows and Oaths mistaken?</l>
                              <l>See the Birds that wing the Sky;</l>
                              <l>These their Mates have ne'er for saken,</l>
                              <l>'Till their Young at least can fly.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Pester'd and worried thus from every Quarter 'tis im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>possible
much longer to prevent discovery!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear, dear <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> confide in me. Any other Disco<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>very
but to me only wou'd be inevitable Perdition to us both.—
Am I treated like a common Prostitute? Can your Gratitude
(wou'd I might say Love!) refuse to let me know the Man to
whom I owe my Ruin?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>You must rely, my dear Princess, upon my Honour;
for I am not, like a fond weak Husband, to be teaz'd into the
breaking my Resolution.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="48"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXXIV. <hi>Beggar</hi>'s Opera. Hornpipe.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Know that Importunity's in vain.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Can then nothing move thee?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Ask not since Denial gives me Pain.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Think how much I love thee.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>What's a Secret in a Woman's Breast?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Canst thou thus upbraid me!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Let me leave thy Heart and Tongue at rest.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Love then hath betray'd me.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heaven's sake, <hi>Deidamia,</hi> if you regard my Love,
give me Quiet.—Intreaties, Fondness, Tears, Rage and the
whole matrimonial Rhetorick of Woman to gain her Ends are
all thrown away upon me; for, by the Gods, my dear <hi>Deida<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mia,</hi>
I am inexorable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>But, my dear <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> (for you oblige me still to call
you by that Name) only imagine what must be the Consequence
of a Month or two.—Think of my unhappy Condition.—
To save my Shame (if you are a Man of Honour) you must
then come to some Resolution.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>'Till I deserve these Suspicions, <hi>Deidamia,</hi> methinks it
wou'd be more becoming your Professions of Love to spare 'em.
—I have taken my Resolutions; and when the time comes,
you shall know 'em: till then be easy, and press me no farther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="49"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXXV. My time, O ye Muses.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>How happy my Days and how sweet was my Rest,</l>
                              <l>Ere Love with his Passions my Bosom distrest!</l>
                              <l>Now I languish with Sorrow, I doubt and I fear:</l>
                              <l>But Love hath me all when my <hi>Pyrrha</hi> is near.</l>
                              <l>Yet why have I griev'd?—Ye vain Passions adieu!</l>
                              <l>I know my own Heart and I'll think thee as true;</l>
                              <l>And as you know my Heart, 'twou'd be folly to range;</l>
                              <l>For who'd be inconstant to lose by the Change?</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>My Life, my Honour, then I implicitly intrust with
you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="44" facs="50"/>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Who wou'd have the trouble of putting on a Character
that does not naturally belong to him! the Life of a Hypocrite
must be one continual Scene of Anxiety. When shall I appear
as I am, and extricate my self out of this Chain of Perplexities!
—I have no sooner escap'd being ravish'd but I am immediate<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly
to be made a Wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>But, dear <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> for my sake, for your own, have a
particular Regard to your Behaviour till your Resolution is ripe
for Execution.—You now and then take such intolerable
Strides, that I vow you have set me a blushing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Considering my continual Restraint, and how much the
Part I act differs from my Inclinations, I am surpriz'd at my
own Behaviour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXXVI. I am come to your House.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Your Dress, your Conversations,</l>
                              <l>Your Airs of Joy and Pain,</l>
                              <l>All these are Affectations</l>
                              <l>We never can attain.</l>
                              <l>The Sex so often varies,</l>
                              <l>'Tis Nature more than Art:</l>
                              <l>To play their whole Vagaries</l>
                              <l>We must have Woman's Heart.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Swearing too, upon certain Occasions, sounds so
very masculine—an Oath startles me.—Wou'd I cou'd cure
my self of these violent Apprehensions!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>As for that matter, there are Ladies who, in their Pas<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sions,
can take all the Liberties of Speech.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Then too, you very often look so agreeably impudent
upon me, that, let me die, if I have not been mortally afraid
my Sisters wou'd find you out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Impudent! are Women so censorious that Looks can<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>not
escape 'em?—May not one Woman look kindly upon
another without Scandal?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>But such Looks!—Nay, perhaps I may be particular,
and it may be only my own Fears; for (notwithstanding your
<pb n="45" facs="51"/>
Dress) whenever I look upon you, I have always the Image of
a Man before my Eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Do what we will, Love at some Moments will be un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guarded.—But
what shall I do about this <hi>Periphas</hi>?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>His Heart is so set upon the Siege, that I know you
can have but very little Persecution upon his Account.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd I cou'd go with him!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>And cou'd you leave me thus?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you only a womanish Fondness? I thought, <hi>Dei<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>damia,</hi>
you lov'd me. And you cannot truly love and esteem,
if in every Circumstance of Life you have not a just Regard for
my Honour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> don't mention it; the very Thought of it
kills me. You have set my Heart in a most violent Palpitation.
—Let us talk no more upon this disagreeable Subject.—
My Sisters will grow very impatient.—Shou'd we stay longer
together I might again be importunate and ask to know you,
and I had rather bear the eternal Plague of unsatisfied Curiosity,
than give you a Moment's Disquiet.—They are now expect<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
us in the Garden, and, considering my present Circum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stances,
I wou'd not give 'em occasion to be impertinent, for
of late they have been horridly prying and inquisitive.—Let
us go to 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>I envy that <hi>Periphas.</hi> His Honour, his Fame, his
Glory is not shackled by a Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXXVII. The Clarinette.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Ah, why is my Heart so tender!</l>
                              <l>My Honour incites me to Arms:</l>
                              <l>To Love shall I Fame surrender?</l>
                              <l>By Laurels I'll merit thy Charms.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>How can I bear the Reflection</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>I balance; and Honour gives way.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Reward my Love by Affection;</l>
                              <l>I ask thee no more than I pay.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>The End of the Second Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <pb n="46" facs="52"/>
                  <head>ACT III. SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Theaspe, Periphas, Artemona.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theasp.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PEriphas,</hi> I have a Favour to ask of you, and po<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sitively
I will not be refus'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majesty may command.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, Nephew, 'tis for your own good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>To obey your Commands, Madam, must be so.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not, <hi>Periphas,</hi> talking to you as a Queen, but
as a Relation, a Friend.—I must have no Difficulties; there<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore
I insist upon your absolute Promise.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not in my own Power, Madam.—<hi>Lycomedes,</hi>
you know hath acceded to the Treaty of Alliance; that to
furnish his Quota, his Troops are already embark'd, and that I
have engag'd my self in his Service.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Why will you raise Obstacles before you know the
Conditions? 'Tis a thing I have set my heart upon, and I tell
you 'tis what in Honour you can comply with.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>My Duty, my Obligations put me entirely in your
Disposal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>You promise then solemnly, faithfully—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>I do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I have remark'd, <hi>Periphas,</hi> that you are prodigiously
fond of the Princess <hi>Calista</hi>'s Daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>I fond of her, Madam!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, <hi>Periphas,</hi> are not you eternally at her Ear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>How I have seen that formidable Hero General <hi>Ajax</hi>
suffer upon your Account!—Of all his Rivals you are his
eternal Torment.—He reddens, sighs, and (as much as is
consistent with such a blustering Soldier's Valour) languishes
whenever you are near her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>You may safely own your Passion, <hi>Periphas,</hi> for I
know you think her agreeable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Besides her being the fashionable Beauty of the Court
(which is sufficient Vanity to make all the young Fellows fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>low
her) you, of all Mankind, in Gratitude ought to like
<pb n="47" facs="53"/>
her.—I know all of 'em envy the particular Distinctions she
shews you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I am convinc'd, of her Merits; and your marrying
her I know wou'd make you both happy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me perish, Madam, if I ever once thought of it!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Happiness you see hath been in my Thoughts.—
I take the settling this Affair upon my self.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>How cou'd you, Madam, imagine I had any Views of
this kind!—What, be a Woman's Follower with Intention
to marry her! Why, the very Women themselves wou'd laugh
at a Man who had so vulgar a Notion of Galantry, and
knew so little of their Inclinations.—The Man never means
it, and the Woman never expects it; and for the most part they
have every other View but Marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>But I am serious, Nephew, and insist upon your Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mise.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XXXVIII. No sooner had <hi>Jonathan</hi> leap'd from the Boat.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>What are the Jests that on Marriage you quote?</l>
                              <l>All ignorant Batchelors censure by Rote;</l>
                              <l>Like Criticks you view it with Envy or Spleen.</l>
                              <l>You pry out its Faults, but the Good is o'erseen.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not in my Power, Madam; 'tis not in my Inclina<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions.—A
Soldier can have but one Inducement to marry,
(and the Woman may have the same Reason too) which is,
the Opportunities of Absence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>You know, Nephew, you have promis'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>But suppose I am already engag'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>That will be another Merit to her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis impossible, Madam.—In a Day or two you
know I am to set out for the Campaign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>A Lady of her romantic Spirit can have no Objec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions
to following the Camp.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="54"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XXXIX. Love's a Dream of mighty Pleasure.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <l>Soldier, think before you marry;</l>
                           <l>If your Wife the Camp attends,</l>
                           <l>You but a Convenience carry,</l>
                           <l>For (perhaps) a hundred Friends.</l>
                           <l>If at home she's left in Sorrow,</l>
                           <l>Absence is convenient too;</l>
                           <l>Neighbours now and then may borrow</l>
                           <l>What is of no Use to you.</l>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I indeed fear'd <hi>Pyrrha</hi> might have started some Dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficulties,
but if you rightly consider the Proposal you can have
none.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Cause of the War we are now engag'd in?
Does not the Fate of <hi>Menelaus</hi> stare me in the Face?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I will have no more of your trifling Objections, <hi>Pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>riphas</hi>;
and as to your Part, from this time I will look upon the
Affair as happily concluded.—All that now remains to be
done is with <hi>Pyrrha.</hi> I have left her to <hi>Deidamia</hi>'s Manage<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment;
and without doubt her good Offices must prevail, for
you can never have a better Advocate.—But shou'd the
Girl be perverse and obstinate!—'Tis impossible. For howe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver
her Heart is already engag'd, no Woman alive can resist
the Ambition of such an Alliance.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="49" facs="55"/>
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>Periphas.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Had I so little Taste of Liberty as to be inclin'd to
marry; that Girl is of so termagant a Spirit!—The bravest
Man must have the dread of an eternal Domestic War.—In a
Tongue-combat Woman is invincible, and the Husband must
come off with Shame and Infamy; for though he lives in per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>petual
Noise and Tumult, the poor Man is only ridiculous to
his Neighbours.—How can we ever get rid of her?—
<hi>Hercules</hi> conquer'd the seven-headed <hi>Hydra,</hi> but his Wife was
a venom'd Shirt that stuck to him to the last.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>Periphas, Ajax.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>This Rencounter, <hi>Periphas,</hi> is as I wish'd.—The Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berties
you have taken—you know what I mean—when
my Honour is concern'd—an Indignity and all that!—
'Tis not to be put up; and I must insist upon an Explanation.—
There is a particular Affair, my Lord.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Your accosting me in this particular manner, Lord
<hi>Ajax,</hi> requires Explanation.—For let me die, if I com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>prehend
you!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>Death, my Lord, I explain! I am not come here to be
ask'd Questions.—'Tis sufficient that I know the Affront,
and that you know I will have Satisfaction.—So, now you
are answer'd—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>I can't say much to <hi>my</hi> Satisfaction, my Lord; for I
can't so much as guess at your meaning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>A Man of Honour, <hi>Periphas,</hi> is not to be trifled
withal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>But a Man of Honour, <hi>Ajax,</hi> is not oblig'd in Cou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rage
to be unintelligible.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>I hate talking.—The Tongue is a Woman's Wea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pon.
Whenever I am affronted; by the Gods, this Sword is
my only Answer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not, <hi>Ajax,</hi> that I decline the Dispute, or wou'd
upon any Account deny you the Pleasure of fighting; yet (if it
is not too much Condescension in a Man of Honour) before
I fight I wou'd willingly know the Provocation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="56"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XL. <hi>Maggy Lawther.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>What is all this idle Chat?</l>
                              <l>Words are out of Season.</l>
                              <l>Whether 'tis or this or that,</l>
                              <l>The Sword shall do me reason.</l>
                              <l>Honour call'd me to the Task;</l>
                              <l>No matter for explaining:</l>
                              <l>'Tis a fresh Affront to ask</l>
                              <l>A Man of Honour's meaning.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>Be it as it will, <hi>Periphas</hi>; we have gone too far al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ready
to retract.—You know, I suppose, of my Pretensions
to a certain Lady.—Now are you satisfied?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>If you had her, my Lord, it had been much more to
my Satisfaction.—I admire your Courage.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="51" facs="57"/>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XLI. Lord <hi>Frog</hi> and Lady <hi>Mouse.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>Oh, then it seems you want a Wife!</l>
                              <l>Shou'd I consent,</l>
                              <l>You may repent,</l>
                              <l>And all her daily Jars and Strife</l>
                              <l>You may on me resent.</l>
                              <l>Thus ev'ry Day and ev'ry Night,</l>
                              <l>If things at home shou'd not go right,</l>
                              <l>We three must live in constant Fight.</l>
                              <l>Take her at all Event.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>Hell, and Furies! I am not to be rally'd out of my
Resentment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Now in my Opinion 'tis flinging away your Courage
to fight without a Cause; though indeed the Men of uncom<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mon
Prowess, by their loving to make the most of every
Quarrel, seem to think the contrary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>You are not so sure of the Lady, <hi>Periphas,</hi> as you
flatter yourself; for whenever I am a Rival, by <hi>Jove,</hi> 'tis not
her Consent, but my Sword, that must decide the Question.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure never a Rival (as you will call me) had a better
Reason for fighting than I have at present; for if I am kill'd,
I shall be out of danger of having the Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>You might spare your Jokes, <hi>Periphas,</hi> for my Cou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rage
wants no Provocation.—If I fall, <hi>Pyrrha</hi> may be yours:
You will then deserve her.—'Till then—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>So he that conquers, as a Reward, I find is to be
married.—Now dear <hi>Ajax,</hi> is that worth fighting for?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Passion for that Lady, <hi>Periphas,</hi> is too publick
to bear Dispute.—Have not I seen you whisper her, laugh
with her? And by some particular Looks at the same time
'twas too evident that I was the Subject of your Mirth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Looks, <hi>Ajax!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="52" facs="58"/>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Looks, my Lord; and I never did or will take
an impertinent one from any Man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Impertinent one!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>Furies! This calm Mockery is not to be born.—
I won't have my Words repeated.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Such Language, <hi>Ajax,</hi> may provoke me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLII. <hi>Richmond</hi> Ball.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>What means all this Ranting?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Cease your joking;</l>
                              <l>'Tis provoking.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>I to my Honour will ne'er be wanting.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Will you do me right?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>What means all this Ranting?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Cease your joking;</l>
                              <l>'Tis provoking.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>I to my Honour will ne'er be wanting.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Talk not then but fight.</l>
                              <l>Give then by Action</l>
                              <l>Satisfaction.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>I'm not in awe, Sir.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Death! will you draw, Sir?</l>
                              <l>Tittle-tattle</l>
                              <l>Is a Battle</l>
                              <l>You may safer try.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>Yet, first, I'd fain know why.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>By <hi>Jupiter, Periphas,</hi> 'till now I never thought you
a Coward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay then—since my own Honour calls upon me.—
Take notice, <hi>Ajax,</hi> that I <hi>don't</hi> fight for the Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They fight.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="53" facs="59"/>
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>Periphas, Ajax, Theaspe, Artemona, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Guard.</speaker>
                     <p>Part 'em.—Beat down their Swords.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They are parted.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 Guard.</speaker>
                     <p>How dar'd you presume to fight in the Royal
Gardens?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Guard.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, in the very Presence!—For see, the Queen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very hard, Sirs, that a Man shou'd be deny'd the
Satisfaction of a Gentleman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord <hi>Ajax,</hi> for this unparallel'd Presumption we for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bid
you the Palace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>I shall take some other Opportunity, my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>Theaspe, Artemona, Periphas.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>And as for you, <hi>Periphas</hi>—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majesty's Rigor can do no less than forbid me
the Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>The Woman, <hi>Periphas,</hi> is the only thing that can
reconcile me to your Behaviour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>That blundering Hero <hi>Ajax</hi> will have it that I am his
Rival. The Man will be almost as miserable without her, as
'tis probable he might be with her.—Oblige us both then,
Madam, and let the General be miserable in his own way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>I cou'd not have imagin'd that obstinate Girl cou'd
have had any Scruples to the Match; but <hi>Deidamia</hi> tells me
she finds her as difficult as you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Since you know, Madam, that <hi>Pyrrha</hi> will have her
own way; for both our sakes, and to save yourself unneces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary
Trouble, your Majesty had better give up this Impossibility.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>Theaspe, Artemona, Periphas, Diphilus, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>To prevent future Mischief, my Lord, his Majesty
puts you under Arrest, and commands you to attend him. Ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>neral
<pb n="54" facs="60"/>
                        <hi>Ajax</hi> is already in Custody.—'Tis his Pleasure too,
that (after you have paid your Duty to him) you embark with
the Troops immediately; and you are not to come ashore again
upon pain of his Majesty's Displeasure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLIII.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <l>In War we've nought but Death to fear,</l>
                           <l>How gracious is the Sentence!</l>
                           <l>For that is easier far to bear,</l>
                           <l>Than Marriage with Repentance.</l>
                           <l>Begirt with Foes, by Numbers brav'd,</l>
                           <l>I'd bless the happy Crisis;</l>
                           <l>The Man from greater Danger sav'd</l>
                           <l>The lesser ones despises.</l>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Majesty then, you find, must dispense with my
Promise 'till after the Expedition.—If the General shou'd be
so happy, to bring <hi>Pyrrha</hi> with him to the Camp, perhaps
we may like one another better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diph.</speaker>
                     <p>The King, Madam, wants to talk to your Majesty
upon Affairs of Consequence.—You will find him in the
Royal Apartment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas</speaker>
                     <p>My Daughters with <hi>Pyrrha</hi> have just turn'd the Walk,
and are coming this way.—You may stay with 'em, <hi>Ar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>temona,</hi>
till I send for you.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>Artemona, Philoe, Lesbia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis horridly mortifying that these Trades-People
will never get any thing New against a Birth-day. They are
<pb n="55" facs="61"/>
all so abominably stupid, that a Woman of Fancy cannot
possibly have the Opportunity of shewing her Genius.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>The Fatigue one hath of talking to those Creatures
for at least a Month before a Birth-day is insupportable; for
you know, Sister, when the time draws so very near, a Wo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>man
can think of nothing else.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>After all, Sister, though their things are detestable,
one must make choice of something or other. I have sent
to the Fellows to be with me this Morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>You are so eternally sending for 'em, one wou'd
imagine you was delighted with their Conversation. For
those hideous Stuffs they will shew us from Year to Year
are frightful, are shocking. How can a Woman have so ill
a Taste as to expose herself in a last Year's Pattern!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Madam, I beg your Pardon. Let me die, if I
saw you!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Our meeting her was lucky beyond Expression, for
I never felt so uneasy a thing as a Secret.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>You know, Sister, we had agreed to trust her with
our Suspicions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet after all when a Sister's Reputation is concern'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>But is not the Honour of a Family of greater Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sequence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Tho she is a Woman and a Favourite, I dare say, if
<hi>Artemona</hi> promises, whatever the suffers she will inviolably
keep it to herself.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>If I had not this Quality I had little deserv'd <hi>The<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>aspe</hi>'s
Friendship.—By all that's Sacred, Ladies, you
may safely trust me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis impossible, Sister, but she herself must have ob<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>serv'd
it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Whatever People have observ'd, 'tis a thing you
know, that no Creature alive can presume to talk upon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Deal fairly and openly with us, <hi>Artemona.</hi>—Have
you remark'd nothing particular of <hi>Deidamia</hi> yonder of late?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Of <hi>Deidamia!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Only look upon her, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Well—what do you think of her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you blind, <hi>Artemona,</hi> or dare not you believe
your Eyes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Her particular Intimacy with <hi>Pyrrha</hi> do you mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Madam!—Then I find we must speak first.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Now, dear <hi>Artemona,</hi> can any Woman alive ima<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gine
that Shape of hers within the compass of common Mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>desty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>But how can one possibly have those Suspicions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="56" facs="62"/>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>She is a Woman, Madam; she hath Inclinations and
may have had her Opportunities that we know nothing of.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLIV. Minuet of <hi>Corelli</hi> in the Ninth <hi>Concerto.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                              <l>We may resolve to resist Temptation;</l>
                              <l>And that's all we can do:</l>
                              <l>For in the Hour of Inclination</l>
                              <l>What cou'd—I or you?</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Though the thing is improbable, 'tis so monstrously
evident that it cannot bear a Dispute.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Then her Bosom too is so preposterously impudent!—
One wou'd think a Woman in her Condition was not con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>scious
of her own Shame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Or imagin'd other People cou'd overlook it as well
as herself.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Then she is so squeamish and so frequently out of
order.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>That she hath all the outward Marks of Female
Frailty must be visible to all Womankind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>But how she came by 'em, there, <hi>Artemona,</hi> is still the
Secret.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>I must own that, by her particular Intimacies with that
forward Creature <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> I suspect her to be her Confident in
this Accident.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>I beg you, Ladies, to turn this Discourse; for <hi>Deida<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mia</hi>
and <hi>Pyrrha</hi> are just coming upon us to join the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>versation.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
                  <stage>Philoe, Lesbia, Artemona, Deidamia, Achilles.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Now I dare swear that careless Creature <hi>Pyrrha</hi> hath
not once thought of her Clothes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="57" facs="63"/>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, dear Lady <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> the thing is not such a trifle,
for 'tis the only Mark of Respect that most People are capable
of shewing. And though that is not your Case, I know
your Gratitude can never omit this publick Occasion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLV. Tom and Will were Shepherds twain.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                              <l>Think of Dress in ev'ry Light;</l>
                              <l>'Tis Woman's chiefest Duty;</l>
                              <l>Neglecting that, our selves we slight</l>
                              <l>And undervalue Beauty.</l>
                              <l>That allures the Lover's Eye,</l>
                              <l>And graces ev'ry Action;</l>
                              <l>Besides, when not a Creature's by,</l>
                              <l>'Tis inward Satisfaction.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>As I am yet a Stranger, Ladies, to the Fashions of the
Country, 'tis your Fancy that must determine me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>How can a Woman of common Sense be so unsoli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>citous
about her Dress!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>And trust a Woman to choose for her! 'Tis a Temp<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tation
to be spiteful that very few of us can resist; for we have
not many Pleasures that can equal that of seeing another Wo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>man
ridiculous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>But you have not, <hi>Pyrrha,</hi> misplac'd your Confidence.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IX.</head>
                  <stage>Philoe, Lesbia, Deidamia, Achilles, Artemona, Servant.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Embroiderer, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>That Woman is everlastingly pestering me for Em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ployment.
Now can she imagine that to promote her tawdry
<pb n="58" facs="64"/>
Trade I can be talk'd into making myself ridiculous by ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pearing
eternally in her odious Embroidery?—I can't see
her now.—But perhaps I may want her for some trivial
thing or other.—Let her call again to morrow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                     <p>The Anti-chamber, Madam, is crowded with Trades-People.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Did not I tell you that I wou'd not be troubled with
those impertinent Creatures?—But hold—I had forgot I
sent for 'em.—Let 'em wait.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>But if those foreign Merchants who lately came into
Port are among 'em—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>There, Sister, is all my Hope. I shall be horridly dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>appointed
if they don't shew us something charming.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Shou'd any Woman alive get Sight of their things be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore
us—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>I cou'd not bear it.—To appear in what another
Woman had refus'd wou'd make the Creature so intolerably
vain!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Are those Merchants I ask you among 'em?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                     <p>They have been waiting, Madam, above this half
Hour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>And did not you know our Impatience?—How
cou'd you be so stupid!—Let us see them this Instant.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE X.</head>
                  <stage>Artemena, Philoe, Lesbia, Deidamia, Achilles.
Ulysses, Diomedes, Agyrtes. [Disguis'd as Merchants.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>Unless you have any thing that is absolutely new
and very uncommon, you will give us and your selves, Gen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tlemen,
but unnecessary Trouble.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Experience, Madam, must have profited very
little by the Honour of dealing with Ladies, if we cou'd ima<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gine
they cou'd possibly be pleas'd twice with the same thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>You might as well offer 'em the same Lover.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>We have learnt the good Manners, Madam, to distin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guish
our Customers.—To produce any thing that had ever
been seen before wou'd be a downright Insult upon the Ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nius
of a Lady of Quality.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>Novelty is the very Spirit of Dress.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me die, if the Fellows don't talk charmingly!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Sensibly, Sister.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="59" facs="65"/>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis evident they must have had Dealings with Ladies
of Condition.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>We only wait your Commands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>We have things of all kinds, Ladies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Of all kinds!—Now that is just what I wanted
to see.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Are not these, Sister, most delightful Creatures?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>We know a Lady can never fix unless we first cloy
her Curiosity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>And if Variety can please, we have every thing that
Fancy can wish.</p>
                     <p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>AIR XLVI. The Bob-tail Lass.</head>
                              <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                                 <desc>music</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <l>In Dress and Love by like Desires</l>
                              <l>Is Woman's Heart perplext;</l>
                              <l>The Man and the Gown she one Day admires,</l>
                              <l>She wishes to change the next.</l>
                              <l>The more you are fickle, we're more employ'd,</l>
                              <l>And Love hath more Customers too;</l>
                              <l>For Men are as fickle, and soon are cloy'd,</l>
                              <l>Unless they have something New.</l>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>But, dear Man, consider our Impatience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd you command the things, Ladies, to be brought
here, or wou'd you see 'em in your own Apartment?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>How intolerably these Fellows love talking!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>How canst thou, Man, ask such a Question!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Here—immediately.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, tis not, Madam, that our Goods can be put out
of Countenance by the most glaring Light—as for that mat<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="60" facs="66"/>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, pry'thee, Fellow, have done.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Diomedes</hi> goes out and returns with <hi>Agyrtes.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>I wou'd not offer you these Pearls, Ladies, if the
World cou'd produce such another Pair.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>A Pair, Fellow—Dost thou think that Jewels pair
like Men and Women because they were never made to agree?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>Now, Ladies, here is all that Art can shew you.—
Open the Packet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>This very individual Pattern, in a blue Pink, had been
infinitely charming.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't you think it pretty, <hi>Deidamia</hi>?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heaven's sake, Lady <hi>Pyrrha.</hi>—Nay, dear
Child, how can any Creature have so little Curiosity!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Look upon it again, Madam.—Never was so de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lightful
a Mixture!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>So soft! so mellow!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>So advantageous for the Complexion!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>I can't bear it, Man; the Colour is frightful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>I hate our own tame home-bred Fancy.—I own I
like the Design—but take it away, Man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>There must be something pretty in every thing that is
foreign. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Ulysses</hi> shews another Piece.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>I am sure, Madam, this must convince you to the
contrary.—Never was any thing so detestable!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heavens sake, Sir, open that other Packet; and
take away this hideous Trumpery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>How coud'st thou make this Mistake?—Never was
such an eternal Blunderer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Opens the Armour.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>How ridiculous is this Accident!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon the Mistake, Ladies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>A Suit of Armour!—You see, <hi>Philoe,</hi> they can at
least equip us for the Camp.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, <hi>Lesbia,</hi> for that Matter it might serve many a
stiff awkward Creature that we see every Day in the Drawing<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>room;
sor their Dress is every way as absurd and preposterous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Another Packet open'd.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>If your Expectations, Ladies, are not now answer'd,
let Fancy own herself at a stand. 'Tis inimitable! 'Tis irre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sistible!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[As the Ladies are employ'd in examining the Stuffs, <hi>Achil<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>les</hi>
is handling and poising the Armour, <hi>Ulysses</hi> observing
him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Achil.</speaker>
                     <p>The Workmanship is curious; and so justly mount<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed!
This very Sword seems fitted to my Hand.—The Shield
too is so little cumbersome; so very easy!—Was <hi>Hector</hi> here,
the Fate of <hi>Troy</hi> shou'd this Instant be decided.—How my
Heart burns to meet him!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="61" facs="67"/>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <stage>[Aside to <hi>Diom.</hi>
                        </stage> That intrepid Air! That Godlike
Look! It must be He! His Nature, his Disposition shews
him▪ through the Disguise <stage>[To <hi>Achilles.</hi>]</stage> Son of <hi>Thetis,</hi> I
know thee, <hi>Greece</hi> demands thee, and now, <hi>Achilles,</hi> the House
of <hi>Priam</hi> shakes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>But what are you, Friend, who thus presume to
know me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>You cannot be a Stranger, Sir, to the Name of <hi>Ulysses.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>As I have long honour'd, I shall now endeavour, Sir,
to emulate your Fame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Know, Sir, <hi>Diomedes</hi>; He too is ambitious to attend
you, and partake your Glory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>Come <hi>Agyrtes</hi>; with him we carry Conquest to the
Confederates.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Agyrtes</hi> takes a Trumpet which lay amongst the Armour,
and sounds.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLVII. My Dame hath a lame tame Crane.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                              <l>Thy Fate then, O <hi>Troy,</hi> is decreed.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                              <l>How I pant!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Achil.</speaker>
                              <l>How I burn for the Fight.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                              <l>Hark, Glory calls.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Achil.</speaker>
                              <l>Now great <hi>Hector</hi> shall bleed.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Agyr.</speaker>
                              <l>Fame shall our Deeds requite.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <stage>[As <hi>Achilles</hi> is going off, he turns and looks on <hi>Deidamia.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="68"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLVIII. <hi>Geminiani</hi>'s Minuet.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Beauty weeps.—Ah, why that Languish?</l>
                              <l>See she calls and bids me stay.</l>
                              <l>How can I leave her? my Heart feels her Anguish.</l>
                              <l>Hence, Fame and Glory. Love wins the Day.</l>
                              <stage>[He drops the Sword and Shield.</stage>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Trumpet sounds, and he takes 'em up again.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR My Dame hath a lame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>as before, Sung in Four Parts as a Catch.</p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy Fate then, O <hi>Troy,</hi> is decreed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>How I pant! How I burn for the Fight!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>Hark, Glory calls. Now great <hi>Hector</hi> shall bleed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Fame shall our Deeds requite.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[As they are going; <hi>Achilles</hi> stops with his Eyes fix'd
on <hi>Deidamia.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>For Heaven's sake, Ladies, support <hi>Deidamia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Never was any thing so astonishing!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="63" facs="69"/>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Run then, <hi>Artemona,</hi> and acquaint the King and Queen
with what hath happen'd.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE XI.</head>
                  <stage>Philoe, Lesbia, Deidamia, Achilles, Diomedes,
Ulysses, Agyrtes.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah Sister, Sister, the Mystery then of that particular
Intimacy between you and <hi>Pyrrha</hi> is at last unravell'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                     <p>Now if it had not been a Man of this prodigious Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sequence,
it had been the same thing.—Sure never unguarded
Woman was so unaccountably lucky!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you leave me, <hi>Achilles</hi>?—Can you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Consider your own Glory, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR XLIX. Gavotte of <hi>Corelli.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Why this Pain?</l>
                              <l>Love adieu,</l>
                              <l>Break thy Chain,</l>
                              <l>Fame pursue.</l>
                              <l>Ah, false Heart,</l>
                              <l>Can'st thou part?</l>
                              <l>Oaths and Vows have bound me.</l>
                              <l>Fame cries, Go;</l>
                              <l>Love says, No.</l>
                              <l>Why d'ye thus confound me?</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Think of my Condition.—Save my Honour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Think of the Honour of <hi>Greece.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Think of your solemn Oaths and Promises.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Nations depend upon you.—Victory, Sir, calls you
hence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="64" facs="70"/>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you, <hi>Achilles,</hi> be perfidious?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you lose your Glory in the Arms of a Woman?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you sacrifice the Fame of your faithful <hi>Deidamia</hi>?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR L. The Scheme.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>O, what a Conflict's in my Breast!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                              <l>What, still in suspence? bid Fame adieu.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>See me with Shame opprest:</l>
                              <l>I curse, yet I love thee too.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                              <l>Let not her Sighs unman your Heart.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Can you then go, and Faith resign?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                              <l>Shou'd I!—How can I part?</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>Your Honour is link'd with mine.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE The Last.</head>
                  <stage>Philoe, Lesbia, Deidamia, Achilles, Ulysses, Arte<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mona,
Diomedes, Agyrtes, Lycomedes, Theaspe,
Diphilus, Periphas, Ajax.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>Hence, <hi>Diphilus</hi>; and presume no more to come into
my Presence. 'Twas your paltry Flattery that made me ridi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culous.—Such
a Genius can never be at a loss for Employ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment,
for I have found you qualified for the very meanest
Offices.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Diphilus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>My Daughter, Sir, I hope, hath put Confidence in a
Man of Honour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="65" facs="71"/>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>My Word, Madam, is as sacred as the most religious
Ceremony.—Yet (though we are already solemnly betroth'd
to each other) 'tis my Request, Madam, that before I leave the
Court the Priest may confirm the Marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Theaspe <hi>whispers</hi> Artemona, <hi>who goes out.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>This might have prov'd a scurvy Affair, <hi>Deidamia</hi>;
for a Woman can never depend upon a Man's Honour after
she hath lost her own to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Achilles <hi>talks apart to</hi> Ulysses, Periphas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>You must own, Madam, that 'twas your own Jeal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ousies
that were the Occasion of <hi>Deidamia</hi>'s Disgrace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>How can you have the Assurance to name it? Does it
not put you in mind of your own?—Let her Marriage to
<hi>Achilles</hi> make us forget every thing past.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>As you was so furiously in Love, Lord <hi>Ajax,</hi> I hope
I shall still retain your Friendship.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>No joking I beg you, young Man.—But pr'ythee,
how came you here? and in a Woman's Dress too!—Your
setting out, Stripling, did not seem to promise much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>The Adventure wou'd be too long to tell you.—I
shall reserve the Story for the Camp.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Artemona</hi> returns with the Priest.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Art.</speaker>
                     <p>The Priest, Sir, is ready.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>The Ceremony waits you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
                     <p>It shall be my Study, <hi>Lycomedes,</hi> to deserve this Alliance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>May you be happy!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theas.</speaker>
                     <p>Let the Priest then join your Hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Achilles, Deidamia, Lycomedes, Theaspe, Lesbia, Philoe,</hi>
                     <hi>Artemona,</hi> retire to the back part of the Stage. The Priest
performs the Ceremony.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Duel, <hi>Ajax,</hi> had made a much better Figure if there
had been a Woman in the Case.—But you know, like Men
of violent Honour, we were so very valiant that we did not
know what we were fighting for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>If you are too free with your Wit, <hi>Periphas,</hi> perhaps
we may know what we quarrel about.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>What testy, <hi>Ajax!</hi> Petticoats have led many a Man in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>to
an Error. How lucky was the Discovery! for had you
found a real complying Woman you had irretrievably been
married.—The Presence of <hi>Achilles</hi> shall now animate the
War.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="72"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR LI. The Man that is drunk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>Was ever a Lover so happily freed!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Try me no more; and mention it never.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                              <l>Suppose you had found her a Woman indeed.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Must I be teaz'd and worried for ever!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                              <l>By Conquest in Battle we finish the Strife;</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                              <l>But Marriage had kept you in Quarrels for Life.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                              <l>Must you be fleering?</l>
                              <l>Truce with your jeering.</l>
                              <l>Know that you Wits oft' paid for your sneering.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>If you had been deceiv'd by a Woman—'tis what
we are all liable to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
                     <p>But <hi>Ajax</hi> is a Man of warm Imagination.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>After this Day let me hear no more of this ridiculous
Affair.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay for that matter any Man might have been deceiv'd;
for Love, you know, is blind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>With my Sword I can answer any Man.—I tell
you, I hate joking.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Lycomedes,</hi> &amp;c. come forwards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>I have the common Cause so much at Heart that I
wou'd not, Son, detain you from the Siege.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="73"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR LII. There liv'd long ago in a Country Place.</head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Deid.</speaker>
                              <l>How short was my Calm! in a Moment 'tis past;</l>
                              <l>Fresh Sorrows arise, and my Day is o'ercast.</l>
                              <l>But since 'tis decreed.—Let me stifle this Tear.</l>
                              <l>Be bold, yet be cautious; my Life is thy Care;</l>
                              <l>On thine it depends; 'tis for thee that I fear.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lycom.</speaker>
                     <p>As both her Country and your Glory are concern'd,
<hi>Deidamia</hi> must learn to bear your Absence.—In the mean time,
<hi>Achilles,</hi> she shall be our Care.—As the Marriage is confirm'd;
let the Dancers, who were preparing for th' approaching Festival,
celebrate the Wedding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ajax.</speaker>
                     <p>But hearkee, young Fellow,—This is the old Soldier's
Play; for we seldom leave Quarters but the Landlord's Daugh<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter
is the better for us.—Hah!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>To</hi> Achilles.</stage>
                  <stage>DANCE.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                     <p>We may for a while put on a feign'd Character, but
Nature is so often unguarded that it will shew itself.—'Tis
to the Armour we owe <hi>Achilles.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="74"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR LIII. Minuet of <hi>Corelli.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Single.</speaker>
                              <l>Nature breaks forth at the Moment unguarded;</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                              <l>Through all Disguise she her self must betray.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Single.</speaker>
                              <l>Heav'n with Success hath our Labours rewarded.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                              <l>Let's with <hi>Achilles</hi> over Genius obey.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR LIV. Saraband of <hi>Corelli.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <gap rend="content:〈♫〉">
                              <desc>music</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Ulys.</speaker>
                              <l>Thus when the Cat had once all Woman's Graces;</l>
                              <l>Courtship, Marriage won her Embraces:</l>
                              <l>Forth lept a Mouse; she, forgetting Enjoyment,</l>
                              <l>Quits her fond Spouse for her former Employment.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>CHORUS.</head>
                           <head>Minuet of <hi>Corelli.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <l>Nature breaks forth at the Moment unguarded;</l>
                           <l>Through all Disguise she herself must betray.</l>
                           <l>Heav'n with Success hath our Labours rewarded;</l>
                           <l>Let's with <hi>Achilles</hi> our Genius obey.</l>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishersadvertisement">
            <pb n="69" facs="75"/>
            <p>February 28, 1733. Just Publish'd, A SELECT COLLECTION of <hi>MOLIERE</hi>'s Co<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>MEDIES,
<hi>French</hi> and <hi>English,</hi> in EIGHT POCKET
VOLUMES, neatly Printed on a Fine Paper, with a curious
Frontispiece to each Comedy. To which is prefix'd a curious
PRINT of the AUTHOR, and his LIFE in <hi>French</hi> and
<hi>English</hi>; Extracted from Monsieur <hi>Bayle, Rapin,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N. B.</hi> That it may be seen how much the <hi>English</hi> Stage has
been indebted to <hi>Moliere,</hi> we have, in this Catalogue, plac'd such
of <hi>Our</hi> Comedies as have been founded upon <hi>His</hi> over-against
the Originals, from whence they were taken.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. I. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>A DEDICATION of the Whole WORK to HER MAJESTY.</item>
                     <item>The LIFE of the AUTHOR.</item>
                     <item>A General PREFACE to the Whole WORK.</item>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">1 Miser, <hi>Shadwel.</hi> Miser, <hi>Fielding.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>1 <hi>L'AVARE.</hi> The MISER.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to <hi>His Royal Highness</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sganarelle ou le Cocu Imaginaire.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Cuckold in Conceit.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to Miss <hi>Wolstenholme.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. II. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">2 Citizen turn'd Gen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tleman,
 <hi>Ravenscroft.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>2 <hi>Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Cit turn'd Gentleman.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to <hi>His Royal Highness</hi> the <hi>Duke.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">3 Love's Contrivances, <hi>Centlivre.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>3 <hi>Le Medicin malgré Lui.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A Doctor and No Doctor.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to Dr. <hi>Mead.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. III. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">4 <hi>Sir</hi> Martin Marral, <hi>Dryden.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>4 <hi>L'Etourdi ou les Contre-Tems.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Blunderer: Or the Counter-Plots.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable <hi>Philip</hi> Earl of <hi>Chesterfield.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Les Precieuses Ridicules.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Conceited Ladies.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to Miss <hi>Le Bas.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. IV. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">5 Squire of Alsatia, <hi>Shadwell.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>5 <hi>L'Ecole des Maris.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The School for Husbands.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lady <hi>Harriot Campbell.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="76"/>
                        <note place="marg">6 Country Wife, <hi>Wicherly.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>6 <hi>L'Ecole des Femmes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The School for Wives.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable Sir <hi>William Yonge,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. V. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">7 Nonjurer, <hi>Cibber.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>7 <hi>Tartuffe, ou L'Imposteur.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Impostor.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to Mr. <hi>Wyndham</hi> of <hi>Clower-Wall,</hi> in <hi>Gloucestershire.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <note place="marg">8 Wanton Wife, <hi>Betterton.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <p>8 <hi>George Dandin, ou le Mari Confondu.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>George Dandin, or the Husband Defeated.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lady <gap resp="#oxf" extent="3+ letters" rend="content:___+">
                              <desc>blank</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. VI. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <note place="marg">9 Plain-Dealer, <hi>Wicherly.</hi>
                           </note>9 <hi>Le Misantrope.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Man-Hater.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Montagu.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>10 <hi>M. De Pourceaugnac.</hi>
                           <note place="marg">10 Trelooby, <hi>Van<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>brugh.</hi>
                           </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Squire Lubberly.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lady <hi>Mary Wortley Montagu.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. VII. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <note place="marg">11 Amphitryon, <hi>Dryden.</hi>
                           </note>11 <hi>Amphitrion.</hi> Amphitryon.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable <hi>George Dodington,</hi> 
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Le Mariage Forcé.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Forc'd Marriage.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lady <hi>Harvey.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <note place="marg">12 Tender Husband, <hi>Steele.</hi>
                           </note>12 <hi>Le Sicilien, ou L'Amour Pointre.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Sicilian, or Love makes a Painter.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to Her Grace the Dutchess of <hi>Richmond.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Vol. VIII. containing,</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Le Malade Imaginaire.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Hypochondriack.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Argyle.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <note place="marg">13 Impertinents, <hi>Shadwell.</hi>
                           </note>13 <hi>Les Fascheux.</hi> The Impertinents.</p>
                        <p>Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Carteret.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb facs="77"/> ⁂ Just Publish'd, The TRAVELS and ADVENTURES of the Sieur
JACQUES MASSE: Being a very entertaining Account
of his Arrival in an unknown Country in <hi>Terra Australis,</hi> after
having suffer'd two Shipwrecks: Of the strange Manners and
Customs of the People: Of his curious Conversations with
the Priests, Judges, and with the KING himself, on the Sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jects
of Religion, Trade, and almost all the Arts and Sciences:
Of his Passage from the Southern Countries to <hi>Goa,</hi> where he
was imprison'd in the Inquisition: Of his being taken by Pirates
in his Voyage from thence to <hi>Lisbon</hi>; and of his Ransom from
Slavery, and Arrival at <hi>London</hi>: Besides many other most di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>verting
Incidents, which are very agreeably interspers'd in the
Narrative.</p>
            <p>Just Publish'd, The BOARDING SCHOOL; or, The SHAM
CAPTAIN. An Opera. As it is perform'd at the Theatre-Royal
in Drury-Lane, by His Majesty's Servants: Written by
Mr. COFFEE, Author of the Beggar's Wedding, and The
Devil to Pay. With the Musick prefixt to each Song.</p>
            <p>Also just Publish'd the last New Play, call'd, CAELIA, or, The Perjur'd LOVER, as it is Acted at the
Theatre-Royal in Drury-Lane, by His Majesty's Servants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N. B.</hi> This Play is founded on a True Tragical Story in
Common Life, and the Incidents very Natural and Moving.</p>
            <p>And the Second Edition of The MOCK DOCTOR: Or, The DUMB LADY
Cur'd, a Comedy done from <hi>Moliere,</hi> with additional SONGS
and Alterations.</p>
            <p>*†* Feb. 28, 1732. In a few Days will be Publish'd, The MISER. A Comedy, taken from <hi>Plautus</hi> and
<hi>Moliere.</hi> By HENRY FIELDING, <abbr>Esq</abbr>. As it is now
Acting at the Theatre-Royal in <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> by His Majesty's
Servants.</p>
            <trailer>Printed for John Watts at the Printing-Office in Wild-Court
near Lincoln's-Inn Fields.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>