<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An enquiry into the danger and consequences of a war with the Dutch:</title>
            <author>Defoe, Daniel, 1661?-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K022860.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3305531845</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An enquiry into the danger and consequences of a war with the Dutch:</title>
                  <author>Defoe, Daniel, 1661?-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for J.Baker,</publisher>
                  <date>1712.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K022860.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3305531845</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Daniel Defoe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Moore, 241</note>
                  <note>Goldsmiths', 4952</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT5337.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>AN
ENQUIRY
Into the
DANGER
AND
CONSEQUENCES
OF A
WAR
With the
<hi>DUTCH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed for <hi>J. Baker,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Boy</hi>
in <hi>Pater-Noster-Row.</hi> 1712.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
         <head>An ENQUIRY into the
DANGER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </head>
         <p>I CANNOT say that I am of the Num<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ber
of those, who wish, that if we have
a War with the <hi>Dutch</hi> they may beat
Us; because it has something in it so unnatu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ral,
for an <hi>Englishman</hi> or a <hi>Britain</hi> to rejoyce
in the Destruction of his own Country, and
in the Triumph of our Neighbours of any
kind over Us, that he cannot see it without
Horror and Aversion; yet I cannot but say,
I wish <hi>those,</hi> who talk with so much Satisfa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ction
of a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> would look
a little into the certain Consequences of such
a War, whether Victory or Disadvantage on
Our Side shall attend it.</p>
         <p>I take a War with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> to have
this very unhappy Circumstance in it, That
if we are beaten, it may be <gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 word" rend="content:〈◊〉">
               <desc>illegible</desc>
            </gap> ruin imme<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diately,
and if we conquer, it may be our
ruin hereafter, so that in general, get or
lose in the Field, we shall certainly lose in
the War.</p>
         <p>The immediate Loss of our Ships, of our
Men, of our Trade, and the farther load<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
this Nation, with a mighty and insup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portable
Expence, are the common Topicks
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
of those who argue in the usual Methods a<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gainst
this War; but though these are con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>siderable,
and shall have something said to
them in their Course; yet these are the least
of the Evils, which if our Fore-sight is not
clouded by the Power and Influence of Par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ties
found, may be by necessary and inevttable
Consequences, to follow the entring at this
time upon a War with the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Situation of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> their Strength
at Sea, their Possessions in the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West-Indies,</hi>
and their reigning Influence in the
<hi>North</hi> and <hi>East</hi> Seas, are Reasons why we
must expect uncommon Mischiefs should at<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tend
our Trade in the beginning of such a
War; this was always the Effect of a <hi>Dutch</hi>
War, and it was remarkable, that in the
last War with the <hi>Dutch</hi> we lost 2000 Sail of
Ships great and small the first Year: No
part of our Commerce is free from them or
out of their reach: On the contrary, some
of the best Parts of our Trade are in great
Danger of being entirely lost to them, such
as the <hi>East-India, African</hi> and <hi>East</hi> Country
Trades in particular; it is apparent, if a
due Enquiry were made, we should see small
hope of continuing and preserving our In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terest
in them under a War with the <hi>Dutch;</hi>
their Collonies of superiour Strength lying
so near ours in the two First, and their Po<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tent
Alliances in the latter, enabling them
effectually to supplant Us.</p>
         <p>The Disturbance they always upon these
Occasions gave us in our <hi>Home Trade,</hi> and the
impossibility of our carrying it on, but with
<pb n="5" facs="4"/>
manifest Disadvantage, is a strong Argument
to open our Eyes in the Case of a <hi>Dutch</hi> War;
there are other Parts which respect our
Coal and Salt Trade, our Corn Trade, our
<hi>Hull</hi> and <hi>Lynn</hi> Carriage, our Trade to <hi>Scot<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>land,</hi>
and our Fishing Trade: In all which,
the Interruptions of Commerce by a <hi>Dutch</hi>
War have been such, as have been felt by
all our People.</p>
         <p>The Gentlemen who are so fond of this
War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> have perhaps not yet
examin'd the Trading Consequences of it,
and as they are Landed Men, and fancy
they are no way dependent upon Trade,
they have forgotten, what so often, and by
so many unanswerable Arguments has been
proved to them, <hi>viz.</hi> That as Trade only
was the Original Cause of the encreas'd Va<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lue
of Lands, and the high Rents which
now the Gentlemen receive; so the decay
and ruin of Trade, must of course sink the
Value of Land, lower the Rents, and re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duce
the Tenant, to an incapacity to sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>port
the Landlord; by which means, a War
will of course affect the Landed-man as well
as the Merchant: Wherefore the Landed
Gentlemen are desired to give themselves the
Trouble to enquire into the following Par<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ticulars,
as they are likely to be affected by
a War with the <hi>States General.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>First,</hi> Whether the Landed Men about
<hi>New Castle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> will not be effected
by the interruption of the Coal Trade? Whe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther
when Coals are at 4 <hi>l.</hi> a Chaldron at
<pb n="6" facs="5"/>
            <hi>London,</hi> and on the Coasts, it will not con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>siderably
lessen the Consumption? And
whether in the last <hi>Dutch</hi> War the Quantity
of Coals carry'd out were not lessen'd above
50000 Chaldron in a Year?</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether the Landed Men borde<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
upon all the Coasts, from <hi>Hull</hi> in the
<hi>North,</hi> to the River <hi>Thames,</hi> and on to the
Coast of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Sussex,</hi> will not be affe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cted
by the Stop put to the vast Exportation
of Corn to <hi>Holland, &amp;c.</hi> the want of which
Sale, must of necessity make the Price fall
in <hi>England,</hi> by which the Tenant, not be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
able to get a Market for his Corn, is
disabled to pay his Rent, or hold his Farm
without an Abatement?</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether the Stop, put to the vast
Exportation of our Woolen Manufactures to
<hi>Holland,</hi> and which will be interrupted, if
not prohibited by a War, will not ruin Mul<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>titudes
of our Manufacturers in the Coun<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>try,
leave the Poor without Employment,
and prevent or greatly lessen, not the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sumption
of Wool only, but the General
Consumption of Provisions, by which the
Landed Men's Estates, must of course be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duced,
and their Rents remain unpaid?</p>
         <p>These Things, if it was imagin'd, any
Man could object against them might be
farther enlarg'd upon, and the particular
Trades which would suffer in such an Inter<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruption
<pb n="7" facs="6"/>
of Commerce, might be examined,
where it would appear.</p>
         <p>That the great Trade of Broad Cloath,
Kersies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> one of the greatest Branches of
Trade in <hi>England,</hi> particularly at <hi>Leeds, Hu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thersfield,
Wakefield, Hallifax, Bradford, Roch<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dale,</hi>
and the adjacent Parts, and where it is
by modest Computation supposed, Four
Hundred Thousand People are employ'd and
maintained in the Woolen Manafacture,
that this great Trade is principally main<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tained
and supported by the Exportation to
<hi>Holland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>That the Stop to that Exportation, must
of necessity encourage the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in the
Making the same kind of Goods in their own
Country, particularly at <hi>Leyden,</hi> where they
have for some Years endeavour'd it, and are
Daily improving.</p>
         <p>That above Two Hundred Thousand
Pound Value of the said Goods are Yearly
exported to <hi>Holland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>That the North-Riding of <hi>York-shire,</hi> Bi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>shoprick
of <hi>Durham,</hi> and great part of <hi>Lan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cashire,</hi>
and <hi>Westmoreland</hi> are supported, by
breeding and feeding Cattle, for the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>suption
of the <hi>West Riding;</hi> and if the <hi>Dutch</hi>
Trade receive such a Check, or Interrupti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on,
the Consequence is evident; the poor
People will want Employ, which want of
Employ is immediately felt, in the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sumption
of Provisions, and that again
in the Rent of our Lands: And indeed it
cannot be a little wonder'd at, to see the
Landed Men in this Nation, value them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves
<pb n="8" facs="7"/>
so much, upon their running down
our Trade, as if the Lands had no Depen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dance
upon Trade, or that Lands cou'd hold
up their Value, if our Trade were decay'd:
This Article of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Trade, will satisfy
any reasonable Person, that it cannot be;
I pray God, we do not too fatally try the
Experiment at this time, nor is this the least
Reason why I mention this Argument at this
time, that our Landed-Men may learn to
know what made them rich, and what may
again reduce them to what they were some
Ages ago.</p>
         <p>It is true, Trade has given us no Land,
<hi>Britain</hi> is no larger than it was before; but
it is not unworthy our Thoughts, and may
be proper to recommend it to these Gentle<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>men
to consider, That Trade has added a
new Value to what we had before; the Rents
of Lands are risen in time to such a Degree,
that what was formerly worth 10 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi>
is now worth 100 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> and what has
done this? What, but our Trade? Our Ge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>neral
Commerce, which had it been more
effectually covered, encouraged and under<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stood,
would have been able to have done
much more.</p>
         <p>Come we next to speak to the <hi>Corn-Trade;</hi>
this is more sensibly understood by those
Gentlemen, whose Estates lye near the Sea,
more particularly upon the Coasts of <hi>Lin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>colnshire,
Yorkshire,</hi> and the several Countries
which border upon the <hi>Humber,</hi> or on the
Navigable Rivers, emptying themselves in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>to
the <hi>Humber,</hi> as also upon the Coasts of
<pb n="9" facs="8"/>
            <hi>Norfolk,</hi> such as <hi>Yarmouth, Cromer, Clye, Wells,
Burnham</hi> and <hi>Lynn,</hi> the Navigations of the
River <hi>Ouse,</hi> and the Towns of <hi>Wisbich,</hi> and
<hi>Spalding</hi> in the Isle of <hi>Ely;</hi> again, on the
Coasts of <hi>Sussex, Essex,</hi> and <hi>Kent,</hi> all which
Counties, find their Daily Advantages from
the incredible Quantity of Corn every Year
exported to <hi>Holland,</hi> without which Expor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tation,
it would be impossible for the Te<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nants
in those Countries to vend the Corn
they owe, and by Consequence, the Lands
in those Counties, must either lye unma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nur'o,
or at least be laid down, and only em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ploy'd
in breeding of Cattle, a poor Trade
and which is now left to the <hi>Northern</hi> and
<hi>Western</hi> Parts of <hi>England,</hi> and to the <hi>Highlands</hi>
of <hi>Scotland;</hi> the Consequence of which
would be the lessening the Value of Land,
sinking the Rents, and reducing the Estates
of the Landed Men.</p>
         <p>These would be some of the more imme<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diate
Consequences of a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi>
and are mention'd here, because as Mankind
are more apt to be sensible of that Mischief
most, which touches them soonest; it can<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>not
but be very reasonable to expect, That
these People, however at present unaffected
with the Danger of a War with <hi>Holland,</hi>
may think fit to change their Minds, when
they examine more stricly into the thing,
and shall find, that they will be immediate<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly
touch'd by it in the most sensible part.</p>
         <p>There are several other immediate Cases,
in which a War with <hi>Holland</hi> will affect us,
in Matters of Trade, and which it having
<pb n="10" facs="9"/>
been so long ago, since we had such a War,
our People are a little too apt to forget:
But which if they please to recollect them<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>selves,
they will find, will more nearly
touch them, than perhaps they are aware
of, as especially the Price of Coals, touch'd
at before, which will particularly affect the
Inhabitants of this City and County's adja<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cent,
where Three Pounds and Four Pounds
a Chaldron have been accounted but a mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>derate
Price for Coals, and which is occa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sion'd
by the direct Situation of the <hi>Hollan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ders,</hi>
whose Ports immediately opening to
the North Channel, the <hi>Colliers</hi> Ships are
in ten Fold more danger from them, than
they can be from the <hi>French</hi> Privateers, in
Case of a War with <hi>France.</hi> It is needless to en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>large
how many other Trades this will affect,
how much dearer it will make all such Goods
as are wrought by Fire, but especially how
severely it will pinch the midling Families
of our Tradesmen and the Poor, who have
no Relief in Case of Cold Weather about
this City, there being no Woods and Forrests
as in the Country, to supply them with
Fewel, and who are put to inexpressible
Hardships in the Winter for want of Coal.</p>
         <p>The Rates of <hi>Salt,</hi> another Necessary of
Life, is a Thing deserves our Consideration
in Case of Trade; the City of <hi>London,</hi> and
all this Part of <hi>England,</hi> being supply'd with
<hi>Salt</hi> from <hi>New Castle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> from whence
the Danger being so great, the Price of
<hi>Salt</hi> was frequently in the late <hi>Dutch</hi> War,
although no Tax was then upon it, at 4 <hi>d.</hi>
            <pb n="11" facs="10"/>
            <hi>per</hi> Pound, and may now possibly be double
that Price.</p>
         <p>These are Matters of Trade, and indeed
are but a small part of what might be said
upon that Subject, but however, may serve
to shew, That a War with <hi>Holland</hi> can ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver
happen, without plunging us into many
great Difficulties, such as will justify me in
saying, That we ought never to engage in
such a War, without such an absolute and un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>avoidable
Necessity, as will abundantly make
the bearing all these Inconveniences easy
and rational to Us.</p>
         <p>But alas! these are but the smaller Consi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>derations
in this Case, and are mentioned here
in order to make good the first part of
the Argument, laid down in the beginning
of this Work: The more fatal Consequences
of a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> are such as respect
the Politick Concerns of <hi>Europe,</hi> and are of
infinite Value to Us: I shall examin them
apart.</p>
         <list>
            <item>I It must be a War in Defence of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>II. It must be ruinous to the <hi>Protestant In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terest.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>III. It must be Dangerous to the <hi>Hannover</hi>
Succession.</item>
            <item>IV. It must be fatal many ways to us, who are
to be engag'd in it.</item>
            <item>V. It must be a War against the general Incli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nation
of the People.</item>
            <item>VI. It must be a War, in which the greatest
Success will be a Loss to Us.</item>
            <item>
               <pb n="12" facs="11"/>
VII. It must be a War, in which we are very
likely to have the Disadvantage.</item>
            <item>VIII. It must be a very bloody War, that will be
far from being carry'd on in Jest, as the present
War with <hi>France</hi> has been, especially at Sea.</item>
         </list>
         <p>I cannot promise to go thorow all these
effectually, in the short Compass of this
Tract: However, I shall begin, and speak<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
more largely to those which are most
necessary, I shall touch lightly the rest,
and perhaps speak more effectually to them
hereafter.</p>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>I. It must be a War in Defence of Popery.</head>
            <p>I know it has been argued on many Oc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>casions,
That this War was not begun on
account of <hi>Religion,</hi> it was the Argument the
<hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Advocates strove to make
use of all along, subtilly to engage the Zea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lous
People the more sincerely in their Quar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rel,
and stir them up to Blood and Destru<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ction:
We find many Instances of this, in
the Accounts of the last few Years, especi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ally
in the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Letter to the
<hi>Pope,</hi> relating to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who
was then newly come over to the Confede<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rates,
wherein he complains of his Royal
Highness joining with <hi>Hereticks</hi> and the Ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies
of God's Church, meaning the <hi>Prussian</hi>
and <hi>Saxe-Gotha</hi> Troops, whom he calls Ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies
to GOD and his Church, and which
he says they impiously brought into <hi>Italy:</hi>
But after all that has been said on that Head,
<pb n="13" facs="12"/>
tho' we are not now on the Foot of a Reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gious
War, yet if we fight with the <hi>Dutch,</hi>
we certainly fight against the Protestant Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ligion
in Defence of Popery; perhaps it may
not be immediately concern'd, but it is so in
its visible Effects, and no Man can be so
blind as not to see it. The Powers hereby
protected are all Popish; Popish, even to
Bigottry, especially the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> They
have not only strengthened themselves
against the Protestant Religion, but by the
Destruction of the Protestants themselves,
and that in the severest manner.</p>
            <p>Let any Man but take a View of them
separately <hi>in France;</hi> how has the <hi>French</hi> Go<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vernor
expelled 400000 Protestants out of
their Dominions, suffering all the Damages,
which the loss of so many Subjects, and their
moveable Estates, must of necessity be to a
Nation, rather than not to root out the
Protestant Religion; and indeed they have
rooted it out of most part of the Nation,
and one Age of Persecution more will most
effectually do it. How have they since pur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sued
the poor Remains of the Protestant Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ligion,
in the Mountains of the <hi>Cevennes,</hi> and
put all that have fallen into their Hands to
Death, by the cruellest Torments imagina<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble?
How have they lately done the same
in the little Principallity of <hi>Orange,</hi> tho' in
all probability they were to restore that
Country upon a Peace? In <hi>Spain,</hi> how
have we found the Aversions of the People,
to our great Damage in the War there, while
our Troops have been Maletreated by the
<pb n="14" facs="13"/>
               <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Porteguese,</hi> even while we came
there to assist them, rejecting their own
Deliverance, <hi>I speak of those well affected to
King</hi> Charles III. only because the Assistance
brought them was carry'd on by Heretick
Forces, and that the Protestants were so
odious to them, that they could not bear
to be deliver'd by them. These are the
People we must fight for, when ever we
take up Arms against the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> for these
the Blood of <hi>English</hi> Men and <hi>Britains</hi> is to
be spilt, and the Wealth of a Protestant
Nation exhausted, and that not only for
the People of these Nations, but for their
very Religion too; could we distinguish
between the Men and their Principles, be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tween
the Interest of the Nations, and the
Interest of their Religion, it were the bet<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter
to be born with: But our Case is ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tremly
hard, for it is not so much the Na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tional
Interest, as the Religious Interest that
eventually will be the Concern of the War,
and we fight even for Popery it self:
The Propagation of the Bigottry and Su<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perstition
of those Nations being so twisted
with their Power, that the latter never
goes without the former, and they never
did extend their Conquest and Dominions
to any Place, where they have not esta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>blished
their Idolatry and Superstition, nay,
nor where they have not apply'd themselves
to expunge and race out the very Name of
the Protestant Religion, and the least Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mains
of the Protestant Worship. This con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>firms
the Head I am upon, that when ever
<pb n="15" facs="14"/>
the unhappy Hour shall come, that the
Sword should be drawn in this Quarrel, it
is drawn by the Nature and Consequence of
the Thing, in Defence of POPERY;
What Protestant then can think of this with<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>out
Horror? How ruinous must this be to
the Protestant Interest! How destructive to
the Safety of Religion, to the Freedom of
Conscience, and to the Prosperity of the
Churches abroad! <hi>Of which by it self;</hi> but
particularly, how dreadful a Work must
this be for Protestants to do? With what
Face can any Man, who is a Professor of
the Protestant Religion, draw his Sword in
such a Quarrel? And which is still worse,
how can any Protestant put his Hand to the
contriving and bringing to pass such a War.
I have no Hand in, or Eye towards, who is,
or is not concern'd in the Measures that have
a Tendency to this; some say one side are
guilty of it, some the other, and both
seem to agree that it will be a Consequence
of what is now doing; but I am desirous
faithfully to represent to both Sides, what
the meaning of a War with <hi>Holland</hi> is, what
it implies, and what Effects will necessarily
follow, that both Parties may lay their
Hands upon their Hearts, and reflect with
Seriousness what they are about, when they
draw their Swords against their Brethren.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>II. It must be ruinous to the Protestant Interest.</head>
            <p>This is little more than the Reverse of the
other as to the part of Religion, because
<pb n="16" facs="15"/>
the Defence of Popery must be the Ruin, or
at least the Damage of the Protestant Reli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gion;
but I choose to call this the <hi>Protestant
Interest,</hi> because tho' the Religious Interest
depends upon it, and must follow the Fate
of it upon all Occasions, yet the Civil and
Politick Interest of the Protestants, is what
I am now speaking of, and how far the
present Case will affect it will soon appear:
Nothing is more evident, than that the King<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>doms
of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>junction
with the States General, are the
main Strength of the Protestant Interest in
the World. The Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> with
the Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> are consi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>derable,
it is true, and not at all to be de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spised;
but alas! how long would all these,
put together, be able to support the Prote<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stant
Cause, or to defend themselves against
the Power of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>German</hi> Popery!
How soon would the Light of the Prote<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stant
Religion in the World be extinguished,
if the Popish Powers of <hi>Europe</hi> were com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bin'd
against those few Northern Provinces!
But the Center of Protestant Strength lies
in the joint Forces, Power and Wealth of
the Two Maritime Potentates, <hi>Great Britain</hi>
and <hi>Holland,</hi> their Forces by Land have alone
been able to match the Popish Powers of
<hi>Europe,</hi> and to look the King of <hi>France</hi> in the
Face, and their United Force at Sea is ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>knowledg'd
to be superiour to all the known
World, tho' all their Naval Strength was put
together.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="16"/>
Upon this Strength the Protestant Inte<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rest,
speaking of second Causes entirely de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pends,
this makes the Protestants formi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dable
to the World; this alone has re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>strain'd
the Popish Powers of the World
from over-running them many Ages ago:
Farther than this, it may not be unnecessary
to reflect, what Blows the Protestant Inte<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rest
has already received in these 20 or 30
Years past, how much weaker it is by Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sequence
than it was before, and thereby
how unable to resist the Effects of new
Enemies, if join'd together; much
more, how little need there is to have
yet deeper Wounds made in their Interest,
than was before: These things are evident
in the following Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Extirpation of the Protestants of
<hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Succession of the Roman Catho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick
House of <hi>Newburgh</hi> to the <hi>Pala<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tinate.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The going over of the Elector of <hi>Saxo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ny</hi>
to the Romish Church.</item>
               <item>4. The weakening and oppressing the
King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and divesting the <hi>Swedes</hi>
(who are Guarrantees of the Treaty of
<hi>Westphalia</hi>) of their Dominions in the
Empire.</item>
               <item>5. The Danger of a Popish Successor to
the Crowns of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In considering these Things, what Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>flections
must needs follow to any one, who
<pb n="18" facs="17"/>
with an impartial Eye, and a just Concern
for the Protestant Interest, can look on the
approaching Danger of a bloody War be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tween
<hi>Great Britain</hi> and the <hi>States General;</hi>
what a mortal Wound this would be to the
Protestant Interest, What a Breach it would
make in the Protestant Strength, and how
effectually it would expose the Protestant
Cause to be over-run by the Arms and In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terest
of the Popish Princes, who we have
always found ready to devour them.</p>
            <p>Let those who want Examples to illustrate
this, look back upon the Year 1672, when
this Nation gull'd by the Arts and Politicks
of Popish Councils, was drawn in to fight
against the <hi>Dutch;</hi> How did it open a way
to all those terrible Conquests, which the
<hi>French</hi> King made upon the <hi>Dutch,</hi> by which
he was within a Trifle of dissolving their
State, and uniting them all to the Kingdom
of <hi>France,</hi> and by which we had like at that
time to have overwhelm'd the Protestant
Religion in the World? And in a Word, by
which this Nation also was at last brought
to such a Desperate Point, that had not
the Revolution fallen in to rescue us from
the Danger, we had fallen into the Ballance
of Power on the Popish Side, and had
help'd to outweigh the Protestants, to their
universal Destruction: This may serve to
warn us all from falling into the like Blind<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness
of Measures, and nothing is more won<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>derful,
than to find our People so willing to
run into it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="18"/>
What can our falling upon the <hi>Dutch</hi> at
this time imply? What can the Effect of it
be? Will it not be an immediate weakening
of them in their Defence of the Protestant
Religion, and a direct strengthing their Ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mies
to destroy them? And will it not be
an effectual weakening of us also, so as at
last perhaps to render us both too weak to
do that, tho' join'd together, which either
of us are able to do now apart, in Defence
of what is the mutual Interest of both?</p>
            <p>Add to this how both Nations are al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ready
exhausted, and emptied by the long
and continu'd Burthen of this heavy and ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pensive
War, that as it has been these 22
Years dreining us, it will require twice that
time at least to restore and recover us: So
that we are in a much worse Condition
to waste one another farther; since it
will of course so entirely expend our Strength
and Capacity for our mutual Defence, that
it must render both Sides an easie Prey to
the Enemy, as is happily express'd by the
Fable of the two small Birds, who having
been long fighting together, the Eagle
came and snatch'd away both.</p>
            <p>Let every considering Protestant summon
his Reason, and in the most affectionate man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ner
persuade the Nations, if it be possible,
to avoid so dangerous a Step as this, which
has a direct Tendency to destroy the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>testant
Interest in the World, and which
cuts off the Hands that should defend it; let
them consider how the Enemies of our Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ligion
would rejoice; how they would pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mise
<pb n="20" facs="19"/>
themselves from these Divisions and
Distractions among Protestants, that one
time or other they should break in and de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vour
the whole Interest; let them remem<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ber
that the like Strife among Christians,
was the very thing that let <hi>Mahomet</hi> the
Great into <hi>Europe,</hi> and gave leisure and op<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portunity
to the Barbarians, to overthrow
the Remains of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Empire, take
<hi>Constantinople,</hi> and plant themselves and their
<hi>Pagan</hi> Superstition on the Ruins of the flou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rishing
Christian Churehes: This was the
time the famous City of <hi>Constantinople</hi> was
taken, and the Emperor <hi>Constantine</hi> slain in it,
after a long Siege by the <hi>Turks:</hi> Not one of
the Christian Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> sending the
least Help, or stirring one Foot to the As<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sistance
of the Christian Emperor, who lost
his Life in the Storm of the City; not that
the Christian Powers of <hi>Europe</hi> were not
able to have reliev'd the City, and to have
driven the <hi>Turk</hi> out of <hi>Europe,</hi> but they were
universally embroil'd in furious Wars against
one another, <hi>France</hi> was just rescuing its self
out of the Hands of the <hi>English,</hi> under the
weak and divided Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> 6th; and
<hi>Germany</hi> was embroil'd in Wars between the
Emperor <hi>Fredrick</hi> and the Pope, by which
Means every Hand was employ'd, and that
Power which should have protected the Chri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stian
Interest was weaken'd to that Degree,
that the Christians were in no Condition to
oppose the victorious <hi>Turks,</hi> but let them
quietly over-run a great part of <hi>Europe.</hi> I
would have all those, who are desirous of
<pb n="21" facs="20"/>
engaging these two <hi>Protestant Nations,</hi> in a
War one with another, read that melan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>choly
Story, and consider how exactly this
would be the Case, between <hi>Papists</hi> and
<hi>Protestants:</hi> Let them consider, what De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>predations
the <hi>Popish</hi> Powers of <hi>Europe</hi>
would make on the <hi>Protestant</hi> Princes du<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ring
such a time: Let them examin in
what Posture we should be to protect the
<hi>Protestant</hi> Interest, in Case of any Excursion
of its <hi>Popish</hi> Enemies; how it would lessen
the Figure the <hi>Protestants</hi> now make, weaken
their Hands, render them Contemptible to
their Enemies, and lay them open to the
Attempts of those, who have been hitherto
restrained only by fear, from devouring
them.</p>
            <p>3. Nor would Victory on either hand
mend it, for the Protestant Interest being
coucerned, but as one Body in the whole
Quarrel would equally suffer, which Side
soever obtained the Victory; and this leads
me to the Third Head, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>III. It must be a War, in which the greatest
Success will be a Loss to Us.</head>
            <p>It will be to no purpose for any Side to
boast of Victory in this War, since their very
Conquest is their Loss, and they are just
so much weaker in the <hi>Protestant Cause,</hi> as
by their Conquest they have weaken'd their
Brethren, since in their Common Interest
they are but one Body, and have but one
<pb n="22" facs="21"/>
Strength, one Interest, and one Foundation
upon which they stand; it is very unhappy
that these things cannot pierce a little into
our Thoughts, but that we are all intent at
such a time as this, either on pushing on a
War, or settling a particular Peace, and leaving
the Views and Prospects of establishing <hi>Europe,</hi>
we are turning our Eyes upon a Breach with
our Protestant Allies; I do not desire to con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cern
the present Debates among Us about
War and Peace in this Matter, I have no<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thing
to do with who <hi>directly,</hi> or who <hi>con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sequently</hi>
push on a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> but
directing my Speech to both Parties, I would
faithfully represent to them, the Ruin and
Distress that such a War would bring upon
the <hi>Protestant Interest</hi> in general; how
which Side soever get the better, <hi>Popery</hi>
alone gains by the Victory; every Battle
fought weakens the very Conqueror as <hi>Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>testant,</hi>
as much as it does those that are
beaten: This is what I would move them
to do, that they may if possible find out
some happy Medium, either on one Side or
other; I do not undertake here to say what,
but <hi>I say,</hi> some happy Medium, to prevent
the giving up the <hi>Protestant Cause</hi> to be de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>voured
by the <hi>Popish Tyrants</hi> of the World;
that <hi>Protestants</hi> may not whet their Swords
against one another, as they already do
their Tongues in a Dreadful and Implaca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble
manner; That they would remember
every Drop of Blood they shed in this Quar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rel,
leaves them just so much the less to op<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose
against <hi>Popish</hi> Power, when that Day
<pb n="23" facs="22"/>
shall come, <hi>as undoubtedly it will,</hi> when the
Fate of the whole <hi>Protestant Interest</hi> may be
try'd by the Sword, and the Forces of all
<hi>Europe</hi> shall be divided in a <hi>Religious War;</hi> I
can compare this unhappy Case of a War,
between <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> to nothing so
well, as to the War between the Children
of <hi>Israel,</hi> against their Brethren of the Tribe
of <hi>Benjamin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is remarkable for the fury of it, as ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pears
in the Tribes Swearing, binding one
another by an Oath, or a great Oath as the
Text hath it, That every Man that came
not up to the Lord at <hi>Mizpeth,</hi> that is, to
fight against <hi>Benjamin,</hi> should be put to
Death; and another Oath they had also
made, <hi>viz.</hi> That they would not any of
them give their Daughters to a <hi>Benjamite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Story is too well known to repeat
the Particulars, the War was carry'd on with
great Fury, and was very bloody, as such
Wars always are; it was so bloody that
they spared neither Age, Sex or Condition,
no, nor the very Cattle; but burnt down
all their Cities, and all that came to hand,
<hi>Judg.</hi> 20. 48. So that the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi>
was entirely cut off, only Six Hundred Men
being left alive of the whole Race: And
what Joy had <hi>Israel</hi> of this Victory! they had
no sooner done it, but see the Title or Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tents
of the next Chapter. <hi>The People bewail
the Desolation of Benjamin:</hi> vide Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s An<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>notations
and Contents, on <hi>Judges</hi> xxi.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="23"/>
Next see the manner of their bewailing it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the People came to the House of God, and a<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bode
there till even before God, and lift up their
voices, and wept sore: And said, O LORD
God of Israel, why is this come to pass in Israel,
that there shonld be to day one Tribe lacking in
Israel? And it came to pass, on the morrow, that
the People rose early, and built there an Altar,
and offered Burnt Offerings, and Peace Offerings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>And the Children of Israel
repented them for Benjamin their Brother, and
said, There is one tribe cut off from Israel this
Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See here the mournful Satisfaction of Vi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ctory
over our Friends! what is the English
of it but this, <hi>There is one Tribe cut off from Is<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rael?</hi>
That is, should <hi>we now</hi> be invaded by the
<hi>Heathen,</hi> by the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> the <hi>Philistines</hi> or
the <hi>Midianites,</hi> or any of the Barbarous Na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions;
there is one Tribe less, to help de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fend
the Borders of <hi>Israel:</hi> Our Brethren of
<hi>Benjamin</hi> are cut off, and we are left naked
on that Side, we are just so much the weaker
by our Victory.</p>
            <p>How exactly does this answer to the
Case before us? Should either Side prevail,
should we beat, should we conquer the <hi>Dutch,</hi>
should the Heathen (<hi>French</hi>) fall in upon
them, and over-run them entirely, <hi>as in</hi> 1672
<hi>they had almost done, by our infatuated Assistance,</hi>
what would be our Joy in this Conquests?
Should we not reflect on our selves after it,
and <hi>repent our selves for Benjamin?</hi> Should we
not say, <hi>why is this come to pass among</hi> Prote<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stants,
<hi>that a Tribe or Nation of</hi> Protestants <hi>is</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="24"/>
               <hi>now lacking in Israel?</hi> Should we not lament
for <hi>Benjamin,</hi> that a Tribe was cut off from
the <hi>Protestant</hi> Strength?</p>
            <p>On the other Hand, should this War fall
heavy on Us, and though Ruin is what we
pretend not to fear, yet might it not so
weaken us, as to expose us an easy Prey to
the <hi>Pretender</hi> and his Party, which would
be the worst sort of Ruin; would not the
<hi>Dutch</hi> themselves, and the whole Body of
the Protestants of <hi>Europe, Bewail the Desolati<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on
of Benjamin,</hi> and repent them for having
lost a Tribe from the <hi>Protestant Israel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let all those, as well of one Side or other,
who are either hasty for, or indifferent in
the Case of a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> look into
these Things, and consider seriously what
they are doing; consider the Consequence
of a War, in which, whether conquering
or conquered, the Interest of the Protestant
Religion suffers, and the Strength of the
Protestant Powers is weakned, and we shall
all have Cause to bewail the Desolation of
our Brethren.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <head>IV. This War will be dangerous to the Protestant
Succession.</head>
            <p>By the Protestant Succession, I suppose
all Men will understand me, to mean the
Succession of the House of <hi>Hannover</hi> to the
Crowns of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> after
the Demise of Her Present Majesty QUEEN
<hi>ANNE,</hi> and I have good Reason, from the
Iniquity of the Times, <hi>wherein Jacobite Di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stinctions</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="25"/>
               <hi>are very subtle and many,</hi> to make this
Explanation. Now let any Man but seriously
examine the Consequences of a War, with
the Guarrantees of that Succession, and what
will he infer, but that however intentio<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nally
it may not be so, yet effectually and
eventually, it will be a War against the <hi>Suc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cession</hi>
it self; not that I enter here into the
Case, whether the Guarrantee of the <hi>Dutch</hi>
were necessary, as was thought by way of
Treaty: Let that be as it will, this is cer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain,
That the <hi>Dutch</hi> as a Protestant State,
Ally'd in Interest to both, <hi>viz.</hi> to the House
of <hi>Hannover</hi> and to the <hi>British</hi> Nation, and
their own Safety, absolutely requiring, that
this Nation should never come into <hi>Popish</hi>
Hands, are an undoubted Natural Security
to the Protestant Succession, and unless their
Power be broken by such a War as this,
must be supposed always to be ready by a
natural Consequence, to assist and support
the said Succession, and all the Friends of
it, with all their Might; they can do no other,
if they are not like us infatuated and blind
to their own Safety and Interest; nor is this
the least part of our Security against the
<hi>Pretender,</hi> and all the <hi>Jacobite</hi> Enemies of the
said Protestant Succession, especially those
of them who are Abroad.</p>
            <p>Those then who propagate, whether o<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>penly
or clandestinely, a Breach between
the Two Nations, are so far real Enemies to
the <hi>Hannover</hi> Succession, let their Views and
Designs, Measures or Pretences be what
they will, such, while they cry out Zealously
<pb n="27" facs="26"/>
for the Protestant Succession, would do well
to tell Us, how shall the Elector of <hi>Hanno<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver</hi>
support his Right? How shall he come
over hither with Forces and Armies in case
of a contending <hi>Pretender,</hi> who may be pri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vately
convey'd hither before him? How
shall he recover the Possession, or come to
the Assistance of his Friends and their Inte<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rest,
who may be oppress'd by a <hi>Jacobite</hi>
Faction; if the <hi>Dutch</hi> are ruin'd, and their
Naval Strength broken by that very Nati<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion
they should come to save?</p>
            <p>A War with <hi>Holland,</hi> would in many re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spects
therefore be a War against the Prote<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stant
Succession, as well as against the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>testant
Religion; nay some who have exa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>min'd
that Affair very nicely, affirm with
me, That there is indeed <hi>no other real Danger</hi>
of the <hi>Hannover</hi> Succession, but the ruining
the <hi>Dutch,</hi> for that whatever the Artifice of
Parties may bring to pass, and however the
<hi>High flying</hi> and <hi>Jacobite</hi> Party in League
with <hi>France,</hi> and other <hi>Popish</hi> Powers, may
form a Conjunction of Interest, so as to erect
the Pretender; nay, tho' they were to set
him upon the Throne, yet that there will al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ways
be such a Body, of the best, the wisest,
and the most considerable People of this Na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion,
steady to the Interest of the House of
<hi>Hannover,</hi> and firm to the Solemn Abjuration
they have made of the <hi>Pretender,</hi> that on
the first appearance of the Protestant Suc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessor,
with any reasonable Force to sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>port
them, they would show themselves able
to overthrow all their Enemies, and restore
<pb n="28" facs="27"/>
the Nation to the Right Establish'd Succes<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sor,
in spight of all the Opposition, that the
Enemies of the Protestant Interest could
make: But if the <hi>Dutch</hi> before this should
be oppressed by a War, and their Naval
Strength and Power broken by us, in vain
we may stretch out our Hands to the Succes<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sor
for help, who cannot without a Fleet
yield us that Assistance, or do himself that
Justice, which otherwise he is very well able
to do, so that fighting against the <hi>Dutch,</hi> is
cutting off the Right-hand of the Successi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on:
On the other hand, should the Forces
of <hi>Britain</hi> be broken or weaken'd in this
War against the <hi>Dutch,</hi> still so much the less
able we shall be to resist the Efforts of the
<hi>Pretender,</hi> whether he comes back't by a <hi>French</hi>
or a <hi>Spanish</hi> Power, or depending upon the
Interest of his <hi>Jacobite</hi> Friends and Faction
at Home; a Nation exhausted, impoverish'd,
and tyr'd out with War, cannot be in so good
a Condition to resist an Invader, nor so
warmly inclin'd to engage in a new War,
against Tyranny and Oppression, as while
we are whole and in Condition; so that
which way soever we take this War, and
which way soever the Success of a <hi>Dutch</hi>
War shall fall, it will be Dangerous if not
Fatal to the Protestant Succession of the
House of <hi>Hannover.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>V. It must be a War fatal many ways to Us,
who are engag'd in it.</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="28"/>
This, besides what relates as before to
the Protestant Interest, and the <hi>Hannover</hi>
Succession, will be consider'd, as it respects
our Commerce, our publick Credit, our ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hausted
Circumstances, and our general Ci<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vil
Interest; what relates to Commerce, has
been touch'd at already, and I may only
add this, that as our Trade in general
is already prodigiously sunk, by the long
Interruption of 22 Years War; the Damage
of which will not in some Ages, <hi>if Ever,</hi> be
wholly repair'd; So a War with <hi>Holland</hi> at
this time, would give such a Blow to that
Part which remains, that in general our
whole Trade would be overwhelmed in Dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ficulties
and Confusions inextricable; the
Employment of the Poor, by the Stop and
Interruption of Commerce in the present
Wars, has in several Parts of <hi>England</hi> been
quite stopt, in others they are taken off of the
Manufactures they were originally bred to. So
that whole Towns remain now Destitute of
so much as the appearance of those Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nufactures
they were formerly wholly ta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ken
up with; our Colonies Abroad, by the
stop of the Consumption and Exportation of
their Produce, occasion'd by the War, are
oblig'd to leave Planting, as in <hi>Virginia</hi> in
particular, and apply themselves to Manu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>factures,
by which in a few Years the sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ply
of Woollen Manufactures, which usual<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly
was sent from hence, will be effectually
stopp'd. All these and many more will be
encreased by a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to whom,
including <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> at this time, we ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>port
<pb n="30" facs="29"/>
more of our Woolen, Manufactures than
to all Parts of the World besides, tho' put
together.</p>
            <p>What then shall be the Condition of our
People, when as before the Export of our
Broad Cloth, Kersies, Serges and Stuffs, of
which the <hi>Dutch</hi> now receive such great
Quantities shall be stop'd, and when the
poor People, who now live upon those Em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ployments,
shall be destitute of Work, and
be left to seek their Bread? Let those
People that think a War with <hi>Holland</hi> of no
Consequence, consider of some Equivalent
for this, and of opening some Trade for
the vent of our Manufactures, which shall
sufficiently supply the Poor with Labour,
and raise Money effectually to pay them.</p>
            <p>If these Things were consider'd, we should
be more cautious, as well of coveting to
make a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as of pleasing
our selves with the Hopes that the <hi>Dutch</hi>
will force us to it.</p>
            <p>I shall not touch at the Consequences,
which some have already spoken to, in case
the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Emperor,</hi> pushing on the
War without Us, should reduce <hi>France,</hi> and
and recover <hi>Spain,</hi> not only without any As<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sistance
from Us, but even against our Will,
the many ways this may be fatal to Us, are
better thought of in private, than made pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick,
and it is hoped the Prudence of our Al<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lies
may avoid pushing us to those Extreme<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ties:
But I cannot omit mentioning again,
tho' spoken to before, how evidently such a
War would open a Door to <hi>the Pretender,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="30"/>
expose these Nations, as a Prey to the <hi>Jaco<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bite</hi>
Interest, as well at Home as Abroad; for
as some Men hope, so I cannot but see, that
in case of a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> the At<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tempts
of the <hi>Jacobite Party</hi> will be inevita<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble;
nor can they be so blind to their own
Interest, as not to know it; and this is the
true Reason, that you cannot converse at
this Time with a <hi>Jacobite,</hi> but you discover
his most Passionate Desire of a War with the
<hi>Dutch;</hi> all their Emissaries are busie, Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>claiming
against the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and Exasperating
our People against the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and if the <hi>States-General</hi>
do stand out against the <hi>British</hi> Mea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sures,
or take any Step that seems a little dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>obliging,
these Men, far from doing Justice
on either Hand, set all their Emissaries at
Work, to aggravate it, and make it appear
worse than really it is: On the other Hand,
the same Party in <hi>Holland</hi> act the very other
Extreme, and there they exclaim against the
<hi>British</hi> Measures, tell the <hi>Dutch</hi> they are Mal<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>treated,
that the <hi>British</hi> Parliament has used
them barbarously; That the <hi>British</hi> Ministry
impose upon them, and cram the Peace down
their Throats, and the like: The Reason is
evident, they seek nothing but a Breach, be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cause
they see clearly that a War is the only
Step that can make way for their Interest,
and open a Door to the Pretender.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>VI. It must be a War against the General Incli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nation
of the People.</head>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="31"/>
This seems to want no Proof, even the
Queen herself and the Ministry, however it
may seem, are averse to it, and the Measures ta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ken
with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> however Calculated to
carry on the Peace with the <hi>French,</hi> have
plainly discover'd, that it is not the Inclination
of the Ministry to break with the <hi>Dutch</hi> if
they can avoid it; they cannot but see, that
it will be <hi>Ruinous to our Trade,</hi> and that the
<hi>Burthens</hi> must be intollerable that must follow,
especially our present Impoverish'd Circum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stances
consider'd: Nor can it be Reasona<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble,
that the Ministry, who give the Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hausted
Condition of the Nation, as the best
and first Reason for making a Peace with
<hi>France,</hi> should at the same Time be so re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gardless
of that exhausted Condition of the
Nation, as to lead them into a War with
<hi>Holland;</hi> this would be to deny what they
had alledg'd before, and Contradict what
was the main Argument given, for Convin<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cing
us of the Necessity of former Measures,
<hi>viz.</hi> That the Nation was Reduced, Exhau<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sted,
Impoverish'd, and the like, and that
some Ages were requir'd to restore our Cir<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cumstances,
and this was acknowledg'd in
many Cases to be true; but the People
will, of course think themselves banter'd and
jested with in all that, if we think fit now
to run into another War, which may be e<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>very
way as fatal and as chargeable as the
other.</p>
            <p>As to the Inclination of the common Peo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ple,
that has many Ways been try'd, the
Aversions that formerly were in our People
<pb n="33" facs="32"/>
against a <hi>Dutch</hi> War, were too well known
to those who observ'd it, <hi>viz.</hi> with what
Backwardness they Engag'd! with what Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>luctance
they Listed! how the poor Seamen
were dragg'd into the Service, like a Bear
to the Stake! It would be too long to enter
upon the Reasons and Considerations which
moved this Aversion, the Thing speaks itself;
they have been long our Friends and Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>federates,
have often Assisted, Relieved, De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>liver'd
Us in our Embroiled Circumstances,
and we cannot without Reluctance, desire
to fight against a People whom we have so
often acted in Conjunction with: We have
look'd upon them as our Friends, as our Bre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thren,
in the late War, and it must be with
Regret, that our People should rejoyce in
contrary Extremes, and sheath their Swords
in the Bowels of those, who they shook
Hands with before.</p>
            <p>Trade, our mutual Converse in Business,
and the long Interwoven Interests of the
two Nations, cannot but Contribute to this
Inclination; and the Damage we shall feel,
and that immediately too, will assist to form
the Aversions which are in our Minds against
the War, and make our People abhorr the
Thoughts of it; but I need not insist upon
this, which every Man knows to be Fact,
and can trace the Original of; I come now
to consider the two last Articles, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="34" facs="33"/>
            <head>VII. That it will be a War, in which we are
very likely to have the Disadvantage.</head>
            <p>Not that I am of the Opinion that the
<hi>Dutch</hi> will beat Us, as some People talk, and
yet farther from pleasing myself with the
Hopes of it, as some pretend we do; but if,
as before, we shall be Losers, even by the
Success we may pretend to have in it, what
then must be the want of that Success, if such
a Case also should happen? Let those who
calmly Examin Things at all, look back on
the Stop of Trade, Loss of Shipping, Ruin
of Merchants, want of Employ for our Peo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ple;
mention'd before in this Tract, and judge
for themselves, as to the Advantages to Us;
but if we should have the worst of it at Sea
also, as no Man can Answer for the uncer<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tain
Events of War; if our Navy should be
Defeated, our Ships, which are our Strength,
receive any fatal Blow, which we are not
sure of the Disadvantages which will follow
to us, are such, as I shall, in hopes they will
never happen, conceal for the present.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> No more shall I think to terrifie any
from a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> by telling them
it will not be a War to be Trifled with; that
the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> when they used to meet
at Sea, do not use to make a Jest of it; fight<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
with the <hi>Dutch</hi> has always had a diffe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rence
in it from fighting with other Nations:
These fight at a distance, and lie and pelt one
another, while they are a quarter of a Mile
or half a Mile off, or pour in their small
<pb n="35" facs="34"/>
Shot upon one another, to pick off their
Men; but when the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> for<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>merly
used to meet, three Sea fights have been
fought with near 80 Sail of a side in one
Summer, the great 3 Deck Ships of 100 Guns
each, sink and burn by one another's Side,
and the Squadrons lie Yard-Arm and Yard-Arm,
pouring in their Cross-Bar, Double
Head and Round, and tearing one another
with that dreadful Fury, that nothing on
Earth can be spoken of, to describe those
Sea fights by; let those who remember the
last <hi>Holland</hi> Wars, tell us, whether the hot<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>test
Action we have had at Sea during this
War, can be compar'd to the Way of fighting
between Us and the <hi>Dutch?</hi> And there is no
Question to be made but the like must follow
again, if a New War begin; This seems evi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dent,
that the Animosity between the Nati<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ons,
is like to be as great as ever, and per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>haps
greater; and the War, if such a mise<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rable
Event should follow, will be Prosecu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted
with the greatest Fury that any War e<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver
was between Us.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid down the Consequences
of such a War, it cannot be thought that
any one in these Nations, who is a Friend
to the Protestant Succession, to the Prote<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stant
Religion, to the general Interest of
the Protestant Powers, to Trade, to the Poor,
or indeed to themselves, can desire to have
these two Protestant Nations engag'd with
one another, especially at such a Time as
this. It is an invidious Task to go about here
to make Enquiry who are, or are not desi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rous
of this War? Or who among us may,
<pb n="36" facs="35"/>
by pushing on their separate Schemes, bring
it to pass by the Consequence of these
Schemes, whether involuntarily or other<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wise,
it is too evident where this lies, to
need an Enquiry, but as I have made this
Piece hitherto independent, and look nei<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther
way, as to Parties, so it seems not at
all needful: The Advice is to both, or all
our Parties, that they would consider very
well what they are doing, what Interest
they are carrying on; whose alone will be
the Advantage; to whom will be the Joy
of such a War: For if these are our Dan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gers,
and if all these Disadvantages threaten
us by a War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> it cannot be,
but that a Proportion of Gain and Advan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tage
will accrue to the Enemy, for what is
our Loss, must on the other Hand be their
Advantage.</p>
            <p>I know, and easily foresee many Things
will be objected here, and it may be neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sary
to speak to them all in their Order,
tho' our Space at the end of this Work is
too short, to say all that might be spoken—The
Objections are such as these, <hi>viz.</hi> Tho'
it be true, that the Consequences of a War
with <hi>Holland,</hi> are, as you have said, yet
what must be done? We are not to let the
<hi>Dutch</hi> insult us, because it is our Disadvan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tage
so many ways to have War. That if
the <hi>Dutch</hi> reject the Measures proposed for
their Advantage, and Ours too, and car<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ry
Things on to an extravagant Height,
THEY force the War and not WE: That
by doing what is incompatible with our
<pb n="37" facs="36"/>
Interest, they in Effect declare the War; so
that it is They make War with the QUEEN,
not the QUEEN with Them: That the
<hi>Dutch</hi> are acted by a Faction from hence,
who prompt and persuade them to stand
out, and put them in hopes, that their do<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing
so, may bring Things to a new Turn
here, and put a new Face upon our Affairs,
and that all these Things push the present
Ministry upon the necessity of taking the
Measures they now pursue, to preserve the
present Government; and if the <hi>Dutch</hi> join
with a Party here, who oppose Her Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jesty's
just Measures, they bring the War
upon themselves, and that Party here are the
Cause, and ought to bear the Blame of the
War, and of all the Inconveniences and Da<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mages
that may follow.</p>
            <p>It is not my Work here to argue for or
against the Parties, as I said before, I am
rather for giving all the Latitude to the
Objectors on either Hand, and therefore I
willingly, for Arguments-sake, allow all
the Objection; but without entring into the
Merit of the Case on the one Side, or the
Other, the Consequences of the War, not
the Necessity of it, is the present Argument
before us.</p>
            <p>If there is a necessity for a War with the
<hi>Dutch,</hi> I am sorry for that unhappy Circum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stance;
but without entring into a Dispute of
the Fact, my Draught of the Consequences
lies as a Caution to all Parties to consider,
with the utmost Seriousness, what that Ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cessity
is, and if possible to remove those
<pb n="38" facs="37"/>
Causes, which bring that Necessity on; for
if the Effects of a <hi>Dutch</hi> War are as before, we
ought to be very well satisfy'd, that our Rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sons
for it are of sufficient Weight to ballance
all the Evils that follow; and if on a due
Enquiry it should be found that these Neces<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sities
are of our own making, and that we
maliciously on both Sides push one another
on to the Extremities, which in their own
nature procure this Mischief. The Excuse
of its being necessary will dwindle away
into, and plainly discover, a wicked Plot to
bring this War upon the Nation, even
for the sake of those very Mischiefs that
so necessarily attend it.</p>
            <p>As to letting the <hi>Dutch</hi> insult us, and put<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ting
the Cause of the War wholly upon
them; if this were true, or should appear,
all that has been said will lye against the
<hi>Dutch,</hi> and not against Us, and were I to
write this in <hi>Holland,</hi> I would perhaps be
able to shew the <hi>Dutch,</hi> how many ways a
War with <hi>Britain</hi> may be fatal and dange<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rous
to them, as well as to us Us: Many of
the Arguments before-mention'd, hold good
on their Side, as well as Ours. The <hi>Hanno<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver</hi>
Succession is, tho' something more re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>motely,
as much their Concern as Ours;
the Protestant Interest ought to lie as near
their Hearts as ours. The Interruptions of
Commerce, the Loss of Ships, Trade and
Goods; These are Things they will bear
their share of, no Question with us: If
they gain by the War; if they Beat us,
they will have as much Cause to mourn for
<pb n="39" facs="38"/>
their Victory as We for our Loss; and as
the Author of the <hi>Review</hi> says very well,
<q rend="inline">"The whole War is but the same thing
as a Man cutting off his Left Hand with
his Right."</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Advice is to them therefore, <hi>equally
as to us,</hi> tho' not quite with the same Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cern;
they ought to study all the Methods
possible to avoid this Breach; they ought to
consider and duly weigh the General Prote<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stant
Interest, and rather abate in some of their
Demands for Peace-sake, and to avoid the
threatning Danger: In short, both Nations,
and every Party or Faction in both Nations,
ought to consider well what they are doing,
and to what a desperate Condition the Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>testant
Interest will be reduced, and nothing
but such unavoidable necessity as will justify
them before God and Man, ought to be
allow'd as a Reason for this War.</p>
            <p>I might descend here to other Particu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lars,
but as they seem to lead more directly
into our present Party Disputes, which
in this Tract, I purpose not to meddle
with, I omit them, and choose to let this
Animadversion respect every Side, that
if possible it may be useful to them all; and
may bring all Parties seriously to apply
themselves, if possible, to heal this Breach
now while it is young, and before the
Wound festers, before it comes up to an In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>flamation
and Mortification, when all the
Endeavours will but encrease the Misery,
and be ineffectual to the Cure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="39"/>
It is our present Misfortune, that our
People on both Sides seem not to see into
the Mischiefs of the present Case, the
Willingness on one Hand, and the Uncon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cernedness
at the Consequences on the other,
which unhappily appear among our People
with respect to a War with <hi>Holland</hi> are very
surprizing, and it seems to me to signify, that
neither of the Parties have duly weigh'd the
thing: These Sheets are written, that they
may not want a Light to see by in this Case,
nor plead Ignorance of the Effects, when
they may have brought them upon us too
late.</p>
            <p>As to those who profess it their Design to
overthrow the present Settlement of this
Nation, I mean the Enemies of the <hi>Revolu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion,</hi>
the Friends of the <hi>Pretender,</hi> the favou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rers
of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny;</hi> these Sheets are
not written for their Conviction, I do not
so much reproach them with desiring a
War with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> because it seems the
only way to bring all their Desires to pass.</p>
            <p>But this may be drawn from thence as a
most direct Consequence, <hi>viz.</hi> That the pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sent
Popular Cry against the <hi>Dutch</hi> is a sad
Token of the Growth and Encrease of
<hi>Jacobitism</hi> among Us, and of the growing
Interest of the <hi>Pretender.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAG.</hi> 11. <hi>The General Heads,</hi> III. and VI. <hi>being
transposed; The Reader is desired to take Notice there<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>of,
and read the one for the other.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>