<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full and true account of a horrid and barbarous revenge by poison: on the body of Mr. Edmund Curll, bookseller; with a faithful copy of his last will and testament. Publish'd by an eye witness.</title>
            <author>Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K023137.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3303357028</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full and true account of a horrid and barbarous revenge by poison: on the body of Mr. Edmund Curll, bookseller; with a faithful copy of his last will and testament. Publish'd by an eye witness.</title>
                  <author>Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6p. ; 2⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Sold by J. Roberts, J. Morphew, R. Burleigh, J. Baker, and S. Popping,</publisher>
                  <date>[1716]</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K023137.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3303357028</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An eye witness = Alexander Pope.</note>
                  <note>Horizontal chain lines.</note>
                  <note>See also: 'A further account of the most deplorable condition of Mr. Edmund Curll'.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Griffith, 52</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT5674.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>A FULL and TRUE
ACCOUNT
OF A
Horrid and Barbarous
REVENGE by POISON, On the Body of
Mr. <hi>EDMUND CURLL,</hi> Bookseller; With a faithful Copy of his
Last WILL and TESTAMENT.</p>
            <p>Publish'd by an Eye Witness.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>So when <hi>Curll</hi>'s Stomach the strong Drench o'ercame,</l>
               <l>(Infus'd in Vengeance of insulted Fame)</l>
               <l>Th' Avenger sees, with a delighted Eye,</l>
               <l>His long Jaws open, and his Colour fly;</l>
               <l>And while his Guts the keen Emeticks urge,</l>
               <l>Smiles on the Vomit, and enjoys the Purge.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Sold by <hi>J. Roberts, J. Morphew, R. Burleigh, J. Baker,</hi> and <hi>S. Pop<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ping.</hi>
Price Three Pence.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
         <head>A Full and True
ACCOUNT
Of a Horrid and Barbarous
REVENGE by POISON, On the Body of Mr. <hi>Edm. Curll,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
         <p>HISTORY furnishes us with Examples of many Satyrical
Authors who have fallen Sacrifices to Revenge, but not
of any Booksellers that I know of, except the unfortunate
Subject of the following Papers; I mean Mr. <hi>Edmund
Curll,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Dial</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> who was Yesterday
poison'd by Mr. <hi>Pope,</hi> after having liv'd many Years an Instance of the
mild Temper of the <hi>British</hi> Nation.</p>
         <p>Every Body knows that the said Mr. <hi>Edmund Curll,</hi> on Monday the
26th Instant, publish'd a Satyrical Piece, entituled <hi>Court Poems,</hi> in the
Preface whereof they were attributed to a <hi>Lady of Quality,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pope,</hi>
or Mr. <hi>Gay</hi>; by which indiscreet Method, though he had escaped one
Revenge, there were still two behind in reserve.</p>
         <p>Now on the Wednesday ensuing, between the Hours of 10 and 11,
Mr. <hi>Lintott,</hi> a neighb'ring Bookseller, desir'd a Conference with Mr.
<hi>Curll</hi> about settling the <hi>Title Page</hi> of <hi>Wiquefort</hi>'s <hi>Ambassador,</hi> inviting him
at the same Time to take a Whet together. Mr. <hi>Pope,</hi> (who is not
the only Instance how Persons of bright Parts may be carry'd away
by the Instigations of the Devil) found Means to convey himself into
the same Room, under pretence of Business with Mr. <hi>Lintott,</hi> who it
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
seems is the Printer of his <hi>Homer.</hi> This Gentleman with a seeming
Coolness, reprimanded Mr. <hi>Curll</hi> for wrongfully ascribing to him the a<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>foresaid
Poems: He excused himself, by declaring that one of his Au<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>thors
(Mr. <hi>Oldmixon</hi> by Name) gave the Copies to the Press, and
wrote the <hi>Preface.</hi> Upon this Mr. <hi>Pope</hi> (being to all appearance re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>concil'd)
very civilly drank a Glass of Sack to Mr. <hi>Curll,</hi> which he as
civilly pledged; and tho' the Liquor in Colour and Taste differ'd not
from common Sack, yet was it plain by the Pangs this unhappy Stationer
felt soon after, that some poisonous Drug had been secretly infused
therein.</p>
         <p>About Eleven a Clock he went home, where his Wife observing his
Colour chang'd, said, <hi>Are you not Sick, my Dear?</hi> He reply'd, <hi>Bloody
Sick</hi>; and incontinently fell a vomiting and straining in an uncommon
and unnatural Manner, the Contents of his vomiting being as Green as
Grass. His Wife had been just reading a Book of her Husband's print<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing,
concerning <hi>Jane Wenham,</hi> the famous Witch of <hi>Hartford,</hi> and her
Mind misgave her that he was bewitch'd; but he soon let her know
that he suspected <hi>Poison,</hi> and recounted to her, between the Inter<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vals
of his Yawnings and Reachings, every Circumstance of his In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>terview
with Mr. <hi>Pope.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Mr. <hi>Lintott</hi> in the mean Time coming in, was extremely afright<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed
at the sudden Alteration he observed in him: <hi>Brother</hi> Curll, says he,
<hi>I fear you have got the vomiting Distemper, which (I have heard) kills
in half an Hour. This comes from your not following my Advice, to
drink old Hock as I do, and abstain from Sack.</hi> Mr. <hi>Curll</hi> reply'd, in
a moving Tone, <hi>Your Author's Sack I fear has done my Business.
Z<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                  <desc>blank</desc>
               </gap>ds,</hi> says Mr. <hi>Lintott, My Author!—Why did not you drink
old Hock?</hi> Notwithstanding which rough Remonstrance, he did in the
most friendly Manner press him to take warm Water; but Mr.
<hi>Curll</hi> did with great Obstinacy refuse it; which made Mr. <hi>Lintott</hi>
infer, that he chose to die, as thinking to recover greater Da<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mages.</p>
         <p>All this Time the Symptoms encreas'd violently, with acute Pains
in the lower Belly. <hi>Brother</hi> Lintott, says he, <hi>I perceive my last Hour
approaching, do me the friendly Office to call my Partner, Mr.</hi> Pember<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ton,
<hi>that we may settle our Worldly Affairs.</hi> Mr. <hi>Lintott,</hi> like a kind
Neighbour, was hastening out of the Room, while Mr. <hi>Curll</hi> rav'd
aloud in this Manner, <hi>If I survive this, I will be revenged on</hi> Tonson<hi>,
it was he first detected me as the Printer of these Poems, and I will re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>print
these very Poems in his Name.</hi> His Wife admonish'd him not to
think of Revenge, but to take care of his Stock and his Soul: And
in the same Instant, Mr. <hi>Lintott</hi> (whose Goodness can never be e<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nough
applauded) return'd with Mr. <hi>Pemberton.</hi> After some Tears
jointly shed by these Humane Booksellers, Mr. <hi>Curll,</hi> being (as he
said) in his perfect Senses though in great bodily Pain, immedi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ately
proceeded to make a verbal Will (Mrs. <hi>Curll</hi> having first
put on his Night Cap) in the following Manner.</p>
         <q>
            <pb n="4" facs="4"/>
            <p>GENTLEMEN, in the first Place, I do sincerely pray Forgive<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness
for those indirect Methods I have pursued in inventing
new Titles to old Books, putting Authors Names to Things they ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver
saw, publishing private Quarrels for publick Entertainment;
all which, I hope will be pardoned, as being done to get an honest
livelihood.</p>
            <p>I do also heartily beg Pardon of all Persons of Honour, Lords
Spiritual and Temporal, Gentry, Burgesses, and Commonalty, to
whose Abuse I have any, or every way, contributed by my Publicati<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ons.
Particularly, I hope it will be considered, that if I have vilify'd
his Grace the Duke of <hi>M<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>gh,</hi> I have likewise aspers'd the late
Duke of <hi>O<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi>; if I have abused the honourable Mr. <hi>W<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi>
I have also libell'd the late Lord <hi>B<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>ke</hi>; so that I have pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>serv'd
that Equality and Impartiality which becomes an honest Man
in Times of Faction and Division.</p>
            <p>I call my Conscience to Witness, that many of these Things which may
seem malicious, were done out of Charity; I having made it wholly my
Business to print for poor disconsolate Authors, whom all other Booksellers
refuse: Only God bless Sir <hi>Richard Bl<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>re</hi>; you know he takes no
Copy Money.</p>
            <p>The Book of the <hi>Conduct</hi> of the <hi>Earl of N<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> is yet unpublish<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed;
as you are to have the Profit of it, Mr. <hi>Pemberton,</hi> you are to run
the Risque of the Resentments of all that Noble Family. Indeed I cau<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sed
the Author to assert several Things in it as Facts, which are only
idle Stories of the Town; because I thought it would make the Book
sell. Do you pay the Author for Copy Money, and the Printer and
Publisher. I heartily beg God's, and my L<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                  <desc>blank</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>N<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi>'s Pardon;
but all Trades must live.</p>
            <p>The second Collection of Poems, which I groundlesly called Mr.
<hi>Prior</hi>'s, will sell for Nothing, and hath not yet paid the Charge of the
Advertisements, which I was obliged to publish against him: There<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore
you may as well suppress the Edition, and beg that Gentleman's
Pardon in the Name of a dying Christian.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French Cato,</hi> with the Criticism, showing how superior it is to
Mr. <hi>Addison</hi>'s, (which I wickedly inscribed to Madam <hi>Dacier</hi>) may be
suppress'd at a reasonable Rate, being damnably translated.</p>
            <p>I protest I have no Animosity to Mr. <hi>Rowe,</hi> having printed Part of his
<hi>Callipaedia,</hi> and an incorrect Edition of his Poems without his Leave, in
Quarto. Mr. <hi>Gildon</hi>'s <hi>Rehearsal</hi>; or <hi>Bays the Younger,</hi> did more harm to
me than to Mr. <hi>Rowe</hi>; though upon the Faith of an honest Man, I paid
him double for abusing both him and Mr. <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heaven pardon me for publishing the <hi>Trials of Sodomy</hi> in an <hi>Elzevir</hi>
Letter; but I humbly hope, my printing Sir <hi>Richard Bl<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>re</hi>'s Essays
will attone for them. I beg that you will take what remains of these
last, which is near the whole Impression, (Presents excepted) and let
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
my poor Widow have in Exchange the sole Propriety of the Copy of
Madam <hi>Mascranny.</hi>
            </p>
         </q>
         <p>Here Mr. <hi>Pemberton</hi> interrupted, and would by no Means consent to this
Article, about which some Dispute might have arisen, unbecoming a dying
Person, if Mr. <hi>Lintott</hi> had not interposed, and Mr. <hi>Curll</hi> vomited.</p>
         <p>What this poor unfortunate Man spoke afterwards, was so indistinct, and in
such broken Accents, (being perpetually interrupted by Vomitings) that the
Reader is intreated to excuse the Confusion and Imperfection of this Ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>count.</p>
         <q>
            <p>Dear Mr. <hi>Pemberton,</hi> I beg you to beware of the Indictment at
<hi>Hicks's-Hall,</hi> for publishing <hi>Rochester</hi>'s bawdy Poems; that Copy will,
otherwise be my best Legacy to my dear Wife, and helpless Child.</p>
         </q>
         <p>
            <hi>The Case of Impotence</hi> was my best Support all the last long Vacation.</p>
         <p>In this last Paragraph Mr. <hi>Curll</hi>'s Voice grew more free, for his Vomitings
abated upon his Dejections, and he spoke what follows from his Close-stole.</p>
         <q>
            <p>For the Copies of Noblemen's and Bishop's <hi>Last Wills and Testaments,</hi>
I solemnly declare I printed them not with any Purpose of Defamation;
but meerly as I thought those Copies lawfully purchased from <hi>Doctors
Commons,</hi> at <hi>One Shilling</hi> a Piece. Our Trade in Wills turning to small
Account, we may divide them blindfold.</p>
            <p>For Mr. <hi>Manwaring</hi>'s <hi>Life,</hi> I ask Mrs. <hi>Old<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                     <desc>blank</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi>'s Pardon: Neither
<hi>His,</hi> nor my Lord <hi>Halifax</hi>'s Lives, though they were of great Service
to their Country, were of any to me: But I was resolved, since I could
not print their Works while they liv'd, to print their Lives after they
were dead.</p>
         </q>
         <p>While he was speaking these Words, Mr. <hi>Oldmixon</hi> enter'd. <hi>Ah!
Mr.</hi> Oldmixon (said poor Mr. <hi>Curll</hi>) <hi>to what a Condition have your Works
reduced me! I die a Martyr to that unlucky Preface. However, in these my
last Moments, I will be just to all Men; you shall have your Third Share of
the</hi> Court Poems<hi>, as was stipulated. When I am dead, where will you find
another Bookseller? Your</hi> Protestant Packet <hi>might have supported you, had
you writ a little less scurrilously, There is a mean in all things.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then turning to Mr. <hi>Pemberton,</hi> he told him, he had several <hi>Taking
Title Pages</hi> that only wanted Treatises to be wrote to them, and earnest<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ly
entreated, that when they were writ, his Heirs might have some
Share of the Profit of them.</p>
         <p>After he had said this he fell into horrible Gripings, upon which Mr.
<hi>Lintott</hi> advis'd him to repeat the Lord's Prayer. He desir'd his Wife to
step into the Shop for a Common-Prayer-Book, and read it by the Help
of a Candle, without Hesitation. He clos'd the Book, fetch'd a Groan,
and recommended to Mrs. <hi>Curll</hi> to give Forty Shillings to the Poor of
the Parish of St. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s, and a Week's Wages Advance to each of his
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
Gentlemen Authors, with some small Gratuity in particular to Mrs.
<hi>Centlivre.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The poor Man continued for some Hours with all his disconsolate
Family about him in Tears, expecting his final Dissolution; when of
a sudden he was surprizingly relieved by a plentiful foetid Stool, which
obliged them all to retire out of the Room. Notwithstanding, it is
judged by Sir <hi>Richard Bl<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:_+">
                  <desc>blank</desc>
               </gap>e,</hi> that the Poyson is still latent in his
Body, and will infallibly destroy him by slow Degrees, in less than a
Month. It is to be hoped the other Enemies of this wretched Statio<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ner,
will not further pursue their Revenge, or shorten this small Peri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>od
of his miserable Life.</p>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>