<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thoughts on the peace, and the probable advantages thereof to the United States of America: By Thomas Paine, ...</title>
            <author>Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K023293.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">cw3315793911</idno>
            <idno type="ecll">1027700700</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thoughts on the peace, and the probable advantages thereof to the United States of America: By Thomas Paine, ...</title>
                  <author>Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4],18,[2]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Philadelphia printed: London reprinted, for J. Stockdale,</publisher>
                  <date>1783.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K023293.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">cw3315793911</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll">1027700700</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Originally published in 1783 as no. XIII of the American Crisis.</note>
                  <note>Later published as an appendix to 'A letter to the Earl of Shelburne'.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Adams, 83.70</note>
                  <note>Sabin, 58241</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT5890.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="halftitle">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>PAINE</hi>'s THOUGHTS ON THE PEACE, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>[Price Sixpence.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <p>THOUGHTS ON THE PEACE, AND THE PROBABLE ADVANTAGES THEREOF TO THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS PAINE, M. A. Of the University of PENNSYLVANIA, and Author of the Pamphlet entitled, "COMMON SENSE," and of <q>A LETTER addressed to the Abbe RAYNAL on the AFFAIRS of NORTH AMERICA,</q>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as also of <q>A LETTER to the EARL of SHELBURNE, on his SPEECH respecting the ACKNOW<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>LEDGMENT of AMERICAN INDEPENDENCE.</q>
            </p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA PRINTED: LONDON REPRINTED. For J. STOCKDALE, in Piccadilly. MDCCLXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb facs="3"/>
         <head>THOUGHTS, &amp;c.</head>
         <p>"THE times that tried men's souls<note place="bottom" n="*">"These are the times that try men's souls." <hi>Crisis, No.</hi> 1, <hi>published December</hi> 19, 1776.</note>" are over—and the greatest and compleatest Revolution the world ever knew, is gloriously and happily accomplished.</p>
         <p>BUT to pass from the extremes of danger to safety—from the tumult of war to the tranquility of peace, though sweet in con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>templation, requires a gradual composure of the senses to receive it. Even calmness has the power of stunning when it opens too in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stantly
<pb n="2" facs="4"/>upon us. The long and raging hur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ricane that should cease in a moment, would leave us in a state rather of wonder than en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>joyment; and some moments of recollection must pass before we could be capable of tasting the full felicity of repose. There are but few instances in which the mind is fitted for sudden transitions: it takes in its pleasures by reflection and comparison, and those must have time to act, before the relish for new scenes is compleat.</p>
         <p>IN the present case—the mighty magni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tude of the object—the various uncertainties of fate it has undergone—the numerous and complicated dangers we have suffered or escaped—the eminence we now stand on, and the vast prospect before us, must all conspire to impress us with contemplation.</p>
         <p>
            <pb n="3" facs="5"/>To see it in our power to make a world happy—to teach mankind the art of being so—to exhibit on the theatre of the universe a character hitherto unknown—and to have, as it were, a new creation entrusted to our hands, are honours that command reflection, and can neither be too highly estimated, nor too gratefully received.</p>
         <p>IN this pause then of recollection—while the storm is ceasing, and the long-agitated mind vibrating to a rest, let us look back on the scenes we have passed, and learn from experience what is yet to be done.</p>
         <p>NEVER, I say, had a country so many openings to happiness as this. Her setting out into life, like the rising of a fair morn<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing, was unclouded and promising. Her cause was good; her principles just and li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>beral;
<pb n="4" facs="6"/>her temper serene and firm; her conduct regulated by the nicest steps of order; and every thing about her wore the mark of honour.</p>
         <p>IT is not every country (perhaps there is not another in the world) that can boast so fair an origin. Even the first settlement of America corresponds with the character of the Revolution. Rome, once the proud mistress of the universe, was originally a band of ruffians. Plunder and rapine made her rich, and her oppression of millions made her great. But America needs never be ashamed to tell her birth, nor relate the stages by which she rose to empire.</p>
         <p>THE remembrance, then, of what is past, if it operates rightly, must inspire her with the most laudable of all ambition, that of
<pb n="5" facs="7"/>adding to the fair fame she began with. The world has seen her great in adversity; struggling, without a thought of yielding, beneath accumulated difficulties; bravely, nay proudly, encountering distress, and rising in resolution as the storm encreased. All this is justly due to her, for her fortitude has merited the character. Let, then, the world see that she can bear prosperity; and that her honest virtue in time of peace, is equal to the bravest virtue in time of war.</p>
         <p>SHE is now descending to the scenes of quiet and domestic life; not beneath the cypress shade of disappointment, but to en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>joy in her own land, and under her own vine, the sweets of her labours, and the re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ward of her toil. In this situation, may she never forget, that a fair national reputation
<pb n="6" facs="8"/>is of as much importance as independence: that it possesses a charm which wins upon the world, and makes even enemies civil: that it gives a dignity which is often supe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rior to power, and commands a reverence where pomp and splendor fail.</p>
         <p>IT would be a circumstance ever to be la<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mented, and never to be forgotten, were a single blot, from any cause whatever, suf<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fered to fall on a Revolution, which to the end of time must be an honour to the age that accomplished it; and which has contributed more to enlighten the world, and diffuse a spirit of freedom and liberality among man<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>kind, than any human event (if this can be called one) that never preceded it.</p>
         <p>IT is not among the least of the calamities of a long-continued war, that it unhinges
<pb n="7" facs="9"/>the mind from those nice sensations which at other times appear so amiable. The conti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nual spectacle of woe blunts the finer feel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ings, and the necessity of bearing with the sight renders it familiar. In like manner are many of the moral obligations of so<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciety weakened, till the custom of acting by necessity, becomes an apology where it is truly a crime. Yet let but a nation con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceive rightly of its character, and it will be chastely just in protecting it. None ever be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gan with a fairer than America, and none can be under a greater obligation to preserve it.</p>
         <p>THE Debt which America has con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tracted, compared with the Cause she has gained, and the advantages to flow from it, ought scarcely to be mentioned. She has it in her choice to do, and to live, as happily as she pleases. The world is
<pb n="8" facs="10"/>in her hands. She has now no Foreign Power to monopolize her Commerce, per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>plex her Legislation, or controul her Pros<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perity. The struggle is over which must one day have happened, and, perhaps, ne<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ver could have have happened at a better time<note place="bottom" n="*">That the Revolution began at the exact period of time best fitted to the purpose is sufficiently proved by the event.—But the great hinge on which the whole ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chine turned is the <hi>Union of the States;</hi> and this Union was naturally produced by the inability of any one State to support itself against a foreign enemy without the assistance of the rest.
<p>Had the States severally been less able than they were when the war began, their united strength would not have been equal to the undertaking, and they must, in all human probability, have failed.—And on the other hand, had they severally been more able, they might not have seen, or, what is more, might not have felt the necessity of uniting; and either by attempting to stand alone, or in small confederacies, would have been separately conquered.</p>
               <p>Now, as we cannot see a time (and many years must pass away before it can arrive) when the strength of any one State, or of several united, can be equal to the whole of the present United States; and as we have seen the extreme difficulty of collectively prosecuting the war to a successful issue, and preserving our national impor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tance in the world; therefore, from the experience we have had, and the knowledge we have gained, we must, unless we make a waste of wisdom, be strongly impressed with the advantage, as well as the necessity, of strength<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ening that happy Union which has been our salvation, and without which we should have been a ruined people.</p>
               <p>While I was writing this note, I cast my eye on the pamphlet <hi>Common Sense,</hi> from which I shall make an ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tract, as it applies exactly to the case. It is as follows:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>I have never met with a man, either in England or America, who hath not confessed his opinion, that a separation between the countries would take place one time or other: and there is no instance in which we have shewn less judgment than endeavouring to de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>scribe, what we call, the ripeness or fitness of the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tinent for Independence.</p>
                  <p>As all men allow the measure, and differ only in their opinion of the time, let us, in order to remove mistakes, take a general survey of things, and en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>deavour, if possible, to find out the <hi>very time.</hi> But we need not go far; the enquiry ceases at once, for <hi>the time hath found us.</hi> The general concurrence, the glorious Union of all things prove the fact.</p>
                  <p>It is not in numbers, but in an Union, that our great strength lies. The Continent is just arrived at that pitch of strength, in which no single Colony is able to support itself, and the whole, when united, can accomplish the matter: and either more or less than this, might be fatal in its effects.</p> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pamphlet Common Sense.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </note>;
and instead of a domineering
<pb n="9" facs="11"/>Master, she has gained an Ally, whose ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>emplary greatness, and universal liberality,
<pb n="10" facs="12"/>have extorted a confession even from her enemies.</p>
         <p>WITH the blessings of Peace, Inde<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pendence, and an universal Commerce, the States, individually and collectively, will have leisure and opportunity to regulate and establish their domestic concerns, and to put it beyond the power of calumny to throw the least reflection on their honour. Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter
<pb n="11" facs="13"/>is much easier kept than recovered; and that man, if any such there be, who, from any sinister views, or littleness of soul, lends unseen his hand to injure it, contrives a wound it will never be in his power to heal.</p>
         <p>As we have established an Inheritance for Posterity, let that Inheritance descend with every mark of an honourable conveyance. The little it will cost, compared with the worth of the States, the greatness of the object, and the value of national character, will be a profitable exchange.</p>
         <p>BUT that which must more forcibly strike a thoughtful penetrating mind, and which includes and renders easy all inferior concerns, is the <hi>Union of the States.</hi> On this our great national character depends.
<pb n="12" facs="14"/>It is this which must give us importance abroad and security at home. It is through this only that we are, or can be nationally known in the world. It is the flag of the United States which renders our ships and commerce safe on the seas, or in a foreign port. Our Mediterranean passes must be obtained under the same style. All our treaties, whether of alliance, peace, or commerce, are formed under the Sovereign<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty of the United States, and Europe knows us by no other name or title.</p>
         <p>THE division of the Empire into States is for our own convenience, but abroad this distinction ceases. The affairs of each State are local. They can go no farther than to itself; and were the whole worth of even the richest of them expended in revenue, it would not be sufficient to support Sove<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>reignty
<pb n="13" facs="15"/>against a foreign attack. In short, we have no other national sovereignty than as United States. It would even be fatal for us if we had—too expensive to be main<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tained, and impossible to be supported. Individuals or individual States may call themselves what they please; but the world, and especially the world of enemies, is not to be held in a awe by the whistling of a name. Sovereignty must have power to protect all the parts which compose and con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stitute it: and as <hi>United States</hi> we are equal to the importance of the title, but otherwise we are not. Our Union, well and wisely regulated and cemented, is the cheapest way of being great—the easiest way of be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing powerful—and the happiest invention in government which the circumstances of America can admit of; because it collects from each State, that which, by being in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>adequate,
<pb n="14" facs="16"/>can be of no use to it, and forms an aggregate that serves for all.</p>
         <p>THE States of Holland are an unfortunate instance of the effects of individual sovereign<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty. Their disjointed condition exposes them to numerous intrigues, losses, calamities, and enemies, and the almost impossibility of bringing their measures to a decision; and that decision into execution, is to them, and would be to us, a source of endless mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fortune.</p>
         <p>IT is with confederate States as with in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dividuals in society: something must be yielded up to make the whole secure. In this view of things we gain by what we give, and draw an annual interest greater than the capital. I ever feel myself hurt when I hear
<pb n="15" facs="17"/>the Union, that great palladium of our li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berty and safety, the least irreverently spoken of. It is the most sacred thing in the constitution of America, and that which every man should be the most proud and tender of. Our citizenship in the United States is our national character: our citizen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ship in any particular State is only our local distinction. By the latter we are known at home; by the former to the world. Our great title is <hi>Americans;</hi> our inferior one varies with the place.</p>
         <p>So far as my endeavours could go, they have all been directed to conciliate the affec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions, unite the interests, and draw and keep the mind of the country together; and the better to assist in this foundation-work of the Revolution, I have avoided all places of pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fit or office, either in the State I live in or in
<pb n="16" facs="18"/>the United States; kept myself at a distance from all parties and party connections, and even disregarded all private and inferior con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cerns: and when we take into view the great work we have gone through, and feel, as we ought to feel, the just importance of it, we shall then see, that the little wranglings and indecent contentions of personal party, are as dishonourable to our characters, as they are injurious to our repose.</p>
         <p>It was the cause of America that made me an author. The force with which it struck my mind, and the dangerous condition the country appeared to me in, by courting an impossible and unnatural reconciliation with those who were determined to reduce her, instead of striking out into the only line that could cement and save her, <hi>A Declaration of Independence</hi>—made it impossible for me,
<pb n="17" facs="19"/>feeling as I did, to be silent: and if, in the course of more than seven years, I have ren<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dered her any service, I have likewise added something to the reputation of literature, by freely and disinterestedly employing it in the great cause of mankind, and shewing there may be genius without prostitution.</p>
         <p>INDEPENDENCE always appeared to me practicable and probable, provided the sen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>timent of the country could be formed and held to the object: and there is no instance in the world, where a people so extended, and wedded to former habits of thinking, and under such a variety of circumstances, were so instantly and effectually pervaded, by a turn in politics, as in the case of Inde<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pendence, and who supported their opinion, undiminished, through such a succession of good and ill fortune, till they crowned it with success.</p>
         <p>
            <pb n="18" facs="20"/>BUT as the scenes of war are closed, and every man preparing for home and happier times, I therefore take my leave of the sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ject. I have most sincerely followed it from beginning to end, and through all its turns and windings: and whatever country I may hereafter be in, I shall always feel an honest pride at the part I have taken and acted, and a gratitude to Nature and Providence for put<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ting it in my power to be of some use to mankind.</p>
         <closer>
            <dateline>
               <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> 
               <date>
                  <hi>April</hi> 19, 1783.</date>
            </dateline>
         </closer>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishersadvertisement">
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <head>NEW BOOKS printed for J. STOCKDALE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Corrected to May</hi> 6, 1783,</p>
            <p>STOCKDALE's NEW COMPANION to the LONDON KALENDAR, and COURT and CITY REGISTER, for the Year 1783; being a List of all the CHANGES in ADMI<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>NISTRATION, from the Accession of the present King, in October 1760, to the present Time. To which is prefixed, a List of the late and present HOUSE of COMMONS, shewing the Changes made in the Members of Parliament by the General Election in September 1780, with the Names of the Candidates where the Elections were contested, the Numbers polled, and the Decisions since made by the Select Committees. Also the Dates when each City and Borough first sent Representatives to Parliament, the Right of Election in each Place, and the sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>posed Number of Voters. To which is added, a complete INDEX of NAMES. Price 1 s.</p>
            <p>{inverted ⁂} <hi>Be careful to ask for</hi> STOCKDALE'S NEW COMPANION, <hi>which may be had separate, or bound with the London Kalendar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corrected to May</hi> 6, 1783,</p>
            <p>THE LONDON KALENDAR, or COURT and CITY REGISTER, for 1783; including all the new Peers lately created; new Members; Alterations in all the different Departments under Government, in Great-Britain, Ireland, and America; with a complete List of the Sovereigns of Europe; the Presidents of the Congress, from 1774; Presidents and Go<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vernors of the American States; and a Number of other new Lists; not to be found in any other Publication. Containing complete Lists of British and Irish Houses of Parliament; Esta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>blishments of England, Scotland, Ireland, America, &amp;c. correct Lists of the Peeresses, Baronets, Universities, Seminaries, Hospi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tals, Charities, Governors, Public Offices; Army, Navy, Col<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lectors at the different Ports, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This London Kalendar is upon a Plan much more extensive and useful than any other Book of the Kind yet published. Price 2 s.</p>
            <p>{inverted ⁂} <hi>Be careful to ask for</hi> THE LONDON KALENDAR, <hi>printed for</hi> J. STOCKDALE, <hi>&amp;c. which may be had bound in the three follow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing different Ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. With The New Companion to the London Kalendar;</item>
               <item>II. With the Arms of all the Peers of England, Scotland, and Ireland;</item>
               <item>III. With Rider's Sheet Almanack or Book Almanack.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A DIALOGUE ON THE ACTUAL STATE OF PAR<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>LIAMENT. Price 1 s.</p>
            <p>The Propriety of Retaining GIBRALTAR, impartially consi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dered. Price 1 s.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="22"/>NEW PAMPHLETS printed for J. STOCKDALE. A LETTER TO THE <hi>EARL</hi> of <hi>SHELBURNE,</hi> ON HIS SPEECH, JULY 10, 1782, RESPECTING THE ACKNOWLEDGEMENT OF AMERICAN INDEPENDENCE.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS PAINE, M.A.</p>
            <p>Of the University of PENNSYLVANIA, and Author of the Pamphlet entitled, "COMMON SENSE;" and of "A LETTER addressed to the Abbe RAYNAL on the Affairs of North America," &amp;c. Price 1 s.</p>
            <p>A LETTER addressed to the Abbe RAYNAL on the Affairs of North America. In which the Mistakes in the Abbe's Ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>count of the Revolution of America are corrected and cleared up. BY THOMAS PAINE. M. A. of the University of Penn<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sylvania, and Author of the Pamphlet, and other Publications, entitled, "Common Sense." 3d Edition, Price 1s. 6 d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be careful to ask for that printed for</hi> STOCKDALE.</p>
            <p>The CONSTITUTIONS of the several INDEPENDENT STATES of AMERICA; the Declaration of Independence; and the Articles of Confederation between the said States. To which are now added, the Declaration of Rights; the Non-Importation Agreement; and the Petition of Congress to the King delivered by Mr. PENN.</p>
            <p>WITH AN</p>
            <p>APPENDIX, containing the Treaties between his Most Chri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stian Majesty and the United States of America; and (never before published) an Authentic Copy of the Treaty concluded between their High Mightinesses the States-General and the United States of America. The whole arranged, with a PRE<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>FAC<gap resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter" rend="content:•">
                  <desc>illegible</desc>
               </gap> and DEDICATION, by the Rev. WILLIAM JACKSON. Nearly printed in One Large Volume in Octavo. Price 6s. in Boards.</p>
            <p>REFLECTIONS upon the Present State of England, and the Independence of America. By THOMAS DAY, <abbr>Esq</abbr> With Additions, Price 2s. 6 d.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>