<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Right Honourable the Mayor and aldermen of the City of London: the humble petition of the colliers, cooks, cook-maids, black-smiths, jack-makers, brasiers, and others, sheweth:</title>
            <author>Arbuthnot, John, 1667-1735.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K023997.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3304581684</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Right Honourable the Mayor and aldermen of the City of London: the humble petition of the colliers, cooks, cook-maids, black-smiths, jack-makers, brasiers, and others, sheweth:</title>
                  <author>Arbuthnot, John, 1667-1735.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 p. ; 1/2⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Roberts, at the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <date>1716]</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K023997.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3304581684</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By John Arbuthnot.</note>
                  <note>A satire : a petition against the innovations introduced by the 'Catoptrical victuallers'.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT8242.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Satire, English</term>
               <term>England -- Economic conditions</term>
               <term>England -- Social life and customs</term>
               <term>Great Britain -- History</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="1"/>
         <head>To the RIGHT HONOURABLE
The MAYOR and ALDERMEN of the
City of <hi>LONDON:</hi>
         </head>
         <head>The Humble Petition
Of the Colliers, <hi>Cooks, Cook-Maids, Black<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>smiths,</hi>
            <hi>Jack-makers, Brasiers,</hi> and Others,</head>
         <opener>SHEWETH;</opener>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT whereas certain <hi>Virtuosi</hi> Disaffected to the Government, and
to the Trade and Prosperity of this Kingdom, taking upon them
the Name and Title of the CATOPTRICAL VICTUALLERS, have
presumed, by Gathering, Breaking, Folding, and Bundling up the
Sun-Beams, by the help of certain <hi>Glasses,</hi> to Make, Produce, and
Kindle up several New <hi>Focus's</hi> or Fires within these His Majesty's
Dominions, and thereby to Boil, Bake, Stew, Fry, and Dress all sorts of Victuals
and Provisions, to Brew, Distil Spirits, Smelt Oars, and, in general, to perform
all the Offices of Culinary Fires; and are endeavouring to procure to themselves
the Monopoly of this their said Invention. We beg leave humbly to represent to
your Honours,</p>
         <p>That such Grant or Patent will utterly <gap resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters" rend="content:•…">
               <desc>illegible</desc>
            </gap>ain and reduce to Beggary your Peti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tioners,
their Wives, Children, Servants, and Trades on them depending; there
being nothing left to them, after the said Invention, but Warming of Cellars and
Dressing of Suppers in the Winter-time. That the abolishing so considerable a
branch of the Coasting Trade as that of the Colliers, will destroy the Navigation
of this Kingdom. That whereas the said <hi>Catoptrical Victuallers</hi> talk of making
use of the <hi>Moon</hi> by Night, as of the <hi>Sun</hi> by Day, they will utterly ruin the
numerous Body of Tallow-Chandlers, and impair a very considerable branch of
the Revenue which arises from the Tax upon Tallow and Candles.</p>
         <p>That the said <hi>Catoptrical Victuallers</hi> do profane the Emanations of that Glorious
Luminary the <hi>Sun,</hi> which is appointed to <hi>Rule the Day,</hi> and not to <hi>Roast Mutton.</hi>
And we humbly conceive, It will be found contrary to the known Laws of this
Kingdom, to Confine, Forestall, and Monopolize the Beams of the Sun. And
whereas the said <hi>Catoptrical Victuallers</hi> have undertaken, by Burning-Glasses made
of Ice, to Roast an Ox upon the <hi>Thames</hi> next Winter: We conceive all such
Practices to be an Encroachment upon the Rights and Privileges of the Company
of <hi>Watermen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>That the Diversity of Exposition of the several Kitchins in this great City,
whereby some receive the Rays of the Sun sooner, and others later, will occasion
great Irregularity as to the Time of Dining of the several Inhabitants, and conse<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quently
great Uncertainty and Confusion in the dispatch of Business: And to those
who, by reason of their Northern Exposition, will be still forced to be at the Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pences
of Culinary Fires, it will reduce the Price of their Manufacture to such
Inequality as is inconsistent with common Justice: And the same Inconveniency
will affect Landlords in the Value of their Rents.</p>
         <p>
            <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
That the Use of the said Glasses will oblige Cooks and Cook-Maids to study
Opticks and Astronomy, in order to know the due Distances of the said <hi>Focus's</hi>
or Fires, and to adjust the Position of their Glasses to the several Altitudes of the
Sun, varying according to the Hours of the Day, and the Seasons of the Year;
which Studies, at these Years, will be highly Troublesome to the said Cooks and
Cook-Maids, not to say any thing of the utter Incapacity of some of them to go
through with such difficult Arts; or (which is still a greater Inconveniency) it
will throw the whole Art of <hi>Cookery</hi> into the Hands of Astronomers and Glass-Grinders,
Persons utterly unskill'd in other parts of that Profession, to the great
Detriment of the Health of His Majesty's good Subjects.</p>
         <p>That it is known by Experience, That Meat Roasted with Sun-Beams is ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>treamly
unwholesome; witness several that have dy'd suddenly after eating the
Provisions of the said <hi>Catoptrical Victuallers</hi>; being that the Sun-Beams taken
inwardly, render the Humours too Hot and Adust, occasion great Sweatings,
and dry up the Rectual Moisture.</p>
         <p>That Sun-Beams taken inwardly, shed a Malignant Influence upon the Brain,
by their natural Tendency towards the Moon; produce Madness and Destraction
at the time of the Full Moon. That the constant use of so great Quantities of
this Inward Light, will occasion the Growth of Quakerism, to the Danger of the
Church; and Poetry, to the Danger of the State.</p>
         <p>That the Influences of the Constellations, through which the Sun passes, will,
with his Beams, be convey'd into the Blood; and when the Sun is amongst the
Horned Signs, may produce such a Spirit of Unchastity, as is dangerous to the
Honour of your Worships Families.</p>
         <p>That Mankind living much upon the Seeds and other parts of Plants, these
being impregnated with the Sun-Beams, may vegetate and grow in the Bowels,
a Thing of more dangerous Consequence to Human Bodies than Breeding of
Worms; and this will fall heaviest upon the Poor, who live upon Roots; and the
Weak and Sickly, who live upon Barley and Rue-Gruel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for which we are
ready to produce to your Honours the Opinions of Eminent Physicians, That the
Taste and Property of the Victuals is much alter'd to the worse by the said <hi>Solar
Cookery,</hi> the Fricasses being depriv'd of the <hi>Haut Gout</hi> they acquire by being dress'd
over Charcoal.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Lastly,</hi> Should it happen by an Eclipse of an Extraordinary Length, that this
City should be depriv'd of the Sun-Beams for several Months; how will His Ma<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>jesty's
Subjects subsist in the Interim, when common Cookery, with the Arts de<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pending
upon it, is totally lost.</p>
         <p>In Consideration of these, and many other inconveniences, your Petitioners
humbly pray, That your Honours would either totally prohibit the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fining
and Manufacturing the Sun-Beams for any of the useful Purposes
of Life, or in the ensuing Parliament procure a Tax to be laid upon them,
which may answer both the Duty and Price of Coals, and which we humbly
conceive cannot be less than Thirty Shillings <hi>per</hi> Yard Square, reserving
the sole Right and Privilege of the <hi>Catoptrical Cookery</hi> to the <hi>Royal Socie<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty,</hi>
and to the Commanders and Crew of the Bomb-Vessels, under the Di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rection
of Mr. <hi>Whiston,</hi> for finding out the Longitude, who by Rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>son
of the Remoteness of their Nations, may be reduc'd to Streights for
want of Firing.</p>
         <p>And we likewise beg that your Honours, as to the forementioned
Points, would hear the Reverend Mr. <hi>Flamsted,</hi> who is the Legal
Officer appointed by the Government to <hi>look after the Heavenly
Luminaries,</hi> whom we have constituted our Trusty and Learned
Solicitor.</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for J. ROBERTS, at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi>
in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1716. [Price 2<hi>d.</hi>]</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>