<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of Katharine, late Duchess of Buckinghamshire and Normanby: By the late Mr. Pope.</title>
            <author>Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K023016.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3301013072</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of Katharine, late Duchess of Buckinghamshire and Normanby: By the late Mr. Pope.</title>
                  <author>Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7,[1]p. ; 2⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for M. Cooper,</publisher>
                  <date>1746.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K023016.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3301013072</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pope claimed to have revised, but not written this work (Correspondence, ed. Sherburn, V, 460).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Griffith, 617</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT5524.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>THE
CHARACTER
OF
<hi>KATHARINE,</hi>
LATE
Duchess of <hi>Buckinghamshire</hi>
and <hi>Normanby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the late Mr. <hi>POPE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON:
Printed for M. COOPER in <hi>Pater-noster-Row.</hi> M.DCC.XLVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
         <head>THE
CHARACTER
OF
<hi>KATHARINE,</hi>
LATE
Duches of <hi>Buckinghamshire,</hi>
&amp;c. &amp;c.</head>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>HE was the Daughter of <hi>James</hi> the
Second, and of the Countess of <hi>Dor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>chester,</hi>
who inherited the Integrity and
Virtue of her Father with happier For<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tune.
She was married first to <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>An<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>glesey,</hi>
and secondly to <hi>John Sheffield</hi> Duke of
<hi>Buckinghamshire</hi> and <hi>Normanby</hi>; with the former
She exercised the Virtues of <hi>Patience and Suffering,</hi>
            <pb n="4" facs="3"/>
as long as there was any Hopes of doing Good by
either; with the latter all other <hi>Conjugal Virtues.</hi>
The Man of finest Sense and sharpest Discernment,
She had the Happiness to please; and in that, found
her only Pleasure. When he died, it seem'd as
if his Spirit was only breathed into her, to fulfill
what he had begun, to perform what he had con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>certed,
and to preserve and watch over what he had
left, <hi>his only Son</hi>; in the Care of whose Health,
the forming of whose Mind, and the Improvement
of whose Fortune, She acted with the Conduct and
Sense of the <hi>Father,</hi> soften'd, but not overcome
with the Tenderness of the <hi>Mother.</hi> Her Under<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>standing
was such as must have made a Figure,
had it been in a Man; but the Modesty of her Sex
threw a Veil over its Lustre, which nevertheless
suppress'd only the Expression, not the Exertion of
it; for her Sense was not superior to her Resolution,
which, when once She was in the Right, preserv'd
her from making it only a Transition to the Wrong,
the frequent Weakness even of the best Women.
She often followed wise Counsel, but sometimes went
before it, always with Success. She was possess'd
of a Spirit, which assisted her to get the better
of those Accidents which admitted of any Redress,
and enabled her to support outwardly with Decency
<pb n="5" facs="4"/>
and Dignity those which admitted of none; yet melt<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed
inwardly through almost her whole Life, at a
Succession of melancholy and affecting Objects, the
Loss of all her Children, the Misfortunes of <hi>Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lations
and Friends, publick and private,</hi> and the
Death of those who were dearest to her. Her
Heart was as compassionate as it was great: Her
Affections warm even to Sollicitude: Her Friend<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ship
not violent or jealous, but rational and per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>severing:
Her Gratitude equal and constant to the
Living; to the Dead boundless and heroical. What
Person soever She found worthy of her Esteem,
She wou'd not give up for any Power on Earth;
and the greatest on Earth whom She cou'd not
Esteem, obtain'd from her no farther Tribute than
Decency. Her Good-Will was wholly directed by
Merit, not by Accident; not measured by the Re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gard
they profess'd for her own Desert, but by her
Idea of theirs: And as there was no Merit which
She was not able to imitate, there was none which
She cou'd envy; therefore her Conversation was
as free from Detraction, as her Opinions from Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>judice
or Prepossession. As her Thoughts were her
own, so were her Words; and She was as sincere
in uttering her Judgment, as impartial in forming
it. She was a safe Companion, many were serv'd,
<pb n="6" facs="5"/>
none ever suffer'd by her Acquaintance: Inoffensive,
when unprovok'd; when provok'd, not stupid: But
the Moment her Enemy ceased to be hurtful, She
could cease to act as an Enemy. She was therefore
not a bitter but consistent Enemy: (tho' indeed,
when forced to be so, the more a finish'd One
for having been long a making.) And her Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceeding
with ill People was more in a calm and
steady Course, like Justice, than in quick and passi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>onate
Onsets, like Revenge. As for those of whom She
only thought ill, She considered them not so much as
once to wish them ill; of such, her Contempt was
great enough to put a Stop to all other Passions that
could hurt them. Her Love and Aversion, her
Gratitude and Resentment, her Esteem and Neglect
were equally open and strong, and alterable only
from the Alteration of the Persons who created them.
Her Mind was too noble to be insincere, and her Heart
too honest to stand in Need of it; so that She never
found Cause to repent her Conduct either to a Friend
or an Enemy. There remains only to speak of her
Person, which was most amiably Majestick, the
nicest Eye could find no Fault in the Outward Li<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>neaments
of her Face or Proportion of her Body;
it was such, as pleas'd wherever she had a Desire
it shou'd; yet she never envy'd that of any other,
<pb n="7" facs="6"/>
which might better please in general: In the same
Manner, as being content that her Merits were
esteemed where She desired they should, She never
depreciated those of any other that were esteemed or
prefered elsewhere. For She aimed not at a general
Love or a general Esteem where She was not known;
it was enough to be possess'd of both wherever she was.
Having lived to the Age of Sixty-two Years; not
courting Regard, but receiving it from all who knew
her; not loving Business, but discharging it fully
wheresoever Duty or Friendship engaged her in it;
not following Greatness, but not declining to pay
Respect, as far as was due from Independency and
Disinterest; having honourably absolv'd all the Parts
of Life; She forsook this World, where She had
left no Act of Duty or Virtue undone, for that
where alone such Acts are rewarded, on the 13th
Day of <hi>March</hi> 1742-3.<note n="*" place="marg">The above Character was written by Mr. <hi>Pope</hi> some Years before Her Grace's Death.</note>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>