<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay on acting: in which will be consider'd the mimical behaviour of a certain fashionable faulty actor, ... To which will be added, a short criticism on his acting Macbeth.</title>
            <author>Garrick, David, 1717-1779.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K023421.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3310912977</idno>
            <idno type="ecll">0246902000</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay on acting: in which will be consider'd the mimical behaviour of a certain fashionable faulty actor, ... To which will be added, a short criticism on his acting Macbeth.</title>
                  <author>Garrick, David, 1717-1779.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4],27,[1]p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for W. Bickerton,</publisher>
                  <date>1744.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K023421.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3310912977</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll">0246902000</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to David Garrick.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT6253.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY on ACTING: In which will be consider'd The Mimical Behaviour OF A Certain fashionable faulty ACTOR, AND THE Laudableness of such unmannerly, as well as inhumane Proceedings. To which will be added, A short CRITICISM On His acting MACBETH.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—So have I seen a Pygmie strut,</l>
               <l>Mouth and rant, in a Giant's Robe.</l>
               <bibl>Tom Thumb.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>—Oh! Macbeth has murder'd G—k.</l>
               <bibl>Shakespear.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for W. BICKERTON, at the <hi>Gazette,</hi> in the <hi>Temple Exchange,</hi> near the <hi>Inner Temple Gate, Fleet-street.</hi> M, DCC, XLIV. [Price Six-pence.]</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY ON ACTING, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AS I have a long Time (twenty Years, or more) made the STAGE, and ACTING, my <hi>Study</hi> and <hi>Entertainment,</hi> I look upon my<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self, and indeed am thought by my Inti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mates, a proper Person to <hi>animadvert upon,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="3"/>
or <hi>approve, the Errors</hi> and the <hi>Excellencies</hi> of the Theatre; and as there can be no better Opportunity offer itself than <hi>now,</hi> when the Town is running after their <hi>little fashi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>onable Actor,</hi> in a Character of which he is, properly speaking, the <hi>Anticlimax</hi> of, or ra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther the <hi>Antipode</hi> of <hi>Shakespear;</hi> I will en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>deavour in the following Dissection of our <hi>Puppet Heroe,</hi> to convince my dear <hi>Country Men</hi> and <hi>Country Women,</hi> that they are madly following an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> or <hi>Will of the Whisp,</hi> which they take for <hi>real substantial Light,</hi> and which I shall prove to be only the <hi>Rush-light of Genius,</hi> the <hi>Idol of Fashion,</hi> and an <hi>Air-drawn Favourite</hi> of the <hi>Imagination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HOW are we degenerated in Taste! <hi>Oh how chang'd! how fallen!</hi>
               <note place="bottom" n="*">
                  <hi>Milton</hi>'s Paradise Lost.</note> That our Thea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tre shall be crowded with Nobility, Ladies and Gentry, to see <hi>Macbeth Burlesqu'd,</hi> or <hi>Be—g—k'd,</hi> which are synonimous, when they might read Mr. <hi>Theobald's Edition of him,</hi> without throwing away their Money,
<pb n="3" facs="4"/>
mispending their Time, ruining their Taste, or running the Hazard of catching a vio<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lent Cold, for a mere <hi>Non-entity:</hi> However, that I may not seem to be prejudic'd against Mr. <hi>G—k,</hi> as I really am not, for I ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mire him, for thus boldly daring to deceive and cheat three Parts of the Nation; I shall, having now crack'd the <hi>Shell</hi> of <hi>my Spleen</hi> against the Town, come to the <hi>Kernel</hi> of <hi>Reason,</hi> and present 'em this <hi>little sweet Nut</hi> of theirs, <hi>worm-eaten</hi> to the <hi>Sight, imbit<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter'd</hi> to their <hi>Taste,</hi> and <hi>abhorr'd</hi> to their <hi>Imaginations,</hi> as <hi>Shakespear</hi> terms it.</p>
            <p>IN order to do this, I shall present my Readers with the following short <hi>Treatise</hi> upon ACTING, which will shew 'em what ACTING <hi>ought to be,</hi> and what the present <hi>Favourite</hi> in Question <hi>is not.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="4" facs="5"/>
            <head>A Short TREATISE UPON ACTING. By which The PLAYERS may be <hi>Instructed,</hi> and the TOWN <hi>Undeceiv'd.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>That I may convince the World, that the <hi>Pub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lick Good,</hi> and no <hi>Private Animosity,</hi> has extracted the following Treatise from its Author. I shall first give an ample and clear <hi>Definition</hi> of <hi>ACTING,</hi> and make the <hi>Natural, Metaphysical,</hi> and <hi>Consequential</hi> Deductions, that will immediately elicite the <hi>Right</hi> from the <hi>Wrong,</hi> and shew my De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>signs are merely <hi>Scientifical,</hi> and not <hi>Sub<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>servient</hi> to <hi>Pique</hi> and <hi>partial Prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="6"/>
ACTING is an <hi>Entertainment of the Stage,</hi> which by calling in the Aid and Assistance of <hi>Articulation, Corporeal Mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Occular Expression, imitates, assumes,</hi> or <hi>puts on</hi> the various <hi>mental</hi> and <hi>bodily E<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>motions</hi> arising from the various Humours, Virtues and Vices, incident to human Na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture.</p>
            <p>THERE are <hi>Two</hi> different Kinds of Exhi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bitions, <hi>viz.</hi> TRAGEDY and COMEDY; the <hi>first</hi> fixes her Empire on the <hi>Passions,</hi> and the more exalted <hi>Contractions</hi> and <hi>Dilations</hi> of the Heart; the <hi>last,</hi> tho' not inferior <hi>(quotidem Science)</hi> holds her Rule over the less enobled Qualities and Districts of human Nature, which are call'd the <hi>Humours:</hi> Now in some Cases, <hi>Passions</hi> are <hi>Humours,</hi> and <hi>Humours Passions;</hi> for the Revenges of an <hi>Alexander</hi> and a <hi>Ha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>berdasher,</hi> may have the same <hi>Fountain,</hi> and differ only in their <hi>Currents,</hi> and tho' the one <hi>(Alexander)</hi> cannot content himself but with the total Subversion of his Ene<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>my's
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
Kingdom, and the other <hi>(the Haber<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dasher)</hi> is satisfy'd with rolling his Antago<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nist in the Kennel; yet, still it is <hi>Revenge,</hi> the Mind of one is equally affected in Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>portion to the other, and all the Difference lies in the different Ways of <hi>satisfying their common Passion.</hi> But now to the Application▪ and Design in Hand. If an Actor, and a <hi>favourite</hi> Actor, in assuming these different Characters with the <hi>same Passions,</hi> shall un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>skilfully differ only in <hi>Dress,</hi> and not in <hi>Execution;</hi> and supposing him right in <hi>One,</hi> and of Consequence absolutely ridiculous in the <hi>Other.</hi> Shall this Actor, I say, in Spite of <hi>Reason, Physicks,</hi> and <hi>common Observation,</hi> be caress'd, applauded, admir'd? But to il<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lustrate it more by Example.—Suppose the <hi>Murder</hi> of <hi>Duncan,</hi> and the <hi>Breaking a Urinal</hi> shall affect the Player in the same Manner, and the only Difference is the <hi>blue Apron</hi> and <hi>lac'd Coat,</hi> shall we be <hi>chill'd</hi> at the <hi>Murderer,</hi> and <hi>roar</hi> at the <hi>Tobacconist?</hi> Fie for Shame!—As the <hi>One</hi> must be ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>solutely the Reverse of Right, I think the Publick, for so gross an Imposition, should
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>
drive <hi>both</hi> off the Stage. When <hi>Drugger</hi> becomes <hi>Macbeth,</hi> and <hi>Macbeth Drugger,</hi> I feel for the Manes of the <hi>Immortal Shake<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spear,</hi> and <hi>Inimitable Ben;</hi> I bemoan the <hi>Taste</hi> of my Country, and I would have the <hi>Buffoon</hi> sacrific'd to appease the <hi>Muses,</hi> and restore to us a true <hi>Dramatick Taste,</hi> by such an examplary Piece of Justice. I shall now, as relative to my my present Subject, describe in what Manner the two abovemention'd Characters <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>men<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tally</hi> and <hi>corporeally</hi> Agitated, under the different Circumstances of the <hi>Dagger,</hi> and <hi>Urinal;</hi> and by that shall more fully deli<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>neate what is meant by <hi>Passions</hi> and <hi>Hu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mours.</hi> When <hi>Abel Drugger</hi> has broke the <hi>Urinal,</hi> he is <hi>mentally absorb'd</hi> with the dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ferent Ideas of the <hi>invaluable</hi> Price of the <hi>Urinal,</hi> and the Punishment that may be inflicted in Consequence of a Curiosity, no way appertaining or belonging to the Busi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness he came about. Now, if this, as it certainly <hi>is,</hi> the Situation of his Mind, How are the different Members of the Body to be agitated? Why Thus,—His <hi>Eyes</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="9"/>
must be revers'd from the Object he is most intimidated with, and by dropping his <hi>Lip</hi> at the some Time <hi>to</hi> the Object, it throws a trembling <hi>Languor</hi> upon every <hi>Muscle,</hi> and by declining the right Part of the Head <hi>to<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>wards</hi> the <hi>Urinal,</hi> it casts the most <hi>comic Terror</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> over all the <hi>upper</hi> Part of the Body, that can be imagin'd; and to make the <hi>lower</hi> Part equally ridiculous, his <hi>Toes</hi> must be <hi>inverted</hi> from the <hi>Heel,</hi> and by <hi>holding</hi> his <hi>Breath,</hi> he will unavoidably give himself a <hi>Tremor</hi> in the <hi>Knees,</hi> and if his <hi>Fingers,</hi> at the same Time, seem <hi>con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vuls'd,</hi> it finishes the compleatest low Picture of <hi>Grotesque Terror</hi> that can be imagin'd by a <hi>Dutch</hi> Painter.—Let this be compar'd with the <hi>modern Copies,</hi> and then let the Town judge.—Now to <hi>Macbeth.</hi>—When the <hi>Murder</hi> of <hi>Duncan</hi> is committed, from an immediate <hi>Conscious<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness</hi> of the Fact, his <hi>Ambition</hi> is <hi>ingulph'd</hi> at that Instant, by the Horror of the Deed; his <hi>Faculties</hi> are intensely rivited to the <hi>Murder</hi> alone, without having the least Consolation of the <hi>consequential Advantages,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="10"/>
to comfort him in that Exigency. He should at that Time, be a <hi>moving Statue,</hi> or indeed a <hi>petrify'd Man;</hi> his Eyes must <hi>Speak,</hi> and his <hi>Tongue</hi> be <hi>metaphorically Si<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lent;</hi> his <hi>Ears</hi> must be <hi>sensible</hi> of <hi>imaginary</hi> Noises, and <hi>deaf</hi> to the <hi>present</hi> and <hi>audible</hi> Voice of his Wife; his <hi>Attitudes</hi> must be <hi>quick</hi> and <hi>permanent;</hi> his Voice <hi>articulately trembling,</hi> and <hi>confusedly intelligible;</hi> the Murderer should be seen in <hi>every Limb,</hi> and yet every <hi>Member,</hi> at that Instant, should seem <hi>separated</hi> from his <hi>Body,</hi> and his <hi>Body</hi> from his <hi>Soul:</hi> This is the Picture of a compleat <hi>Regicide,</hi> and as at that Time the <hi>Orb below should be hush as death;</hi> I hope I shall not be thought <hi>minutely circumstantial,</hi> if I should advise a <hi>real</hi> Genius to wear <hi>Cork Heels</hi> to his Shoes, as in this Scene he should seem to <hi>tread on Air,</hi> and I promise him he will soon discover the great Benefit of this (however seeming <hi>trifling) Piece of Advice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE only Way to arrive at <hi>great Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cellency</hi> in <hi>Characters</hi> of <hi>Humour,</hi> is to be very
<pb n="10" facs="11"/>
conversant with <hi>Human Nature,</hi> that is the noblest and best Study, by this Way you will more accurately discover the <hi>Workings of Spirit</hi> (or what other Physical Terms you please to call it) upon the different <hi>Mo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>difications</hi> of <hi>Matter.</hi> Would the Painter produce a perfect Piece to the World, let him <hi>Copy from the Life,</hi> let Nature herself sit to the Artist: Wou'd a Player perform equally excellent in <hi>his</hi> Profession, let him be introduc'd into the World, be conver<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sant with <hi>Humours</hi> of every Kind, digest 'em in his <hi>Mind,</hi> let 'em be cherish'd by the <hi>genial Warmth</hi> of his <hi>Conception, trans<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>planted into the fair Garden</hi> of his <hi>Judg<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ment,</hi> there let 'em <hi>ripen to Perfection,</hi> and become <hi>his own. Hic Labor! Hoc Opus!</hi> The late celebrated Mr. <hi>Dogget,</hi> before he perform'd the Character of <hi>Ben,</hi> in <hi>Love for Love,</hi> took Lodgings in <hi>Wapping,</hi> and <hi>gather'd thence</hi> a <hi>Nosegay</hi> for the whole Town: Another Comedian <hi>now living,</hi> tho' not upon the Stage (it being so replete with greater Geniuses) has been observ'd con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stantly to attend the <hi>'Change</hi> for <hi>Weeks toge<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="12"/>
before he exhibited one of <hi>Shakespear</hi>'s most inimitable and <hi>difficult</hi> Characters, and so far succeeded by his <hi>great Attention</hi> and <hi>Observation</hi> of the <hi>Manners, Dress,</hi> and <hi>Behaviour</hi> of a <hi>particular Tribe of People,</hi> that the <hi>Judgment, Application,</hi> and <hi>extra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ordinary Pains</hi> he took to divert the Publick <hi>rationally,</hi> was amply return'd with crowd<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ed Theatres, and <hi>unequall'd Applauses;</hi> nay, to so <hi>great a Degree</hi> did they shew their Approbation to this <hi>Pains-taking Genius,</hi> that he is at present more known by the Name of the <hi>Character he perform'd,</hi> than by <hi>his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall not enter into the Reasons why he is at present excluded Theatre, but shall only, as an Advocate for the Publick, say that I wish for <hi>their</hi> Sake, that there were many such Actors as him upon <hi>both</hi> Theatres.</p>
            <p>I have, in as concise a Manner as possi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble, given my Sentiments of <hi>Acting,</hi> by <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Precept;</hi> but there will very
<pb n="12" facs="13"/>
soon be publish d a more compleat and ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>panded <hi>Treatise upon</hi> ACTING, with an accurate <hi>Description</hi> of each <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Passion,</hi> their <hi>Sources</hi> and <hi>Effects;</hi> by which the <hi>Players</hi> may be taught to renounce their <hi>Errors,</hi> and the <hi>Town</hi> its Judgment of <hi>Act<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Actors.</hi>—</p>
            <trailer>Here Ends the Essay upon Acting.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Some <hi>Critical OBSERVATIONS</hi> upon the Character of <hi>MACBETH,</hi> as it is at present <hi>Attempted</hi> at the <hi>Theatre-Royal</hi> in <hi>Drury-Lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE following Critque is design'd as a Supplementary Appendix to the fore<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>going <hi>Essay on</hi> ACTING, and as that was not so <hi>full</hi> and <hi>investigating,</hi> as my Imagination had at first form'd it, I shall in this short <hi>Survey of Heroism in Miniature,</hi> still have my Eye upon the <hi>Essay on</hi> ACTING, and at the same Time convince the Publick, that they have <hi>insensibly</hi> been <hi>misguided</hi> by
<pb n="13" facs="14"/>
               <hi>Fashion,</hi> and that they have in <hi>the Dark run-a-ground</hi> their <hi>Reputation</hi> on the <hi>Sandy Banks</hi> of <hi>Error:</hi> But I shall now fix a <hi>Lanthorn</hi> at the <hi>Poop</hi> of their <hi>Misconceptions,</hi> they shall <hi>see their Distress,</hi> I will set my <hi>Hand</hi> to the <hi>Pump</hi> of <hi>Conviction,</hi> clear the Vessel from <hi>sixteen Feet Water</hi> of <hi>Anti-Taste,</hi> keep it from <hi>foundering,</hi> hoist up the <hi>Flag</hi> of <hi>Criticism,</hi> and once more <hi>pilot</hi> their <hi>Understandings</hi> into the <hi>Harbour</hi> of <hi>True Judgment:</hi> But Metaphor apart, what is the <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Macbeth?</hi> He is an ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>perienc'd General, crown'd with Conquest, <hi>innately Ambitious,</hi> and religiously Humane, spurr'd on by <hi>metaphysical</hi> Prophecies, and the <hi>unconquerable Pride</hi> of his <hi>Wife,</hi> to a Deed, <hi>horrid</hi> in <hi>itself,</hi> and <hi>repugnant</hi> to his Nature; but as it is the <hi>Ladder</hi> to the <hi>swell<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Act of the Imperial Theme,</hi> his <hi>Milk</hi> soon becomes <hi>Gall,</hi> imbitters his whole Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>position, and the Consequence is the <hi>Murder</hi> of <hi>Duncan,</hi> the <hi>taking off</hi> of <hi>Banquo,</hi> and his own <hi>Coronation.</hi> Thus stands <hi>Macbeth.</hi> Now to our Inferences. <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Ambi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion,</hi> the two Grand <hi>Characteristicks</hi> of <hi>Mac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>beth,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="15"/>
form in the <hi>Mind's Eye</hi> a Person of <hi>near six Feet High, corpulently Graceful,</hi> a <hi>round Visage,</hi> a <hi>large hazel Eye, aquiline Nose, prominent Chest,</hi> and a <hi>well-calv'd Leg,</hi> rather inclin'd to that which is call'd an <hi>Irish Leg;</hi> this, I say, would be the <hi>Painter's</hi> Choice, was he to give us the <hi>Macbeth</hi> of <hi>his Imagination;</hi> I mention this only to prove that Mr. <hi>G—k</hi> is not form'd in the least, <hi>externally,</hi> no more than <hi>inter<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nally,</hi> for that Character, and tho' there are many Figures in the World would become it very well, tho' not exactly co-incident with my Description, yet the nearer they approach to it, they will the better <hi>look Ambition, Heroism,</hi> and <hi>Murder.</hi> Mr. <hi>G—k,</hi> could he <hi>Speak</hi> the <hi>Part,</hi> is well form'd for <hi>Fleance,</hi> or one of the <hi>Infant Shadows</hi> in the Cauldron Scene, but for the Manager to impose <hi>him</hi> upon the Town for a <hi>Macbeth,</hi> and to refuse taking <hi>another Comedian</hi> into his House, is such an Example of <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudence,</hi> that is not to be <hi>paralell'd</hi> but by his own <hi>unparalell'd</hi> Be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>haviour.—Mr. <hi>G—k</hi>'s Dress is very faulty
<pb n="15" facs="16"/>
too, <hi>his</hi> Coat should be <hi>Banquo</hi>'s, and <hi>Banquo</hi>'s his, and for this Reason; <hi>Red</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> suits the Dignity of <hi>Macbeth,</hi> and at the same Time implies, a more <hi>principal</hi> and <hi>exalted</hi> Character, without derogating, or taking from the Rank of <hi>Banquo</hi> in <hi>Red</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> who <hi>titularly</hi> bears an <hi>equal</hi> Sta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion as <hi>Commander,</hi> tho' <hi>militarily</hi> bears an <hi>inferior</hi> Proportion as <hi>Man:</hi> This Distinction is very nice, and perhaps may not glare upon common Readers, as defin'd here, but was this Decorum nicely preserv'd, the Eyes of all, from the <hi>Critick</hi> to the <hi>Ground<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ling</hi> (as <hi>Shakespear</hi> calls 'em) would imme<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diately convey to the Mind the several De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>grees and minute Distinctions of the Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter, from the Colour and Trimmings of his Apparel:—I shall leave it to the Con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sideration of the Publick, whether or no a <hi>Tye Wig</hi> is more eligible than a <hi>Major,</hi> or a <hi>plain Hat,</hi> than a <hi>lac'd one,</hi> for my own Part, I say, <hi>No.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="17"/>
SO much for <hi>Dress</hi> and <hi>Figure;</hi> now I shall proceed to the more difficult and phy<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sical Parts of the Character, and shall con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sider the <hi>Action, Speaking</hi> and <hi>Conception</hi> of our <hi>modern Heroe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE first Words of the Part,—<hi>So foul and fair a Day I have not seen,</hi> in my Opi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nion are spoke wrong; <hi>Mackbeth</hi> before his Entrance has been in a great Storm of Rain, Thunder, &amp;c. Now as the Audi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ence have been appriz'd of this, by the three▪ Witches, he should very <hi>empha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tically</hi> describe the quick Transition from being <hi>wet to the Skin,</hi> to being almost in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stantaneously <hi>dry'd again:</hi> Tho' I can't con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vey in Writing the Manner how it <hi>should</hi> be spoke, yet every Reader may compre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hend how it <hi>ought</hi> to be spoke, and know that in the Manner it is <hi>now</hi> spoke, the Sentiment is <hi>languid, unintelligible,</hi> and <hi>un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>descriptive.</hi> I shall now examine the most remarkable Scene in the whole Play, which
<pb n="17" facs="18"/>
is that of the <hi>Air-drawn Dagger.</hi> This I shall make appear he has mistook from the Beginning to the End.—<hi>Macbeth,</hi> as a Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>paration for this Vision, is so prepossess'd, from his Humanity, with the Horror of the Deed, which by his more prevailing Am<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>bition he is incited to, and for the Perpe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tration of which, he lies under a promissary Injunction to his Lady, that his Mind being torn by these different and confus'd Ideas, his Senses fail, and present that <hi>fatal Agent</hi> of his Cruelty,—the <hi>Dagger,</hi> to him:—Now in this visionary Horror, he should not rivet his Eyes to an <hi>imaginary</hi> Object, as if it <hi>really</hi> was there, but should shew an <hi>unsettled Motion</hi> in his Eye, like one not quite awak'd from some disordering Dream; his <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Fingers</hi> should not be <hi>im<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>moveable,</hi> but <hi>restless,</hi> and endeavouring to disperse the Cloud that over shadows his optick Ray, and bedims his Intellects; here would be Confusion, Disorder, and Agony! <hi>Come let me clutch thee!</hi> is not to be done by <hi>one</hi> Motion only, but by several <hi>succes<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sive Catches</hi> at it, first with one Hand, and
<pb n="18" facs="19"/>
then with the other, preserving the same Motion, at the same Time, with his Feet, like a Man, who out of his Depth, and half drowned in his Struggles, <hi>catches</hi> at <hi>Air</hi> for <hi>Substance:</hi> This would make the Spec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tator's Blood run cold, and he would almost feel the Agonies of the Murderer himself. I have spoke of the Scene following the Murder, in my <hi>Essay on Acting,</hi> and shall only say, that the <hi>Daggers</hi> are near an Inch and half too long, in Proportion to the Heighth of the Murderer. The Night-Gown, he appears in, after the Murder, ought to be a <hi>Red Damask,</hi> and not the frippery<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>flower'd one of a <hi>Foppington;</hi> but when <hi>Taste</hi> is wanting in <hi>Trifles,</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> in <hi>Essentials,</hi> how can we hope to see the THEATRE flourish? I must make a Remark upon him in the <hi>Banquet Scene,</hi> which is the most glaring Absurdity that ever was com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mitted by an Actor: When <hi>Banquo</hi>'s Ghost gets Possession of <hi>Macbeth</hi>'s Chair, and the latter, frighted at his Appearance, by Words and Actions, says, <hi>Which of you have done this?</hi> Meaning the Murder of <hi>Banquo;</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="20"/>
here the Actor should address himself to the <hi>Guests,</hi> and not keep a <hi>fix'd Eye</hi> upon the <hi>Ghost;</hi> he should turn his Head <hi>from Banquo,</hi> and say, to the Lords at Supper, <hi>Which of you have done this?</hi> For to speak to the <hi>plural</hi> Number, and look at the <hi>singular (Banquo</hi> only) is most absurd and ridiculous. Then at the <hi>second</hi> Appearance of the Ghost, at the Words, <hi>Dare me to the Desart with thy Sword, Macbeth</hi> should draw his Sword, and put himself in a Pos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture of Defence; and when he comes to, <hi>Hence horrid Shadow!</hi> he should make a home Thrust at him, recover himself upon the <hi>Ghost</hi>'s moving, and keep passing at him till he has got him quite out of the Room: The Manner it has been done <hi>heretofore,</hi> which is keeping the Hand upon the Sword, and following him out, is not so natural and effecting, as the Way I propose; and if any Objection is made, that <hi>Macbeth</hi> should know, that <hi>Ghosts</hi> are not <hi>vulnerable,</hi> I an<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>swer, <hi>Macbeth</hi>'s Horror confounds him, and his Actions must denote the <hi>Non Compos.</hi> Here I must take Notice of an Omission in
<pb n="20" facs="21"/>
the Part of <hi>Banquo;</hi> when he appears at the Banquet, he ought to rise in a <hi>Red Cloak,</hi> as he was seen to cross the Stage in one, imme<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diately before his Murder; this would throw a great Solemnity upon the Figure of <hi>Ban<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quo,</hi> and preserve the Decorum of the Stage.—I must likewise observe, that in <hi>Shakespear</hi>'s Time, the Actors wore their own Hair, and now, from the present Fa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>shion of wearing Wigs, some Speeches are become absurd, such, for Instance, is this of <hi>Macbeth, Never shake thy Goary Locks at me;</hi> when at the same Time the Ghost is seen in a <hi>Tye Wig:</hi> If I might be allow'd to propose an Alteration (with all imaginable Deference to the immortal <hi>Shakespear)</hi> in order to avoid this Blunder, I would have the Actor say, <hi>Never shake thy Goary</hi> TYE <hi>at me;</hi> if the Word <hi>Wig</hi> is thought more Poe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tical, it will be equally good, as they are both Monosyllables.</p>
            <p>AS I have not yet left the <hi>Banquet Scene,</hi> I must observe that the <hi>Attitude G—k</hi> stands in, at the second Appearance of the
<pb n="21" facs="22"/>
Ghost, is absolutely wrong: <hi>Macbeth</hi> here should <hi>sink</hi> into <hi>himself,</hi> or rather, if I may be allow'd the Expression, <hi>hide</hi> himself be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hind <hi>himself;</hi> or to illustrate it more by Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ample, <hi>Si parvis comporere, &amp;c.</hi> he should imitate the contracting Power of a <hi>Snail,</hi> preserving at the <hi>same Time a slow awful manly</hi> folding up of his Faculties, and as his <hi>Body</hi> gathers up gradually at the Vision▪ his <hi>Mind</hi> should keep the same Time, and denote its strong Workings and Convulsions▪ at his <hi>Eyes;</hi> the Glass of Wine in his Hand should not be dash'd upon the Ground, but it should fall <hi>gently</hi> from him, and he should not discover the least Consciousness of hav<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing such a Vehicle in his Hand, his Me<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mory being quite lost in the present Guilt and Horror of his Imagination. <hi>The Banquet</hi> itself, which is suppos'd to be a <hi>Regal</hi> one, should not be compos'd of a few <hi>Apples, Oranges,</hi> and such like Trash, but of <hi>hot</hi> costly <hi>Viands,</hi> and large Pyramids of <hi>wet Sweetmeats,</hi> and <hi>Savoy Biscuits;</hi> this would cast an inconceiveable Grandeur upon the Scene, and add greatly to the Horror of
<pb n="22" facs="23"/>
the Ghost.—<hi>Macbeth</hi> says, <hi>To Night we hold a</hi> SOLEMN <hi>Supper, Sir;</hi> which <hi>So<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lemnity</hi> should be preserv'd, by having seve<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ral <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>inferior Clergy</hi> at the Table, and of Consequence the <hi>supernatural</hi> Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pearance of <hi>Banquo,</hi> would strike with dou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble Force on the Minds of the Audience, by their <hi>Spiritual</hi> Presence. I could shew that this Play is even deficient in every <hi>little Decoration,</hi> but this one gross Blunder will suffice to give us an Idea of all the rest.</p>
            <p>AS my Criticisms upon the three first Acts of <hi>Macbeth</hi> have been more full and extended than I at first design'd 'em, I shall reserve my Observations upon the two last, for another <hi>Sixpenny</hi> Pamphlet, to which I shall subjoin a Criticism upon <hi>Co<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lombine Courtezan,</hi> which I shall examine critically, Scene by Scene, and lay open the Imperfections of that Piece, discernable to the meanest Capacity, and shall prove, by undeniable <hi>Conclusions,</hi> drawn from known <hi>Postulata,</hi> that the <hi>worst</hi> Play that ever <hi>Shakespear</hi> wrote, is greatly preferable to the
<pb n="23" facs="24"/>
whole Performance of <hi>Colombine Courtezan.</hi> I am very sensible what Difficulties and Pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>judices I have to surmount in such an Un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dertaking; but as I have the Reputation of my Country at Heart, I am resolv'd to pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>secute my laudable Intentions with indefa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tigable Care, and unwearied Diligence.</p>
            <p>IN short, to sum up the Whole of my present Observations upon this Head, as I profess the strictest Adherence to Truth, despise Flattery, and am incapable of Fear, I will venture to affirm, there is not one pleasure-giving Scene throughout the whole Play of <hi>Macbeth,</hi> as it is now acted: But as I will ever do Justice to Merit, I must own I felt some Pleasure at seeing Mr. <hi>Mills</hi>'s <hi>Green Ribbon and Star,</hi> in the Cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter of <hi>Duncan;</hi> the unexpected Intro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duction of the <hi>Scotch Order</hi> was an agree<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>able Novelty, and discover'd great Fancy in the Actor; therefore I could not refrain from giving it <hi>here</hi> a deserved Commenda<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, and it shall always meet with my Ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>probation in the <hi>Theatre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="25"/>
I think I cannot better finish a Criti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cism on <hi>Macbeth,</hi> than with a succinct De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>scription of the Talents and Capacity of its Author. <hi>Shakespear</hi> was a Writer not to be confin'd by <hi>Rule;</hi> he had a <hi>despotick Power</hi> over all Nature; <hi>Laws</hi> would be an <hi>Infringement</hi> of his <hi>Prerogative;</hi> his <hi>scepter'd Pen</hi> wav'd Controul over every <hi>Passion</hi> and <hi>Humour;</hi> his <hi>Royal Word</hi> was not only <hi>Ab<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>solute,</hi> but <hi>Creative; Ideas, Language,</hi> and <hi>Sentiment</hi> were his <hi>Slaves,</hi> they were <hi>chain'd</hi> to the <hi>Triumphal Car</hi> of his <hi>Genius;</hi> and when he made his <hi>Entry</hi> into the <hi>Temple of Fame,</hi> all <hi>Parnassus</hi> rung with <hi>Acclamations;</hi> the <hi>Muses</hi> sung his <hi>Conquests,</hi> crown'd him with never-fading <hi>Laurels,</hi> and pronounc'd him <hi>Immortal.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>Here ends the Criticism on <hi>Macbeth.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>I shall at once convince the World of my Impartiality with Regard to Mr. <hi>G—k,</hi> by allowing him all the Merit that <hi>Mimickry</hi> can give him, which, to be sure, is very
<pb n="25" facs="26"/>
pleasant over a Bottle, tho' despicable on the Stage.—But how his being a good <hi>Mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mick</hi> should entitle him to be a <hi>great Actor,</hi> I can't so easily comprehend; the <hi>Punch</hi> of a <hi>Puppet Shew,</hi> and the <hi>Heroe</hi> of a <hi>Theatre,</hi> are as different in their Characters as the Materials they are each compos'd of. But how can he answer it to Conscience, and his fellow Creatures, his endeavouring, by modulating his Organs of Speech and Ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion, to those of other Actors, to render them contemptible, by such a visible Expo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sure of their Infirmities? 'Tis <hi>wicked,</hi> 'tis <hi>unjust,</hi> 'tis <hi>inhumane!</hi> and the People who are diverted by it, and applaud him for it, are <hi>barbarous, unciviliz'd,</hi> and <hi>unfeeling.</hi> A <hi>Pick-pocket</hi> is less culpable than a <hi>Mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mick:</hi> Suppose, for Instance, an Actor of either Theatre, coming out of the Play-House, has his Pocket pick'd of Ten or a Dozen Shillings, in the <hi>Piazza,</hi> or in <hi>Ca<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>therine-street;</hi> Care, Oeconomy and his Bu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>siness, makes the Loss easy: But if the same Actor is made ridiculous, and looses the <hi>Means</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="27"/>
of replenishing his aforesaid pick'd-pocket, the <hi>Mimick</hi> that deprives him of ever having his Pocket <hi>pick'd</hi> again, either in the <hi>Pi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>azza,</hi> or <hi>Catharine-street,</hi> is the Pick-pocket himself. I believe <hi>Mimickry</hi> was never thought of before in this Light; therefore let it be <hi>consider'd,</hi> let it be <hi>condemn'd.</hi> Besides, as a farther Confir<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mation of the <hi>Unlaudableness</hi> of such Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ceedings, I am told the very <hi>mimick'd</hi> Ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tors themselves are not very easy under this Treatment, and are resolv'd never to be reconcil'd to any future <hi>Analysis</hi> of their <hi>Looks, Tones,</hi> or <hi>Gestures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS I am now oblig'd (for want of Room) to curb the <hi>Impetuosity of my Pen,</hi> and stop its <hi>critical Carears,</hi> I shall in a very short Time lay before the Publick, another Pam<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phlet, with some more additional Remarks upon the same Subject, which will be a <hi>proper Appendix</hi> to the <hi>Essay on Acting;</hi> and call'd <hi>An Essay on the common Sewers,</hi> vulgarly stil'd <hi>Common Shores,</hi> in which will
<pb n="27" facs="28"/>
be consider'd the <hi>Use</hi> and <hi>Abuse</hi> of <hi>Bum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fodder,</hi> with some curious Observations upon the <hi>present State of Politicks, both at Home and Abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>