<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Liberty-Hall: or, a test of good fellowship. A comic opera, in two acts. As it is performed with the greatest applause at the Theatre-Royal in Drury-Lane.</title>
            <author>Dibdin, Charles, 1745-1814.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K024330.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3315373401</idno>
            <idno type="ecll">0947900900</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Liberty-Hall: or, a test of good fellowship. A comic opera, in two acts. As it is performed with the greatest applause at the Theatre-Royal in Drury-Lane.</title>
                  <author>Dibdin, Charles, 1745-1814.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38p. ; 8⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and sold by G. Kearsley,</publisher>
                  <date>1785.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K024330.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3315373401</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll">0947900900</idno>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Charles Dibdin.</note>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT9039.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="halftitle">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>LBERTY-HALL: OR, <hi>A Test of Good Fellowship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[Price ONE SHILLING.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="2"/>
            <p>LIBERTY-HALL: OR, <hi>A Test of Good Fellowship.</hi> A COMIC
OPERA, IN TWO ACTS. AS IT IS PERFORMED WITH THE GREATEST APPLAUSE AT THE
<hi>THEATRE-ROYAL</hi> IN DRURY-LANE.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for the AUTHOR, and sold by G. KEARSLEY, at No.
46, in FLEET-STREET. M.DCC.LXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatispersonae">
            <pb facs="3"/>
            <head>DRAMATIS PERSONAE.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Sir Ephraim Rupee,</label>
               <item>Mr. SUET.</item>
               <label>Lord Lofty,</label>
               <item>Mr. STAUNTON.</item>
               <label>Rupee,</label>
               <item>Mr. BARRYMORE</item>
               <label>English,</label>
               <item>Mr. BANNISTER.</item>
               <label>Fidgit,</label>
               <item>Mr. R. PALMER.</item>
               <label>Ap Hugh,</label>
               <item>Mr. DODD.</item>
               <label>Nettle,</label>
               <item>Mr. FAWCETT.</item>
               <label>Seabright,</label>
               <item>Mr. WRIGHTEN.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Aurelia,</label>
               <item>Miss GEORGE.</item>
               <label>Lucy,</label>
               <item>Miss PHILLIPS.</item>
               <label>Patience,</label>
               <item>Mrs. WILSON.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="4"/>LIBERTY-HALL, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <head>ACT I.</head>
            <div type="scene">
               <stage>SCENE, A Lawn before a large handsome House, pretty
forward, and rather on one Side is fixed a Mar<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>quee, where young <hi>Rupee,
Fidget, Nettle, Ap Hugh,</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> are at Breakfast,
Servants waiting.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>CHORUS.</speaker>
                              <l>LIGHT and tripping as you tread,</l>
                              <l>With printless steps along the mead,</l>
                              <l>With air ingenuous, open, free,</l>
                              <l>Hither come, sweet Liberty!</l>
                              <l>Health waits thee in thy blest domain,</l>
                              <l>Come, and hold thy jocund reign!</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                              <l>Here's the true seat of Liberty;</l>
                              <l>We sit, sing, chat, and sip our tea,</l>
                              <l>Discuss the modish topics round,</l>
                              <l>While jest, and jibe, and joke abound;</l>
                              <l>Abusing, as it serves our ends,</l>
                              <l>The state, the weather, and our friends.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                              <l>Then light and tripping, &amp;c.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <pb n="8" facs="5"/>
                              <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                              <l>Britons well read in freedom's lore,</l>
                              <l>Say all they know and ten times more;</l>
                              <l>Coblers teach kings—and where's the crime?</l>
                              <l>Let beards wag freely—truths sublime,</l>
                              <l>Fall sometimes from the coarsest tongue,</l>
                              <l>As order out of Chaos sprung.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                              <l>Then light and tripping, &amp;c.</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>Letters for your honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Have I leave?
 <stage>[reads]</stage> from India—Sir—hum—hum—my trusty Bengal factor gives me lively hopes, that many
 months will not elapse before I embrace a beloved sister I have not
 seen since her infancy—here is her own letter,
 hum—hum—Aurelia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Rupee—hey—how is it?—is your father
 really dead, and is the fortune equal to your expecta<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! the old gentleman's as peaceable as an embalmed Egyptian;
 and as to the fortune, 'tis beyond my hopes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>I am sorry for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Sorry, Nettle!—why so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Why! because it will be all thrown away upon such flies as
 Fidget here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>You would have no objection, I suppose, to his throwing it
 away upon wasps like yourself—don't be so envious, Nettle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>I envious, Sir!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Envious—Aye, as a lady's monkey of her lov<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>er's
 caresses.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>You only think so because I am not like you, a
 possessor of no pleasures but what are distant or impos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sible,
 a stupid, senseless, anticipater of enjoyment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, and what then! I appeal to Rupee, if there is any harm in
 such a character.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>None in the world—I think you the most ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>commodating
 little creature alive; and for pinning a lady's tucker, catching a poney, being
 bound for a thousand pounds, or stropping a razor, I don't think there's
 your fellow in the county.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>I knew Rupee would praise me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="6"/>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>And you really think a flexibility of temper a pusillanimity
 of soul, a placid, insipid, damned unfeeling serenity?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! the most despicable thing in nature; why a man might as
 well be a piece of informed freestone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>I have heard, and audited, and peen wit<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness, look you, of
 your tisputes and tifferences, and as I am confinced and persuaded you are
 fery good friends in the mane, I to tesire and peseech you to shake
 hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>You are a pretty accommodater of differences! a Welchman full of
 pride, petulance, and pedigree, hot as a leek, and amorous as a goat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, look you, Mr. Nettle, it is petter to be proud of a good
 heart than a malicious one; it is petter to be exasperated at receiving a
 wrong than toing one; and as to hur peticree, if hur happens to be more
 honorably tesoended than those who enfy hur, it is the fault of hur
 ancestors and not hurself.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Well said, Ap Hugh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, and truly said too. I have heard him talk with pleasure
 a hundred times of his Judors and his Llwel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lins, and his Walladers and his
 Gummeries; and as to being amorous, who would not excuse it, when there is
 such a temptation as this?—to be sure, as to reputation, we won't
 say much about that; but what then? there are many demure ones with better
 characters and worse sentiments.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh,</speaker>
                  <p>It is a ferry just, and a ferry generous re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mark, look you.
 Oh! 'tis an angel, a fallen one to be sure; put when her peholds hur poor Ap
 Hugh, pecomes plind to hur errors and pack slidings, look you, and can see
 nothing put hur charms and fifacities—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <l>Were patience kind to me,</l>
                           <l>Oh he de nos!</l>
                           <l>Far plyther than a coat I'd be,</l>
                           <l>Oh he de nos!</l>
                           <l>Leap, skip and pound would poor Ap Hugh,</l>
                           <l>And capriole and caper too,</l>
                           <l>And frisk and jump and dance, look you,</l>
                           <l>Oh he de nos!</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="10" facs="7"/>But patience very cruel is,</l>
                           <l>Oh he de nos!</l>
                           <l>With jibes, cheers, and mockeries,</l>
                           <l>Oh he de nos!</l>
                           <l>Which makes to sigh and sob, Ap Hugh,</l>
                           <l>And whining his sad fortune rue,</l>
                           <l>And crieve and croan and crunt, look you,</l>
                           <l>Oh he de nos!</l>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE II.</head>
               <stage>Rupee, English.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus have I an extempore Comedy in my house, nature not only
 supplying me with matter but scenes and decorations, and here comes a
 principal cha<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racter, an Englishman, who traces his origin from the Saxon
 Heptarchy, prodigal of pleasure as Henry the 5th with his mad associates,
 and estimable as that exemplary prince after he had renounced his
 extravagancies. Ha! English, the honour of a visit from you is as kind as
 it is unexpected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, faith, 'tis a satisfaction I should give my<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self
 oftner, but our pursuits are different, and why should we meet to
 disagree?—I am bound by a singular though indulgent father—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>I know it—his dying injunctions were, that you should
 never see London, that you should dine four times a year with the vestry,
 hang a stag's horns in your hall, brew your own October, and roast an ox at
 Christ<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mas. Mine, I thank him, enjoin'd me no such con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>duct—he went
 abroad—accumulated a large fortune—died—and left me to
 spend it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>With which you purchase pleasure at the expence of
 happiness—last night, for example.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! I am with you; but what mighty harm! a nobleman's carriage
 breaks down in a quagmire, occa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sioned by the late floods, and I invite my
 lord and his suite to my house.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and a stage-coach, in about a quarter of an hour after
 breaks down in the same quagmire, in which are a venerable old man and his
 lovely daughter, whose appear<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ance being less splendid than my lord's,
 they are left to shift for themselves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="8"/>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! they are safe at Seabright's, my steward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>No thanks to you—I saw them there this
 morn<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing—they are lately arrived from India, and their busi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness it
 seems no less concerns you than themselves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>And they have chosen you, I suppose, for their
 advocate—their cause will have weight in such able hands. Will you
 dine here? Believe me, I long to cultivate the closest intimacy with
 you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Try the test, which life is the most rational, and I accept,
 this gage of friendship—I'll dine with you, and you and your friends
 shall sup with me, and if before we part, you do not confess my conduct
 to be more reasonable than your's, I'll change my ground and be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>come as
 errant a votary of dissipation as you or the mad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dest of your
 adherents.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>A match—when am I to see this Indian queen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Presently—Ah! Rupee—I wish I could plead as
 successfully the cause of another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Lucy—Seabright's charming daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>What would you say of her, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>That she is miserable, and you have made her so; that you
 have stolen her heart, and I fear her honor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>That's very well faith, I did not expect this—what!
 man—are not you and I young, high-blooded? will you make me believe,
 while your companions have been beating the bushes of a morning, you have
 never stolen away to the arms of some cherry-cheeked farmer's daughter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I am incapable of the crime you insinuate; a true
 English sportsman holds his tenants comfort and security as inviolate
 as his own. The chase ought to be for the destruction of beasts of prey
 and the extermination of vermin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="9"/>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>When faintly gleams the doubtful day,</l>
                                 <l>Ere yet the dew-drops on the thorn</l>
                                 <l>Borrow a lustre from the ray</l>
                                 <l>That tips with gold the dancing corn,</l>
                                 <l>Health bids awake and homage pay,</l>
                                 <l>To him who gave another morn.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>And well with strength his nerves to brace,</l>
                                 <l>Urges the sportsman to the chase.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>II.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>"<note place="bottom" n="*">The lines marked with
 inverted commas are to be omitted in the repre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sentation</note>Do we pursue
 the timid hare,</l>
                                 <l>"As trembling o'er the lawn she bounds?</l>
                                 <l>"Still of her safety have we care,</l>
                                 <l>"While seeming death her steps surrounds,</l>
                                 <l>"We the defenceless creature spare,</l>
                                 <l>"And instant stop the well taught hounds.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>"For cruelty should ne'er disgrace</l>
                                 <l>"The well earn'd pleasure of the chase.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>III.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Return'd with shaggy spoils well stor'd</l>
                                 <l>To our convivial joys at night,</l>
                                 <l>We toast, and first our country's lord,</l>
                                 <l>Anxious who most shall do him right;</l>
                                 <l>The fair next crowns the social board,</l>
                                 <l>Britons should love as well as fight,</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>For he who slights the tender race,</l>
                              <l>Is held unworthy of the chase.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <pb n="13" facs="10"/>
               <head>SCENE III.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Seabright's</hi> house, <hi>Sir Ephraim</hi> and
<hi>Seabright.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I never heard of such a devil of an ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>travagant villain
 in my life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sea.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, Sir Ephraim, his excesses are without end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well well, we must endeavour to cure them; he believes me to
 be dead, and his sister in India, he has forgot her of course; and as for
 me, I have nothing to do but keep aloof till our plot is wrought to its height;
 but what gives me the greatest pleasure in this business is, that the
 son of my old friend Hengist English will join our designs against my
 son. I remember his father and I talked of him and my Aurelia when they were
 little ones; I should not be sorry to revive the idea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sea.</speaker>
                  <p>You could not choose a worthier son-in-law; he is the idol
 of the county.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, we'll make my boy the idol of the county too. We,
 starched old fellows, Seabright, don't give latitude enough to the fiery
 feelings, and tow<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ering spirits of a mettled young dog like him; consider
 his princely fortune, his elegant connections.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sea.</speaker>
                  <p>These, Sir, are so many mirrors for mens ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tions, which
 will reflect nothing as a beauty, but what has a tendency to honour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>And I hope there are a great many such ten<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dencies in my
 Ephraim; what has he done? accuse him of something; has he neglected to
 relieve indigent me<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rit? has he pitifully sold his principles for the
 smiles of power? has he seduced the wife or daughter of his friend?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sea.</speaker>
                  <p>Daughter of his friend, Sir!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay—I'd never forgive that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sea.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, it's very hard—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis very severe judging; but if you know any thing, speak
 out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sea.</speaker>
                  <p>What a question! Miss Aurelia Sir—good heaven!</p>
                  <stage>[goes off.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <pb n="14" facs="11"/>
               <head>SCENE IV.</head>
               <stage>—<hi>Aurelia, Lucy.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! Aurelia! well but, Seabright—how, gone!—he has
 left me very abruptly methinks—afraid of offending I
 suppose—that's nonsense; he might have said what he
 pleased.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Aurelia</hi> comes on, followed by two or three
<hi>Lascars,</hi> one car<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rying a monkey, another a maccaw,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Here I am</l>
                              <l>With my ching wham wham,</l>
                              <l>Gay splendid and dazzling pronounce me,</l>
                              <l>While chang whang whang,</l>
                              <l>As their citrons they twang,</l>
                              <l>My slaves and attendants announce me.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Lascars with their tymbals,</l>
                              <l>Go thrum thrum thrum,</l>
                              <l>And give the alarm by their drumming;</l>
                              <l>While females, their cymbals</l>
                              <l>Go strum strum strum,</l>
                              <l>Proclaiming her title that's coming. Here I am,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>At length the mutes</l>
                              <l>With their dulcet flutes,</l>
                              <l>So sweetly join the cymbals strum,</l>
                              <l>And qualify the tymbals thrum;</l>
                              <l>'Till having stunn'd the listening ears</l>
                              <l>With whing, chang chang,</l>
                              <l>And ching whang whang,</l>
                              <l>At length the motley train appears. Here I am,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="12"/>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>You are in fine spirits this morning, Aurelia; you'll never
 forget the sprightly wildness of the east; I wish I could see your
 companion half so merry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh lord, Sir, you'll get nothing from her but sighs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>I have observed it, and if I mistake not, di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vined the
 cause too; 'twas a wicked Sylvan to steal so tender a heart—hey!
 Lucy,—well well, don't blush, but come tell me, daughters judge more
 charitably of young fellows than fathers, what do you think of my son?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>Think of him, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, is he not an elegant, fine young fellow?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe there is no doubt of that, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>And now as to his vices and follies, as they are called.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>Dear Sir, how should I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>I beg your pardon, you young girls make shrewd remarks—I
 have had hints.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>Hints, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, hints; in short, do you believe him capable of a
 premeditated dishonourable action?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh!
 <stage>(cries)</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>She's crying ready to break her heart, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Hey-day, what's all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear Lucy, an't you well?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>I beg your pardon, ma'am, I am lately so low-spirited, and
 so little fit for company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why really, Lucy, this is very unaccountable. I have noticed a
 sort of coolness between you and your father, but it looked rather like
 unhappiness than anger; let me intercede. You know, Lucy, you are my
 god-daughter, and should consider me as a second father; come, come, be
 chearful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I am obliged to you for your advice, but the best
 precepts are thrown away upon an impractica<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble subject; you add to my griefs
 by bringing them to my recollection, but when the thorn of affliction rankles
 in the heart, busy remembrance may irritate, but con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>not extract it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="13"/>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Who to my wounds a balm advises,</l>
                              <l>But little knows what I endure;</l>
                              <l>The patient's pain to torture rises</l>
                              <l>When medicine's try'd and fails to cure.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>What can the wisest council teach me,</l>
                              <l>But sad remembrance of my grief?</l>
                              <l>Alas! your kindness cannot reach me,</l>
                              <l>It gives but words—I ask relief.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE V.</head>
               <stage>—<hi>Sir Ephraim, Aurelia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Old Seabright surely gets crabbed and pee<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vish; how can this
 poor girl have offended him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear papa, that's not her grief.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>What is then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>One I fancy you would not be very fond of curing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you mean?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>I mean that after so much anxiety for a beloved son, you
 would hardly consent that he should throw him<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self away upon your
 steward's daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Phoo, phoo—nonsense—impossible!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, my dear Sir, you have no observation, didn't you
 perceive her sensible confusion whenever you spoke of him? didn't she
 sigh, faulter, tremble, and hesitate, and then burst out a crying?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, 'tis very true; her father too was ter<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ribly shocked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>And I should not wonder if it was a scheme be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tween
 them—As to the lady she is so soft and sentimental!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>And so was the papa; he had his tenden<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cies, and his mirrors,
 and his afflictions; we must think of this.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="scene">
               <pb n="17" facs="14"/>
               <head>SCENE VI.</head>
               <stage>—<hi>Sir Ephraim, Aurelia, English.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir Ephraim you must disappear from hence as fast as can,
 unless you wish your son to see you, for here he comes in full
 sail.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>In full sail indeed! why zounds, he and his company look like
 a troop of Bacchanals—Ah! I'll make one in their pious orgies before
 long.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE VII.</head>
               <stage>English, Aurelia, Rupee.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>[Speaking behind.]</stage> Fidget, shew his lordship
 the avenue leading to the Park, and I'll wait for you here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Rupee, I have the pleasure to introduce to you a fair
 supplicant, whose story you will find singular and interesting: you
 are also concern'd in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>How so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll tell you, sir—My father acquir'd a consi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>derable
 fortune, which my brother squanders away in loose and idle
 pleasures—In his affairs your's are closely involved, the wealth of
 both having sprung from the same source.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Very likely: I have extensive India connections—His
 name, pray?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>You will hear it from my father, sir; at present I require
 your speedy interference in this business, left it come too late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Why too late?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>His excessive dissipation and blind partiality for
 disreputable and worthless objects may leave him without the means of
 assisting me or himself.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>A sad fellow, this same brother of your's, ma'am!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>One would think she was describing you, Rupee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh yes! I dare say I shall get just such another
 sermon from my sister when she arrives.—What, he is incorrigible,
 is he, ma'am?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>As much so as vanity, affluence, and intercourse with knaves
 and flatterers can make him; besides, I fear we shall be too late on
 another account.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="15"/>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, what's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>There was a rumor, as I came over, that your title to your
 fortune is very equivocal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed.
 <stage>[With indifference.]</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I have seen a gentleman who means to lay claim to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith, Rupee, this seems to be a serious business.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Not at all—We Nabobs, according to rumor, hold our
 fortunes at the pleasure of the public; but while we keep unaccounted
 thousands for sops to an enquiring Cerberus, he may growl, but in the end
 he'll be sure to fawn, and let us pass.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
               <stage>Rupee, English, Aurelia, Lord Lofty.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>Upon my consequence, 'tis a shame you should have this
 trio so long to yourselves—by my dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tinction, she is a lovely
 creature—Rupee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>My lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>This girl's come to you about disagreeable business.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>She is, my lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>I am in love with her; I'll take her off your hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>A gallant proposal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>O lord! tis nothing at all for me: I always catch them on the
 wing—at first sight—ha—pop down they come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Bravo!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>But perhaps ma'am, I can't tempt you—youth, a fine
 figure, talents, white teeth, an earldom, and fifty thousand a year won't be
 worth your acceptance—Hey, Rupee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, shall I beg you'll see me to my father?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>By my title, it must not be—my dear ma'am, it will kill
 me; stretch me, by my condition I shall ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pire with grief.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Don't be uneasy, my lord, you'll see the lady again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>Hartshorn to my fainting fancy, or may I die a plebeian,
 you'll leave hope with me at least, ma'am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="16"/>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Ne'er yet did lover</l>
                                 <l>Hope discover,</l>
                                 <l>'Till won by sighs and wishes tender;</l>
                                 <l>To reward him,</l>
                                 <l>We accord him</l>
                                 <l>That presage of our hearts surrender.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Hope's the reward of faithful hearts,</l>
                                 <l>Herald of every joy propitious,</l>
                                 <l>The course on which the lover starts,</l>
                                 <l>Eager to reach that goal he wishes.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>When you a lover's title prove,</l>
                                 <l>So kind, so true—well pleas'd to greet
 you,</l>
                                 <l>This hope, the harbinger of love,</l>
                                 <l>With winning smiles shall haste to meet
 you.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE IX,</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Lord Lofty, Rupee, Nettle, Fidget, Hairbrain,</hi> other
Company, and <hi>English,</hi> who returns after having gone off with
<hi>Aurelia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>An angel! or may I die without heirs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>(coming on)</stage> Upon my soul, Nettle, you use his
 lo<gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter" rend="content:•">
                        <desc>illegible</desc>
                     </gap>dship very scurvily; what can
 be more noble than to be, as I may say, the sun of generosity to the
 world of science?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Or rather the moon, for 'tis but a borrowed light.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>No, 'tis you are the moon, for all the light you give is by
 reflection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Well said, Fidget.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, let Nettle alone, I know him of old; his head is like the
 Denaides with their sieves, always overflowing and always empty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Something like your taste then, my Lord—how often have
 I seen you sit with rapture to see a fellow mincing along like a figure
 cut out in spermaceti, per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sonating <pb n="20" facs="17"/> Julius Caesar,
 or Marc Antony, and giving command to an army, or laws to an empire, in the
 tone of a bullfinch or a child's three-penny whistle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith, Nettle, I so far join you in this last re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mark, that
 I would rather hear my friend English sing the old plaintive song of Jack
 Ratling in his manner, than the finest warbling the Hay-Market can afford
 us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps the gentleman will favour us with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>With great pleasure, my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Jack Ratlin was the ablest seaman,</l>
                                 <l>None like him could hand, reef and steer;</l>
                                 <l>No dangerous toil but he'd encounter,</l>
                                 <l>With skill, and in contempt of fear.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>In fight a lion; the battle ended,</l>
                                 <l>Meek as the bleating lamb he'd prove;</l>
                                 <l>Thus Jack had manners, courage, merit—</l>
                                 <l>Yet did he sigh—and all for love.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>II.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>The song, the jest, the flowing
 liquor—</l>
                                 <l>For none of these had Jack regard;</l>
                                 <l>He, while his messmates were carousing,</l>
                                 <l>High sitting on the pendant yard,</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Would think upon his fair one's beauties,</l>
                                 <l>Swear never from such charms to rove;</l>
                                 <l>That truly he'd adore them living,</l>
                                 <l>And dying—sigh—to end his love.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>III.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>The same express the crew commanded</l>
                                 <l>Once more to view their native land,</l>
                                 <l>Among the rest brought Jack some
 tidings—</l>
                                 <l>Would it had been his love's fair hand!</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Oh fate!—her death defac'd the letter,</l>
                                 <l>Instant his pulse forgot to move;</l>
                                 <l>With quiv'ring lips and eyes uplifted,</l>
                                 <l>He heav'd a sigh—and dy'd for love.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="18"/>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>Bravo!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, ay, while you have such goods as these, you need not go
 to foreign markets.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                  <p>Rupee, yonder comes Ap Hugh: we have been teazing him to death,
 till the poor Welshman's like a horse in the pillars, he neither stands
 nor goes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Here he comes, what shall we say to him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                  <p>The comicalest notion alive; let us send him to
 Coventry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Well thought of; will you join him, my lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lord L.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, I'll be as errant a school-boy as the best of you.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="scene">
               <head>SCEN X.</head>
               <stage>—To them, <hi>Ap Hugh.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Saaf you saaf you, coot people—I be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lieve I have some
 favours and obligations, and first of all, Mr. Nettle, what is the
 reason—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Goats and monkeys.
 <stage>(turning away from him.)</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, it is ferry pretty monkeys you are inteed, and it is ferry
 pretty chipes and cheres, but I counsel and warn you. Ah! Mr. English, I
 pray you—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>(looking him full in the face)</stage> Oh he de nos.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh</speaker>
                  <p>Odds my cholers and my passions, is hur to be be played a
 pass and moreover a scurvy trick? but all is one—Mr. Rupee, I too
 tesire—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>(speaking to Lord Lofty)</stage> you say very true, my
 lord, the passions of Welchmen are like mad bleak, they swim upon the
 surface, but nothing can sink them to the level of reason.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>A mad pleak! is hur a fish, or a bleak or a trout? if hur is a
 trout, I can tell you, you do not go the way to tickle her. My deer Patience, I
 too be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>seech you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Rupee, don't you remember one Ap Hugh we had with us?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, he fell in love with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes poor fellow, I first slighted him, and he first went
 mad and then hanged himself.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Hur believes hur shall co mad inteed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot bear to see him so unhappy; they have sent you to
 Coventry, Ap Hugh—'twas all Nettle's doings.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="19"/>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not tout it, and if I was to sent him to the tiffels and
 belzebubs he would be only among his relations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, dinner's served.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, gentlemen, first for the dinner, and then for the
 Burgundy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>Bravo!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>CHORUS.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>What if my pleasures fools condemn,</l>
                                 <l>Because I am not dull like them,</l>
                                 <l>Because no minute I let pass</l>
                                 <l>Unmarked by a convivial glass?</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Or else returned from strife and noise,</l>
                                 <l>I tempt the fair to softer joys;</l>
                                 <l>A mortal with a soul divine,</l>
                                 <l>Alternate crown'd with love and wine.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>II.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>These shall on earth my being share,</l>
                                 <l>And when I'm gone, if in my heir</l>
                                 <l>My spirit live, let him not mourn,</l>
                                 <l>But see emboss'd upon my urn:</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Bacchus and Venus in a wreath,</l>
                                 <l>With this inscription underneath:</l>
                                 <l>"This mortal had a soul divine,</l>
                                 <l>"Alternate crown'd with love and wine."</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>END OF THE FIRST ACT.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <pb n="23" facs="20"/>
            <head>ACT II.</head>
            <div n="1" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>—A Shrubbery.</stage>
               <stage>Patience, English.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>ENGLISH seems to have got hold of this business pretty
 well—I remember old Ratsbane was the lawyer fellow, well enough; and if
 he really has joc<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>key'd Rupee, so much the better for Lucy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Png.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Hairbrain, do you think we shall be a match for
 Rupee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>What, about Lucy—ay, ay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Well I am glad to find you are so confident of
 success.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>Confident! come—to speak in your sporting
 way—I'll bett you five hundred to fifty, that if that young filly is but
 guided by me, tho' he jockey'd her across the flat, and run away from the
 ditch, she catches him at the turn of the lands, and wins the race in a
 canter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art a generous girl.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why as to that, I was accessary to Lucy's mis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fortunes;
 and I should give but a bad sample of my promis'd Reformation, if I did not
 assist to get her out of them—besides this is not half the
 mischief on foot—there's a pretty deep stake to play with my lord;
 he has <pb n="24" facs="21"/> his plots too—there are more folks to be
 ruin'd, I can tell you, if matters could be brought to bear; but no,
 no—that won't do—there's misery enough in the world without his
 assistance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>You have some excellent sentiments: 'tis a pity you could
 not be brought to a little reformation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, to tell you the truth, I am not without hope that when Ap
 Hugh finds I rigidly pursue the re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>form I have planned, he may be wrought on
 to make, in the language of the world, an honest woman; and then, should
 fortune bless me with a daughter, the care of her morals should be an
 atonement for the neglect of mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Nobly resolv'd!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>—LUCY.</speaker>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Oh transports beyond measure!</l>
                                 <l>Oh exstacy of pleasure!</l>
                                 <l>What unknown joys possess me!</l>
                                 <l>The world will now confess me</l>
                                 <l>That honor'd, happy thing, a wife.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Should unexpected crosses</l>
                                 <l>Misfortunes breed and losses,</l>
                                 <l>My husband's cares to soften,</l>
                                 <l>I'll tenderly and often</l>
                                 <l>With kisses banish every strife.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Thus I'll discharge so duly,</l>
                                 <l>So constantly, so truly,</l>
                                 <l>So well my duty's promise;</l>
                                 <l>That, pain and care far from us,</l>
                                 <l>Sweet shall be our cup of life.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <pb n="25" facs="22"/>
               <head>SCENE II.</head>
               <stage>—ENGLISH, AURELIA.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear Aurelia, a thousand impertinent things have
 maliciously prevented me from paying my devoirs to you; however, 'twill not
 be difficult to woo you; we are both children of nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, but where's my oriental splendor, that lan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>guid
 happiness, that sickening delight, which, from its excess of luxury, was
 at once both pleasure and satiety?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>In these arms what Nabob can boast so extensive an
 empire as my heart; or slave, so perfect an obedience to your
 will?—Then for amusement, I'll turn you out a deer shall keep his
 hunters at bay like the subtil pard; and if you wish to lounge in litters
 and palanquins, I have ploughmen as agile as Lascars, and horses as
 strong as elephants.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Charming!—you are not a bit like an Indian
 galant—I'll describe one to you—He comes out with an anticipated
 consumption, holds a timorous command, escapes assassination by
 miracle, gets hated abroad, cen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sured at home—marries, and dies of a
 catalogue of un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>titled diseases.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>What a description!—thank fortune, then who reserved
 me for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Upon my word—I don't know that I shall marry you.
 Apropos—now I think of it, I am offended with you—how came you to
 conceal all this fine busi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness of Miss Lucy from me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>I! my dear Aurelia?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! no not you, you know nothing of her in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tention to cheat my
 brother, first of his senses and then of his fortune; but I would have
 you, for your own sake, take care how you tamper in this business, for in
 my mind, he who abets the brother's folly can have but little regard for the
 sister's happiness.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>But, Aurelia—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, it is the same thing to me; it shall be either peace or
 war, India or English—say but the word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="23"/>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Prepar'd each army in its way,</l>
                              <l>Would you hostilities should cease,</l>
                              <l>Do you the olive branch display;</l>
                              <l>I'll smoke the calimut of peace.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>But if in arms we must be found,</l>
                              <l>Haste to the field and let us see</l>
                              <l>If your trumpet or my war-hoop's sound,</l>
                              <l>Can loudest cry—to victory.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE III.</head>
               <stage>English, Lucy.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>So so, now must I make an enemy of either my mistress or
 my honor—to affront the latter might be to lose both, and as our
 mistresses are often offended and pleased they know not why, I'll e'en
 keep my ho<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nor, which I am sure will never be out of humour with me, unless
 I deserve it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>I beg your pardon, I thought Miss Rupee had been here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>She is this instant gone, and in a perfect pet, I can tell
 you, at my entering the lists as your champion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Sir?—I don't understand you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear Lucy, I wou'd be cautious of offend<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing your gentless
 and delicacy, but 'tis necessary I should speak out—In a word, I
 have consulted your father on the subject of Rupee's treachery towards you,
 who, but for my persuasions, would have carried his resentment to a
 length more becoming the honest feelings of a man then the wary prudence of a
 peasant—I appeased him however, and am, I think, now by the help of
 one of Rupee's engines, on the eve of such a discovery as must be of
 service to us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>I fear, Sir, you know not what you under<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>take.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="24"/>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, I do—take courage, Lucy—you'll be happier,
 and then in the words of my favourite song, you shall pardon the treason
 for the sake of the traitor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! that song—how often have I sung it and wept!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Then sing it now, and rejoice that the disagree<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>able part of
 it is past, and all that's pleasurable in it to come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>—LUCY.</speaker>
                              <lg>
                                 <lg>
                                    <l>When faries are lighted by night's silver
 queen,</l>
                                    <l>And feast in the meadow, or dance on the
 green,</l>
                                    <l>My Lumkin aside lays his plough and his
 flail</l>
                                    <l>By yon oak to sit near me, and tell his fond
 tale.</l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <lg>
                                    <l>And tho' I'm assur'd the same vows were
 believ'd</l>
                                    <l>By Patty and Ruth he forsook and deceiv'd,</l>
                                    <l>Yet so sweet are his words, and like truth
 so appear,</l>
                                    <l>I pardon the treason, the traytor's so
 near.</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </lg>
                              <lg n="2">
                                 <head>II.</head>
                                 <lg>
                                    <l>I saw the straw bonnet he bought at the
 fair,</l>
                                    <l>The rose-colour'd ribbons to deck Jenny's
 hair,</l>
                                    <l>The shoe-tyes of Bridget, and, still worse
 than this,</l>
                                    <l>The gloves he gave Peggy for stealing a
 kiss.</l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <lg>
                                    <l>All these did I see, and with heart-rending
 pain,</l>
                                    <l>Swore to part; yet I know when I see him
 again,</l>
                                    <l>His words and his looks will like truth so
 appear,</l>
                                    <l>I shall pardon the treason, the traytor's so
 dear.</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </lg>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <pb n="28" facs="25"/>
               <head>SCENE III.</head>
               <stage>English, Rupee.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>English—If I had not the greatest regard for you I
 should laugh in your face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed!—'tis lucky then your friendship shields me
 from your ridicule. Why so much mirth, pray?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing—Your fine Indian adventurer has con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sented to an
 elopement with my lord, that's all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>For shame, Mr. Rupee! the lady in question is a woman of
 honor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell you she is an errant town bite, and but that the title
 and fortune of his lordship are more splendid than your's, she would have
 tricked you as compleatly as she means to gull him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot bear it, Mr. Rupee—you know not who you
 abuse—but I will not reproach you, you'll endure enough before you
 sleep, your Liberty-Hall is convulsed to the very center, Sir; it totters
 over your head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed! and did your woman of honour tell you that too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Both her and her father—he who has a better right here
 than you have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! oh! oh! I shall never have done laugh<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing—her
 father!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Sir, before many hours are over your head, you will
 confess yourself a dependant on his very bounty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Why zounds, man, I possess my fortune by my father's
 will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>I know it—but there was one material circum<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stance
 omitted, which alone could give you a title to it.—he forgot to die.
 <stage>(aside)</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>So they have told you, and I dare say, under the influence of
 your oriental empress, you believe it.—However, to snatch you at
 once from your infatuation, I am going to lend Lord Lofty my coach, and five
 thou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sand pounds, to accelerate his project.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <pb n="29" facs="26"/>
               <head>SCENE V.</head>
               <stage>—<hi>English, Patience, Nettle, Fidget, Ap
Hugh.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Lend him five thousand pounds! that must be
 prevented—but what does he mean by an elopement?—oh! I see
 it—Hairbrain's deep stake, I'll bett a thou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                  <p>And I'll go your halves—I have made an ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pointment in the
 Indian gentlewoman's name, where his Lordship may kick his heels long enough
 to no pur<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pose.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Excellent!—well, what success?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                  <p>What with the old pettifogger, all bank; as good a licence as
 ever started from Doctors Commons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>And he'll come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                  <p>Who? the lawyer! why he's to get something by it, is not
 he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Now for Rupee's probation—'twill be severe, but 'tis
 necessary; he must smart to be cured—thank Heaven his affairs are
 retrievable—a spendthrift in his career is like the racer on which he
 betts his money,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>See the course throng'd with gazers, the sports
 are begun,</l>
                                 <l>The confusion but hear! I'll bett
 you—done—done;</l>
                                 <l>Ten thousand strange murmurs resound far and
 near,</l>
                                 <l>Lords, hawkers and jockies assail the tir'd
 ear.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>While, with neck like a rainbow, erecting his
 crest,</l>
                                 <l>Pamper'd, prancing and pleas'd—his head
 touching his breast,</l>
                                 <l>Scarcely snuffing the air, he's so proud and
 elate,</l>
                                 <l>The high mettl'd racer—first starts for
 the plate.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <pb n="30" facs="27"/>
                              <head>II.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>
                                    <note place="bottom" n="*">The second and third
 Stanzas omitted in the Representation.</note>Now reynard's turn'd out, and
 o'er hedge and ditch rush,</l>
                                 <l>Hounds, horses, and huntsmen all hard at his
 brush;</l>
                                 <l>They run him at length, and they have him at
 bay,</l>
                                 <l>And by scent and by view, cheat a long tedious
 way.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>While alike born for sports of the field or the
 course,</l>
                                 <l>Always sure to come thorough a staunch and fleet
 horse;</l>
                                 <l>When fairly run down, the fox yields up his
 breath;</l>
                                 <l>The high mettled racer—is in at the death.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>III.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Grown aged, us'd up, and turn'd out of the
 stud,</l>
                                 <l>Lame, spavin'd and windgall'd, but yet with some
 blood;</l>
                                 <l>While knowing postilions his pedigree trace,</l>
                                 <l>Tell his dam won the sweepstakes, his father
 that race.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>And what matches he run to the ostlers count
 o'er,</l>
                                 <l>As they loiter their time at some hedge
 ale-house door;</l>
                                 <l>While the harness sore galls, and the spurs
 his sides goad,</l>
                                 <l>The high-mettled racer's—a hack on the
 road.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="4">
                              <head>IV.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Till at last, having labour'd, drudg'd early and
 late,</l>
                                 <l>Bow'd down by degrees, he bends on to his fate;</l>
                                 <l>Blind, old, lean, and feeble, he tugs round a
 mill,</l>
                                 <l>Or draws sand, till the sand of his hour-glass
 stands still.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>And now, cold and lifeless, expos'd to the
 view,</l>
                                 <l>In the very same cart which he yesterday
 drew;</l>
                                 <l>While a pitying crowd his sad relicks
 surrounds,</l>
                                 <l>The high-mettled racer—is sold to the
 hounds.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="28"/>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>(coming on)</stage> Coxcombs and ideots!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>What's the matter, Nettle?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Why there's that fool Ap Hugh drunk with ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tacy; because this
 pretty lady has given him some encou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ragement, he is sputtering, singing,
 and ejaculating his transports in broken Welsh—here he comes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Kif her a crate deal of burgundy, and kif her luff, and kif her
 sweet kisses look you—oh! it is her pretty Patience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>So Ap Hugh, how art lad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Hur is not Ap Hugh, hur is a Cod and a Jupiter, and moreover a
 happy mortal to poot look you; oh! her could sing matricals like a dying
 swan, and hur could caper as high as a plue mountain—oh! it is hur
 pretty Patience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>How the ideot's taken with this wench!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not so crate a wench as you are a coxcombe, Mr. Nettle,
 and Mr. thistle, and Mr. prior; you are an adder, and a fiper, and a snake;
 for you have a sting in your mouth, and you carry poison in your worts, put
 hur will make you eat your worts, poison and all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pat.</speaker>
                  <p>Pacify him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh yes, I'll pacify him—come, Ap Hugh, don't be in a
 passion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Hur is not in a passion, hur is in love—Oh! it is
 pretty to be in love.</p>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When by hur side hur sits and sings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And cupids with their fluttring wings.—</hi>
                     <stage>(sings)</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Better put him to bed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! I pray you let her be put to ped—where is hur
 Patience? it is ferry pretty to be put to ped, <hi>when by hur side,
 and</hi>— <stage>(sings)</stage> Is it not a pretty Patience, my little
 Fitchet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="29"/>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! she has the carnation of Titian, and the softness of
 Carlo Dolce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! it is ferry tolce, and it is sweet, and it is exstatic,
 and it is angels and cherubims, and hea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vens, and paradice;
 <stage>(seeing <hi>Patience</hi>)</stage> Oh! there is hur
 Patience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Why you don't love her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ap Hugh.</speaker>
                  <p>Not luff her!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Do salmons love a lucid stream?</l>
                                 <l>Do thirsty sheep love fountains?</l>
                                 <l>Do Druids love a doleful theme?</l>
                                 <l>Or goats the craggy mountains?</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>If it be true these things are so,</l>
                                 <l>As truly she's my lovey,</l>
                                 <l>And os wit I yng carie I</l>
                                 <l>Rwy fi dwyn dy garie di</l>
                                 <l>As—Ein dai tree pedwar pimp
 chweck—go</l>
                                 <l>The bells of Aberdovey.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>II.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Do keffels love a whisp of hay?</l>
                                 <l>Do sprightly kids love prancing?</l>
                                 <l>Do curates crowdies love to play?</l>
                                 <l>Or peasants morice-dancing?</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>If it be true, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                           </lg>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="33" facs="30"/>Re-enter <hi>Nettle,</hi> to
<hi>Fidget.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Was there ever such a house?—full of confu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sion and
 extravagance!—just as I prophesied, the fel<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>low's ruined.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Who, poor Rupee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Finished, done up.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>I pity him from my very soul.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis more than I do—a dissipated, low-born,
 purse-proud—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>He is gone to Sir Edward English's; let us fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>low
 him—we should all unite to comfort the poor fellow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, I'll comfort him with a good whole<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>some lecture; an
 upstart, pitiful— <stage>(going)</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Poor, good-natured, honest, worthy—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>(pushing <hi>Fidget</hi> before him)</stage> Get along
 with your stupid pity.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE VII.</head>
               <stage>—A Gothic hall.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Rupee</hi> speaking to a servant—afterwards
<hi>English.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, Sir; I'll wait for your master here—There is
 a noble, bold honour, in the actions of English, which I vainly endeavour to
 imitate—that I love Lucy, is true—that I have seduced her, I
 blush, and confess—but I hate to be forced into any thing—we
 shall see what's to be done.—So, English, where are the mighty
 perils I was threatened with? every thing here wears an air of tranquillity,
 and the place announces itself by the title you have given it—the
 Mansion of Content.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Rupee, be assur'd, the task I have under<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>taken is an
 unwilling one; but it proceeds from the purest esteem—I shall touch
 you home, but you ought to thank me—he who has the courage to wring his
 friend's heart, merits more from him, than he who flat<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ters his vanity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, this is shaking hands before we go to fifty-cuffs, at
 least—come, come, perhaps I am not so <pb n="34" facs="31"/> bad as you
 imagine—I was thinking how to do Lucy justice as you came in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Suppose it should not be in your power, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you mean?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Suppose one of those marriages which were so many decoys
 to seduction, and all which you thought counterfeit, should prove real.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come, no false alarms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>The alarm is too just—you are married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Death, and Hell!—married!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Your confidential friend, Mr. Ratsbane, has tricked you into a
 marriage, not with a view of serving the lady, or you; but himself.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Infamous rascal!—I'll sacrifice him to appease that
 justice he has so often violated.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Patience—the lady and the credentials are within; all that
 troubles me at present, is the situation of poor Lucy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! villain!—till this moment I never look'd upon my
 enormities otherwise than as youthful folly, and pardonable vivacity.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="scene">
               <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
               <stage>—<hi>Lucy, English, Rupee.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>—LUCY.</speaker>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Hear me, unkind and cruel, hear me,</l>
                                 <l>In pity to the griefs I feel!</l>
                                 <l>Or smiling turn and kindly cheer me,</l>
                                 <l>Or here will I for ever kneel.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>'Twixt life and death the soul to fetter,</l>
                                 <l>Ah! who can bear't? My sentence speak:</l>
                                 <l>Than love, bear it unblest 'twere better;</l>
                                 <l>The woe-worn heart at once should break.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="32"/>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Was ever man so compleatly the object of his own contempt? By
 one cursed contrivance of an insi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dious knave, I am not only involved in a
 marriage with some wretch I despise; but prevented from redressing a
 beautiful creature I adore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>I am happy to find these are your feelings; for this is the
 very object to whom you are really married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Come to my arms, possess my love, and partake my
 fortune!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>You have no fortune to give her, Rupee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, English, no more trials; you have car<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ried your point
 handsomely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>I wish they were but trials.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Nettle, Fidget</hi> following.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Your servant, Mr. Rupee; 'tis all up with you, I find.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p> 
                     <stage>[Coming on.]</stage> Where's Rupee? Oh lord! there's the
 devil to pay at the house yonder—ten or twelve swarthy ill-looking
 scoundrels are in possession—and our poor,
 dear—Liberty-Hall is put under an arrest.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a very comical jest, gentlemen; but if you have any
 regard for your bones, you'll cary it no farther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>Poor fellow, how he looks? How do you do, Rupee?—upon my
 soul, I pity you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Pity from thee!—thou worm, thou nothing!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come, Mr. Rupee, be humble and know yourself.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>And are you to teach me, snarling mastiff? I'll go and know
 the truth of all this. What villain can be hardy enough to pretend a claim to
 my fortune?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="scene">
               <pb n="36" facs="33"/>
               <head>SCENE IX.</head>
               <stage>To them <hi>Sir Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Seabright.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you think of me, you dog?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>My father, thank heaven!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>And well you may for putting a project in my head to shew you
 the use of riches before you came to the possession of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>I do from my soul, sir—Your attention to my welfare
 sets my unworthiness before me in such a light—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, profit by the reflection, for fear I should take
 it in my head to die in good earnest.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Far, far, be that day—No, sir, live, and let me merit
 your forgiveness.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I believe there are hopes of your re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>formation since this
 last conduct to Lucy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>How, sir! do you approve?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Why this surpasses my hopes! I thought nothing could have
 moved you on that subject.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Not while there appeared to be a design on my fortune: but as
 it is, it is your affair—mine, the cause of every honest man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>But in the midst of all this, where's my sister!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Who, the Indian adventurer? Gone off with my lord, to be
 sure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>A truce, a truce, I beseech you—I confess my<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>self
 conquered, and call for quarter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>And I give it you: My lord is safe, and to<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>morrow we'll
 request his repayment of the five thousand pounds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>But my sister.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="scene">
               <pb n="37" facs="34"/>
               <head>SCENE the last.</head>
               <stage>—To them <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>I am here, and happy in this proof of my dear brother's
 affections.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear Aurelia!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ma'am, have you nothing to say to me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes: you have been very good, and I'll requite your kindness
 in any way that you shall ask and my fa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther approve.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>That's generous!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>How's this? signing and sealing without the lawyer! 'tis too
 late for him or the parson to-night; but that's no reason we should not
 have the fiddles.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>What, the fiddles! oh, I'll go and fetch 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>And I'll get away from such a set of fools and madmen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, Ephraim, you have escap'd a pretty tumble.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, sir, I am giddy when I think of the pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cipice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                  <p>Never was such a providential intervention; where must your
 career have finished? when in four and twenty hours you have shut your two
 dearest relations out of your house to make room for a stranger, to whom
 you have lent your service, your coach, and your money, to seduce your own
 sister.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Eph.</speaker>
                  <p>Because, forsooth, this stranger happened to be a lord,
 and those are the hopeful idols you have wor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>shipped in your temple of
 Liberty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rup.</speaker>
                  <p>I resign it with pleasure, Sir—This day has convinced
 me, that freedom is no longer the gift of Hea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ven, when it degenerates into
 licentiousness, and that a work began in the Temple of Liberty is best
 sanctified when finished in the mansion of content.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="38" facs="35"/>
                  <p> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>AIR.</head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Lucy.</speaker>
                              <l>No longer slow-consuming care</l>
                              <l>And grief by turns devour me:</l>
                              <l>My heart's grown light, I tread on air,</l>
                              <l>Delicious joys o'erpow'r me.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                              <l>No low'ring clouds shall overwhelm</l>
                              <l>Henceforth our hopes on folly's sea;</l>
                              <l>For wary prudence takes the helm,</l>
                              <l>To guide the bark of Liberty.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                              <l>Increasing blessings may ye prove!</l>
                              <l>For nobly hast thou won her;</l>
                              <l>They only pay the price of love</l>
                              <l>Who purchase it with honor.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                              <l>No low'ring, &amp;c.</l>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                              <l>Like this good creature, prithee say,</l>
                              <l>Was ever such another?</l>
                              <l>Oh, that the sister's love could pay</l>
                              <l>Thy friendship to the brother!</l>
                           </sp>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>