<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd in Lambeth-chapel, at the consecration of ... John Lord Bishop of Bangor, on Sunday, Jan. 4th 1701/2. By William Hayley,:</title>
            <author>Hayley, William, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006</date>
            <availability n="CC-by-sa" status="restricted">
               <p>
                  <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
                     <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/3.0/88x31.png"/>
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</ref>
               </p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="TCP">K025272.000</idno>
            <idno type="docno">CW3322796500</idno>
            <idno type="ecll"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd in Lambeth-chapel, at the consecration of ... John Lord Bishop of Bangor, on Sunday, Jan. 4th 1701/2. By William Hayley,:</title>
                  <author>Hayley, William, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4],27,[1]p. ; 4⁰.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>printed for Jacob Tonson,</publisher>
                  <date>1702.</date>
                  <idno type="TCP">K025272.000</idno>
                  <idno type="docno">CW3322796500</idno>
                  <idno type="ecll"/>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a half-title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note>
                  <note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT10730.</note>
                  <note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2p5.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>This electronic text file was keyed from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. Character capture and encoding have been done following the guidelines of the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which correspond roughly to the recommendations found in Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="titlepage">
            <pb facs="1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd in <hi>Lambeth-Chapel,</hi> AT THE CONSECRATION OF THE Right Reverend Father in God JOHN Lord Bishop of BANGOR, On <hi>Sunday, Jan.</hi> 4th 1701/2.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM HAYLEY,</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Chichester.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonson</hi> within <hi>Gray's-Inn-Gate,</hi> next <hi>Gray's-Inn-Lane,</hi> 1702.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
         <head>A SERMON Preach'd at the Consecration of JOHN Lord Bishop of <hi>Bangor.</hi>
         </head>
         <epigraph>
            <bibl>Ephes. iv. 11, 12.</bibl>
            <q>
               <hi>And he gave some Apostles; and some Prophets; and some Evangelists; and some Pastors and Teachers.—for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Ministery, for the Edify<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing of the Body of Christ.</hi>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>THese Words contain the Substance of the Apostle's design both in this Chapter, and in his more copious Discourse upon the same Subject in the 12th and 14th Chapters of his First Epi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> In which places he
<pb n="2" facs="3"/>
gives us an Account of the <hi>Government</hi> insti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tuted in the Church of Christ; the diversity of its <hi>Officers,</hi> and their <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Powers;</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of the Institution, and the Spring of their <hi>Commission;</hi> together with the great <hi>End</hi> and Purpose for which this wise Admi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nistration was contriv'd and established: Things of the highest Importance, and very pertinent to the present <hi>Occasion:</hi> And there<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fore I shall, as far as the time allotted for my Discourse will permit, take notice of these several things, under the several Parts of my Text, and then conclude with such <hi>Observations</hi> as naturally flow from this Doctrine.<list>
                  <item>I. Here is an Account of the several Or<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ders entrusted with the Government of the Church. <hi>Some Apostles, and some Prophets, and some Evangelists, and some Pastors and Teachers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. The Apostle here tells us who was the Author of this Establishment. <hi>He gave,</hi> even our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ</hi> himself, who <hi>descended into</hi> the Grave, <hi>the lower parts of the Earth,</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="4"/>
and then <hi>ascended far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things.</hi> v. 9, 10.</item>
                  <item>III. We are here Instructed in the End and Design of this Dispensation; And are made acquainted, that all this was done <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Ministery, for the Edifying of the Body of Christ.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <p>I. I begin with the first, <hi>The several Orders,</hi> &amp;c. where it may be needful (1) to shew that there was a <hi>Disparity</hi> in these Orders, as to their Office, and a <hi>Subordination</hi> in their Ministery. (2) To consider what they were, wherein they differ'd, and what were the pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culiar <hi>Employments</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> of each Of<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fice; and (3) to reflect upon the Goodness and Providence of God, by which they have all been continued down to the present time, and establish'd in this our Church.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there was a <hi>Subordination</hi> in the Office of the several Orders in the Christian Church. Now this appears from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Reasoning</hi> and <hi>Allusions,</hi> both here, and in the other Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> At the 4th Verse of this Chapter he tells the <hi>Ephesians,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="5"/>
that the Church of Christ is <hi>one Body,</hi> that <hi>there is one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptism, and one God and Father of all;</hi> and yet he adds at the 7th verse, <hi>But unto every one of us is given Grace, according to the measure of the gift of Christ.</hi> i. e. agreeably to the true meaning of the Original word <gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 word" rend="content:〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉">
                  <desc>foreign</desc>
               </gap> in this and other places, to every one of us is given his <hi>Office</hi> or employment in the Church, different ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cording to the different gifts, which it has pleased our Lord to bestow upon us.</p>
            <p>And this he exemplifies in the following Verse, by representing our Saviour distribu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ting these Gifts, as <hi>Conquerors</hi> used to do, when they made triumphal Entries into their Capital Cities, after some notable Victories over their Enemies; when we know it was usual to disperse among the People <hi>Medals</hi> of different Bigness and different Metal, and other <hi>Gifts,</hi> some of greater and some of lesser price. Thus our Lord <hi>Jesus</hi> when he had conquered Satan and Sin, and Hell and Death, and made his Triumphant Entry into Heaven, distributed the different Gifts of his holy Spirit, in such <hi>kinds</hi> and such <hi>proportions</hi> as the Persons and Offices required to which
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>
they were conveyed. v. 8. <hi>Wherefore he saith when he ascended up on high, he led captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men,</hi> some <hi>Apo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stles,</hi> some <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But least the <hi>Subordination</hi> of the different Orders should not sufficiently appear from this <hi>disparity</hi> of their Gifts, our Apostle ren<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ders it yet more evident 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. by com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>paring them to the several parts of the Body of man; where he not only tells us at the 4. v. &amp;c. that <hi>there are diversities of Gifts, dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ferences of Administrations</hi> and <hi>diversities of Operations;</hi> but that these have a <hi>relation</hi> to, and a <hi>dependance</hi> upon one another, as the <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Hands,</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> have in mans Bo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dy, v. 12. <hi>For as the Body is one and hath many Members, and all the Members of that one Bo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dy, being many, are one Body, so also is Christ,</hi> that is, in his Body the Church. Now we know in our Bodies, the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet,</hi> &amp;c. are not only <hi>different,</hi> but <hi>subordinate;</hi> the Feet must walk by the di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rection of the <hi>Eye</hi> and the Hands act at the command of the <hi>Head,</hi> otherwise the Acti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ons will be <hi>disorderly,</hi> and the whole Body must suffer. And if there be not the like
<pb n="6" facs="7"/>
regard in the Inferior Officers in the Church toward the Superior; but all affect to di<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rect them selves, and to be the Head; there can be nothing else but <hi>Schism</hi> and <hi>Confusion</hi> in it, for <hi>if all will be one Member, where then is the Body?</hi> v. 19.</p>
            <p>I shall crave leave only to add to this Head, that this subordination of Ministers in the Church of Christ, is agreeable to what was practis'd both under the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and that of <hi>Moses;</hi> I need not take notice of the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, who were left to bare <hi>Reason</hi> in this matter; among whom we every where find a <hi>distinction</hi> of dignity in the Orders of their Priests; the thing being evi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dent among the Worshippers of the <hi>True</hi> God, who were not without some light of <hi>Revelation</hi> even under the Law of Nature, long before the <hi>Mosaical</hi> dispensation; <hi>Abra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ham</hi> himself paid Tithes to <hi>Melchizedec,</hi> and was blessed by him, and <hi>without all contra<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>diction the Less is blessed of the Greater,</hi> as the Author to the <hi>Heb.</hi> argues c. 7. v. 7. The <hi>Priesthood</hi> was a natural right of <hi>Primogeni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture</hi> at first, and God by a particular Com<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>mand order'd the <hi>First-Born</hi> to be Sancti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fied
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>
to his Service; and 'tis no question but these are the <hi>Priests</hi> which we read of before the giving of the Law. <hi>Exodus,</hi> 19. 21, 22. <hi>The Lord said unto</hi> Moses <hi>go down, charge the People least they break through unto the Lord, to gaze and many of them perish; and let the Priests also which come near to the Lord, Sancti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>fy themselves, least the Lord break forth among them.</hi> And yet these first Born, thus honour'd with the Priesthood, were subject to the <hi>Heads</hi> of their <hi>Families,</hi> and commanded by them. Thus <hi>Moses,</hi> and under him the Twelve Heads of <hi>Tribes,</hi> and the Seventy Fathers of <hi>Families,</hi> governed the Church, till it pleased God to take to himself the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> instead of the <hi>First-Born;</hi> and then the <hi>High-Priest, Priests,</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nister'd in the Service of God, in an undeni<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>able <hi>Subordination.</hi> From all which I think it is very plain, that a <hi>Co-ordinate</hi> ministery, or a <hi>Parity</hi> among all such as are employed about holy things, is a Scheme that never was found in any <hi>Nation,</hi> or <hi>Age</hi> of the World; it was never either Commanded of God, or Invented by Men, till the confusi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ons of <hi>Late</hi> times brought it forth, and
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>
let the <hi>Enemies</hi> of our Church have the honour of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Subordination of these Offices be<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing Establish'd, we are now to consider what they were, wherein they differ'd, and what were the peculiar Employments and Powers of each Office. Now in order to find out this, we must compare the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of them in this place, with the other in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. Here it is, <hi>he gave some Apostles, and some Prophets, and some Evangelists, and some Pastors and Teachers.</hi> There it is thus, <hi>God hath set some in the Church, first Apostles, secon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>darily Prophets, thirdly Teachers;</hi> after which no more <hi>Orders</hi> are named, but only those <hi>Powers</hi> that attended them in their work; <hi>Mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>racles, Gifts of Healing,</hi> &amp;c. and at v. 29. the Apostle asks, <hi>Are all Apostles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers?</hi> and without enquiring after more <hi>Orders,</hi> asks only of the Exercise of such <hi>Powers</hi> as are before mentioned. <hi>Are all workers of Miracles? Have all the gift of Healing? Do all speak with Tongues? Do all Interpret?</hi> Whence it seems very reasonable to infer, that <hi>Apostles, Prophets and Evange<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lists</hi> in the one place, must be the same with
<pb n="9" facs="10"/>
               <hi>Apostles, Prophets and Teachers</hi> in the other, and that <hi>Pastors and Teachers</hi> which are ad<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ded over and above in my <hi>Text,</hi> must not be different <hi>Officers</hi> from those before named, but other <hi>Words</hi> for the same Officers, rela<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ting to the different manner of receiving their <hi>Commission,</hi> or the different parts of their Employments. And therefore it is the Judgment of very Learned men that <hi>Prophets and Evangelists</hi> and <hi>Prophets and Teachers</hi> are the very same Ministers, with <hi>Pastors and Teachers,</hi> with this only difference, that the <hi>former</hi> were such as out of the <hi>First-Fruits</hi> of the Believers were set apart and consecrated to their Office by the <hi>Manifestation of the Spirit,</hi> or by a Supernatural effusion of Gifts proper to their Employments. The <hi>latter</hi> were such as were Ordained and Constitu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ted by <hi>Imposition of Hands,</hi> as stated Gover<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nours of the Churches allotted to their Charge. However this be, it is plain that <hi>Evangelists</hi> in the one place are called <hi>Teach<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ers</hi> in the other, from their <hi>Teaching</hi> and In<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>structing their Converts, and it seems as rea<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sonable that Christian <hi>Prophets</hi> may be called <hi>Pastors</hi> from their <hi>Feeding</hi> and Governing their Flocks; so that whether these are dif<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ferent
<pb n="10" facs="11"/>
Names for the very same <hi>Persons,</hi> or whether they signify the same <hi>Office,</hi> but with this difference, that the one respects it, as gi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ven immediately by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and the other by the Imposition of the Hands of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> the result will be the same; that there are only <hi>Three</hi> Orders properly here in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tended, and that it is of their Office and Em<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ployments that we are to enquire.</p>
            <p>And I the rather encline to this Conclusi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on, because it is agreeable to the <hi>Promise</hi> and <hi>Prediction</hi> of our <hi>Saviour</hi> himself, while he was upon Earth. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 34. <hi>Behold I send to you Prophets, and Wise men, and Scribes, and some of them you shall kill and crucify,</hi> &amp;c. Where there are only these Three Orders promis'd; the <hi>Second</hi> of which though here first placed, are called by the same name as in the <hi>Text, Prophets.</hi> The <hi>Apostles</hi> are called <hi>Wise men,</hi> agreeably to their distinguishing Gift, which we shall see by and by was the <hi>Word of Wisdom;</hi> and therefore St. <hi>Luke,</hi> who was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Evangelist, calls them by the same Name which St. <hi>Paul</hi> himself gives them, that of <hi>Apostles</hi> c. 11. v. 49. <hi>Therefore also said the Wisdom of God, I will send them Prophets</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="12"/>
               <hi>and Apostles, and some of them shall they Slay and Persecute,</hi> &amp;c. and for the <hi>Third</hi> sort, our Saviour calls them <hi>Scribes</hi> from the nature of their Office; for the Office of the <hi>Scribes</hi> was to Teach the Law, and for this reason they are in the Gospels frequently call'd by the name of <hi>Doctors</hi> or <hi>Teachers</hi> of the Law. So that <hi>Evangelists</hi> or <hi>Teachers</hi> under the Gos<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pel whose Office was <hi>parallel</hi> to theirs, might very properly bear the same <hi>Name,</hi> for to <hi>Teach</hi> and <hi>Preach the Gospel; teaching and preaching Jesus Christ</hi> are the same things in Scripture. <hi>Luk.</hi> 20. 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 42. Thus our Savi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>our built the <hi>Christian</hi> Church upon the Model of the <hi>Jewish,</hi> and in condescension to that people, and in pursuanee of the <hi>Types</hi> that preceded, was pleased as it were to Copy their <hi>High-Priest, Priests, and Levites,</hi> in the Orders of the Ministery, which he establish'd under the Gospel.</p>
            <p>We are then in the next place to consider the different <hi>Employments</hi> of these Three Or<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ders, and the different <hi>Powers</hi> that enabled them to discharge the same. And because the Higher always included the Lower, it may not be amiss to begin with the Lowest
<pb n="12" facs="13"/>
first, and so to ascend to what was peculiar to the rest.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Evangelists</hi> or <hi>Teachers:</hi> their busi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ness was properly to <hi>preach</hi> the Gospel to <hi>Ʋnbelievers,</hi> to convince them of its Truth by working <hi>Miracles,</hi> and to <hi>Baptize</hi> them upon their Conversion. An account of which we have in the 8<hi>th</hi> c. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> where we are taught that the <hi>Apostles</hi> remaining at <hi>Je<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rusalem,</hi> the rest were <hi>dispersed into</hi> Judea <hi>and</hi> Samaria <hi>preaching the Word.</hi> And that parti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cularly <hi>Philip,</hi> who was one of the Seven <hi>Deacons,</hi> and is called the <hi>Evangelist, went down to</hi> Samaria, <hi>and preached Christ to them.</hi> v. 5. And that notwithstanding the Opposi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tion of <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, they <hi>believed</hi> Phi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lip, <hi>preaching the things concerning the Kingdom of God, and the name of Jesus Christ, beholding the Miracles and Signs which were done, and were Baptized both Men and Women,</hi> v. 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Prophets</hi> besides this, were to <hi>pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>side</hi> in the Assemblies of the <hi>faithful,</hi> to per<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>form Divine Offices, Administer the Lords Supper, and Instruct their Flocks in the Scrip<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tures, and in the fuller knowledge of the Truths of the Gospel; and of this St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="14"/>
gives us a large Account in the 14. c. o 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> where he exhorts them to desire the gift of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> rather than that of <hi>Tongues,</hi> shewing, that <hi>Tongues were a Sign to them that believe not, but Prophesying serveth not for them that believe not, but for them that believe</hi> v. 22. and he ocasionally mentions all the parts of the Christian Prophets Office in that Chapter; his <hi>Preaching</hi> v. 3. <hi>He that Prophe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sieth speaketh unto men to Edification, and Ex<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>hortation and comfort.</hi> His <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Sing<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing</hi> Praises v. 15. <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the Ʋnderstanding also: I will Sing with the Spirit, and Sing with the Ʋnderstanding also.</hi> Which <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Singing</hi> are likewise in the Old Testament called <hi>Prophesying.</hi>
               <note n="inter" place="marg">1 Kin. 18. 29. 1 Sam. 10. 5. 1 Chr. 25. 1.</note> And last of all his Celebrating of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi> v. 16. which is there called <hi>Blessing</hi> and <hi>giving of Thanks</hi> 
               <gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 span" rend="content:〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉">
                  <desc>foreign</desc>
               </gap> by all which he shews, that the <hi>Prophets</hi> Office was peculiarly directed to the Edification of <hi>Believers,</hi> and for this reason he tells them v. 4. <hi>He that speaketh in an unknown Tongue edifieth himself, but he that Prophesieth edifieth the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="15"/>
3. The <hi>Apostles</hi> besides all this, had the Su<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>preme <hi>care of all the Churches</hi> upon them; they were to give <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> for their establishment, to <hi>Confirm</hi> Converts, <hi>Ordain</hi> Church Officers, and <hi>Govern</hi> and <hi>Direct</hi> them when Ordain'd; and by this means to preserve that <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> which became the Church of Christ. Thus we find in the forementioned 8th of the <hi>Acts.</hi> v. 14. that <hi>when the Apostles had heard that</hi> Samaria <hi>had receiv'd the Word of God,</hi> by <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Evangelist, they sent unto them</hi> Pe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ter <hi>and</hi> John, the Apostles, <hi>who when they were come down, prayed for them that they might rec<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>eive the Holy Ghost. For as yet he was fallen upon none of them, only they were Baptized in the Name of the Lord Jesus; then laid they their hands on them and they received the Holy Ghost.</hi> That is, the Powers and Gifts of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> which fitted them for the several parts of the <hi>Ministery:</hi> for so we see it. <hi>Acts,</hi> 19. 6. when <hi>Paul</hi> hah laid his hands upon those Converts at <hi>Ephesus, the Holy Ghost came upon them, and they spake with Tongues and Prophecyed.</hi> i. e. had the Power of <hi>Miracles,</hi> and particularly that of <hi>Tongues</hi> given them to convert <hi>Ʋn<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>believers,</hi> and that of <hi>Prophecy</hi> to direct the
<pb n="15" facs="16"/>
               <hi>Faithful.</hi> And besides this we find the same Apostle c. 14. 21. going over the several <hi>Churches, Confirming the Souls of the Disciples, exhorting them to continue in the Faith, ordain<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing them Elders</hi> or Church Officers <hi>in every Church,</hi> and then <hi>commending them to the Lord on whom they believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such was the <hi>Subordination</hi> of <hi>Officers</hi> in the Church of Christ. And it pleased our Lord to accommodate his <hi>Gifts</hi> to the Na<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ture of their several Employments, and these we have likewise laid down, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 8. &amp;c. <hi>To one is given by the Spirit the word of Wisdom, to another knowledge by the same Spirit, to ano<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ther Faith by the same Spirit.</hi> Where the Gifts of <hi>Wisdom, Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> Answer to the Three sorts of Ministers. v. 28, 29. <hi>Apostles, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Faith,</hi> the gift of <hi>Evangelists</hi> or Teachers, is meant the Faith of <hi>Miracles,</hi> ac<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cording to what our Saviour says to his Dis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ciples <hi>Mark</hi> 11. 22. <hi>Have Faith in God, for verily I say unto you whosoever shall say to this Mountain, be thou remov'd and be thou cast into the Sea, and shall not doubt in his heart, but shall believe that those things which he saith shall</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="17"/>
               <hi>come to pass, he shall have whatsoever he saith.</hi> And from this, <hi>Stephen</hi> is said <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 8. to be <hi>full of Faith and Power, and to do great won<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ders and Miracles among the People.</hi> And that this is the Faith here mentioned is evident from what follows, which is an enumerati<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>on of some of the great <hi>Powers</hi> of this Faith. <hi>To one the gifts of Healing, to another the work<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing of Miracles,</hi> 
               <gap resp="#oxf" extent="1 word" rend="content:〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉">
                  <desc>foreign</desc>
               </gap>, properly the casting out Devils, <hi>to another Prophecy,</hi> or foretelling things to come, <hi>to another discerning of Spirits, to another divers kinds of Tongues, to another the interpretation of Tongues,</hi> all Supernatural Powers for the convincing of Unbelievers, and necessary for the first Preachers of Christiani<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty, who were <hi>unlearn'd</hi> and plain men, and therefore preached Christ not by the Strength of human <hi>Eloquence</hi> and Persuasion, but by the Testimony of <hi>Miracles</hi> and the demon<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stration of the Power of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Knowledge,</hi> the gift of Christian <hi>Pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phets,</hi> seems to be meant the Understanding of the <hi>Scripture</hi> and the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of the Go<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spel; how they were foretold in the Prophe<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cies of old, and how accomplish'd in our Saviour Jesus; and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> joyns
<pb n="17" facs="18"/>
these things together 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 2. <hi>Though I have the gift of</hi> Prophecy <hi>and understand all</hi> Myste<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ries <hi>and all</hi> Knowledge, <hi>and though I have all Faith, so that I could remove Mountains and have no Charity, I am nothing.</hi> And this Gift also was a necessary qualification for those who were to Instruct <hi>Believers,</hi> and preach to the Assemblies of Persons converted; whose knowledge was to be improv'd, whose Faith was to be confirmed, and whose Growth in the understanding of the Gospel, was to be promoted, by these Labourers in the Vine<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>yard of Christ.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But the principal Gift was that of <hi>Wis<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dom,</hi> communicated to the <hi>Apostles</hi> the Su<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pream Governours of the Christian Church, to support them in the greatest and most difficult Task, that of <hi>Government;</hi> Wisdom to direct even the Preachers and Prophets themselves in their several Functions, to con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>trive the most proper Methods for the <hi>Plan<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ting</hi> of Christianity, and the most prudent Rules, for the nourishing and <hi>preserving</hi> it; and to find out the fittest <hi>Instruments</hi> for both; Wisdom to Instruct them when to bear with
<pb n="18" facs="19"/>
               <hi>Patience,</hi> when to condescend with <hi>Meekness,</hi> and when to resist with <hi>Courage</hi> and punish with <hi>Vigor.</hi> A gift infinitely beyond any of the rest here mentioned, though not appear<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ing in the same pomp with the Miraculous operations of the Spirit, which the <hi>Corinthi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ans</hi> were for that reason too fond of. With<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>out this the <hi>Preachers</hi> might have been un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ruly, the <hi>Prophets</hi> disorderly, and the <hi>zealous</hi> themselves indiscreet: and therefore it pleased the Wisdom of God to consult the Strength, and Order, and Peace of his Church, by placing therein an Authority that might <hi>preside</hi> over the Subordinate Officers in it, that might direct the <hi>Imprudent,</hi> restrain the <hi>Disorderly,</hi> encou<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rage the <hi>Laborious,</hi> and take care that all things might be done in that <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>De<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cency</hi> which becomes the Body of Christ.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) Thus does the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of God ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pear in settling the Oeconomy of his Church: But we must in the Third place Adore his <hi>Goodness</hi> in having preserved this excellent Order to us, however unworthy of so great a Blessing. We have, thanks be to the Divine Providence, not only our <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="20"/>
answerable to the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Evangelists</hi> in my Text, but we have the <hi>Apostolical</hi> Authority derived to us by a continued Succession of our <hi>Bishops</hi> from the Apostles themselves. Such as these the Scripture tells us the Apo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stles committed their Authority to, such have all ages of the Church acknowledged for the Successors of the Apostles, and it has been by the Care and Conduct of such, that <hi>He<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>resies</hi> have been conquer'd, <hi>Schisms</hi> prevented or repair'd; and the purity of the Christian <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Discipline</hi> handed down to our pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>sent times; and therefore we have a great deal of reason to be thankful to Almighty God, that among all the Confusions of this latter Age, he has been pleased to pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>serve to us this inestimable advantage.</p>
            <p>Nor ought we to overlook the <hi>Grace</hi> and Mercy of God, who in these times of diffi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>culty, has been pleased to give to the <hi>present</hi> Governours of our poor Church, so plenti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ful an effusion of that <hi>Spirit of Wisdom</hi> which attended the Apostles their Predecessors, and who constantly directs them in supplying the places of those whom their Lord calls away from their Labours, with persons distinguish'd
<pb n="20" facs="21"/>
with the visible <hi>Characters</hi> of the same Spi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rit; with that <hi>Wisdom which is from above, first pure, then peaceable, gentle and easy to be en<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>treated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, without Partiality and without Hypocrisy.</hi> And may God every day make us more <hi>sensible</hi> of the Greatness of this Blessing, more <hi>fruitful</hi> un<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>der it, and more <hi>thankful</hi> for it, that he may be prevail'd upon to continue it down to our <hi>Posterity,</hi> and to preserve his own Insti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tution to the end of the World. And this leads me to my Second General, where I am to enquire after,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <p>II. The <hi>Author</hi> of this Establishment. And in this I need be but very short, since he ap<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pears so visible in the Discourse of our Apo<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>stle in both the places I have mention'd; 'Tis our <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi> whom he declares to be the Original of these Orders, and 'tis to his <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> that he tells us the Church is in<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>debted for those several Gifts that accom<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>pany them. v. 7, 8. of this Chapter. <hi>To every one of us is given Grace</hi> or Office <hi>accor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ding to the measure of the gift of</hi> Christ. <hi>When he led Captivity Captive,</hi> He <hi>gave Gifts unto</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="22"/>
               <hi>men. By</hi> Christ <hi>the whole Body is fitly joyned together and compacted by these</hi> several Joynts. v. 16. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 5. <hi>There are diversities of Operations, but the same</hi> Lord; <hi>and</hi> God <hi>hath set some in the Church, first Apostles, se<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>condly Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. v. 28. and he adds, that their Gifts are the <hi>manifestation of the Spirit,</hi> that though there be diversities of them, yet they all proceed from that one <hi>Spirit.</hi> And that <hi>all these worketh that one and the same</hi> Spi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>rit <hi>dividing to every man severally as he will.</hi> v. 11. So that whatever men may say, out of an itch of <hi>Novelty,</hi> or out of a design to <hi>weaken</hi> or <hi>abolish</hi> the Establishment, to prove this Order to have been the effect of <hi>Choice</hi> and the result of human <hi>Deliberation,</hi> must all vanish before the clear light of the word of God, and we must see the <hi>Divine</hi> Origi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nal of our Church Government, in spite of all the Labour that is taken to reduce it to the Inventions of <hi>Men.</hi> Our <hi>Lord</hi> himself has raised his Spiritual Temple according to his own method, and his Church is <hi>built upon the Foundation of the Apostles and</hi> Christian <hi>Prophets,</hi> Jesus Christ <hi>himself being the chief corner Stone.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="22" facs="23"/>
            <p>III. We must therefore hasten to the Third thing to be considered, the <hi>end</hi> and design of this Dispensation, in these Words. <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Ministry, for the edifying of the Body of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here are Three Excellent ends of this Order, to which we must briefly give a distinct Consideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The first is <hi>The perfecting of the Saints,</hi> Or the Uniting the several Members of Christ's Church to <hi>one another,</hi> and to himself their <hi>Head,</hi> that by the Ministery of the different Parts his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> might be orderly conveyed to the whole <hi>Body</hi> for its Spiritual improvement and <hi>Perfection;</hi> for so it fol<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>lows v. 13. <hi>Till we all come in the Ʋnity of the Faith, and of the Knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect Man, unto the measure of the Stature of the fulness of Christ.</hi> And this is consonant to what the Apostle says upon the same occasion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 25. All this was done, <hi>That there should be no Schism in the Body, but that the Members should have the same care one of another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="23" facs="24"/>
2. The Second end is <hi>The work of the Mi<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nistery,</hi> that it might be <hi>regular,</hi> and <hi>decent</hi> and <hi>successful</hi> to that great end for which it was Ordained; that all who are employed in it, might be confin'd to their proper <hi>Posts</hi> and proper <hi>Work,</hi> and not obstruct the pro<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>gress of the Gospel by wandring out of their due Ranks and Stations, that the <hi>Feet</hi> might not affect the work or place of the <hi>Hands,</hi> and neither of them that of the <hi>Head;</hi> but that they might remember that 'tis <hi>God</hi> who <hi>hath set the Members every one in the Body, as it has pleased him,</hi> and that <hi>if they were all one Member, there would be no Body.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 18. 'Tis in pursuance of this, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> c. 14. commands that all things in the Christian As<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>semblies be done <hi>decently and in Order,</hi> and that the Prophets themselves observe the Rules prescribed them, telling them v. 32. that <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets are Subject to the Prophets, for God is not the Author of confusion but of peace, as in all Churches of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third end is what follows from the blessing of God upon the work of the Ministery, and that is, the <hi>Edifying of the Body of</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="25"/>
               <hi>of Christ,</hi> the confirming Believers in a sound <hi>Faith</hi> and a holy <hi>Life;</hi> the former St. <hi>Paul</hi> instances in at the 14th. v. <hi>That we henceforth be no more Children tossed to and fro, and car<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ried about with every wind of Doctrine, by the slight of men, and cunning craftiness whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</hi> And the latter at v. 17. <hi>this I say therefore and testifie in the Lord that ye henceforth walk not as other Gen<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tiles walk in the vanity of their minds.</hi> And he joins both together at v. 15. <hi>but speaking the truth in Love ye may grow up into him in all things which is the head even Christ.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <p>Thus have we consider'd the different <hi>Or<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ders</hi> of the Ministery, the <hi>Author</hi> of the Insti<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>tution, and the <hi>Ʋsefulness</hi> of it to the Church of Christ, suffer me now to draw two or three Conclusions from what has been said, which I shall do very briefly, and so con<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>clude.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) Is the Manifestation of the Spirit <hi>given to every man to profit withall?</hi> Were these Orders Instituted, not to gratifie the Vanity or Ambition of the <hi>Persons</hi> employ'd, but to serve and feed the <hi>Flock</hi> of Christ? then all those that are call'd to any holy Function
<pb n="25" facs="26"/>
must remember, that they are called to be <hi>Watchful</hi> and <hi>Diligent;</hi> to deny themselves and to guide others; to labour hard, to bear much, and to apply their whole Thoughts to acquit themselves to their great Master, and to carry on the Salvation of those Souls which he has <hi>purchas'd with his own Blood.</hi> And whoever shall through <hi>Pride</hi> or <hi>Sloth</hi> or <hi>unconcern</hi> neglect this work of the Lord, or do it deceitfully, he betrays a Sacred Trust, abuses his Talents, and will one day receive the bitter Sentence of the unprofita<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ble Servant.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Is <hi>God</hi> the Author of this Institution? and is the <hi>Church</hi> edified by the work of its Pastors? Then are they that <hi>Labour in the Word and Doctrine</hi> entitled to a <hi>double Honor,</hi> both for the dignity of their <hi>Commission,</hi> and the benefit that arises from their <hi>Service.</hi> And therefore their Persons ought to be re<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>spected, their necessities supplyed, and their endeavours promoted by those that are committed to their Charge, and they should be <hi>esteemed very highly in Love, both for their Master's and their Work's sake.</hi> And if there be any so bold as to despise their
<pb n="26" facs="27"/>
Office, or to contemn or prophane the sa<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>cred Functions in which they serve, he must remember that he affronts God that sent them, and injures the Church of Christ, for whose good they were sent, and must here<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>after be accountable for both, at the Tribu<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>nal of our Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) Lastly did our Saviour <hi>Institute,</hi> and has he <hi>preserv'd</hi> in his Church such a <hi>Subor<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>dination</hi> of Ministers as we have describ'd, and for such excellent <hi>Ends;</hi> Men ought then to be very careful of breaking in upon this establishment, both as they tender the honour of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and the good of his <hi>Church.</hi> Sure it must be bold to pretend to alter by <hi>Human</hi> Authority, or for reasons of our own, what was settled by the Authori<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty of our <hi>Lord,</hi> for reasons of such weight, as the <hi>perfecting of the Saints, the work of the Ministry, and the edifying of the Body of Christ.</hi> Nor can it well be imagin'd that they are true Friends to the <hi>Edification of Christ's Body</hi> to <hi>purity</hi> of Doctrine, or <hi>Holiness</hi> of Life or the <hi>Ʋnity</hi> of the Church, who would inno<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>vate in these things, and alter that Form of Church Government, which the Wisdom of
<pb n="27" facs="28"/>
Christ our head, establish'd for this end, for the <hi>Beauty</hi> and order of his Body, and for the <hi>Happiness</hi> of its Members. May we therefore be truly thankful to God for the pre<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>servation of this <hi>primitive</hi> Government. May we be zealous for it's <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Sup<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>port,</hi> and <hi>Continuance;</hi> and above all may the Persons employed in it be a <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> to their Function. May the Piety and Wisdom of our <hi>Fathers,</hi> and the Labours and Order of their <hi>Clergy,</hi> make the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a Pattern for the Governours and Pastors of all other Churches. And may God give a visible Blessing to their endeavours, in rendring their <hi>Flocks</hi> discernable from the rest of the Christian World, in puri<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>ty of <hi>Faith,</hi> rectitude of <hi>Manners,</hi> and union of <hi>Hearts.</hi> That so Imitating the Apostolical Churches in Doctrine, Practice and Discipline, we may be an Exemplary Part of the Church <hi>Militant</hi> in this World, and a Glorious Part of the Church <hi>Trium<lb rend="hidden" type="hyphenInWord"/>phant</hi> in a Future.</p>
         </div>
         <closer>Amen.</closer>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>